<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/web-apps/status/status_20060222.xml">
  <title>Web-apps Status Report</title>

  <author>
    <mail link="wrobel@gentoo.org">Gunnar Wrobel</mail>
  </author>

  <abstract>
    This is the status of the Gentoo/Web-Applications Project. It will
    be posted regularly, but not with a static frequency.
  </abstract>

  <license/>

  <version>1.0</version>
  <date>2006-02-22</date>

  <chapter>
    <title>Status Reports</title>
    <section>
      <title>Preliminaries</title>
      <body>

	<p>
	  This is the status report of the Gentoo/Web-Applications
	  Project. It will be posted regularly, but not with a static
	  frequency.  All questions can be posted
	  to <mail>web-apps@gentoo.org</mail>.
	</p>

	<p>
	  The Gentoo/Web-Applications Team, has its own project page
	  (just like almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find
	  it at http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/web-apps/. You can also
	  contact us via IRC at #gentoo-web using the Freenode IRC
	  server.
	</p>

	<p>
	  This status report is mainly concerned about the progress
	  made between Jan 1, 2005 and Dec 31, 2005.
	</p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Status Report in Figures</title>
    <section>
      <body>

	<ul>
	  <li>
	    218 unique bugs were assigned
	    to <mail>web-apps@gentoo.org</mail> and fixed during the
	    last year.
	  </li>

	  <li>
	    The Gentoo/webapps team has grown to 11 developers.
	  </li>
	</ul>

      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Web Applications Overlay</title>
    <section>
      <body>

	<p>
	  We created a Portage
	  <uri link="http://svn.gnqs.org/projects/gentoo-webapps-overlay">
	    overlay
	  </uri>
	  that contains ebuilds for applications that we do not want
	  to maintain in the main tree. Such applications either lack
	  a developer willing to maintain it in Portage or have not
	  been reviewed for security. In addition it is intended to
	  serve as a playground for new developers wishing to join our
	  team.
	</p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Documentation</title>
    <section>
      <body>

	<p>
	  We created an introduction to the webapp.eclass:
	</p>

	<ul>
	  <li>
	    <uri link="/proj/en/webapps/webapp-eclass.xml">webapp.eclass Documentation</uri>
	  </li>
	</ul>

	<p>
	  It explains the Gentoo way of installing web
	  applications. While it can serve as a gentle introduction
	  for beginners it also provides detailed information for the
	  experienced ebuild scripter.
	</p>

	<p>
	</p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>webapp-config</title>
    <section>
      <body>

	<p>
	  We recently switched from the old bash version
	  of <c>webapp-config</c> to a version implemented in Python,
	  which is much faster and easier to maintain.
	</p>

	<p>
	  The new version has been available in the unstable tree
	  since January and only a few minor bugs had to be corrected
	  since then. We intend to mark it stable on the different
	  architectures in one or two weeks.
	</p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

</guide>
