<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/gdp/formatting-guide.xml">
<title>Gentoo Documentation Project Formatting Guide</title>

<author title = "Author">
<mail link = "zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail></author>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>8 July 2003</date>

<abstract>This guide will cover the formatting basics for GDP documentation.</abstract>

<chapter>
	<title>Introduction</title>
		<section>
			<title>What this guide is for</title>
			<body>
			<p>The purpose of this guide is to provide some examples of proper formatting
			for GDP (Gentoo Documentation Project) documentation. Before reading this guide,
			it is expected that you have read both the
			<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/doc/xml-guide.xml">XML Guide</uri> and the
			<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-policy.xml">Documentation Policy</uri>.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>The Basics</title>
		<section>
			<title>Basic layout</title>
			<body>
			<p>Since the main goal of the GDP is to create clear and concise documentation, it
			comes as no big surprise that our documentation follows a strict set of formatting
			guidelines. Not only do these guidelines ensure that our documentation is structurally
			clear, but they keep the documentation portable, enabling the documentation
			to be migrated with website changes and transformed into a number of different formats,
			such as Postscript or PDF.
			</p>

			<p>The layout of a basic GDP guide is very hierarchial. The overall guide is contained
			in a <i>guide</i> tag, with main topics in <i>chapter</i> tags, and sub topics in
			<i>section</i> tags contained within the greater <i>chapter</i> tags. Basically,
			the form of a document follows much that of a college type outline:
			</p>
			
			<pre caption = "Sample guide layout">
&lt;guide&gt;
	&lt;chapter&gt;
		&lt;title&gt;Main Topic 1&lt;/title&gt;
		&lt;section&gt;
			&lt;title&gt;Subtopic 1&lt;/title&gt;
			&lt;body&gt;
			&lt;p&gt;Information here...&lt;/p&gt;
			&lt;/body&gt;
		&lt;/section&gt;
	&lt;/chapter&gt;
&lt;/guide&gt;
			</pre>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Using the right tags in the right place</title>
			<body>
			<p>The Gentoo/ GDP XML format has a ton of tags that do many nifty things. The problem
			is, there are so many tags that do similar tasks, it is hard to know which tags should
			be used where. For starters, the <i>i</i> tags are used to highlight text for emphasis.
			For example: Make sure you <i>never</i> do <c>rm -rf /</c>. The <i>e</i> tag on the other
			hand, italizes words for a less enhancing effect. For example: It is <e>highly</e>
			recommended to remove Windows in great times of frustration. As far as emphasizing commands,
			the <i>c</i> tag is the correct tag to use. For example: Please run <c>etc-update</c>
			after each <c>emerge -u world</c>, or suffer the wrath of the bug-wranglers.
			</p>

			<p>Additionally, in order to keep <uri link="http://www.w3.org">W3C</uri> compliance,
			do not place <i>note</i>, <i>warn</i>, <i>info</i>, etc, tags inside of a <i>p</i> tag.
			Please be smart with how you write your guides, and if you are ever in doubt of validility,
			check the document (in its HTML form) with the <uri link="http://validator.w3.org">W3C validator</uri>.
			</p>
			
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Using <i>pre</i> tags</title>
			<body>
			<p><i>pre</i> tags are usually used to insert examples into documents. A <i>pre tag</i> in
			a live document would look like this:
			</p>

			<pre caption = "I am a pre tag">
Hi there!
		Formatting
				does
					matter
							here...
			</pre>

			<p>The first thing that you probably noticed was that the tabbed in words are, well, tabbed in.
			Reason being, formatting <i>does</i> matter in <i>pre</i> tags. For example, I can type a paragraph
			inside of a <i>p</i> tag with indents, returns at the end of lines, etc. As you well know, those
			formatting attributes are not picked up by the XML processing. <i>pre</i> tags are special
			due to the fact that they do pick up formatting attributes, as depicted above. Moral of the story?
			To maintain proper code indentation, indent the tag line (&lt;pre caption = &quot;foo&quot;&gt;), but not
			the content contained within, except of course if you mean to have the <i>pre</i> content formatted.
			</p>

			<p>Secondly, all <i>pre</i> tags are to have a caption. If you look at the above example, that
			<i>pre</i> container has the caption of <e>I am a pre tag</e>. This is done by giving the
			<i>caption</i> argument to the tag, so the tag declaration looks like so:
			</p>

			<pre caption = "A pre caption example">
	&lt;pre caption = "Example pre tag and caption"&gt;
Pre text...FOO!
	&lt;pre&gt;
			</pre>

			<p>Last, but surely not least, keep the length of your <i>pre</i> content to under 80 characters!!!
			I cannot stress the importance of this. If the content is over 80 characters, printed documentation
			becomes unreadable. Please, don't make me yell at you for this!
			</p>
			
			<p>Of course, if in doubt, you can always check the existing documentation that resides in CVS.
			</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Line breaks</title>
			<body>
			<p>For the sake of us developers, please linebreak when your line of text is at about 80 characters.
			What this means is, hit return when you are typing every once and awhile. Remember, formatting only
			matters in <i>pre</i> tags, so linebreak all that you want in the other tags!
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		
		<section>
			<title>Indenting, please</title>
			<body>
			<p>XML documentation is code, so please, please, indent correctly.
			All of our guides use a tabspace setting of 4. In <c>vim</c> this would be set by entering
			command mode, and then doing <c>:set ts=4</c>. If you don't use vim, you are not exempt.
			Enough said, nothing more to see here, moving on.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>The not so basics</title>
		<section>
			<title>Encoding</title>
			<body>
			<p>All GDP documentation must be encoded in the <i>UTF-8</i> encoding scheme. Encoding all documentation
			UTF-8 makes everyone's lives easier, especially the translators, as UTF-8 is easily portable
			across languages. An easy way to format your document in UTF-8 is to use <c>iconv</c>:
			</p>

			<pre caption = "Using iconv">
<codenote>replace iso-8859-1 with the document's original encoding</codenote>
<c>$ iconv -f iso-8859-1 -t UTF-8 -o output_xml</c>
			</pre>
			</body>
		</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Resources</title>
	<section>
		<title>Contacts</title>
		<body>
		<p>If you have any questions or concerns about this document, or the formatting process,
		feel free to contact the GDP team using the <i>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</i> mailinglist.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
