<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/virtualization/index.xml,v 1.13 2009/11/22 23:28:30 cardoe Exp $ -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>virtualization</name>
<longname>Gentoo Virtualization Project</longname>
<date>22 Nov 2009</date>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="dev-zero@gentoo.org">Tiziano Müller</mail>
</author>
<author title='Editor'>
<mail link="cardoe@gentoo.org">Doug Goldstein</mail>
</author>

<description>
The Gentoo Virtualization Project maintains packages shared between the different virtualization
(sub-)projects and provides documentation and tools to the user to make Gentoo a first choice platform
as both host and guest system.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
With the various virtualization solutions are also tools available to manage more than one kind of virtual machine.
Furthermore it is possible to share certain knowledge on how to setup and administer such systems.
This project exists as a general virtualization project to maintain common packages, to collect documentation and to give
the user a general overview what's available on all Gentoo platforms.
</p>

<p>
This includes (combination of) the following techniques:
KVM, Qemu, Lguest, Xen, VMWare, VirtualBox, vServer, OpenVZ, Linux Containers, Solaris Zones, FreeBSD Jails
</p>
</longdescription>

<goals>
    <p>
        The current goal is to bring all stakeholders together and to define the next steps.
        Furthermore, mailinglist, irc-channel, mail-alias, etc. have to be created.
        Shortly after defining how the different sub-projects should interact, a public announcement has to be made.
    </p>
</goals>

<subproject ref="/proj/en/vmware/index.xml" inheritmembers="no"/>

<dev role="member" description="Various Virtualization Packages/KVM">dev-zero</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Qemu, bochs">lu_zero</dev>
<dev role="member" description="KVM/libvirt">cardoe</dev>
<dev role="member" description="KVM">jmbsvicetto</dev>
<dev role="member" description="KVM">tommy</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Xen">rbu</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Xen">marineam</dev>
<dev role="member" description="VirtualBox">jokey</dev>
<dev role="member" description="VMware">vadimk</dev>
</project>
