<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide link="evoldap.htm">
<title>Using Udder Evolution with LDAP</title>
<author title="Udder LDAP Developer"><mail link="andrd@gentoo.org">Abhishek Amit</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This document shows how to use Evolution to acess an address book using LDAP</abstract>
<version>0.1</version>
<date>26 Jun 2003</date>
<chapter>
<title>Configuration</title>
<section>
<title>Basic</title>
<body>
<p>In order to set up Evolution pull up the Settings dialog. This can be accessed from the Tools menu. Click on the icon on the left for Directory servers and click Add. You can enter whatever you would like for the display name. I personally call it <c>Gentoo</c>. For the server name enter <c>trout.gentoo.org</c>. Set the Log in method to <c>Using Distinguished Name(DN)</c>. In the field labeld Distinguished Name enter your Distinguished Name. For me this is uid=andrd,dc=gentoo,dc=org.</p>
<p>Move onto the next tab(Connecting) and set the port number to <c>636</c>. As you will notice, this makes it change the setting <c>Use SSL/TLS</c> to Always, which is what we want. This should be all you need to do on this tab.</p>
<p>Move to the next tab(Searching) tab and enter <c>dc=gentoo,dc=org</c> in the field labelled Search base. You should now be able to view the directory. </p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Autocompletion</title>
<body>
<p>If you would like, you can set up Evolution to pull names and addresses for autocompletion from the LDAP directory. In order to set this up go back to the settings dialog and click on the icon for Folder Settings and move to the tab for Autocompletion Folders. Click on Add, and expand the heading Other Folders, under which you should be able to find the folder for the directory server. Again, this name will vary depending on what you set as the name when creating the directory. This should make Evolution pull names from the LDAP directory.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Viewing Directory</title>
<section>
<title>Viewing Directory</title>
<body>
<p>In order to view the directory you must click on the name of the folder you are in to expand a list, and click on whatever you named your directory. As I named mine Gentoo, I click on Gentoo to view the directory. At this point Evolution will prompt you for your password. Simply enter whatever your password is and you will now have access to the LDAP directory. </p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
