<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/extreme-security/projectmanagement/Attic/index.xml,v 1.1 2007/10/27 21:29:59 pappy Exp $ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/extreme-security/projectmanagement/index.xml">
    <title>Extreme Security Project Management</title>
    <author title="Author">
        <mail link="pappy@gentoo.org">Alexander Gabert</mail>
    </author>
    
    <!--
    <author title="Contributor">
        <mail link="XXX">YYY</mail>
    </author>
    <author title="Editor">
        <mail link="XXX">YYY</mail>
    </author>
-->
    
    <abstract>
        
        The management of the timetables and the excellence of processes in an open source development project is often underestimated.
        
    </abstract>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <date>2007-10-27</date>
    
    
    <chapter>
        <title>
            Introduction to project management
        </title>
        <section>
            <body>
                <p>
                    The management of the timetables and the excellence of processes in an open source development project is often underestimated.
                </p>
                <p>
                    However, this does not mean we cannot make a difference.  For this reason there shall be a precise structure how development and interaction between developers takes place.
                    From the first impression, this may seem bizarre and obscure, but when developers feel constrained to exact and clear processes developed by their own team, there is hope
                    that the team can work better together and have more fun enjoying working solutions free of hidden bugs or concealed dependencies from a certain developer.
                </p>
                <!--
                <note> 
                </note>
-->
            </body>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter>
        <title>
            Project management in source repositories
        </title>
        <section>
            <title>
                Repository structure
            </title>
            <body>
                <p>
                    This is the typical layout of a source repository:
                </p>
                
                <pre caption="Normal SVN source repository">
                    167417 drwxr-xr-x 3 pappy pappy 4096 Oct 23 22:28 branches
                    558597 drwxr-xr-x 3 pappy pappy 4096 Oct 23 22:28 tags
                    14013668 drwxr-xr-x 6 pappy pappy 4096 Oct 23 22:28 trunk
                </pre>
                
                <p>    
                    There is nothing wrong with it.  But there are ways to make it better for a team developing security technology.
                </p>
                
                <p>
                    This is the expected structure in an extreme-security hosted project:
                </p>
                
                <pre caption="SVN source repository with review folder">
                    167417 drwxr-xr-x 3 pappy pappy 4096 Oct 23 22:28 branches
                    14016466 drwxr-xr-x 2 pappy pappy 4096 Oct 27 22:07 review
                    558597 drwxr-xr-x 3 pappy pappy 4096 Oct 23 22:28 tags
                    14013668 drwxr-xr-x 6 pappy pappy 4096 Oct 23 22:28 trunk
                </pre>
                
                <p>
                    In this scenario, the trunk is the mainline of development containing reviewed components from the branches of the developers
                    or the development subteams (2-3 persons).
                </p>
                
                <p>
                    Development of code and documentation is done in branches, then independently reviewed by a group of persons (must not be experts on the topic)
                    and then either committed to the trunk by a reviewer or given back to the developer or the subteam with the sourcecode or documentation
                    marked with "TODO" tags where it needs improvement or errors fixed.
                </p>
                
                <note>
                    <!--
                        
                        TODO
                        
                        - write development model (design, develop, review, publish)
                        
-->
                </note>
                
            </body>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
</guide>
