<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/games/games-ebuild-howto.xml,v 1.20 2014/09/05 18:35:33 creffett Exp $ -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Games/Ebuild_howto">
<title>Gentoo Games Ebuild HOWTO</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="egore@gmx.de">Christoph Brill</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author/Editor">
  <mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide outlines the best practices for creating ebuilds for games on Gentoo.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.13</version>
<date>23 May 2007</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>
This guide is intended to give an overview of how to write good games ebuilds.
Writing games ebuilds using the best possible style allows for your submission
to be added to Gentoo quickly and with no issues. There are several simple
steps that you can follow to achieve this goal, starting from games ebuilds
basics to some really nice tricks to work around the broken state of some
upstream packages. This guide also tries to point out common mistakes made when
contributing an ebuild.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Prerequisites</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>
First and foremost, this document will show you the proper way
to write an ebuild, starting with the file naming and placement.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Installing vim</title>
<body>

<p>
This ebuild guide recommends using "vim" for creating ebuilds.
Together with "gentoo-syntax" you can create ebuilds quite simply.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing vim and gentoo-syntax">
# emerge app-editors/vim app-vim/gentoo-syntax
</pre>

<p>
Now vim will have proper syntax highlighting for ebuilds.  It
also has a default template for ebuilds.  If you are unfamiliar
with vim, I recommend reading the
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/vi-guide.xml">
Learning vi</uri> guide to familiarize yourself with it.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Creating a games ebuild in your overlay</title>
<body>

<p>
We are going to create a game ebuild in your portage overlay.
The first thing you will need to do, is to decide which game you
would like to write as an ebuild.  Next, you will want to decide
which category your game best fits.
</p>

<ul>
<li>games-action</li>
<li>games-arcade</li>
<li>games-board</li>
<li>games-emulation</li>
<li>games-engines</li>
<li>games-fps</li>
<li>games-kids</li>
<li>games-misc</li>
<li>games-mud</li>
<li>games-puzzle</li>
<li>games-roguelike</li>
<li>games-rpg</li>
<li>games-server</li>
<li>games-simulation</li>
<li>games-sports</li>
<li>games-strategy</li>
<li>games-util</li>
</ul>

<p>
If, for example, your game is a soccer game named "kickball",
you would create a directory in your local overlay like follows.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating your overlay directory">
# mkdir -p /usr/local/portage/games-sports/kickball
</pre>

<p>
If the package is a binary package, and does not support
compilation, then append a "-bin" to the end of the package name
to make up the portage package name.  If the package is a demo
version of a commercial, or otherwise full-version game, please
name the package with "-demo" appended to the end of the package
name.  This is a requirement, and is a good idea.  Next, you will
need to know the version number of the package.  It might be needed
to convert this number into a format suitable to portage.  The
ebuild naming policy can be found in the
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/handbook/handbook.xml?part=2">
developer handbook</uri> online.  After deciding on the category
and naming of your new ebuild, we will want to start editing on it.
</p>

<pre caption="Using vim to edit your ebuild">
# cd /usr/local/portage/games-sports/kickball
# vim kickball-1.0.ebuild
</pre>

<p>
At this point, vim will populate out a skeleton ebuild for you.
It should look like the following.
</p>

<pre caption="Skeleton ebuild example">
# Copyright 1999-2007 Gentoo Foundation
# Distributed under the terms of the GNU General Public License v2
# Header: $

DESCRIPTION=""
HOMEPAGE=""
SRC_URI=""

LICENSE=""
SLOT="0"
KEYWORDS="~x86"
IUSE=""

DEPEND=""
RDEPEND=""
</pre>

<p>
This actually is a fully functional ebuild, but we will
definitely need to do some more editing to get it in a usable
state.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Writing the ebuild</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>
Writing the ebuild is the meat of this document.  We start by
describing the elements above and add elements to our ebuild to
create a fully working ebuild for our new game.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>inherit games</title>
<body>

<p>
The first thing we will do is add <c>inherit games</c> to the
ebuild.  The games team prefers this to be located between the
header and the description lines, surrounded by a blank line.  This
is where you inherit eclasses.  If you use a function from an
eclass, you must inherit it.  Also, always list the games eclass
last, unless using another games eclass to override the default
games functionality.  More on this will be explained later.  The
games eclass, which will be explained below, is full of functions
common to all games ebuilds, and also sets up new defaults for
certain ebuild functions, such as pkg_preinst, pkg_postinst,
src_compile, and pkg_setup.  It also contains some variables that
we will use across all games ebuilds, to maintain consistency.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the description of the package.  The description should
be no more than a single line, and should give a quick overview of
the game.  Try to make it descriptive, yet succinct.  A good
example for our kickball game would be "a fast-paced SDL soccer
game with network play".
</p>

<note>
Please do not add something like "kickball is" to the
beginning of the description.  It is redundant and unwanted by the
games team.
</note>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>HOMEPAGE</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the location of this package's homepage.  This should
always be linked to the English version of the page, if available.
This should also <b>never</b> contain any variables.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SRC_URI (and friends)</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the first real interesting thing in our ebuild, and also
the first place for potential problems.  Most upstream packagers
use very strange names for their packages.  Let's say kickball
uses sourceforge.net's distribution system.  The file is named
"kick-ball-src-v1.0.tar.gz".  As you can see, this does not fit
the package name in portage.  There are a few portage variables
which can be used here.  The two that I will be discussing are ${P}
and ${PV}, which refer to the package name and version, and
package version, respectively.  If you need to make changes to
these, it is recommended to use MY_P or MY_PV, as needed.  Proper
games team coding style places these variables above DESCRIPTION,
but in the same block.  In this example, we are going to set MY_P
to "kick-ball-src" and MY_PV to "v${PV}".  We want to use the ${PV}
variable within MY_PV so that future upgrades are easier.
</p>

<note>
Never hard-code package versions within an ebuild unless
there is absolutely no other choice.
</note>

<p>
This makes our SRC_URI look like the following.
</p>

<pre caption="SRC_URI example 1">
SRC_URI="mirror://sourceforge/${PN}/${MY_P}-${MY_PV}.tar.bz2"
</pre>

<p>
This would cause portage to search the sourceforge mirrors for
kickball/kick-ball-src-v1.0.tar.bz2, which is exactly what we are
looking to find.  If the package sources are named to match the
package, then the SRC_URI line is much simpler.
</p>

<pre caption="SRC_URI example 2">
SRC_URI="mirror://sourceforge/${PN}/${P}.tar.bz2"
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>LICENSE</title>
<body>

<p>
The license is an important point in your ebuild.  It is also a
common place for making mistakes.  Try to check the license on any
ebuild that you submit.  Often times, the license will be in a
COPYING file, distributed in the package's tarball.  If the license
is not readily apparent, try contacting the authors of the package
for clarification.  For a list of available licenses, look in
<c>/usr/portage/licenses</c>.  Also, if the license requires the
user to accept the license before installation, then you will need
to set GAMES_CHECK_LICENSE="yes" in your ebuild.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SLOT</title>
<body>

<p>
Leave SLOT="0" unless you know what you are doing.  The slot is
designed to allow two different version packages, that are not
compatible and not conflicting, to exist on the system
simultaneously.  A good example of this is gtk+ 1.x and gtk+ 2.x
packages.  So far, there have been no games where this is the case,
so most likely you will never need to change this.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>KEYWORDS</title>
<body>

<p>
This should state the architectures on which you have tested the
game.  Since every package should start in a testing state, prefix
all architectures with a "~" to show this state.  Also, do not list
any architecture which you cannot personally test.  If you are
writing the ebuild on x86, then the KEYWORDS would be "~x86".
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>IUSE</title>
<body>

<p>
Does this package have additional features that can be toggled
on and off?  IUSE lists all the USE flags that this package is
capable of using.  Do not list any USE flags here which are not
used by the package, and also, do not forget to list any USE flags
here that you use within the package ebuild.  For the meaning of
each global USE flag, please check
<c>/usr/portage/profiles/use.desc</c> and
<c>/usr/portage/profiles/use.local.desc</c> for more information.
A local USE flag is used for any additional feature that does not
fall under the scope of the already-defined global USE flags.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>DEPEND</title>
<body>

<p>
This variable is used to build the dependency tree for packages
that are required to build this package.  You should list all
packages that are used not only by the game build itself, but also
in the ebuild, so if you use "unzip" in your ebuild, you must also
add it to DEPEND.  These packages are only used at build time.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>RDEPEND</title>
<body>

<p>
This variable is used for run-time dependencies.  If left
undefined, portage assumes RDEPEND to be equal to DEPEND.  These
are dependencies required by the package to run.  If you have
packages listed here, you should also refer to this in DEPEND as
follows, otherwise, remove RDEPEND completely.
</p>

<pre caption="DEPEND with RDEPEND example">
RDEPEND="virtual/opengl"
DEPEND="${RDEPEND}
app-arch/unzip"
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>S and upstream packaging</title>
<body>

<p>
The S variable is used to store the starting location that the
ebuild should use for performing work.  By default, this is
S=${WORKDIR}/${P}.  If the upstream packager did not use a
subdirectory when packing their package, which is common with zip
file distribution, then you would set S as follows.
</p>

<pre caption="S with no subdirectory example">
S=${WORKDIR}
</pre>

<p>
If the upstream packager did not include a version number, but did
use the package name, then S would be set as follows.
</p>

<pre caption="S with no version example">
S=${WORKDIR}/${PN}
</pre>

<p>
If you do not need special handling, leave S= out of the ebuild.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>src_unpack</title>
<body>

<p>
The default src_unpack from portage tends to be all you need for
most ebuilds.  This function is used to unpack the sources for a
particular package.  A few examples of when you would want a
src_unpack function are below.
</p>

<pre caption="Makeself archive example">
src_unpack() {
unpack_makeself
}
</pre>

<p>
By default, both unpack and unpack_makeself use ${A} as the target
to unpack.  You can also specify the target, if you need to only
unpack a single download, rather than them all.  A good example of
this comes from the ut2003 ebuild.
</p>

<pre caption="unpack and unpack_makeself example">
src_unpack() {
unpack_makeself linux_installer.sh
unpack UT2003CrashFix.zip
}
</pre>

<p>
As you can see, each function specifically calls a certain file to
be unpacked.  If you need additional steps before compilation, such
as making changes to a Makefile, then you will need add it into a
src_unpack function.  Now, in this final example, let's pretend
that our fictional package, kickball, has both a broken Makefile,
and also a binary that must be removed for compilation to complete.
</p>

<pre caption="kickball src_unpack example">
src_unpack() {
unpack ${A}
cd "${S}"
sed -i \
-e "/TARGET/s:/usr/bin/:${GAMES_BINDIR}:" Makefile \
|| die "sed Makefile failed"
rm -f kickball
}
</pre>

<p>
This function shows us several important things that we need to
know about games ebuilds.  First, when making your own src_unpack,
you must always include your own unpacking methods, or use the
built-in functions.  Next, you see that we cd to our unpacked
location, ${S}, which must be quoted.
</p>

<p>
Now, imagine a line like "TARGET=/usr/bin/" in the game's Makefile.
This is wrong for Gentoo, since by default games binaries go into
"/usr/games/bin", which is defined by "${GAMES_BINDIR}" in
games.eclass.  Always use the variable to refer to the games binary
location, as this allows users to specify for themselves where they
want the games to install their binaries by overriding this
variable.  There are several other games-specific variables
available for you to use, which will be explained further in the
document.
</p>

<p>
You will also notice that we have added "|| die" after each
required external command.  This is necessary, since it stops the
emerge process if that command failed.  Never omit these as all
important external commands need it.  All die messages should be
short and to the point.  Good examples are above.  There is no die
after unpack, as it does its own checking and aborts the emerge
process on its own.
</p>

<p>
We did not add a die after the rm above.  The reason for this is
the presence of kickball will cause the build to fail, but the lack
of the file will not hurt us in any way.  Remove only items that
stop the ebuild from working when present.  If there are, for
example, Makefiles for 25 different systems, just ignore them.
They will not be installed unless we specifically ask for them to
be during src_install, and they will be deleted by portage at
the end of the completed emerge.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>src_compile</title>
<body>

<p>
This function is where both the configuration and compilation
steps take place.  By default, this function is slightly different
for games ebuilds than for non-games ebuilds.  The default function
looks as follows.
</p>

<pre caption="Default src_compile for games.eclass">
src_compile() {
egamesconf || die "egamesconf failed"
emake || die "emake failed"
}
</pre>

<p>
As you can see, we use the egamesconf function, rather than econf.
The egamesconf function is a wrapper function that runs
"./configure" with the proper paths for a Gentoo games ebuild.
</p>

<p>
We use emake instead of make.  This is standard for all Gentoo
ebuilds where make is called.
</p>

<p>
Since both of these commands are essential for our source-based
game, we use "|| die" with a proper die message in our ebuild.
This causes the emerge to stop if one either of these steps fails.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>src_install</title>
<body>

<p>
After completing the compilation of the game, we need to actually
install it.
</p>

<pre caption="Example src_install">
src_install() {
dogamesbin ${PN} || die "dogamesbin failed"

insinto "${GAMES_DATADIR}"/${PN}
doins -r data/* || die "doins failed"
dodoc README manual.pdf

# optional
doicon ${PN}.xpm
make_desktop_entry ${PN} KickBall ${PN}.xpm

prepgamesdirs
}
</pre>

<p>
This is a complete src_install for our fictional kickball package.
As you can see, it contains a few functions that are specific to
the games.eclass, which I will discuss fully below.
</p>

<p>
First, we have dogamesbin, which works like dobin, except that it
puts the binaries into "${GAMES_BINDIR}".  This allows for user
customized binary directories, without the user needing to edit
the ebuild directly.
</p>

<p>
Next, we tell the ebuild to use "${GAMES_DATADIR}/${PN}" as the
default location for our doins calls.  We follow this up with a
"doins -r" to install the data.  Again, we use the variables to
allow users to modify these locations without editing the ebuild.
</p>

<p>Now, we install the documentation that ships with the package.
You should always install documentation for the package.  In some
cases there will be some optional documentation, such as a
walk-thru.  For these, you wrap them behind a conditional on the
doc USE flag and add doc to IUSE.  Never install any COPYING or
INSTALL files, as this information is redundant for portage.
</p>

<p>
We also use two optional commands.  The first, doicon, is from the
eutils.eclass.  This eclass is inherited by the games.eclass, but
if you use functions from it, it is advised to inherit the eclass
yourself.  Remember that the eclass goes <b>before</b> games.eclass
on the inherit line.  As you can guess, doicon installs an icon
file into <c>/usr/share/pixmaps</c>.
</p>

<p>
Next is make_desktop_entry, also from eutils.eclass.  This function
creates a freedesktop.org-compliant .desktop entry for this
package, which gives it a menu item in the GNOME or KDE menus, or
in the menu of any other freedesktop.org-compliant window manager.
</p>

<p>
The last function is not optional.  We use prepgamesdirs last in
our src_install function, as it goes through the directories and
files that are to be installed and sets proper permissions and
ownership on them.  The owner is set to root, with the group being
set to "${GAMES_GROUP}".
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The games.eclass</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>
The games eclasses are designed to fill any needs for writing an
ebuild for a game on Gentoo.  There are separate eclasses for some
of the more commonly modified titles.  These eclasses will be
discussed further later.  For now, we are going to focus on
games.eclass.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Variables</title>
<body>

<p>
The games.eclass provides many variables that control all aspects
of a games ebuild.  Below is a listing of the variables provided by
the eclass, their defaults, and a description of each.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<th>Variable</th>
<th>Default</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_PREFIX</ti>
<ti>/usr/games</ti>
<ti>This is the prefix into which games are installed</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_PREFIX_OPT</ti>
<ti>/opt</ti>
<ti>This is the prefix into which binary games are installed</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_DATADIR</ti>
<ti>/usr/share/games</ti>
<ti>This is the location into which games should installi
their data</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_DATADIR_BASE</ti>
<ti>/usr/share</ti>
<ti>This is the same as ${GAMES_DATADIR}, but some packages
append "games" to the directory</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_SYSCONFDIR</ti>
<ti>/etc/games</ti>
<ti>This is a global configuration directory for games</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_STATEDIR</ti>
<ti>/var/games</ti>
<ti>This location is where games store writable state data,
such as score files</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_LOGDIR</ti>
<ti>/var/log/games</ti>
<ti>This is the default location for log files, such as
that created by a dedicated server</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_LIBDIR</ti>
<ti>NULL</ti>
<ti>This variable should not be used in any ebuilds but can
be set by the user to override the games_get_libdir function
</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_BINDIR</ti>
<ti>/usr/games/bin</ti>
<ti>Location used by dogamesbin</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_ENVD</ti>
<ti>90games</ti>
<ti>File that holds environment settings for games, such as
the binary path</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_USER</ti>
<ti>root</ti>
<ti>Default owner for games files</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_USER_DED</ti>
<ti>games</ti>
<ti>Default user for dedicated servers</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_GROUP</ti>
<ti>games</ti>
<ti>Group which owns all games and group in which game
players should be members</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>GAMES_CHECK_LICENSE</ti>
<ti>NULL</ti>
<ti>This should be used if you need to have the user accept
the ebuild's license before installation.  If you require
this, set GAMES_CHECK_LICENSE="yes" in your ebuild before
calling games_pkg_setup and be sure that games_pkg_setup
is called before any other actions take place in your
pkg_setup function.</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
One thing you need to be aware of when creating a games ebuild is
that we do not allow games to write to /usr, so any game that does
so will need to be patched to write to ${GAMES_STATEDIR} or
${HOME} instead.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Functions</title>
<body>

<p>
There are many functions within the games.eclass for you to use.
Some of them are convenience functions, and some of them are an
absolute requirement.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<th>Function</th>
<th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>games_get_libdir</ti>
<ti>This function prints the architecture-specific location
into which games ebuilds should install libraries.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>egamesconf</ti>
<ti>As we discussed before, egamesconf is used to configure
your package for proper paths on Gentoo.  If your package
requires a "./configure" step, then egamesconf is a
requirement.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>gameswrapper</ti>
<ti>The gameswrapper function is an internal function for
the games.eclass and should never be used in your ebuild.
Its purpose is to modify the default locations for
installation of normal Gentoo ebuild functions.  The
following few functions are all wrapped with gameswrapper.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>dogamesbin</ti>
<ti>This is our first function using gameswrapper.  This
function performs the same actions as dobin, but is wrapped
to install into ${GAMES_BINDIR} instead of the default of
/usr/bin.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>dogamessbin</ti>
<ti>This funtion wraps the dosbin function, and is used for
adding files to ${GAMES_PREFIX}/sbin.  This function is not
very common, as most games expect anyone in the games
group to be able to use all of its functions.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>dogameslib</ti>
<ti>This function wraps the dolib function.  It is used for
installing libraries into the proper directory.  Be aware that
this function installs the libraries into directories
based on $(get_libdir).  This means the default location
on AMD64 would be /usr/games/lib64, rather than the
expected /usr/games/lib.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>dogameslib.a</ti>
<ti>This function wraps dolib.a and like dogameslib, it
installs into the architecture-specific default location.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>dogameslib.so</ti>
<ti>This function wraps dolib.so and like dogameslib, it
installs into the architecture-specific default location.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>newgamesbin</ti>
<ti>This function works the same as dogamesbin, except it
gives you the opportunity to rename the binary.  This is
useful for wrapper scripts, where storing the script in
portage requires a different name to differentiate it from
other files in ${FILESDIR}.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>newgamessbin</ti>
<ti>This function works the same as dogamessbin, except it
gives you the opportunity to rename the binary.  This is
useful for wrapper scripts, where storing the script in
portage requires a different name to differentiate it from
other files in ${FILESDIR}.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>games_make_wrapper</ti>
<ti>This is our last function that employs gameswrapper.
This function is used for creating a wrapper in
${GAMES_BINDIR} that points to your actual game binary.
This is mostly used for binary games that are installed
into ${GAMES_PREFIX_OPT}.  You should avoid using a wrapper
whenever possible.  It is best to patch the sources
to resolve any issues, instead.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>gamesowners</ti>
<ti>This function is used internally by prepgamesdirs to
setup the owner of the files installed by the ebuild to
${GAMES_USER}:${GAMES_GROUP}.  You should never call this
function yourself.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>gamesperms</ti>
<ti>This function does not appear to be used.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>prepgamesdirs</ti>
<ti>This function is used to ensure that all files
installed by games ebuilds have the proper permissions.
This function should be called last in src_install, as it
potentially touches every file and directory installed by
the ebuild.  The purpose of this function is to ensure that
the files and directories are writable by ${GAMES_USER},
readable by ${GAMES_GROUP}, and not readable or executable
by anyone else.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>gamesenv</ti>
<ti>This function sets up the default PATH and LDPATH for
games ebuilds.  It is called automatically by the
games_pkg_postinst function and should not be run
manually.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>games_pkg_setup</ti>
<ti>This is the default games.eclass pkg_setup function.
It does several things to ensure that games will run
correctly under Gentoo.  First, it runs enewgroup to
create the ${GAMES_GROUP} group and enewuser to create
the ${GAMES_USER} and ${GAMES_USER_DED} users.  If
${GAMES_CHECK_LICENSE} is defined, it will ask the
user to accept the package's license via check_license.
If your ebuild requires its own pkg_setup function, then
be sure to call this function from within yours.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>games_src_compile</ti>
<ti>This is the default games.eclass src_compile function.
It is actually quite simple as it only runs the following
commands.  First, it checks if configure is executable,
then it runs egamesconf.  Then, if checks for the existence
of a Makefile, and runs emake.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>games_pkg_preinst</ti>
<ti>This is the default games.eclass pkg_preinst function.
It is used to copy files from ${GAMES_STATEDIR} to the
temporary location used by portage prior to merging.  This
ensures that any state information files are not unmerged
with the old package during an upgrade.  If your ebuild
requires its own pkg_preinst function, then be sure to call
this function from within yours.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>games_pkg_postinst</ti>
<ti>This is the default games.eclass pkg_postinst function.
First, it runs gamesenv to setup the environment.  This is
also the function that warns the user about the games group
requirement for playing games on Gentoo.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>games_ut_unpack</ti>
<ti>This function is used to unpack .uz and .uz2 files that
are typically associated with the Unreal Tournament series
of games.  It can take either a file name or a directory
name as an argument.  Use of this function requires that
your ebuild has games-util/uz2unpack in DEPEND.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>games_umod_unpack</ti>
<ti>This function is used to unpack .umod, .ut2mod, and
.ut4mod files that are typically associated with the
Unreal Tournament series of games.  This function requires
an installation of one of these games, and is generally
only used for modifications to these games.</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
This covers all of the games.eclass functions.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>
