<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>Games</name>
<longname>Gentoo Games Project</longname>
<date>13 Jul 2004</date>
<author title="Author">Chris Gianelloni</author>

<description>
	The Games project manages the games-* categories in Portage.
</description>

<longdescription>
	The Games project manages all games that are added into the Portage
	tree.  We're the guys that put the fun into Gentoo.  We also manage a few
	utilites that are used heavily in many games, such as the SDL* libraries.
</longdescription>

<goals>
	The games project aims to turn Gentoo into the premiere Linux gaming
	platform.  We strive to have the best compatability not only for free
	games, but also for commercial titles.
</goals>

<dev role="lead" description="Project coordinator, games-roguelike">vapier</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Loki/Epic/Id titles">wolf31o2</dev>
<dev role="member" description="everything except games-fps">Mr_Bones_</dev>

<herd name="games"/>

<extrachapter position="goals">
	<title>Gentoo Games Bugs FAQ</title>
	<section>
		<body>
		<ol>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">Which Product/Component should I pick?i</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3">What severity should I use for version bumps or new game requests?</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect4">Why shouldn't I mark a Games bug as "blocker"?</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect5">How long should I wait before filing a version bump request?</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect6">What information do I need to post with my bug report?</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect7">What if I am not running on an x86 kit?</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect8">When should I open a new bug rather than comment on an old one?</uri></li>
		</ol>
                </body>
	</section>
        <section>
                <title>Which Product/Component should I pick?</title>
                <body><p>You should always select the "Gentoo Linux" product and the "Games" component when filing any bug for an ebuild in <c>games-*</c> or <c>dev-games</c>.  This ensures that the bug is immediately assigned to the Games team, which allows for us to get the bug as quickly as possible.</p></body>
        </section>
	<section>
		<title>What severity should I use for version bumps or new game requests?</title>
		<body><p>Requests for having an ebuild bumped to the latest version or to have an ebuild for a new game written or added to the portage tree should always be filed with a severity of "enhancement" since these are not bugs affecting functionality.</p></body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Why shouldn't I mark a Games bug as "blocker"?</title>
		<body><p>This one is not only quite common, but also quite simple to answer.  A bug in a Games ebuild will never cause your system to be destroyed or otherwise unusable.  Games are for entertainment purposes and as such, immediately get a lower priority than more important aspects of a Gentoo system, such as the toolchain.</p></body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>How long should I wait before filing a version bump request?</title>
		<body><p>We typically follow the development of many of the more popular games.  In many cases, we maintain contact with the authors and are active in the community.  We are generally aware of new events in the Linux gaming community before the public.  A good rule of thumb is to wait at least 48 hours before posting an enhancement request for a new game or a version upgrade to an existing game.  This allows the developers time to work bugs which are possibly of higher priority than the game request.  Remember once again that all of us have other functions in Gentoo which usually take a higher priority.</p></body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>What information do I need to post with my bug report?</title>
		<body><p>As in any bug report, you should <b>always</b> post the output of <c>emerge --info</c> into every bug report that you submit.  If you think there are other pertinent pieces of information that could possibly help us in tracking down the bug, then be sure to include that information, too.  Anything you can provide us could possibly be the one piece of information that we need to accurately and quickly resolve the bug.  This could include information such as your method of installation in a CD-based install, or the situation in which the bug occurs.</p></body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>What if I am not running on an x86 kit?</title>
		<body><p>You should be sure to make note of your using a non-x86 architecture.  You should also set the platform to your appropriate platform.  Last, you should add the architecture team alias to the CC list for the bug.  This is the architecture name at gentoo.org, ex. <c>amd64@gentoo.org</c>.  This ensures that not only the Games team, but also the developers on the architecture team which your problem is occuring get all of the information as quickly as possible.</p></body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>When should I open a new bug rather than comment on an old one?</title>
		<body><p>You should always open a new bug unless your problem is producing the exact same error, you have tried the workarounds or fixes in the ebuild, and your error is occurring on a same-versioned ebuild.  Do not make comments on an already resolved bug if you are seeing a similar problem in a newer version of a game, as this makes it hard to track individual problems.</p></body>
	</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Want to help?</title>
<section>
<body>
	<p>If you want to get involved with improving Gentoo's gaming experience,
	we'd like to hear from you! The main thing you'll want to do is be active
	on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo's Bugzilla</uri>. Also
	please join games project members in #gentoo-games on irc.freenode.net.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
