<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<news gentoo="yes" category="gentoo">

<!-- Enter your name here -->
<poster>quantumsummers</poster>

<!-- Date to be displayed - usually the GWN release date -->
<date>2010-05-07</date>

<!-- Title of the news item - don't forget to change the date -->
<title>2010 Gentoo Foundation Inc. Secretary's Report</title>
<body>

<!-- Alter to your own likings -->
<p>
<b>Community Milestones</b>
</p>

<p>
Gentoo celebrated 10 Years of compiling with a new livedvd release and
screenshot competition. The so-called Gentoo-Ten project continues to release
regular updates to the live disks. Original artwork for the release was
contributed by Ben Stedman.
</p>

<p>
<b>501(c)(3) and SFLC</b>
</p>

<p>
Towards the goal of tax-exempt status with IRS as a non-profit corporation and
as well as the goal of maintaining general legal council for the Foundation and
its members the board has engaged, pro bono, the Software Freedom Law Center.
</p>

<p>
<b>Infra Purchases</b>
</p>

<p>
Recently, one of Gentoo's long time sponsors underwent significant corporate
restructuring that necessitated the migration of several key infrastructure
services. To accomplish this the Foundation purchased 6 Atom-based server
systems. These systems are hosted at the Oregon State University Open Source
Lab. Thanks to the OSL for supporting Gentoo! 
</p>

<p>
<b>Foundation Web Space</b>
</p>

<p>
In the endeavour to communicate better with developers, our members,and the user
community, we have added to the Foundation web space on gentoo.org the following
pages:
</p>

<p><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/motions/index.xml">Foundation
		Meeting Motions</uri></p>
<p><uri
		link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/minutes/2010/index.xml">Foundation
		2010 Meeting Agenda and Logs</uri></p> 
<p><uri
		link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/minutes09/index.xml">Foundation
		2009 Meeting Agenda and Logs</uri></p>

<p>
<b>Elections and Membership</b>
</p>

<p>
As of the recording date established for the Trustee Election 31 January 2010 we have 217 Members. 
</p>

<p>
<b>Gentoo Foundation Trustees 2010-01</b>
</p>

<p>
Previous Trustees re-elected, running unopposed in the Gentoo Foundation Trustees 2010 election.
</p>

<p>
<b>Gentoo Foundation Referendum 2009-01</b>
</p>

<p>
This election was held to determine whether or not the Foundation should accept financial contributions from organizations that use Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
53 votes cast yielding a turnout of 25&#37;.
</p>

<ul>
<li>46 yes</li>
<li>6 no</li>
<li>1 present</li>
</ul>

</body>
</news>
