<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/kde/kde-stable/Attic/index.xml,v 1.1 2012/09/03 17:50:28 creffett Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/desktop/kde/stable/index.xml" lang="en">
<title>KDE Stable Team</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="creffett@gentoo.org">Chris Reffett</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The objective of the kde-stable subproject is to test KDE releases and release candidates thoroughly before stabilization.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2012-08-21</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Currently, most KDE team members run unstable versions of KDE, leading to only basic
testing being conducted on KDE packages by arch testers during stabilization. This
subproject remedies that lack of testing by creating a specific group of testers,
comprised of both developers and non-developers, who will run a stabilization
candidate version of KDE and test it thoroughly before the stabilization process begins.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>What you get</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
In addition to the warm, fuzzy feeling inside that comes from contributing to
Gentoo, members of kde-stable will be given +v (auto-voice) in #gentoo-kde. Additionally,
if members wish to contribute directly to the KDE team overlay, participating and
contributing to the kde-stable project can help demonstrate trustworthiness to 
KDE team members.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>What to do</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Members of the subproject will be directed to start testing a particular KDE version
when a bug is filed in preparation for stabilization, and to use that version
in a normal day-to-day manner in order to find bugs.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Requirements</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Members of the kde-stable team do not need to be developers, but they need to use
KDE on a routine basis and run a stable environment with only the requested KDE
version keyworded as testing.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Participating</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Currently under discussion; those interested in joining should contact <mail 
link="ago@gentoo.org">ago</mail> or <mail link="creffett@gentoo.org">
creffett</mail>. Subject to change in the future.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Current release</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Members should be testing KDE 4.9.1 at present.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
