<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-policy.xml,v 1.21 2006/07/08 17:21:18 neysx Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="doc-policy.xml">

<title>Gentoo Linux Documentation Policy</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John P. Davis</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="dberkholz@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholz</mail>
</author>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<abstract>
This document contains the Gentoo Documentation Policy, which is the
base document which all Gentoo Documentation developers and
Contributors should know and exercise.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>3.17</version>
<date>2005-12-22</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Linux Documentation team aspires to create exceptionally
professional documentation that is immediately clear and concise to the
end user. In order to fulfill this goal, we have very specific rules and
guidelines that <e>all</e> documentation must go through prior to
dissemination on our website, or elsewhere.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Covered Topics</title>
<body>

<p>
This policy will cover the following topics:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Documentation Project Team Organization</li>
<li>Documentation Guidelines</li>
<li>Documentation Team Recruitment</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Documentation Project Team Organization</title>
<section>
<title>Organization</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project Team is split into several smaller teams
that work in tandem with each other. Each smaller team represents an active
development team of a Gentoo Documentation Subproject.
</p>

<!--
<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project is strategically led by a top-level Manager
as required by the <uri link="/doc/en/management-structure.xml">Gentoo
Management Structure</uri>. This document also describes the responsibilities
of the Strategic Manager with respect to Gentoo Linux.
</p>
-->

<p>
For day-to-day managerial tasks, the Gentoo Documentation Project has an
Operational Manager. This person keeps track of all short-term tasks
related to documentation. The Operational Manager and Strategic Manager can be
one and the same if the Strategic Manager wishes so.
</p>

<p>
Currently these positions are taken by the following people:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Position</th>
  <th>Developer Name</th>
  <th>Developer Nick</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Strategic Manager</ti>
  <ti>Sven Vermeulen</ti>
  <ti><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">swift</mail></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Operational Manager</ti>
  <ti>Xavier Neys</ti>
  <ti><mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">neysx</mail></ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Every subproject has a Strategic Manager of its own, and may have an
Operational Manager if deemed appropriate. His responsibilities to the Gentoo
Documentation Project (GDP) are listed in the <e>Manager responsibilities</e>
section of the <uri
link="/doc/en/management-structure.xml#doc_chap1_sect5">Gentoo Management
Structure</uri> document.
</p>

<p>
Every subproject of the Gentoo Documentation Team is listed on the
<uri link="/proj/en/gdp/">GDP Webpage</uri>, along with their respective
Strategic Managers.
</p>

<p>
The decision on adding a subproject is in the hands of the Strategic Manager.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation Project Team Members</title>
<body>

<p>
Every member of the Gentoo Documentation Project must be subscribed to
the <mail link="gentoo-doc-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail>
mailing list. This mailing list will be used to discuss all
documentation-related issues. This mailing list is open to all interested
parties, developer or not.
</p>

<p>
Every member of the Gentoo Documentation Project must be part of the
<mail link="docs-team@gentoo.org">docs-team@gentoo.org</mail> alias.  This
alias is <e>only</e> used by <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri> to inform the documentation
team about bugs regarding the Gentoo Documentation. You can add yourself by
editing <path>/var/mail/alias/misc/docs-team</path> on dev.gentoo.org.
</p>

<p>
Members of the Gentoo Documentation Team should be available at
<c>#gentoo-doc</c> on <uri link="http://www.freenode.net">irc.freenode.net</uri>
whenever they are online.
</p>

<p>
Depending on the assignment or responsibilities, a member may have limited CVS
access to <c>cvs.gentoo.org</c>. Full CVS access is restricted to Gentoo
Developers. Read-only CVS access may be granted to recruits.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation Translation Teams</title>
<body>

<p>
Every language should be backed up by an official Translation Team. This
team is led by a <e>Lead Translator</e> and perhaps a <e>Follow-On Lead
Translator</e>, who both have CVS commit access. If for any reason the
<e>Lead Translator</e> cannot perform his duties, the <e>Follow-On Lead
Translator</e> is in charge. If the <e>Follow-On</e> is unavailable, the
mentor(s) is/are in charge of the language.
</p>

<p>
If a translated document for an unsupported language is contributed, the Gentoo
Documentation Team will not publish it officially. Such documents shall not be
linked to the website until an official Translation Team of that language is
formed.
</p>

<p>
When a language is officially supported, but the team does not have any
members willing to take on the responsibilities of the <e>Lead
Translator</e>, all links to the documents will be removed from the site.
However, the documents will stay available in case the language becomes
officially supported again.
</p>

<p>
For more information Gentoo document translations, please consult the
<uri link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/translators-howto.xml">
Translators Howto for Gentoo Documentation</uri> and the
<uri link="/proj/en/gdp/international.xml">
GDP Internationalisation Subproject</uri> page.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Documentation Guidelines</title>
<section>
<title>Legal Issues</title>
<body>

<p>
Every document published by the Gentoo Documentation Project must be
licensed by the <uri
link="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/">Creative Commons
Attribution-ShareAlike License</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Every document must have the following tag inside its GuideXML
source code between the <c>&lt;/abstract&gt;</c> and the <c>&lt;version&gt;</c>
tags:
</p>

<pre caption = "Licensing notice for the Gentoo Documentation">
&lt;/abstract&gt;
<i>
&lt;!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license --&gt;
&lt;!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 --&gt;
&lt;license/&gt;
</i>
&lt;version&gt;...&lt;/version&gt;
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bugs and Updates</title>
<body>

<p>
Every bug reported on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>
should be handled as fast as possible. If a bug cannot be handled
in a timely fashion, the reporter of that bug should be informed about
this using a comment on the bug, and the bug should be registered in the
<uri link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/metadoc-guide.xml">metadoc.xml</uri> file, if
applicable. The Strategic or Operational Manager may decide that a bug has a
higher priority and should be addressed ahead any other task the assignee
is responsible for.
</p>

<p>
Whenever a Gentoo Documentation Team member takes care of a bug, he or
she should assign the bug to herself/himself, but make sure that
<c>docs-team@gentoo.org</c> is on the Cc-list. A bug may not be taken away from
another Gentoo Documentation Team member without their approval; unless consent
has been received from the Operational Manager.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Document Development</title>
<body>

<p>
Every Gentoo Documentation Team may handle documentation development as it sees
fit. However, when the document is finished, it should be transformed into
<uri link="/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">GuideXML</uri> and made available on the
Gentoo CVS infrastructure. It must also be registered in the
<uri link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/metadoc-guide.xml">metadoc.xml</uri> file if
applicable.
</p>

<p>
When a new document is started or a big change is needed, a bug should be filed
at <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>
concerning the development of this document. If there is already a bug
in the database that requests a change to the documentation, a new bug
does not have to be filed. Grammatical, syntactical or small changes
do not require a bug to be filed on <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri> as well.
</p>

<p>
All changes in contents of the document, except for typo fixes in text
itself or in the comments to code listings, should lead to version
number (and date) increase. Note that the change of a Code Listings should
definitely cause an increase of the version number and date.
</p>

<p>
All changes in XML formatting should lead to version (and date) bumps only in
case the layout of the document changes.
</p>

<p>
Whether or not to increment the major version number instead of minor version
number or other is up to the editor.
</p>

<p>
Every update of a translation should copy the new version information
verbatim from the master English document so fully synchronised
translations have the same version information.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reviewing and Committing</title>
<body>

<p>
To maintain a high-paced documentation development cycle, technical or
intrusive changes to documents can be propagated immediately to the document.
This is allowed only <e>if</e> the editor is absolutely confident the changes
are functional. If you are not absolutely confident (for instance because a
user has told you how to fix it but you cannot verify yourself), have the
changes reviewed by a Gentoo Developer that can verify the changes are apt.
</p>

<p>
High-volume, technical or intrusive changes must be accompanied by a bug report
on <uri>http://bugs.gentoo.org</uri>. This bug number <e>must</e> be mentioned
in the CVS log to allow backtracing of changes.
</p>

<p>
If a bugfix includes changes to content as well as internal coding changes,
both changes must be committed separately. This allows translators to focus
on the relevant changes regarding content and ignore the coding changes.
</p>

<p>
If the document in question is a translation, the <e>Lead Translator</e> of the
affected language is responsible for the document. Only the
<e>Lead Translator</e> may commit the document to the CVS repository. However,
if the <e>Lead Translator</e> is currently "in training", the trainee's mentor
should commit the changes.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sanctions</title>
<body>

<p>
Malicious conduct by developers has never been an issue. However, it should be
noted that documentation developers that misuse their position by
</p>

<ul>
  <li>deliberately providing wrong information to users or developers</li>
  <li>deliberately writing flawed documentation</li>
  <li>deliberately corrupting documents</li>
  <li>
    deliberately go against the decisions made policy-wise or through a
    consensus-model on the Gentoo Documentation mailinglist
  </li>
  <li>
    not performing at all for a long time without informing the GDP, and without
    replying to the Operational Manager's request for a status update
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
will be reported to the <uri link="/proj/en/devrel/">Gentoo Developer
Relations</uri> project.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Documentation Team Recruitment</title>
<section>
<title>Contributors, Authors, Translators</title>
<body>

<p>
Everyone interested in contributing documentation, editing existing
documentation, writing new documentation or translating documentation is
welcome to join the team. There are no rules or strings attached to
this. Just make sure you are subscribed to <c>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</c>,
and you have fully read this policy and understand it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Recruitment Process</title>
<body>

<p>
The Documentation Project has a strict recruitment process outlined below.
This process can not be deviated from in any circumstance. We have opted for
this recruitment process to assure ourselves that the recruit is well informed
about the Gentoo Documentation Policy and the Gentoo Coding Style. It has proven
to be quite effective even though many contributors see it as a too large burden
to cross.
</p>

<p>
This recruitment process is meant only for requests to the Gentoo Documentation
Repository through CVS. Being listed as the maintainer or Point-Of-Contact for a
certain document or range of documents is granted by a simple request to the
Operational Manager or Project Lead.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Phase 1: Contributions</title>
<body>

<p>
No recruitment process starts without investigating the contributions done
already to the Gentoo Documentation Project. The number of contributions must be
large to assure a good knowledge of GuideXML, Coding Style and policy. The
contribution period must be large as well to inform the contributor about the
time-consuming position and pressure the application involves.
</p>

<p>
The number of contributions and period over which the contributions should be
made depends on the position which the contributor solicits for. Although it is
difficult to write down these measurements in numbers, the following table
should give a general overview. Final decision however lays in the hands of the
Operational Manager.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Position</th>
  <th>Minimal Activity</th>
  <th>Minimal Period</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Full-time Developer</ti>
  <ti>2 updates per week</ti>
  <ti>1 month</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Part-time Developer</ti>
  <ti>4 updates per month</ti>
  <ti>1 month</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
An update constitutes a non-trivial update to any documentation, translation or
otherwise, completely written by the contributor and committed after review by
any existing documentation developer. The period is fixed - increasing the
contributions does not decrease the period. Also, we don't average the
contributions over time to make sure the contributor doesn't give a contribution
burst, and then waits until the Phase is over.
</p>

<p>
Without this phase we can not know if the contributor understands what it takes
to be a documentation developer. The validation of this activity happens through
bugzilla reports.
</p>

<p>
Any request for CVS access that does not allow a development activity as written
down in the aforementioned table will not be taken into account.
</p>

<p>
If you feel that you have shown sufficient amount of contributions, contact
the Operational Manager of the Gentoo Documentation Project. He
will ask you for your coordinates and other information, and then arrange
for the next phase to be started.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Phase 2: Read-Only CVS Access</title>
<body>

<p>
During phase 2, the recruit is given read-only access to the Gentoo
Documentation Repository, allowing him to generate commit-ready patches for
the tree. During this period, which is roughly the same as the aforementioned
table, his patches are not edited by a documentation developer anymore, but
are either committed as-is or refused. The recruit is also assigned to a
full-time documentation developer (the mentor) which will guide him through
these last phases.
</p>

<p>
The quality of the contributions are in this phase most important - every patch
that does not follow the Documentation Policy, Coding Style or other guideline
that affects the document is refused.
</p>

<p>
During this period, you:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    are advised to learn about Gentoo's inner workings.
    This is required as you will be asked later on to answer Gentoo's <uri
    link="/proj/en/devrel/quiz/staff-quiz.txt">Staffing Quiz</uri>.
  </li>
  <li>
    will be asked to fill in the <uri
    link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-quiz.xml">Gentoo Documentation Project
    Quiz</uri>. You need to successfully pass this entire quiz (all questions)
    before you can continue with the next Phase.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Phase 3: Gentoo Recruitment</title>
<body>

<p>
When Phase 2 is finished, the Operational Manager will contact <uri
link="/proj/en/devrel">Developer Relations</uri> and give a final "Go!" for the
Gentoo recruitment process after which you will be given a Gentoo e-mail
address and be appointed to one or more subprojects.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
