<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>knowledge base</name>
<longname>Gentoo Knowledge Base</longname>
<date>2006-05-13</date>

<description>
To improve the users their experience, a Gentoo Knowledge Base provides answers
to many specific questions and problems they might encounter. The KBase project
develops and maintains this knowledge base.
</description>

<longdescription>

<p><b>Goal</b></p>

<p>
The Gentoo Knowledge Base informs the users about tasks, problems or features he
is looking for. It can be queried using natural language questions and easily
adjusted by developers in charge of the topic. The
knowledge base does not inform users about bugs that are fixed with new releases
(or will be fixed) and will not contain documentation guides.
</p>

<p><b>Rationale</b></p>

<p>
When we look at the software projects today, we find that information has
broadened beyond documentation and the detail level has deepend to an almost
individual, precise answer for every question. It is no longer reasonable to
suggest that documentation is sufficient to succesfully aide users with
exploring the world of software use. Documentation is a (and perhaps even the
most) powerful tool to guide users through complex topics. Yet documentation
mainly focuses on a large reader base. Whenever topics become too detailed,
they become difficult to fit inside a certain hierarchical structure.
</p>

<p>
Such a structure is required by users who need to find documentation quickly. A
major help is, of course, a search feature that spans all documentation.
However, when hundreds of (seemingly similar yet different) topics are 
available, many search technologies fail. Natural language queries often express
more details than a regular, boolean expression, but not that many search
technologies allow such queries.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Knowledge Base is an effort to extend the information Gentoo delivers
with precise answers to specific questions. Each topic in the repository must be
owned by at least one knowledgeable developer, written in a structured manner
and should leave no room for different interpretations. General topics must
provide direct links to the documentation.
</p>

</longdescription>

<!-- Developer Roles -->
<!-- (with CVS access) -->
<dev role="lead" description="Project Manager">swift</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="Developer">anpereir</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="Developer">nightmorph</dev>

<!-- Project Specific Pages/Documentation 
<resource link="foo/bar.xml">title</resource>
-->

<!-- Subprojects
<subproject ref="blabla.xml"/>
-->

<extrachapter>
<title>Participate</title>
<section>
<title>Can someone participate?</title>
<body>

<p>
Definitely, and this is actually most wanted. Although the KB will be maintained
by developers, this doesn't mean users are left in the dark. Therefore we have
started a mailinglist (<c>gentoo-kbase@gentoo.org</c>) where everyone can join
the discussions and help with the development of the knowledge base.
</p>

<p>
Once the knowledge base is in place, we will be needing lots and lots of eyes to
double-check the topics. So be sure to join the mailinglist! You can subscribe
by sending a mail to <c>gentoo-kbase+subscribe@gentoo.org</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
