<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<project>
<name>releng</name>
<longname>Release Engineering</longname>

<description>
The official top-level project focused on coordinating and improving the
creation of official releases of Gentoo Linux.
</description>

<longdescription>
Release Engineering ("releng") is the official Gentoo top-level project focused
on coordinating and improving the creation of official releases of Gentoo Linux.
</longdescription>

<dev role="lead" description="releng lead, catalyst">drobbins</dev>
<dev description="catalyst">zhen</dev>
<dev description="x86 guy">seemant</dev>
<dev description="AMD64, general assistance/coordination">avenj</dev>
<dev description="livecd, genkernel, catalyst">livewire</dev>
<dev description="store">cybersystem</dev>

<subproject ref="/proj/en/releng/catalyst/index.xml" inheritresources="yes"/>
<extraproject name="store" lead="drobbins">
The <uri link="http://store.gentoo.org">Gentoo Store</uri> is not an official Release Engineering sub-project, but the Store and
Release Engineering coordinate very closely. All official Gentoo Linux releases are made available
in the Gentoo Store. In addition, all maintenance releases are made available in the Gentoo Store as
soon as possible, so that customers can benefit from the latest fixes and improvements.
</extraproject>

<extraproject name="build/research hardware" lead="drobbins">
Release Engineering maintains its own set of hardware that is used for the building of releases, as well as the
porting of Gentoo Linux to new architectures. Currently, this hardware consists of a dual-CPU 900Mhz zx6000 Itanium 2 system with 10GB of
RAM on extended loan from HP and an NForce3-based AMD64 system donated by NVIDIA. Both systems are running Gentoo Linux, and
access is provided to these systems for those interested in assisting the "amd64" and "ia64" ports, as well as those in the
general Linux/free software community who need access to these architectures to perform porting/QA work. If you are a developer
(Gentoo Linux or otherwise) who could benefit from access to these boxes, please contact <mail>drobbins@gentoo.org</mail>.</extraproject>

<goals>
The goal of Release Engineering is to continually improve the quality,
timeliness and overall procedures for creating official Gentoo Linux releases,
as well as acting as the official coordinators for creating new Gentoo Linux
releases. This project is very much focused on ensuring that the initial
quality of every official release is as high as possible, and that the "from
CD" experience is as positive for as many of our users as possible.
</goals>			

<extrachapter position="resources">
	<title>What consititutes a release?</title>
		<section>
		<body>
		<p>
			Every release consists of an offical version number, such as "1.4", and a number of architectures
			that are officially supported. Part of the Gentoo Linux release policy is to generally not hold up a
			release if certain less-popular architectures are not quite ready; therefore, an official release
			of Gentoo Linux may not offer builds for all the architectures for which there are ongoing development
			efforts.
		</p><p>
			In addition, every architecture that is part of an official release includes the following
			components:
		
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>stage tarballs</li>
			<li>portage snapshot</li>
			<li>livecd runtime environment</li>
			<li>pre-built packages</li>
			<li>installation documentation</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
		</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="top">
	<title>News/Release Roadmap</title>
		<section>
		<body>
		<table>
		<tr>
			<th>Date</th>
			<th>Version</th>
			<th>Phase</th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<th>14 July 2003</th>
			<ti>1.4</ti>
			<ti>completed (x86, ppc)</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<th>11 Sept 2003</th>
			<ti>1.4 maintenance release 1</ti>
			<ti>completed (x86)</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>30 Nov 2003</ti>
			<ti>1.4.1</ti>
			<ti>planned x86 rebuild, possible AMD64 release (with 2.6 kernel)</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>15 Feb 2004</ti>
			<ti>1.5</ti>
			<ti>2.6 kernel support, likely IA64 release</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>TBA</ti>
			<ti>1.6</ti>
			<ti>Optional NPTL support, possibly other things</ti>
		</tr>
</table>
<p>As of 4 Oct 2003, there has been one maintenanace release for 1.4 for x86, and a maintenance
		release for PowerPC is currently being created and will be available soon. There may be one additional maintenance release for x86, and then
		efforts will be directed towards the official 1.4.1 release.</p>
		<p>1.4.1 tenative release goals are as follows:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>If possible, have it ready in early Jan 2004</li>
		<li>Full bug-fixed rebuild of x86 livecd runtime environment using new stager scripts</li>
		<li>AMD64 architecture/NVIDIA NForce3 hardware support if possible</li>
		<li>More standardization of release procedure (file lists of CD contents on releng site, official release notes)</li>
		<li>Snapshot taken late December</li>
		<li>Get additional architectures supported: Alpha, Sparc</li>
		</ul>
		<p>The 1.4.1 release goals are fluid and are subject to change. In general, we are not planning anything
		particularly ambitious and are focusing primarily on improving the quality of our releases.</p>
		
		</body>
		</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
