<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>December 23rd, 2002</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
	<mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
	<mail link="nesta@iceburg.net">Brice Burgess</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
	<mail link="carlos@pubbawup.net">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
        <mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
	<mail link="david@phrixus.net">David Narayan</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
	<mail link="plate@gol.com">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
	<mail link="mail@psharp.uklinux.net">Peter Sharp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="lanark@lanark.com.ar">Lanark</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of December 23rd, 2002.</abstract>
<version>Volume 1, Issue 1</version>
<date>23 Dec 2002</date>
<chapter>
	<title>Official Launch of the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
	<body>
	<p>
	Welcome to the inaugural issue of the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter.  
	</p>
	<p>
	The GWN was started as a way of giving the Gentoo community one source of information about the Gentoo Linux project.  The GWN will summarize issues and discussions from the community, as well as major news items and announcements, as well as security vulnerabilities, bugs and changes to the Portage tree.  As we gather <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> from the user community, we will continue to add features and additional areas of coverage to the GWN, with the ultimate goal being to make this newsletter your main source of information about Gentoo Linux.  
	</p>
	<p>
	The GWN would not be possible without the contributions of various members of the Gentoo community.  We are actively seeking additional volunteers to help make the GWN even better.  Please see the end of this newsletter for information about how you can help. 
	</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">Gentoo Stable Project Announcement</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3">Portage Snafu Causes Confusion in the Community</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect4">CVSup Under Consideration as Replacement for rsync</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect5">Policy for CVS Ebuilds in Gentoo</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Gentoo Stable Project Announcement</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		<mail link="blizzy@gentoo.org">Maik Schreiber</mail> writes:
		</p>
		<p>
		<e>In light of ~arch masking and the result of more and more ebuilds becoming stacked on the "testing" pile without being removed from
there, I took the time to whip up a new web site that is designed to become a central point to remedy that. </e>
		</p>
		<p>

			The result is a <uri link="http://gentoo-stable.iq-computing.de">Web site</uri> that lists each and every ebuild in the Portage tree.  Using this system, users can "mark" a package as running properly on their system.  They can also enter comments, such as "fails when using gcc 3.2.1" or other specific information.  The developers can then look at the marked packages and, when they feel comfortable that enough users are marking a package as "stable", remove the ~arch masking.
		
		With enough Gentoo users providing solid, consistent feedback on the various ebuilds, this system will go a long way towards reducing the number of "problem" ebuilds and improving the overall quality of the Portage tree.  Users are encouraged to participate and provide feedback to <mail link="blizzy@gentoo.org">Maik</mail>.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Portage Snafu Causes Confusion in the Community</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Recently, an upgraded version of Portage was released (2.0.45-r6) that contained a signficant bug causing <c>gcc</c> to hang when executed. As one might guess, this caused a fair amount of confusion and problems within the Gentoo Linux community. Fortunately, Seemant Kulleen (Gentoo Linux Development Manager) was quick to post some <uri link="http://cvs.gentoo.org/~seemant/">instructions</uri> to solve the issues and the new version of Portage was quickly rolled back to the older, stable version.
		More importantly, this bug helped to identify the need for further definition of the Portage release process to ensure that proper QA is enforced. As a result, Daniel Robbins updated the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/policy.xml">Gentoo Linux Development Policy</uri> with a new chapter dealing specifically with future releases of Portage and informed all developers of this policy clarification.    
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>CVSup Under Consideration as Replacement for rsync</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			There has been some discussion in the Gentoo developer community about migrating away from Portage's dependency on rsync and instead utilizing <uri link="http://www.cvsup.org">CVSup</uri>.  Currently used in FreeBSD's ports system, CVSup offers a few distinct advantages, as well as challenges, over rsync:
 		<ul>
			<li>Local changes will be preserved if you want them to, just like anoncvs. Anyone who's ever had their package.mask file overwritten by an <c>emerge rsync</c> will appreciate this feature.</li>
			<li>CVSup is faster and more efficient than rsync. This means that CVSup can improve the efficiency of our Portage mirroring system.</li>
			<li>CVSup's threaded design allows for file transfer begin almost immediately, unlike rsync which must build a complete file list first. Surprisingly, CVSup uses the rsync algorithm (which is very efficient) internally to synchronize individual files, but uses a better approach than rsync when coordinating the updates of large numbers of files.</li>
			<li>CVSup is written in Modula 3, which means that transitioning to CVSup will require some non-trivial steps to ensure that we have proper Modula 3 support on all architectures.</li>
			<li>CVSup also has the added psychological benefit of making FreeBSD users feel more at home.</li>
 		</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Policy for CVS Ebuilds in Gentoo</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		A recurrent theme in the Gentoo Linux community is the issue of CVS ebuilds -- those ebuilds that install a CVS snapshot of software, or those that use the <path>cvs.eclass</path> to install a "live" version of a CVS tree. These ebuilds are popular for things like Phoenix nightly builds. Daniel Robbins has updated the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/policy.xml">Gentoo Linux Development Policy</uri> to reflect Gentoo's stance on CVS ebuilds (both "snapshot" and "live") in the official Portage tree.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Security</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect2">GLSA: exim</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect3">GLSA: mysql</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect4">GLSA: squirrelmail</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect5">GLSA: fetchmail</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect6">New Security Bug Reports</uri></li>
			</ul> 
		</p>
		</body>

	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: exim</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Exim has a format string bug in its daemon that permits a privileged admin user to perform a root exploit.
                The exploit has been demonstrated.
			<ul>
				<li>Severity: low - local root exploit available to exim admin user.</li>

				<li>Packages Affected: exim</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge exim.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=26580">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>GLSA: mysql</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		MySQL has two vulnerabilties, the first related to a heap overflow and the other permitting writing nulls to
                 arbitrary memory addresses.  The vulnerabilities permit a remote server crash exploit. 
                 No exploit currently reported in the wild.  
			<ul>
				<li>Severity: moderate - DOS attack (server crash).</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: mysql</li>

				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge mysql.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=26444">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://security.e-matters.de/advisories/042002.html">Advisory</uri></li> 
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>

		<title>GLSA: squirrelmail</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Squirrelmail exposes a cross-site scripting vulnerability that permits spoofed information in input for filter_dir
                and mailbox.  This permits an xss attack on the site.  A sample exploit has been published.
			<ul>
				<li>Severity: moderate to high  - permits remote scripting</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: squirrelmail</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge squirrelmail.</li>

                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=26443">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://f0kp.iplus.ru/bz/008.txt">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: fetchmail</title>

		<body>
		<p>
		Fetchmail has a buffer overflow in the default configuration that permits a remote DOS or arbitrary code execution
                as the user fetchmail operates as.  No reported exploit in the wild.
			<ul>
				<li>Severity: high - remote exploitation by the fetchmail user (potentially root).</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: fetchmail</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge fetchmail.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=26442">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>

                                <li><uri link="http://security.e-matters.de/advisories/052002.html">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New Security Bug Reports</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		There are several recent new security bugs posted to bugzilla.  Links to the pertinent bugs are found below:
			<ul>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=10421">10421 - glibc</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=11537">11537 - cyrus-imap</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=11686">11686 - openldap</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12186">12186 - cyrus-sasl</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12187">12187 - wget</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12188">12188 - canna</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12190">12190 - perl</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12447">12447 - libpng</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12450">12450 - cups</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Heard In The Community</title>
	<section>
		<title>Web Forums</title>
		<body>
		<p><b>Glibc 2.3 stable and painfree</b></p>
		<p>For a week it looked as if compiling the freshly unmasked glibc 2.3 free of errors was like 
winning in a lottery. Now things are definitely looking up, the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=25727">highly entertaining thread</uri> has been made unsticky, 
and the general sentiment seems to be that less aggressive compiler flags may well be the only
thing you need to do to make it happen.</p>
		
		<p><b>Distributed Compiling</b></p>
    	<p>There has been much discussion on the use of <uri link="http://distcc.samba.org">distcc</uri> with Gentoo. Given that Gentoo is a &quot;compile-from-source&quot; distribution, distributed compiles would greatly speed up installation times. However, distcc also has some problems that many alert Gentoo users have pointed out.
		</p>
		<p>The following threads reference distcc and its uses:
		<ul><li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=16455">distcc -
		it works (quick but dirty...)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=26740">Attempting
		to install on a devilishly underpowered computer</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=26945">Automated
		emerge with distcc!</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=22092">Programs
		that can't get emerged with distcc &amp; tips</uri></li></ul>
		</p>
		
		<p><b>Gentoo HURD? Gentoo Mach? Gentoo BSD?</b></p>

        <p>The idea of a non-Linux kernel as an additional Gentoo variant has occasionally popped up in the forums before, but the past two weeks have seen a remarkable boost of popularity for the HURD and other microkernels. These threads mostly deal with the question whether there should be a Gentoo HURD or not, but the top one includes an interesting discussion of the underlying microkernel architecture.</p>
        <p>
        <ul><li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=25401">An introduction to the Linux kernel</uri></li>
        <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=26923">HURD or Mach kernel for Gentoo?</uri></li>
        <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=25172">Gentoo Gnu/HURD?</uri></li></ul>
        </p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>gentoo-user</title>
		<body>
		<p><b>Gentoo 'Stable'</b></p>
		<p>
		Rainer Groesslinger noted his worries on the current condition of Gentoo
		'stable'. To most, it appears that Gentoo's stable branch is veering in the
		direction of Debian; stable, yet immensley outdated. While this may be desirable
		for certain production servers, it leaves desktop users in the dust. Rod Roark 
		implies that because Gentoo is source-centered, it has the ability to quickly
		implement package upgrades. Why then is the 'latest and greatest' stable version
		of Mozilla 1.2.1 not in Gentoo's stable branch? A solution hasn't been reached,
		however everyone involved agrees that using 
		<uri link="http://gentoo-stable.iq-computing.de/">http://gentoo-stable.iq-computing.de/</uri>
		is a good start. If you haven't already, please familarize yourself with the 
		'Gentoo Linux Stable' <uri link="http://gentoo-stable.iq-computing.de/">site.</uri>
		</p>

		<p><b>The Right Stuff</b></p>
		<p> 
		For those of you who aren't sure if you've "perfected" your system,
		Bruce Nourish posted an excellent response to a question about cron
		and log daemons. After all, it is the flexibility that Gentoo encourages
		which sets it apart from its more mundane competitors. In short, he recommends
		dcron and syslog-ng. Find out why by following this 
		<uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/17679/">thread.</uri>
		</p>

		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>gentoo-dev</title>
		<body>
		<p><b>Portage and Quality Assurance.</b></p>
		<p>
		The portage-2.0.45-r6 ebuild contains a bug that 
		prevents it from working when installed. Some users expressed that
		new versions of Portage, as a fundamental part of 
		the Gentoo infrastructure, should go through a more strict
		quality assurance (QA) process before allowing users to 
		emerge it. Daniel Robbins (Chief Architect of Gentoo Linux)
		posted his <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6160">view</uri> of this incident.
		</p>

		<p><b>New MIPS Gentoo Port Effort Started.</b></p>
		<p>  
		Nicholas Wourms wrote a
		<uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6045">call</uri> for participants in a new effort to port
		Gentoo to the MIPS architecture. <e>"[...] I've  
		been working on it over the last few days.  I've almost 
		finished getting a netboot and cd image prepared, after 
		which I plan to start working on ebuilds.  So, I  wanted to 
		test the waters and see if anyone with a MIPS box (not PS/2) 
		was interested in helping and/or testing this once I have it 
		ready."</e>. Looks like 
		Jeff Utter posted a similar
		<uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/2080">call</uri> six months ago!
		</p>
		<p><b>Suggested Improvement for Portage.</b></p>
		<p>
		Stefano Peluchetti
		filed a 
		<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12184">bug</uri> 
		in which he proposes a
		new functionality in Portage that will allow 
		<c>emerge -p package_name</c> to output not only information
		about the dependencies of a given package
		but also the use flags that affect the compilation of the 
		package and its dependencies! Anyone dare to implement it? ;-)
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>International Gentoo</title>
	<section>
		<title>Quite Literally: Phoenix From the Ashes</title>
		<body>
    	<p>The computer center and networking at the University of Twente in the Netherlands were almost totally consumed by a fire that raged
through a building on campus four weeks ago. It took the admins a while to restore everything, but
they finally have all network services up and running again, including a
comparatively powerful Gentoo rsync mirror, reports <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=26004">The DJ</uri>, not entirely displeased
with the fact that they now have brand new hardware to base their FTP servers on...</p>
<figure link="http://www.utwente.nl/nieuws/brand-twrc/en/engels1.doc/index.html.jpg" short="An arsonist set fire to this building on campus" caption="An arsonist set fire to this building on campus" />
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Portage, Ports and Other Packagers...</title>
		<body>
		<p>When it comes to Unix vs. Linux, Japan is one of the rare countries
		where BSD may have a significant headstart. Last Wednesday, Japanese
		Gentoo evangelist <uri link="http://pcweb.mycom.co.jp/news/2002/12/18/21cl.jpg">Masatomo Nakano</uri>
		bravely stepped into the lion's den and confronted about 100 participants
		at the annual Japan Unix Society's (JUS) BSD/Linux Day in Yokohama. One of
		this year's topics were application packagers for Unix and Linux: Debian's
		dpkg, Red Hat's rpm, FreeBSD's ports, and Gentoo's portage. "It was relatively easy to
		make them comprehend what portage is about, because so many people here are
		FreeBSD users", says Nakano, hoping his intervention on the panel will help
		Gentoo conquer some of the ground largely occupied by Berkeley
		derivatives, rather than "Lainacks" - as local BSD zealots deliberately
		mispronounce it. In a Linux market otherwise dominated by local(ized)
		distributions like Turbolinux, Plamo and Kondara (reputedly reborn as
		Momonga Linux), Nakano pledges to continue increasing the popularity of
		Gentoo Linux in Japan. Japan's Gentoo user community has moved ahead one
		important step on this path with the grand opening of a brand new website,
		<uri link="http://www.gentoo.gr.jp">http://www.gentoo.gr.jp</uri>, earlier this month. </p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Portage Watch</title>
	<section>
		<title>Security Updates (see above)</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li>exim - fixed in exim-4.10 and above</li>
				<li>mysql - fixed in mysql-3.23.54 and above</li>
				<li>squirrelmail - fixed in squirrelmail-1.2.10 and above</li>
				<li>fetchmail - fixed in fetchmail-6.20 and above</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>The following stable packages were added to the portage tree this week</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li>app-docs/php-docs - HTML documentation for PHP
				<uri>http://www.php.net/download-docs.php</uri></li>
				<li>app-editors/hteditor - An editor for executable files
				<uri>http://hte.sf.net</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/asr-manpages - A set of humorous man pages developed on alt.sysadmin.recovery
				<uri>http://debian.org</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/cube - Landscape-style engine that pretend to be an indoor first person shooter engine
				<uri>http://wouter.fov120.com/cube</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/exult - an Ultima 7 game engine
				<uri>http://exult.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/flightgear - An open source flight simulator
				<uri>http://www.flightgear.org</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/fortune-mod-smac - Quotes from the Alpha Centuri : Alien Crossfire tech tree
				<uri>http://homepages.ihug.com.au/~alana</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/funny-manpages - Funny manpages from various sources
				<uri>http://debian.org</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/gnono - A rewrite of the windows card game WUNO
				<uri>http://www.paw.co.za/projects/gnono</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/phobiaiii - Just a moment ago you were safe in your ship, behind five inch armour
				<uri>http://www.lynxlabs.com/phobiaIII</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/scid - a free chess database application
				<uri>http://scid.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/sdlsasteroids - a rework of Sasteroids using SDL
				<uri>http://sdlsas.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/xbomb - a Minesweeper clone
				<uri>http://www.gedanken.demon.co.uk/xbomb</uri></li>
				<li>app-games/xfrisk - The RISK board game
				<uri>http://morphy.iki.fi/xfrisk</uri></li>
				<li>app-i18n/koffice-i18n-ca</li>
				<li>dev-lang/pm3 - Modula-3 compiler
				<uri>http://www.elegosoft.com/pm3</uri></li>
				<li>dev-ml/findlib - OCaml tool to find/use non-standard packages
				<uri>http://www.ocaml-programming.de/programming/download-caml.html</uri></li>
				<li>dev-perl/Safe - Compile and execute code in restricted compartments
				<uri>http://search.cpan.org/src/ABERGMAN/Safe-2.09/README</uri></li>
				<li>dev-perl/Apache-Session - Perl module for Apache::Session
				<uri>http://search.cpan.org/author/JBAKER/Apache-Session-1.54</uri></li>
				<li>dev-perl/HTML-SimpleParse - A bare-bones HTML parser, similar to HTML::Parser, but with a couple important distinctions
				<uri>http://www.cpan.org/authors/id/KWILLIAMS/HTML-SimpleParse-0.10.readme</uri></li>
				<li>dev-perl/Lingua-EN-Inflect - Perl module for Lingua::EN::Inflect
				<uri>http://search.cpan.org/author/DCONWAY/Lingua-EN-Inflect-1.88</uri></li>
				<li>dev-python/medusa - A framework for writing high-performance network servers in Python
				<uri>http://oedipus.sourceforge.net/medusa</uri></li>
				<li>dev-python/omniORBpy - A robust high-performance CORBA ARB for Python.
				<uri>http://omniorb.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
				<li>dev-util/byacc - The best variant of the Yacc parser generator
				<uri>http://dickey.his.com/byacc/byacc.html</uri></li>
				<li>media-libs/allegromp3 - An Allegro wrapper for the mpglib MP3 decoder part of mpg123
				<uri>http://nekros.freeshell.org/delirium/almp3.php</uri></li>
				<li>media-libs/guilib - A simple widget set for SDL
				<uri>http://www.libsdl.org/projects/GUIlib</uri></li>
				<li>media-libs/jpgalleg - The jpeq routines are able to load almost and JPG image with Allegro
				<uri>http://orbflux.com/jpgalleg</uri></li>
				<li>media-libs/loadpng - Load and save PNG files with Allegro
				<uri>http://www.alphalink.com.au/~tjaden/loadpng</uri></li>
				<li>net-ftp/jftpgw - A small FTP gateway
				<uri>http://www.mcknight.de/jftpgw</uri></li>
				<li>net-misc/gsmlib - Library and Applications to access GSM mobile phones
				<uri>http://www.pxh.de/fs/gsmlib</uri></li>
				<li>net-misc/linuxsms - A console perl script for sending SMS to cell phones
				<uri>http://linuxsms.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
				<li>net-misc/mico - A freely available and fully compliant implementation of the CORBA standard
				<uri>http://www.mico.org</uri></li>
				<li>net-misc/mknbi - Utility for making tagged kernel images
				<uri>http://etherboot.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
				<li>net-misc/nforce-net - Kernel module for the NVIDIA's nForce network chip
				<uri>http://www.nvidia.com</uri></li>
				<li>sys-kernel/win4lin-sources - Full sources for the Linux kernel with win4lin support</li>
				<li>x11-misc/bbdate - Blackbox date display
				<uri>http://bbtools.windsofstorm.net/available.phtml</uri></li>
				<li>x11-misc/bbtime - Blackbox time watch
				<uri>http://bbtools.windsofstorm.net/available.phtml#bbsload</uri></li>
				<li>x11-misc/e-fancylauncher - E-FancyLauncher epplet
				<uri>http://www.docs.uu.se/~adavid/Epplets</uri></li>
				<li>x11-plugins/gkacpi - ACPI monitor for Gkrellm
				<uri>http://uname.dyndns.org/~uname/software.php</uri></li>
				<li>x11-plugins/wmdots - Multi shape 3D rotating dots
				<uri>http://dockapps.org/file.php/id/116</uri></li>
				<li>x11-themes/mplayer-skins - Collection of mplayer themes
				<uri>http://www.mplayerhq.hu</uri></li>
				<li>net-wireless/kwavecontrol - Tool for WaveLAN cards
				<uri>http://kwavecontrol.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Updates to notable packages</title>
			<body>
			<p>
				<ul>
					<li>Portage - portage-2.0.46-r2</li>
					<li>Kernels - 
							ac-sources-2.4.20-r2;
							acpi-sources-2.4.20-r9;
							ck-sources-2.4.20-r2;
							development-sources-2.5.52;
							lolo-sources-2.4.20.1_pre5;
							sparc-sources-2.4.21_pre1;
							win4lin-sources-2.4.20-r1
					</li>
					<li>mysql - mysql-3.23.54a</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New use variables</title>
			<body>
			<p>
				<ul>
					<li>acpi - Adds support for Advanced Configuration and Power Interface</li>
					<li>apache2 - Chooses Apache2 support when a package supports both Apache1 and Apache2</li>
					<li>gps - Adds support for Global Positioning System</li>
					<li>oav - Adds support for anti-virus from the openantivirus.org project</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
			</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Bugzilla</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>

			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect3">Bugs of Note</uri></li>
                        </ul>                           
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Statistics</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
                bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  In the last 7 days, activity
                on the site has resulted in:
			<ul>
				<li>224 new bugs this week</li>
				<li>1150 total bugs currently marked 'new'</li>

				<li>559 total bugs curently assigned to developers</li>
                                <li>50 bugs that were previously closed have been reopened.</li>
			</ul>
                <note>There are currently 1759 bugs open in bugzilla. Of these: 28 are labelled 'blocker', 71 are labelled 'critical',
                and 103 are labelled 'major'.</note>
		</p>
                <p>
                The developers and teams with the highest apparent bug-related workload are:
			<ul>
				<li><mail link="carpaski@gentoo.org">Nicholas Jones</mail>, with 232 open bugs</li>

				<li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</mail>, with 156 open bugs</li>
				<li><mail link="lostlogic@gentoo.org">Brandon Low</mail>, with 110 open bugs</li>
				<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org">The KDE Team</mail>, with 97 open bugs</li>
				<li><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>, with 83 open bugs</li>
			</ul>

                Please lend them (and the entire development team) your good thoughts, spare karma and ongoing support.
                </p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Bugs of Note</title>
		<body>
		<p>

		Each week, we will single out a few bugs for special mention, because they have been provoking significant
                discussions, they are particularly problematic, they are amusing or simply because they struck our fancy.
                This week's featured bugs are (in no particular order):
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=5902">
                                     Bug 5902</uri> is a discussion about security concerns around running emerge
                                     as root, and ways to make it work as an unprivileged user process.</li>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=9946">
                                     Bug 9946</uri>, which was a problem with the daily snapshots not updating
                                     that was provoking some conversation in the forums, is apparently resolved
                                     or about to be so.</li>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=11136">

                                     Bug 11136</uri>, about a new MPlayer ebuild to support QuickTime/Sorenson,
                                     has been seeing a remarkable amount of traffic - possibly due to the release of LOTR
                                     trailers.</li>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=11473">
                                     Bug 11473</uri> discusses problems with the Mozilla-1.2.1 ebuild and plugin support.</li>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=8067">
                                     Bug 8067</uri> was a problem with the absence of PCMCIA support on the 1.4 install disk, which has been resolved.</li>

				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=10578">
                                     Bug 10578</uri> discusses how to resolve a portage failure after syncing using the 
                                     rescue portage.</li>
			</ul>
                If you have a pet bug that you feel is not getting the care and attention that it deserves, please drop us a note.
                We can't guarantee that it will make next week's list, but we can guarantee that it will be considered.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
    <title>Tips and Tricks</title>
    <body>
    <p><b>Manually resetting a service</b></p>
    <p>Have you ever tried to restart a crashed service and gotten the
       following error message?
    </p>
    <pre>
    * WARNING: <e>service name</e> has already been started
    </pre>
    <p>If so, you can manually reset the service with the following command</p>
    <pre>
    # <i>/etc/init.d/<e>service name</e> zap</i>
    </pre>

    </body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, Adds and Changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following devs recently left the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li>Zach Welch (zwelch)</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following devs recently joined the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li>John Christian Stoddart (chiguire) -- Documentation</li>
				<li>Thomas Raschbacher (LordVan) -- Python/Printing</li>
				<li>Troy Dack (TaD) -- Testing and Tweaking</li>
				<li>Jon Portnoy (avenj) -- ICC-based profile for Gentoo</li>
				<li>Peter Brown (rendhalver) -- XEmacs</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following devs recently changed roles or took on new responsibilities within the Gentoo project:
			<ul>
				<li>Sascha Schwabbauer (cybersystem) -- Mail Admin, rsync Admin</li>
				<li>John Davis (ZhEN) -- Bugzilla</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Subscribe to the GWN mailing list</title>
	<body>
	<p>Would you prefer to receive the GWN via email?  Subscribe to our mailing list by sending a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail></p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<body>
	<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail></p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Feedback</title>
	<body>
	<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make GWN better.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
