<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>January 6th, 2003</subtitle>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of January 6th, 2003.</abstract>
<version>Volume 2, Issue 1</version>
<date>06 Jan 2003</date>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="nesta@iceburg.net">Brice Burgess</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="carlos@pubbawup.net">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="david@phrixus.net">David Narayan</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="plate@gol.com">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="mail@psharp.uklinux.net">Peter Sharp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="matje@lanzone.be">Mathy Vanvoorden</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="tom.vanlaerhoven@luc.ac.be">Tom Van Laerhoven</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="nicolas.ledez@free.fr">Nicolas Ledez</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="gui@moolfreet.com">Guillaume Plessis</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="thevedge@thevedge.net">Eric St-Georges</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="anfini@free.fr">John Berry</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="riverdale@linuxmail.org">Martin Prieto</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="citizen428@cargal.org">Michael Kohl</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="lassahn@web.de">Steffan Lassahn</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="haim@lame.at">Matthias Brandstetter</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="mush@monrif.net">Marco Mascherpa</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="paper@tiscali.it">Claudio Merloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="venturasbarbeiro@ig.com.br">Ventura Barbeiro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="lanark@lanark.com.ar">Lanark</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Start the New Year with a Donation to the Gentoo Linux Project</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">New Gentoo Linux Prelinking Guide</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">Perl 5.8 and libperl</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect5">Future improvements to Gentoo Linux in the works</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Start the New Year with a Donation to the Gentoo Linux Project</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		As we enter the New Year, we invite everyone who has benefitted from their use of Gentoo Linux to make a <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org">donation</uri> to the Gentoo Project.  Its through your generous donations that the Gentoo Project is able to have a presence at the upcoming <uri link="http://www.linuxworldexpo.com/">LinuxWorld Expo</uri>.  Donations also help to support other development efforts, such as sponsoring developers so they can work full time on Gentoo Linux.  Donations can be made via PayPal as well as check.
		</p>
		<p>
		Additionally, if you know of a company that may be interested in sponsoring the Gentoo Linux free software project through a regular monthly donation, please email <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail> directly.  Among other things, corporate sponsorships allow Gentoo developers to work full time on Gentoo Linux.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New Gentoo Linux Prelinking Guide</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		A new <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/prelink-howto.xml">Gentoo Linux Prelinking Guide</uri> has been posted.  Prelinking can cut the startup times of applications, especially larger ones such as KDE and GNOME, by as much as 50% or more.  Many Mandrake and RedHat users have sung the praises of prelinking and its effect on overall system speed, so it is certainly a welcome addition to Gentoo Linux.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Perl 5.8 and libperl</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Recently, an issue was raised among the developers about how to effectively deal with Perl 5.8.  Perl 5.8 uses a shared library (libperl) that is incompatible with earlier versions of Perl, including Perl 5.6.1.  Users upgrading to Perl 5.8 could find any apps previously compiled with Perl 5.6.1 to now be broken given the libperl incompatiblity.  The solution for Gentoo Linux is to numerate the various versions of libperl to allow multiple versions to coincide with each other.  So, as an example:
		<ul>
			<li>perl-5.6 gets libperl.so.0.5.6</li>
			<li>perl-5.8 gets libperl.so.1.5.8</li>
			<li>perl-x.y gets libperl.so.2.x.y</li>
		</ul>
		This solution should allow the Perl 5.6.1 --> Perl 5.8 upgrade to proceed smoothly, and it will also serve as a solution for future binary compatibility problems.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Future improvements to Gentoo Linux in the works</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		While the current focus of the Gentoo developers is on getting Gentoo Linux 1.4_final out the door, that doesn't mean future improvements aren't also being discussed.  In addition to the Gentoo Reference Platform, which is designed to establish a stable baseline for Gentoo Linux, formal in-house testing and approval of hardware may be on the horizon.  This process, which would provide users of Gentoo a set of components known to work with Gentoo Linux, should help avid Gentoo users make future hardware purchasing decisions.  In addition to hardware testing, there are some tantalizing improvements to Portage coming up as well, including:		
		<ul>
			<li><b>Caching of emerge messages for later display</b> -- Anyone who has ever emerged a list of packages has probably experienced the frustration of seeing informational messages scroll past as Portage moves from package to package.  This feature will allow those messages to be cached in a safe place so they can be displayed at a later time (such as at the end of an entire 'emerge -u world'.</li>
			<li><b>Reverse dependency checking in Portage</b> -- one of the most-often requested Portage features, reverse dependency checking will warn you if you try to unmerge a package that other installed packages depend upon.</li>
			<li><b>Dependency-based remerging</b> -- this feature will allow certain packages to be remerged if necessary, based on the dependencies of another package.  With this feature, upgrading CUPS will force Ghostscript to be rebuilt as well, even if no upgrade of Ghostscript is available.  This feature will go a long way towards resolving shared library incompatibilities.</li>
		</ul>
		Nick Jones (carpaski) is working on these Portage improvements as well as others and is quickly catching up on the backlog of Portage feature requests.  While no firm timeline exists for delivery of these features, the future of Portage certainly looks bright.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Security</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">GLSA: leafnode</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">GLSA: xpdf</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">GLSA: cups</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect5">New Security Bug Reports</uri></li>
			</ul> 
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: leafnode</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The leafnode NNTP server can be forced into an unterminated and unresponsive loop when a particular article is requested,
		causing the client to reconnect, creating a new process.  Repitition of this cycle can make the entire system unresponsive.
			<ul>
				<li>Severity: moderate - remote DOS (process spawning)</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: leafnode-1.9.24 and earlier</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge leafnode.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28343">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: xpdf</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The pdftops filter (included in Xpdf and CUPS) has an integer overflow bug that can be exploited remotely to gain the privileges
		of the target user or, in some circumstances, of the lp user.
			<ul>
				<li>Severity: high - remote exploit in the wild</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: xpdf-1.01-r1 and earlier</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge xpdf.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28342">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://www.idefense.com/advisory/12.23.02.txt">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: cups</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Several vulnerabilities in the CUPS printing package (including the integer overflow noted above) permit a number of exploits, including
		an exploit of multiple vulnerabilities that permits root access to the file system.  The exploits have been demonstrated and published.
			<ul>
				<li>Severity: critical - remote root exploit in the wild</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: cups-1.1.17_pre20021025 and earlier</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge cups.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=27949">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://www.idefense.com/advisory/12.19.02.txt">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New Security Bug Reports</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The last two weeks saw many of the outstanding security bugs cleared with new releases of the affected packages.  
		The following new security bugs have been posted: 
			<ul>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12811">mod_php</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12988">dhcpd</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Heard In The Community</title>
	<section>
		<title>Web Forums</title>
		<body>

	    <p><b>Selective rsync strategies</b></p>

	    <p>This discussion raises its head every few months, meaning it probably has a point. Some people wish to cut down on bandwidth usage when they synchronize their portage tree by eliminating packages or classes they definitely don't want, need or even imagine to install, ever. The discussion and a few DIY ideas how to cope with the problem:
	    <ul>
		<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28044">a portage killfile</uri></li>
	    <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=23607">Selective emerge rsync to cut down on bandwidth usage</uri></li>
		</ul>
		</p>

	    <p><b>PCMCIA Worries Anticipating Gentoo 1.4</b></p>

	    <p>A large number of forum regulars have begun expressing anxiety about the missing pcmcia_cs and yenta_socket PCMCIA kernel modules in the second release candidate, and by consequence, they fear, in the pending release of Gentoo 1.4. A handful of threads are dominated by users of laptops and notebooks without built-in NICs, who rely on PCMCIA for access to the Internet (and eventually to a successful Gentoo installation). Their worries are getting hard to overlook, and some appear to have given in and use alternative install methods:
	    <ul>
	    <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28281">yenta_socket on 1.4 rc2</uri></li>
	    <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28413">Installing Gentoo on a laptop that needs yenta_socket</uri></li>
	    <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=14894">installing 1.4-rc1 and pcmcia_core</uri></li>
		</ul>
		It should be noted that the PCMCIA situation in linux in general is not that great.  With two sets of drivers (stock kernel drivers and pcmcia-cs packages) that are incompatible with one another, ensuring support for all PCMCIA devices is a challenge.  Gentoo developers are working on including support for both sets of drivers on the Gentoo Linux 1.4 LiveCD, which should allow the widest range of compatiblity for all laptop users.
		</p>
		<p>
		If anyone has a spare laptop that they would be interested in donating to the Gentoo Linux project, this would help greatly in improving PCMCIA support on the LiveCDs.  If you're interested in donating a laptop, please contact <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail> directly.
		</p>


    <p><b>Overclockers beware!</b></p>

    <p>Forum moderator Phong pretty much sums it up: Overclocking is a bad idea when all it does is break compilations for a mere 100 Mhz of performance gain on the CPU, less than 5 percent on most of today's x86 PCs.
		<ul><li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=27564">Seg Fault Hell (thinking of dropping Gentoo)</uri></li></ul>
	</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>gentoo-user</title>
		<body>
		<p><b>Round 689,554 of the Text Editor Holy War</b></p>
		<p>
 		There's nothing like starting off the New Year with a good flame war about text editors, and gentoo-user has been having a great one over the past few days.  The festivities seem to have started with <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104138315028463&amp;w=2">this post</uri> and proceeded from there.  At last count, there were approximately <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;w=2&amp;r=1&amp;s=Vi%2FNano+flames&amp;q=b">60 messages</uri> in response to this post and the war continues on.
		</p>
		<p><b>New Docbook eclass solves SGML problems</b></p>
		<p>
 		Recent updates to the Docbook/SGML system in Gentoo caused some problems for some users.  Matthew Turk (satai) posted a <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104144948228162&amp;w=2">message</uri> that explains how to fix these issues, along with a link to a more <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/~satai/sgmlfix.html">detailed explanation</uri>.
		</p>
	
		<p><b>Gentoo's supported hardware</b></p>
		<p>
  Freeman Tan asked for a list of official 'gentoo supported hardware'. Those more familar
  with linux would agree with Tom von Schwerdtner's statement; "distro supported hardware 
  is mostly a misconecption". The linux kernel provides support for hardware, and it is up
  to the distro's 'installer' to detect and add support for the present devices. Gentoo is
  unique in that it doesn't have a formal installer but rather aids the installee through 
  the intimate process of setting up a linux system from scratch. Providing you're able to
  boot into this system, you'll be able to add support for your devices later. A google
  search for "[hardware] +linux" will generally send you in the right direction. The 
  <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104135883514141&amp;w=2">thread</uri>
  concludes that "no, there is no official gentoo supported hardware".  However, as we noted above, formal in-house testing of hardware may be in the works for Gentoo Linux.  Stay tuned.
		</p>
		<p><b>How do I telnet into my new Gentoo box?</b></p>
		<p>  	
  First and foremost it should be known that telnet is "obsolete, broken, insecure, 
  and should never be used". If you still want to live on the wild side, make sure
  netkit-telnetd has been emerged, and you have an inetd server setup. This 
<uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104105195014103&amp;w=2">discussion</uri>
  has detailed instructions. Secure Shell (sshd) is the highly recommended alternative
  to telnet and much easier to install.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>gentoo-dev</title>
		<body>
		<p><b>USE Aware Emerge.</b>
		Martin Svenningsson posted
		a very nifty 
		<uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6303">patch</uri> to allow 
		<c>emerge</c> to display which USE flags affect the compilation
		of each package!
		</p>

		<p><b>Gentoo Stable Site Update.</b></p>
		<p>
		Maik Schreiber posted an 
		<uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6350">announcement</uri> with the updates done 
		on the <uri link="http://gentoo-stable.iq-computing.de">Gentoo Stable website</uri>: 
		<e>"Hi, a few updates to the Gentoo Stable site have been made: (1). The query page is now a little easier to use. For example, you get selection boxes where possible (category, arch etc.). (2). A new filter has been added: You can now filter on "Portage status on {x86, ppc, sparc, alpha} {is, is not} {stable, unstable/testing, does not work, unmarked}". (3). Various speed improvements regarding query have been made. [...]"</e>. Joachim Blaabjerg <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6361">chipped in</uri> with <e>"Are there any tools available that scans the system for packages that are 
merged and marked unstable (~), and submits those as "merged successfully on 
my system"? I know I have a lot of unstable packages on my system, but I 
haven't got the time to through all of them and submit them to the 
Gentoo-stable site."</e> and Peter Ruskin sent in a 
<uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6362">script</uri> to do just that!
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo International</title>
    <body>

	    <p class="secthead">Gentoo UK Being Constituted</p>

<p>They're not exactly out of the starting blocks yet, but a handful of British Gentoo users seems determined to follow their French, German, Korean and Japanese counterparts' example in creating a more formal support network for Gentooistsn their country. <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28246">The thread</uri> has just begun to gain momentum. In particular, they are looking for a catchy domain name, feel free to make suggestions...</p>

<p class="secthead">Iberian Peninsula Tops Spanish community</p>

    <p>If a <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=11939">forum poll</uri> is anything to go by, the vast majority of Spanish-speaking Gentooist comes from Spain. They're being followed by users in Argentina and Urugay, a few Mexicans and Spanish-speaking US citizens, but a rather large proportion of people lives in a place oddly called "other"... 
</p>
<p class="secthead">More Gentoo Linux Users Everywhere:
ZetaGrid</p>
<p>A 
<uri
link="http://www.zetagrid.net/servlet/service/teammembers?team=Gentoo+Linux+Users+Everywhere">
Gentoo team</uri>
has been formed for 
<uri link="http://www.zetagrid.net/">ZetaGrid</uri>
, a distributed computing project sponsored by IBM Germany whose distinguishing technical
feature is the secure Java kernel it provides, preventing access
from outside and securing its communications. The current project
is the verification of 
<uri link="http://www.zetagrid.net/zeta/rh.html">Riemann's
Hypothesis</uri>
: about 2500 computers are working on it, calculating about 2
billion zeroes of the Riemann zeta function each day. Sebastian
Wedeniwski, the scientist who created ZetaGrid, hopes to use
ZetaGrid's results to come up with a proof for the hypothesis. If
he succeeds, he'll split the $1,000,000 prize from the 
<uri link="http://www.claymath.org/">Clay Mathematics
Institute</uri>
with the top 100 users; there are other prizes, including one
awarded to the user whose computer finds a result disproving the
hypothesis, if that happens instead. 
<uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=1326">
Tantive</uri>
has made an ebuild for the client but it's still masked, for more
information see 
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28511">Zetagrid
- team: Gentoo Linux Users Everywhere</uri>.
</p> 

</body>

</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Portage Watch</title>
<section>
<title>Security Updates (see above)</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li>cups - fixed in cups-1.1.18</li>
<li>xpdf - fixed in xpdf-2.01</li>
<li>leafnode - fixed in leafnode 1.9.31</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The following stable packages were added to portage this week</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li> app-emulation/blight_input : An input plugin for the mupen64 N64 emulator
<uri>http://mupen64.emulation64.com/</uri></li>
<li> app-emulation/mupen64 : A Nintendo 64 (N64) emulator
<uri>http://mupen64.emulation64.com/</uri></li>
<li> app-emulation/nestra : NES Emulator
<uri>http://nestra.linuxgames.com</uri></li>
<li> app-games/c++robots : ongoing 'King of the Hill' (KotH) tournament
<uri>http://www.gamerz.net/c++robots/</uri></li>
<li> app-games/emilia-pinball : SDL OpenGL pinball game
<uri>http://pinball.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> app-games/gxmame : GXMame is a frontend for XMame using the GTK library, the goal is to provide the same GUI as mame32.
<uri>http://gxmame.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> app-misc/gcolor : A simple color selector.
<uri>http://gcolor.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> dev-libs/libhtmlparse : libhtmlparse is a HTML parsing library. It takes HTML tags, text, etc and calls callbacks you define for each type of token in the document.
<uri>http://msalem.translator.cx/libhtmlparse.html</uri></li>
<li> dev-util/jam : jam (Just Another Make) - advanced make replacement
<uri>http://www.perforce.com/jam/jam.html</uri></li>
<li> dev-util/fenris : Fenris is a tracer, GUI debugger, analyzer, partial decompiler and much more
<uri>http://razor.bindview.com/tools/fenris/</uri></li>
<li> media-libs/libexif : Library for parsing, editing, and saving EXIF data
<uri>http://libexif.sf.net/</uri></li>
<li> media-sound/jack-cvs : A low-latency audio server - cvs version
<uri>http://jackit.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> net-dialup/mingetty : A compact getty program for virtual consoles only.
<uri></uri></li>
<li> net-misc/udhcp : udhcp Server/Client Package
<uri>http://udhcp.busybox.net/</uri></li>
<li> net-misc/ksambaplugin : KSambaPlugin is a KDE 3 plugin for configuring a SAMBA server.
<uri>http://ksambakdeplugin.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
<li> net-news/sn : Hassle-free Usenet news system for small sites
<uri>http://infa.abo.fi/~patrik/sn/</uri></li>
<li> net-p2p/giftoxic : A GTK+2 giFT frontend
<uri>http://giftoxic.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> net-www/fetch : Fetch is a simple, fast, and flexible HTTP download tool built on the HTTP Fetcher library.
<uri>http://cs.nmu.edu/~lhanson/fetch/</uri></li>
<li> net-www/http-fetcher : HTTP Fetcher is a small, robust, flexible library for downloading files via HTTP using the GET method.
<uri>http://cs.nmu.edu/~lhanson/http_fetcher/</uri></li>
<li> sys-apps/hfsplusutils : HFS+ Filesystem Access Utilities (PPC Only)
<uri>http://ftp.penguinppc.org/users/hasi/</uri></li>
<li> sys-apps/tinylogin : worlds smallest login/passwd/getty/etc
<uri>http://tinylogin.busybox.net/</uri></li>
<li> sys-devel/prelink : Modifies executables so runtime libraries load faster
<uri>ftp://people.redhat.com/jakub/prelink</uri></li>
<li> sys-devel/kgcc : Modern GCC C compiler for building kernels
<uri>http://www.gnu.org/software/gcc/gcc.html</uri></li>
<li> net-wireless/wepattack : WLAN tool for breaking 802.11 WEP keys
<uri>http://wepattack.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>

</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Updates to notable packages</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li>sys-apps/portage - portage-2.0.46-r3.ebuild; portage-2.0.46-r4.ebuild; portage-2.0.46-r5.ebuild; </li>
<li>sys-libs/glibc - glibc-2.3.1-r3.ebuild; </li>
<li>sys-kernel/* - aa-sources-2.4.21_pre2-r2.ebuild; development-sources-2.5.54.ebuild; lolo-sources-2.4.20.1_pre9.ebuild; lolo-sources-2.4.20.1_rc1.ebuild; lolo-sources-2.4.20.1_rc2.ebuild; </li>
<li>dev-php/php - php-4.3.0.ebuild; </li>
<li>dev-db/postgresql - postgresql-7.3.1.ebuild; </li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New USE variables</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li>ev6 - Assume Alpha processor is EV6 or better</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Bugzilla</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Bugs of Note</uri></li>
                        </ul>                           
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Statistics</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
                bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  In the last 7 days, activity
                on the site has resulted in:
			<ul>
				<li>269 new bugs this week</li>
				<li>1322 total bugs currently marked 'new'</li>
				<li>524 total bugs curently assigned to developers</li>
                <li>47 bugs that were previously closed have been reopened.</li>
			</ul>
                There are currently 1893 bugs open in bugzilla. Of these: 40 are labelled 'blocker', 74 are labelled 'critical',
                and 113 are labelled 'major'.
		</p>
                <p>
                The developers and teams with the highest apparent bug-related workload are:
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="mailto://carpaski@gentoo.org">Nicholas Jones</uri>, with 271 open bugs</li>
				<li><uri link="mailto://azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</uri>, with 133 open bugs</li>
				<li><uri link="mailto://lostlogic@gentoo.org">Brandon Low</uri>, with 107 open bugs</li>
				<li><uri link="mailto://kde@gentoo.org">The KDE Team</uri>, with 105 open bugs</li>
				<li><uri link="mailto://drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</uri>, with 83 open bugs</li>
			</ul>
                Please lend them (and the entire development team) your good thoughts, left-over turkey, and ongoing support.
                </p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Bugs of Note</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Each week, we will single out a few bugs for special mention, because they have been provoking significant
                discussions, they are particularly problematic, they are amusing or simply because they struck our fancy.
                This week's featured bugs are (in no particular order):
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=13055">
                                     Bug 13055</uri> describes problems with portage wanting to uninstall newer versions
				     of packages, probably because of an issue with counter values in /var/db/pkg/.  Maik Schrieber
				     provides a script to fix the issue.</li>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=13074">
                                     Bug 13074</uri> discusses a problem with emerging xmms, possibly because of the xmms ebuild depending
				     on an incompatible autoconf/automake version.  An excellent example of reporter/developer interaction.</li>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=8539">
				     Bug 8539</uri> discusses a frequently cross-reported problem of OpenOffice emerges destroying fonts on
				     affected systems.  The bug report includes two workarounds and remains open.</li>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=5152">
                                     Bug 5152</uri> provides a fix to the mysql start script that provides for user modifications to the default data
				     directory.  This is a nice example of community members providing patches via the bugzilla interface.</li>
				<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=9849">
                                     Bug 9849</uri> describes ebuild failures when cdroms are mounted or directories (like /home) are NFS mounts.</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Tips and Tricks</title>
	<body>

		<p class="secthead">Updating a Gentoo system</p>

		<p>Most Gentoo users are familiar with the Portage system used to install software. One of the features that you may not be familiar with is that Portage can also update your entire system at once.  This is known as an 'update world'.</p>
		To run an update world, use the following command: 
		<pre># <i>emerge --update world</i></pre>

		<p>Sometimes that doesn't get everything though. To make the upgrade even more complete, use the --deep option.</p>

		<pre># <i>emerge --update --deep world</i></pre>

		<p>This option calculates the dependencies of the dependencies to ensure that everything on your system is brought up to date.</p>

	</body>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Moves, Adds and Changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li>Nicholas Wourms (dragon) -- MIPS</li>
				<li>Tobias Eichert (viz) -- xfs-sources</li>
				<li>Matthew J. Fanto (mattjf) -- secure-gentoo, kernels</li>
				<li>Yannik Koehler (ykoehler) -- KDE</li>
				<li>Luca Barbato (lu_zero) -- ATI, LiveCD</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo project.
			<ul>
				<li><e>Jared Hudson (jhhudso) -- Gentoo Linux 1.4 QA Testing Coordinator</e></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Subscribe to the GWN mailing list</title>
	<body>
	<p>Would you prefer to receive the GWN via email?  Subscribe to our mailing list by sending a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail></p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<body>
	<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail></p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Feedback</title>
	<body>
	<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make GWN better.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
