<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>April 7th, 2003</subtitle>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of April 7th, 2003.</abstract>
<summary>Yes, it was a joke.  Portage moves to a new, more secure format.</summary>
<version>Volume 2, Issue 14</version>
<date>7 April 2003</date>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="nesta@iceburg.net">Brice Burgess</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="david@phrixus.net">David Narayan</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="mail@psharp.uklinux.net">Peter Sharp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="kim@thinkit.dk">Kim Tingkaer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="matje@lanzone.be">Mathy Vanvoorden</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="tom.vanlaerhoven@luc.ac.be">Tom Van Laerhoven</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="phj.dijkstra@home.nl">Peter Dijkstra</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="bernieke@bernieke.com">Bernard Bernieke</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="zu@pandora.be">Vincent Verleye</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="linux@sejo.be">Jochen Maes</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="yngwin@xs4all.nl">Ben De Groot</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="j.jaarsma@dordrecht.arbounie.nl">Jelmer Jaarsma</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="nicolas.ledez@free.fr">Nicolas Ledez</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="gui@moolfreet.com">Guillaume Plessis</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="anfini@free.fr">John Berry</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="riverdale@linuxmail.org">Martin Prieto</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="madeagle@gentoo.org">Steffen Lassahn</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="haim@gentoo.org">Matthias F. Brandstetter</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="yanestra@web.de">Klaus-J. Wolf</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="mush@monrif.net">Marco Mascherpa</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="paper@tiscali.it">Claudio Merloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="kage-chan@gentoo.org">Daniel Ketel</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="hagi@p1d.com">Yoshiaki Hagihara</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="andy@billydpro.com">Andy Hunne</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="yasunori@mail.portland.co.uk">Yasunori Fukudome</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="venturasbarbeiro@ig.com.br">Ventura Barbeiro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="blueroom@digitalmente.net">Bruno Ferreira</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="gustavo@felisberto.net">Gustavo Felisberto</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="rjlouro@rjlouro.org">Ricardo Jorge Louro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="lanark@lanark.com.ar">Lanark</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="julio@castillobueno.com">Julio Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="s3r@fibertel.com.ar">Sergio G&#243;mez</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="pablo.leira@pitagoral.com">Pablo Pita Leira</mail>	
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@castillobueno.com">Carlos Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="tirant@menta.net">Tirant</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="jfreire@ya.com">Jaime Freire</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="krusty_ar@yahoo.com">Lucas Sallovitz</mail>
</author>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Yes, it was a joke</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Portage moves to a new, more secure format</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Yes, it was a joke</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Last week's issue, which was conveniently delayed a day so it could be released on April 1, contained a story about the adoption of the RPM format for package management.  The results of this April Fools' Joke were far more successful than we had hoped for.  (Some might argue it was too successful)  Needless to say, it was a joke and the Gentoo development team has no plans to move away from the ebuild format as its standard means of package management.
		</p>
		<p>
		Now please stop sending us hate mail.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Portage moves to a new, more secure format</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		As part of an overall effort to improve the security of Gentoo Linux, the Portage development team is starting to implement some new features in Portage which will allow for increased security in our package management and distribution systems.  One of the first new features that users will notice is digests of every file involved in the merge process, including ebuilds, patches and source tarballs.  In addition to offering increased security, these digests will help isolate and track down corrupt ebuilds or other files on our rsync and source mirrors.</p>
		<p>
		The next step in the process will be signing these digest files with a GPG key to ensure non-repudiation.  While there is still some discussion amongst the development team on the best way to achieve this, the current leading solution involves each developer signing ebuilds individually, and then one master Gentoo "uberkey" signing all of the developer keys to establish a Gentoo "web of trust".  Developer keys will be made available through public keyservers, as well as on <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org">www.gentoo.org</uri>
		</p>
		<p>
		The goal of what has come to be known as "Secure Portage" is to provide a robust package management system that offers end-to-end security in the emerge process.  As yet, there is no confirmed timeline on when the entire system will become available, but the digesting portion is in testing now and the rest will soon follow.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Security</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">GLSA: sendmail</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3">GLSA: krb5 and mit-krb5</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect4">GLSA: openafs</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect5">GLSA: dietlibc</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect6">New Security Bug Reports</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect7">gentoo-security</uri></li>
			</ul> 
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: sendmail</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                The sendmail MTA has a stack overflow vulnerability in the way that it checks email addresses.  This
                vulnerability could be exploited remotely to execute a DoS attack,  gain control of the sendmail server,
                or potentially execute arbitrary code under the privileges of the server (typically root).
                </p>
                
                        <ul>
				<li>Severity: Critical - Potential remote root compromise.</li>
				<li>Packages Affected:  net-mail/sendmail versions prior to sendmail-8.12.9</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge sendmail, emerge clean.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=44892">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://www.cert.org/advisories/CA-2003-12.html">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: krb5 and mit-krb5</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                Multiple vulnerabilities in the krb5 and mit-krb5 implementations of the Kerberos authentication protocol
                have been identified.  These include a buffer overrun that permits a DoS attack on he Kerberos administration
                daemon, a chosen-plaintext attack that permits impersonation of other principals, and buffer overrun and underrun
                problems that permit unusual names and hosts (which could be used in other attacks).
                </p>
                
                        <ul>
				<li>Severity: Critical - Authentication compromise.</li>
				<li>Packages Affected:  app-crypt/krb5 versions prior to krb5-1.2.7-r2 and
                                                        app-crypt/mit-krb5 versions prior to mit-krb5-1.2.7</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge krb5 and/or mit-krb5, emerge clean.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=44893">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://web.mit.edu/kerberos/www/advisories/MITKRB5-SA-2003-003-xdr.txt">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: openafs</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                A cryptographic weakness in Kerberos 4 permits a chosen-plaintext attack to impersonate other principals in the realm.
                The openafs distributed file system uses Kerberos 4, and is consequently vulnerable to an impersonation attack.
                </p>
                
                        <ul>
				<li>Severity: Critical - Authentication compromise.</li>
				<li>Packages Affected:  net-fs/openafs versions prior to openafs-1.3.2-r1</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge openafs, emerge clean.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=44890">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://www.openafs.org/pages/security/OPENAFS-SA-2003-001.txt">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>GLSA: dietlibc</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                The xdrmem_getbytes() function included in dietlibc contains an integer overflow vulnerability
                that could be used by a remote attacker to execute an rpc call that permits an exploit on the
                vulnerable service.
                </p>
                
                        <ul>
				<li>Severity: High - Remote service exploit.</li>
				<li>Packages Affected:  dev-libs/dietlibc versions prior to dietlibc-0.22-r1</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge dietlibc, emerge clean.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=44894">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://www.eeye.com/html/Research/Advisories/AD20030318.html">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New Security Bug Reports</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		There were no new security bugs this week that are still outstanding.
                </p>
		</body>
	</section>	
	<section>
		<title>gentoo-security</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                Marcus Martin posted an <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-security&amp;m=104920408624890&amp;w=2">
                idea</uri> about including "emerge security" functionality that would automatically update packages for which
                a GLSA had been released.  This prompted a fair bit of discussion, with the consensus being that it was a good 
                idea (albeit one that might not be trivially easy to implement) and had already been documented as 
                <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=5835">bug #5835</uri>.
                </p>
                <p>
                Chris Frey <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-security&amp;m=104873935409280&amp;w=2">posted</uri> 
                a script for providing a set of md5sums on the master portage server to allow gentooers to check for trojaned ebuilds.
                This was proposed as a stopgap measure while we wait for signed ebuilds.  The post prompted some discussion, including
                criticism that it might overburden servers and their administrators as well as potentially redirect developer resources
                from a more robust final solution in portage.  The discussion was brought to a conclusion by Nicholas Jones' 
                <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-security&amp;m=104879793011018&amp;w=2">post</uri> which pointed out
                that the problem was moot because we would begin to see a solution as early as portage-2.0.47.
                </p>
		</body>
	</section>	
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Featured Developer of the Week</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Seth Chandler</p>
<figure
link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030407_sethbc.jpg" short="Seth Chandler, aka sethbc" caption="Seth Chandler, aka sethbc" />
<p>
Everyone likes to complain about how slow <uri link="http://www.OpenOffice.org/">OpenOffice</uri> is, but it's still one of the most full-featured and MS Office-compatible suites out there.  This week's featured developer, <mail link="sethbc@gentoo.org">Seth Chandler</mail>, is in charge of the openoffice and openoffice-bin packages, and also maintains keychain, writes some docs, and is also one of the three PPC co-leads.  His primary duty - fixing bugs that crop up with OpenOffice - takes up most of his time, but he also helps take up the slack when other developers go missing.  Seth began using Gentoo about two years ago, and was invited to the Gentoo development team five months ago by Spanky, whom he knew from school, because they needed someone to be in charge of OpenOffice.  Through his work with Gentoo, he has become a regular of IRC channels and mailing lists related to OpenOffice, and has been contributing to OpenOffice's <uri link="http://www.openoffice.org/project_issues.html">IssueZilla</uri> because Gentoo's bleeding-edge nature means that problems are often noticed here before they are on other distributions.
</p>
<p>
During the day, Seth is a student at <uri link="http://www.wpi.edu/">Worcester Polytechnic Institute</uri>, and will go to Cornell Law School once he graduates.  His three computers (a Dual P3, a Dual Athlon MP 2100, and a 15.2-inch Powerbook) all run Gentoo, although the Mac dual boots with OS X.  He runs Waimea-cvs and qmail on all of his boxen, and his favorite apps include gaim-cvs, xchat-2, kmail, aterm, and gkrellm.  Both of his x86 machines run the latest sources, which at the time of the interview was 2.5.65-mm2, but when he's feeling spicy he'll run off a live BitKeeper repo.
</p>
<p>
Seth is a member of the <uri link="http://atlanta.braves.mlb.com/">Atlanta Braves</uri> ground crew and has been enjoying working down there for 15 years; his father is the team doctor.  He says he goes to school in the offseason.
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard In The Community</title>
<section>
	<title>Web Forums</title>
	<body>
	<p><b>Slithering Along the Bleeding Edge</b></p>

	<p>The development tree of the Linux kernel is advancing towards 2.6 rapidly, and several threads in the forums are making clear that Gentooists are pretty much following the development as closely as possible. Not without the occasional problem, apparently...</p>
	<p><ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=44859">development kernel 2.5.66 what works / doesn't work for you?</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=45637">Patches for mm-sources 2.5.66r3</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	<p><b>Best April Fool's Joke Ever</b></p>

	<p>Check the first link in our list: The forums had actually predicted that this would happen... But the threat of Portage's disappearance hit a nerve in many faithful Gentoo users, and many went into shock for anything between a split-second to several hours. They shouted abuse at their screens or room mates, and threatened to start deleting their portage tree before it dawned on them: They'd been had... And amidst the outrage over Gentoo's alleged move to RPM, only a handful of Germans found the second false news in last week's GWN.</p>
	<p><ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=44880">No GWN today?</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=44980">Portage 2.1 moving to RPM</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=45028">emerge -> rpm?</uri> (German)</li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=45646">Portage 2.1 e lsb</uri> (Italian)</li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=45039">Gentoo basé sur les rpm ???</uri> (French)</li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	<section>
     <title>gentoo-user</title>
     <body>
       <p><b>Gentoo Corporate Usage?</b></p>
       <p>
	   With over 60 responses so far, this week's busiest thread on gentoo-user asks about companies (preferably large ones) that are using Gentoo in a production environment.  Many people responded indicating they didn't feel Gentoo was appropriate for a production environment, noting too many problems with their own personal systems.  Others indicated that Gentoo ran quite happily in a production role, often serving upwards of 150,000 clients.  The responses are obviously quite varied and, in many cases, off-topic, but the thread does contain quite a few interesting insights into the trials and tribulations of using Gentoo Linux in a production environment.
		</p>
		<ul>
		<li><uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?t=104930176600004&amp;r=3&amp;w=2">Survey: Gentoo Corporate Usage?</uri></li>
		</ul>
		<p><b>Package management for non-ebuild software</b></p>
		<p>
		Jan Drugowitsch asked about managing software packages installed outside of Portage on a Gentoo Linux system.  Responses were varied and helpful, pointing to several open source projects which might fit the bill.
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li><uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;w=2&amp;r=1&amp;s=package+management+for+non-ebuild&amp;q=b">Package management for non-ebuild software</uri></li>
		</ul>
	</body>
	</section>
<section>
  <title>gentoo-dev</title>
  <body>
  <p><b>Portage Programming Question</b></p>
  <p>Robin H. Johnson
     <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-dev&amp;m=104900613027231&amp;w=2">asked</uri>
	 about the availability of some documentation on the Portage DB API and he received a nice surprise
	 when he was told to type <c>python</c> [RETURN] <c>help()</c> [RETURN] <c>portage</c> to get to
	 Python's interactive help.
  </p>

  <p><b>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS="~arch" equivalent?</b></p>
  <p>Jani Monoses was
     <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-dev&amp;m=104877565711737&amp;w=2">wondering</uri>
	 if there is a more simple solution to the use of the long <c>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS="~arch" emerge package_name</c>.
	 Thomas M. Beaudry
	 <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-dev&amp;m=104877651312869&amp;w=2">chipped in</uri>
	 with the suggestion to use Bash aliases (see <c>man bash</c>). And another Thomas
	 <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-dev&amp;m=104877594312098&amp;w=2">contributed</uri>
	 with his alias definition <c>alias expmerge='ACCEPT_KEYWORDS="~x86" emerge'</c>.
  </p>
  </body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo International</title>
    <body>

	<p class="secthead">A French Meta-Project for the Meta-Distribution</p>

<p>Gentoo France is re-emerging itself: After the establishment of <uri link="">gentoofr.org</uri> in July last year (and carefully maintaining their good relations with the older project), a new organisation founded by Baptiste Simon, Guillaume Morin and Mark Krauth called frgentoo.net is now gathering supporters and activists willing to help with a new initiative for French translations of Gentoo documentation and tutorials, organising IRC channels and mailing lists, and generally wanting to round up more than just the usual suspects. The new club wants to provide a whole range of services around Gentoo Linux in France, and is determined to do things right by the community from day one. frgentoo's first elections for all posts in the association are going to be held by the end of the month, candidate submissions for coordinator and project leader roles are possible until 11 April, with the elections to be held by electronic vote between 14 and 20 April.
</p>

	<p class="secthead">International Event Calender</p>

<p>While the K&#246;ln-Bonn community is still publicly discussing the agenda for their first meeting, two events in the US have emerged at somewhat shorter notice:</p>
	<ul>
	<li><b>USA</b>: The University of Southern Mississippi in Hattiesburg is having a "Gentoo Saturday" on 12 April. Development kernel performance and general installation help will be at the center of the event, held on the University's campus in the Bobby Chain Technology Building, Room 202 starting from 10:00 to 14:00. Check the corresponding <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=45616">forum thread</uri>, further details are <uri link=" http://www.99b.org/lug/gentoo.html
">here</uri>.</li>
	<li><b>USA</b>: If you happen to live in places with names like Metuchen, Old Bridge or Hackensack, the first meeting of the New Jersey Gentoo Linux User Group may well be what you've been waiting for. The happy NJ-GLUG lot has agreed on the Cafe52 on Easton Avenue in New Brunswick as their venue for the initial get-together, on 16 April at 20:00. Coordination for this meeting is done via <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=42874">this forum thread</uri>.</li>
	<li><b>Germany</b>14 May is now the official date for Gentoo users in the K&#246;ln/Bonn region, and now they also have decided on a time (17:00) and a venue: Hellers Brauhaus, Roonstrasse. Tell the others about your intentions to come <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=40510">right here</uri>.</li>
	</ul>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Portage Watch</title>
<section>
<title>The following stable packages were added to portage this week</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li> app-games/tetrix : A GNU TetriNET server <uri>http://tetrinetx.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Updates to notable packages</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li>sys-apps/portage - portage-2.0.47-r13.ebuild; </li>
<li>sys-kernel/* - gs-sources-2.4.21_pre6.ebuild; hardened-sources-2.4.20.ebuild; mm-sources-2.5.66-r2.ebuild; mm-sources-2.5.66-r3.ebuild; ppc-sources-2.4.20-r4.ebuild; selinux-sources-2.4.20-r3.ebuild; sparc-sources-2.4.20-r7.ebuild; </li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New USE variables</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li>debug - Tells configure and the makefiles to build for debugging.  Effects vary accross packages, but generally it will at least add -g to CFLAGS.  Remeber to set FEATURES+=nostrip too.</li>
<li>emacs - Adds support for GNU Emacs</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Bugzilla</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<ul>
                <li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect3">Closed Bug Ranking</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect3">New Bug Rankings</uri></li>
                </ul>                           
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Statistics</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
                bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  In the last 7 days, activity
                on the site has resulted in:
                </p>
			<ul>
				<li>288 new bugs this week</li>
				<li>751 bugs closed or resolved this week</li>
                                <li>3 previously closed bugs were reopened this week.</li>
				<li>2386 total bugs currently marked 'new'</li>
				<li>450 total bugs currently assigned to developers</li>
			</ul>
                <p>
                There are currently 2895 bugs open in bugzilla. Of these: 63 are labeled 'blocker', 107 are labeled 'critical',
                and 227  are labeled 'major'.
		</p>
                </body>
        </section>
        <section>
		<title>Closed Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs
                this week are:
                </p>
		<ul>
		<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">The Gnome Team</mail>, with 64 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		<li><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>, with 29 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=drobbins%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		<li><mail link="raker@gentoo.org">Nick Hadaway</mail>, with 28 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=raker%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		<li><mail link="george@gentoo.org">George Shapovalov</mail>, with 26 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=george%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		<li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</mail>, with 21 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=azarah%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		<li><mail link="mholzer@gentoo.org">Martin Holzer</mail>, with 21 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mholzer%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
        <section>
		<title>New Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs this week are:
                </p>
		<ul>				
                <li><mail link="raker@gentoo.org">Nick Hadaway</mail>, with 23 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=raker%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>				
                <li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</mail>, with 19 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=azarah%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>							
                <li><mail link="x86-kernel@gentoo.org">The x86-kernel Team</mail>, with 17 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=x86-kernel%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>			
                <li><mail link="mkennedy@gentoo.org">Matthew Kennedy</mail>, with 16 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=mkennedy%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>			
                <li><mail link="livewire@gentoo.org">Bob Johnson</mail>, with 15 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-28&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=livewire%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
                </ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>
<body>
    <p class="secthead">Changing File Attributes</p>
<p>
This week's tip explains how to use <c>chattr</c> to keep important system files secure. The &quot;change attribute&quot; command, or <c>chattr</c>, can be used to add or change existing file attributes for things such as synchronous updates, tighter file security, and more. However, this command is only available on ext2 or ext3 partitions.
</p>
<p>
    A list of common attributes and their associated flags is listed below. For a more complete list see <c>man chattr</c>.
    <ul>
        <li> (A) Don't update atime </li>
        <li> (S) synchronous updates </li>
        <li> (a) append only </li>
        <li> (d) no dump </li>
        <li> (i) immutable </li>
        <li> (j) data journalling </li>
        <li> (t) no tail-merging </li>
    </ul>
    <note>
        The 'j' option can only be used with ext3.
    </note>
    <note>
        The 'j', 'a' and 'i' options are only available to the superuser
    </note>
</p>
<p>
First make sure that you have chattr installed by emerging e2fsprogs.
</p>
<pre caption="Installing Required Files">
# <i>emerge e2fsprogs</i>
</pre>
<p>
To set attributes on files, use the <c>chattr</c> command and to view attributes, use the <c>lsattr</c> command.
</p>
<pre caption="Examples of using chattr and lsattr">
<codenote>Set the immutable bit on a file so it cannot be changed or removed</codenote>
# <i>chattr +i myfile</i>
# <i>lsattr myfile</i>
----i-------- myfile
<codenote>Testing the immutable flag by attempting to delete the file</codenote>
# <i>rm myfile</i>
rm: cannot remove `myfile': Operation not permitted
<codenote>Set myfile to append-only</codenote>
# <i>chattr +a myfile</i>
# <i>lsattr myfile</i>
-----a------- myfile
# <i>echo testing > myfile</i>
myfile: Operation not permitted
# <i>echo testing >> myfile</i>
<codenote>no errors - file was appended to</codenote>
</pre>
<p>
Some instances where this may be useful is keeping important files safe from deletion. Remember that even root can't delete a file that is immutable or append-only without first explicitly removing that attribute. Using this flag on <path>/etc/passwd</path> or <path>/etc/shadow</path> files keeps them safe from an accidental <c>rm -f</c> and also ensures no new accounts can be added in the event of an exploit. Keeping other files append-only means once they are written, that data can't be changed. Logs are a good candidate for this to keep them from being tampered with. With <c>chattr</c> and <c>lsattr</c>, you now have a few new tools to keep your system secure.
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, Adds and Changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li>Peter Brown (rendhalver)</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Makoto Yamakura (yakina) -- Japanese documentation </li>
				<li>Peter Bilitch (hsinhsin) -- Gentoo documentation</li>
				<li>John Mylchreest (johnm) -- Gentoo documentation</li>
				<li>Joe Kallar (blademan) -- Sparc documentation</li>
				<li>Ashton Mills (martigen) -- Gentoo documentation</li>
				<li>Thomas Pedley (shallax) -- Gentoo xbox</li>
				<li>Robin Johnson (robbat2) -- ufed, mysql, php</li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo Linux project.</p>
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<body>
	<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Feedback</title>
	<body>
	<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make GWN better.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Other Languages</title>
	<body>
	<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
