<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>February 3rd, 2003</subtitle>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of February 3rd, 2003.</abstract>
<summary>KDE 3.1 Released, mirror slowness and Gentoo server migrations.</summary>
<version>Volume 2, Issue 5</version>
<date>3rd Feb 2003</date>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="nesta@iceburg.net">Brice Burgess</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="david@phrixus.net">David Narayan</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="plate@gol.com">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="mail@psharp.uklinux.net">Peter Sharp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="matje@lanzone.be">Mathy Vanvoorden</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="tom.vanlaerhoven@luc.ac.be">Tom Van Laerhoven</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="roel@roel.ath.cx">Roel Adriaans</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="nicolas.ledez@free.fr">Nicolas Ledez</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="gui@moolfreet.com">Guillaume Plessis</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="thevedge@thevedge.net">Eric St-Georges</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="anfini@free.fr">John Berry</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="riverdale@linuxmail.org">Martin Prieto</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="madeagle@gentoo.org">Steffen Lassahn</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="haim@gentoo.org">Matthias F. Brandstetter</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="mush@monrif.net">Marco Mascherpa</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="paper@tiscali.it">Claudio Merloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="kage-chan@gentoo.org">Daniel Ketel</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="hagi@p1d.com">Yoshiaki Hagihara</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="andy@billydpro.com">Andy Hunne</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="yasunori@mail.portland.co.uk">Yasunori Fukudome</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="venturasbarbeiro@ig.com.br">Ventura Barbeiro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="blueroom@digitalmente.net">Bruno Ferreira</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="gustavo@felisberto.net">Gustavo Felisberto</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="rjlouro@rjlouro.org">Ricardo Jorge Louro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="lanark@lanark.com.ar">Lanark</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="julio@castillobueno.com">Julio Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="s3r@fibertel.com.ar">Sergio Gómez</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="pablo.leira@pitagoral.com">Pablo Pita Leira</mail>	
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@castillobueno.com">Carlos Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="tirant@menta.net">Tirant</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="jfreire@ya.com">Jaime Freire</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="krusty_ar@yahoo.com">Lucas Sallovitz</mail>
</author>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">KDE 3.1 Released</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Mirror slowdowns</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">Gentoo server migrations</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect5">Gentoo IRC channels changing networks</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>KDE 3.1 Released</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		On Tuesday, KDE 3.1 was released to the Linux community, with Gentoo ebuilds available the same day.
		This new release contains many new <uri link="http://promo.kde.org/3.1/feature_guide.php">features</uri>
		and security enhancements.  While there have been some reports of troubles, the upgrade process seems to be
		going fairly smoothly for most users.  The largest complaint so far has been the amount of time necessary
		to compile the new version of KDE, with many users reporting significant increases from KDE 3.0 compile
		times.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Mirror Slowdowns</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		One of the side affects of the KDE 3.1 release has been the significant slowdowns of the distfile mirrors
		for most Gentoo users.  Additionally, due to the increasing popularity of Gentoo, ibiblio (the main mirror
		provider of Gentoo Linux distfiles) has been forced to divert much of the Gentoo traffic onto a secondary
		'relief' server.  While this has helped to distribute the load somewhat, the sheer number of Gentoo-releated
		requests coming is maxing out the capacity of the server and causing http requests to be queued.  This
		can cause slowdowns and timeouts during emerges and has also caused some problems on the Gentoo.org
		web site since many images are sourced from ibiblio.
		</p>
		<p>
		Work is being done to transfer web site images to another location which should alleviate many of the
		broken images people have been seeing on www.gentoo.org of late.  As for the overall mirror slowness,
		users are encouraged to find and use a mirror closest to them and be patient as the KDE 3.1 tidal wave 
		subsides.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Gentoo server migrations</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		One of the main Gentoo Linux servers is being retired and, as such, some Gentoo services are being 
		distributed to alternate servers.  bugs.gentoo.org has already been migrated over to the same server
		that hosts forums.gentoo.org.  Other services will be migrated as well over the next few days.  During 
		this process, users may notice some glitches as the DNS changes work their way around the net. 
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Security</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><e>There were no security alerts this week.</e></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect1">New Security Bug Reports</uri></li>
			</ul> 
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New Security Bug Reports</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The following security-related bug reports were submitted to the bugzilla database this week:
			<ul>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=14842">app-crypt/mit-krb5</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=14844">net-mail/mailman</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=14845">dev-perl/Mail-SpamAssassin</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=14846">sys-apps/slocate</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=14628">net-p2p/qt-dcgui</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Featured Developer of the Week</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Mark Guertin</p>
<figure link="gerk.jpg" short="Mark Guertin aka Gerk" caption="Mark Guertin" />
<p>
This week's featured developer, <mail link="gerk@gentoo.org">Mark Guertin</mail>, is the senior development manager for Gentoo PPC.  He's in charge of coordinating the PPC development team and keeping things together, as well as doing plenty of bug wrangling and testing of PPC packages in an effort to get the best QA possible for the PPC arch.  Mark began using Gentoo when he heard that there was an unofficial port to PPC.  Jumping in two feet first, it wasn't long before he started the #gentoo-ppc channel, built a site providing Gentoo PPC binaries, and ended up becoming a developer.  Alongside five x86 machines running everything from Gentoo to Windows XP, Mark is running seven PPC boxen (mostly Gentoo except a few holdouts on a version of Slackware he ported to PPC long ago), including some arcane dual, and even quad-processor boxen, but his PPC mania doesn't end there: Mark has recently made some changes to yabootconfig, an automatic configurator for the <uri link="http://penguinppc.org/projects/yaboot/">Yaboot</uri> boot manager for PPC, allowing it to autodetect and setup even triple-boot with Mac OS 9, OS X, and Linux, and has also been, for several years,  hosting and maintaining the build machines for <uri link="http://ppckernel.org/">ppckernel.org</uri>, a site that builds binary kernels from several PPC trees, tailoring some for specific hardware configurations, using an automated kernel build system (gkb - the GNU kernel builder, written by a friend of his).  Mark also wrote <uri link="http://cvs.gentoo.org/~gerk/xeasyconf/">Xeasyconf</uri>, an automatic configurator for X in PPC written specifically for Gentoo PPC but usable with other distros too.  One of his favorite applications at the moment is <uri link="http://ich.bin.kein.hoschi.de/fish/">kio-fish</uri>, a flexible kio-slave that, given shell access and some standard UNIX commands, allows you to access a remote filesystem as if it were local.
</p>
<p>
A resident of Toronto, ON in Canada, Mark works as an IT manager and database programmer for a graphics printing/design house during the day, and as the lead developer of <uri link="http://www.cartwise.ca/">Cartwise</uri>, a highly successful B2B e-commerce suite.  When he's not hacking away at something, Mark has a 100% digital computerized home recording studio with which he enjoys writing, performing, producing, and engineering music.  You can hear some of Mark's music <uri link="http://artists.mp3s.com/artists/521/horsebeaters_anonymous.html">here</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Heard In The Community</title>
	<section>
	<title>Web Forums</title>
	<body>
	<p><b>Gentoo Artwork, Anyone? - Post Your Requests...</b></p>

	<p>It started rather innocuosly, with a single guy called <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=11355">port001</uri> just wanting to try out a few visual effects. Then he got ahead of himself and offered everyone the possibility to request an icon for their favourite application. Within a week, the designer posse has grown to eight Gentooists with a predilection for pretty knobs, and between them they've already created one of the biggest collections of buttons for window managers around. And just in case your software isn't represented yet, you can request it at the same thread, or just grab the Photoshop or Gimp template and do it yourself. And why stop when it's beginning to make sense: Congratulations to the creation of the Gentoo Environment Agency:
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=29321">My X-Chat Icon</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=31958">The Gentoo Icon Set</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=32276">Gentoo Environment Agency</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	<p><b>Tricky Laptops</b></p>

	<p>When it comes to mobile computing, Windows users are to be envied. Not only do they get their portable computers with an operating system preinstalled, no: the laptop manufacturers also do everything in their might to make the hardware actually comply with said operating system. Meanwhile, back in the jungle, Linux users have to post caveats and warnings all over the place to prevent worse things from happening during their installation attempts. Latest example documented in the forums: power management in the 1.4 LiveCD kernel that does very bad things to HP Omnibooks...
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=31254">Kernel panic: Kernel tried to kill INIT!!! (SOLVED)</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>

	<p><b>Some DIY Ebuild Scripting</b></p>

	<p>On mailing lists and newsgroups, it's rare to find people who answer to threads that went silent months ago. But in the forums, occasionally a threads just needs to mature for a few months, and then suddenly someone will pick it up, post a few additions and make it all the more useful. Here's a perl script for building packages you can grab and install on a less powerful machine or replicate across your network:
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=12026">building packages without installing them</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	<p><b>Forum Now Hosting Bugs</b></p>

	    <p><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=1742">rac</uri> posted an announcement that sent shivers down the spines of a few people who thought that phpBB had finally revealed some terminal flaws. Fear nothing, it's just <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri> that is now being hosted on the same machine as the forums. This looks like the perfect occasion to remind people to search for prior occurrences of their own problem. And best try searching both the forums and the particularly fine assortment of bugs in Gentoo at the sister-site. Unless you don't mind becoming a target of the dreaded "Spot the dup" thread, that is:  
	    <ul>
		<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=32724">Forums are now hosting bugs</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28820">Report possible duplicate posts here</uri></li>
		</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
    <!-- insert gentoo-user summary here -->
	<section>
	     <title>gentoo-user</title>
	     <body>
	       <p class="secthead">Mirror, Mirror on the wall...</p>
	       <p>
	       ... who's the fastest one of them all? With the onset of KDE 3.1 final, ibiblio.org's pipes appeared clogged with Gentoo users scrambling to grab the latest sources. Two threads were spawned on gentoo-user complaining of decreased download speeds and requesting alternatives. Adam Mercer <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104343629629967&amp;w=2">noted</uri> the existence of GENTOO_MIRRORS variable in /etc/make.conf along with the page <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/where.xml">http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/where.xml</uri> to aid you in selecting a preferred mirror, and avoiding the 'flakiness' of ibiblio.org.
	       </p>
	       <p class="secthead">There's more than one kind of Java</p>
	       <p>
	       Tom Eastman wrote that he has exclusively used Sun's JDK for all things Java. After becoming a Gentoo'er, he didn't miss the fact that his system relies on Blackdown's JDK by default. This of course raised the interesting question, which is better? Ben Ricker's <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104387085031123&amp;w=2">response</uri> pointed us in the direction of good benchmarks located at <uri link="http://www.volano.com/benchmarks.html">http://www.volano.com/benchmarks.html.</uri> In short, it depends on what Java is being used for and that all the JVMs will suffice for 'general desktop' usage.
	       </p>
	     </body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>gentoo-dev</title>
		<body>
	  <p><b>Portage irk</b></p>
	  <p>
	    Emiel Kollof 
	    <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6810">writes</uri>:
	    <e>"Why is it, when I unmask a package (with a  higher version number than the 
	      "official one") by using <c>ACCEPT_KEYWORDS</c>, portage downgrades it on the next 
	      <c>emerge -u world</c> to a lower version? This is very irritating behaviour. Can it 
	      be turned off or disabled somehow?"</e>. Caleb 
	      <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6816">answered</uri> with a 
	      solution and J Robert Ray pointed to a 
	      <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=12069">patch</uri> in bugzilla to add 
	      just that functionality.
	  </p>
	  
	  <p><b>Follow-up: Methods for managing etc files</b>
	   </p><p>
	   Jeff Kowing
	    <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6778">says</uri>:
	    <e>"Having seen my name mentioned in the bright lights of GWN[...] 
	      I was inspired to add an auto update feature to etc-update.  It works
	      by saving md5sums before you do a big emerge.  After a big emerge, it
	      uses those md5sums to determine which config files you have personally
	      modified.  Those you have never modified will be auto updated."</e> See
	      Bugzilla <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=14666">Bug 14666</uri>. 
	  </p>
	  
	  <p><b>Portage Database Management</b>
	  </p><p>
	  Ingo Krabbe <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6796">wonders</uri>
	    if there are any plans to have Portage use a database in order to improve speed.
	  </p>
	</body>
  </section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo International</title>
    <body>
	    <p class="secthead">Unofficial European Gentoo Websites (cont'd)</p>

<p>Ever since Enrico Morelli started Gentoo's Italian web outpost on 1 May 2002, he is getting help from two friends. The three of them maintain the one European Gentoo website the GWN managed to overlook last week: gentoo.it... A system administrator by day, Enrico has put Gentoo on every single piece of hardware he could lay hands on at work. Not that anybody in his department at the University of Florence would have been surprised about that, since he also was the person to introduce Linux in the Magnetic Resonance Center in the first place, some ten years ago. Now everything and the kitchen sink have Gentoo installed on them, including the institute's mail server, several workstations and an entire Mosix-cluster. The gentoo.it server still has its three admins, and it appears they're in contact with more volunteers, but sadly, the server suffers from slow connections and rigid conditions for Internet provisioning at its present location. If anyone knows where to host cheaply in Italy, has a spare server that could accomodate a PHP-driven forum or a mailing list, or maybe would like to help the Italian Gentoo community via contributions to their excellent documentation and security alert website, contact gentoo-dev@gentoo.it. 
<ul><li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.it">Italy: Gentoo Linux Italia</uri></li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Portage Watch</title>
<section>
<title>The following stable packages were added to portage this week</title>
<body>
<p>
<note>Because of the pending release of 1.4_final, the Portage tree is currently frozen.  As such, no new stable packages were introduced to Portage this week</note>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Updates to notable packages</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li>sys-kernel/* - development-sources-2.5.59-r3.ebuild; development-sources-2.5.59-r4.ebuild; development-sources-2.5.59-r5.ebuild; development-sources-2.5.59-r6.ebuild; gs-sources-2.4.21_pre3-r3.ebuild; usermode-sources-2.4.19-r41.ebuild; usermode-sources-2.4.19-r42.ebuild; usermode-sources-2.4.19-r43.ebuild; usermode-sources-2.4.19-r44.ebuild; usermode-sources-2.4.19-r45.ebuild; usermode-sources-2.4.19-r46.ebuild; usermode-sources-2.4.19-r47.ebuild; wolk-sources-4.0_pre9.ebuild; </li>
<li>dev-db/mysql - mysql-3.23.55.ebuild; </li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New USE variables</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li>ethereal - Adds support for ethereal wiretap log support in kismet</li>
<li>usb - Adds USB support to applications that have optional USB support (e.g. cups)</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Bugzilla</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect3">Closed Bug Ranking</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect4">New Bug Rankings</uri></li>
                        </ul>                           
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Statistics</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
                bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  In the last 7 days, activity
                on the site has resulted in:
			<ul>
				<li>287 new or re-opened bugs this week</li>
				<li>1590 total bugs currently marked 'new'</li>
				<li>568 total bugs curently assigned to developers</li>
                <li>52 bugs that were previously closed have been reopened.</li>
			</ul>
                There are currently 2210 bugs open in bugzilla. Of these: 43 are labelled 'blocker', 80 are labelled 'critical',
                and 151 are labelled 'major'.
		</p>
                </body>
        </section>
        <section>
		<title>Closed Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs this week are:
			<ul>
				<li><mail link="raker@gentoo.org">Nick Hadaway</mail>, with 22 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;resolution=TEST-REQUEST&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;emailtype1=exact&amp;email1=raker%40gentoo.org&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25">closed bugs</uri></li>
                                <li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org">The KDE Team</mail>, with 15 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;resolution=TEST-REQUEST&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;emailtype1=exact&amp;email1=kde%40gentoo.org&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25">closed bugs</uri></li>    
                                <li><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John P. Davis</mail>, with 11 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;resolution=TEST-REQUEST&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;emailtype1=exact&amp;email1=zhen%40gentoo.org&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25">closed bugs</uri></li>    
                                <li><mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail>, with 10 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;resolution=TEST-REQUEST&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;emailtype1=exact&amp;email1=lordvan%40gentoo.org&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25">closed bugs</uri></li>  
                       </ul>
                </p>
		</body>
	</section>
        <section>
		<title>New Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs this week are:
			<ul>				
                                <li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org">The KDE Team</mail>, with 24 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?action=wrap&amp;bug_file_loc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;bugidtype=include&amp;chfield=%5BBug%20creation%5D&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;emailtype2=substring&amp;field0-0-0=noop&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;long_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;query_format=report-table&amp;resolution=---&amp;short_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;type0-0-0=noop&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=kde%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
                                <li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</mail>, with 23 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?action=wrap&amp;bug_file_loc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;bugidtype=include&amp;chfield=%5BBug%20creation%5D&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;emailtype2=substring&amp;field0-0-0=noop&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;long_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;query_format=report-table&amp;resolution=---&amp;short_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;type0-0-0=noop&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=azarah%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>, with 14 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?action=wrap&amp;bug_file_loc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;bugidtype=include&amp;chfield=%5BBug%20creation%5D&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;emailtype2=substring&amp;field0-0-0=noop&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;long_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;query_format=report-table&amp;resolution=---&amp;short_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;type0-0-0=noop&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=drobbins%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="carpaski@gentoo.org">Nicholas Jones</mail>, with 13 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?action=wrap&amp;bug_file_loc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;bugidtype=include&amp;chfield=%5BBug%20creation%5D&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;emailtype2=substring&amp;field0-0-0=noop&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;long_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;query_format=report-table&amp;resolution=---&amp;short_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;type0-0-0=noop&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=carpaski%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="raker@gentoo.org">Nick Hadaway</mail>, with 12 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?action=wrap&amp;bug_file_loc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;bugidtype=include&amp;chfield=%5BBug%20creation%5D&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-01-25&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;emailtype2=substring&amp;field0-0-0=noop&amp;keywords_type=allwords&amp;long_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;query_format=report-table&amp;resolution=---&amp;short_desc_type=allwordssubstr&amp;type0-0-0=noop&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=raker%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
			</ul>
                </p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>
  
<body>

	<p class="secthead">Setting Your Terminal Title</p>

<p>
	Since most Gentoo users frequently use terminals (xterm, Eterm, etc.), this week's tip shows how to make them more useful by adding information to the title. We can add the username, hostname, and working directory into the terminal title, making it easier to see where a terminal is, especially if it is minimized. Instead of having to open up the full terminal window, a quick glance at the taskbar is all that's necessary.
</p>

<p>If you use Bash, add the following to your <path>~/.bashrc</path> file.
<pre caption="~/.bashrc">
SHORT_HOST=`hostname -s`

if [ "$SHELL" = '/bin/bash' ] || [ "$SHELL" = '/bin/sh' ]
then
    case $TERM in
        rxvt|*term)
        PROMPT_COMMAND='echo -ne "\033]0;${USER}@${SHORT_HOST}: ${PWD}\007"'
        ;;
    esac
fi
</pre>
</p>

<p>If you use Zsh, add the following to your <path>~/.zshrc</path> file. Zsh users can see the current directory if at a prompt, or any commands if a program is running.
<pre caption="~/.zshrc">
if [ "$SHELL" = '/bin/zsh' ]
then
    case $TERM in
        rxvt|*term)
            precmd() { print -Pn "\e]0;%n@%m - %~\a" }
            preexec () { print -Pn "\e]0;%n@%m - $1\a" }
            ;;
    esac
fi
</pre>
</p>
<p>
The idea for this weeks tip came from the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=18106">Gentoo Forums</uri>.  This functionality has also made its way into /etc/skel/.bashrc, so many user accounts may have this information in their .bashrc files already.  
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, Adds and Changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li>Peter Johanson (latexer) -- Wireless and laptops</li>
				<li>Jason Shoemaker (kutsuya) -- Python</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo project.
			<ul>
				<li>Tobias Eichert (viz) -- audio/sound related stuff</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<body>
	<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Feedback</title>
	<body>
	<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make GWN better.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Other Languages</title>
	<body>
	<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>

