<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>March 17th, 2003</subtitle>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of March 17th, 2003.</abstract>
<summary>Update from the Game Developers Conference, GWN looking for contributors, rsync.gentoo.org shows some strain, Gentoo Linux launches a "hardened Gentoo" effort, new items at the Gentoo Store</summary>
<version>Volume 2, Issue 11</version>
<date>17 March 2003</date>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="nesta@iceburg.net">Brice Burgess</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="david@phrixus.net">David Narayan</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="mail@psharp.uklinux.net">Peter Sharp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="kim@thinkit.dk">Kim Tingkaer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="matje@lanzone.be">Mathy Vanvoorden</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="tom.vanlaerhoven@luc.ac.be">Tom Van Laerhoven</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="roel@roel.ath.cx">Roel Adriaans</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="phj.dijkstra@home.nl">Peter Dijkstra</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="nicolas.ledez@free.fr">Nicolas Ledez</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="gui@moolfreet.com">Guillaume Plessis</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="anfini@free.fr">John Berry</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="riverdale@linuxmail.org">Martin Prieto</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="madeagle@gentoo.org">Steffen Lassahn</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="haim@gentoo.org">Matthias F. Brandstetter</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="mush@monrif.net">Marco Mascherpa</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="paper@tiscali.it">Claudio Merloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="kage-chan@gentoo.org">Daniel Ketel</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="hagi@p1d.com">Yoshiaki Hagihara</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="andy@billydpro.com">Andy Hunne</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="yasunori@mail.portland.co.uk">Yasunori Fukudome</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="venturasbarbeiro@ig.com.br">Ventura Barbeiro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="blueroom@digitalmente.net">Bruno Ferreira</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="gustavo@felisberto.net">Gustavo Felisberto</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="rjlouro@rjlouro.org">Ricardo Jorge Louro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="lanark@lanark.com.ar">Lanark</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="julio@castillobueno.com">Julio Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="s3r@fibertel.com.ar">Sergio G&#243;mez</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="pablo.leira@pitagoral.com">Pablo Pita Leira</mail>	
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@castillobueno.com">Carlos Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="tirant@menta.net">Tirant</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="jfreire@ya.com">Jaime Freire</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="krusty_ar@yahoo.com">Lucas Sallovitz</mail>
</author>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Update from the Game Developers Conference</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">GWN looking for contributors</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">rsync.gentoo.org shows signs of strain as Gentoo Linux continues to grow</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect5">Gentoo Linux launches a "hardened Gentoo" effort</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect6">New items at the Gentoo Store</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Update from the Game Developers Conference</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		As <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20030303-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1_sect2">reported earlier</uri>, Gentoo Linux was present at the recent Game Developers Conference as an official member of the NVIDIA booth.  Dean Bailey was Gentoo's official representative and was joined by Emmett Plant,
		CEO of <uri link="http://www.xiph.org/">Xiph.org</uri>.  Between Dean, Emmet and the compelling combination of Unreal Tournament 2003 and Gentoo, the conference was a success and introduced many game developers to the wonders of Gentoo Linux.</p>
		<figure link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030317_gdc.jpg" short="Alron and Emmet Plant at the GDC" caption="Dean Bailey in the jungle hat and Emmet Plant in the suit at the GDC"/>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GWN looking for contributors</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		It's hard to believe that the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is now almost four months old.  The ride so far has been a mixture of fun, frustration and plenty of excitement.  Each week, we get several emails commenting on how much people enjoy the GWN which is a great help in keeping the GWN team motivated.  In an effort to maintain the quality and comprehensiveness that our readers have come to expect from the GWN, we need your help in filling the following positions on our team:	
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li><e>Mailing List Coordinator</e> -- Follow the threads on gentoo-user, gentoo-dev and some of the other more popular mailing lists.
			Work with the other mailing list coordinators to write up a summary of the top 3-4 threads of each list</li>
			<li><e>Forums Coordinator</e> -- Follow the forums on the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri>.  Work with the other
			mailing list coordinators to write up a summary of the top 3-4 threads on the forums for that week</li>
			<li><e>Feature writer</e> -- Have an idea for an article you want to write for the GWN?  Let us know!</li>
		</ul>
		<p>
		If you're interested in one of the positions above, please send us an email at <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">gwn-feedback@gentoo.org</mail>.  Remember that it's folks like you that make the GWN possible.</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>rsync.gentoo.org shows signs of strain as Gentoo Linux continues to grow</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		As most Gentoo Linux users know, rsync.gentoo.org is a very important domain name.  What many people don't know, however, is exactly how rsync.gentoo.org works.  Currently, rsync.gentoo.org resolves to one of 20 different IP addresses through a process known as DNS round robin resolution.  This essentially is a way of randomly distributing the load of rsync.gentoo.org across multiple servers globally.  As Gentoo Linux continues to grow, we've continued to add rsync mirrors to our rotation as generous Gentoo users donate their servers and bandwidth to host a mirror of our Portage tree.</p>
		<p>
		This past week, Gentoo Linux hit an unusual problem as the number of rsync mirrors in the rsync.gentoo.org rotation increased to the point where the total query response packet size became too large for UDP to handle, causing DNS to fall back on TCP to transmit the larger packet size.  Despite the fact that this is perfectly valid behavior according to <uri link="http://www.faqs.org/ftp/rfc/rfc1035.txt">RFC 1035</uri>, many firewalls are still configured to block TCP traffic on port 53.  This caused some <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=40230">problems</uri> among the Gentoo user community as some folks found themselves unable to resolve <e>rsync.gentoo.org</e>, which also meant they were unable to successfully run <e>emerge sync</e>.
		</p>
		<p>
		As a short-term solution, the number of rsync mirrors in the <e>rsync.gentoo.org</e> rotation was reduced to allow responses to be sent over UDP.  As Gentoo Linux continues to grow, however, this will not be a permanent solution.  Instead, we're working on two longer-term solutions:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Migrating to the use of continent and country codes for rsync mirror rotations.  Please see this week's Tips &amp; Tricks section for examples on how to set up your box to use this new system.</li>
			<li>Changing our core DNS infrastructure to allow the continued expansion of the <e>rsync.gentoo.org</e> rotation without causing the response packet to become too large.  Look for more information about this in a future version of the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter.</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Gentoo Linux launches a "hardened Gentoo" effort </title>
		<body>
		<p>
		An official effort to build a hardened version of Gentoo Linux was launched this week.  Built using many of the userland tools, as well as the access controls currently available in <uri link="http://www.nsa.gov/selinux/">Security-Enhanced Linux</uri>, this effort should be of interest to anyone running a Gentoo server in an environment that demands a higher level of security.</p>
		<p>Anyone interested in participating in this effort should <mail link="gentoo-hardened-subscribe@gentoo.org">sign up</mail> on the gentoo-hardened mailing list.</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New items at the Gentoo Store</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Based on requests from Gentoo Linux users, the number of items available at the <uri link="http://www.cafeshops.com/cp/store.aspx?s=gentoolinux">Gentoo Linux Merchandise Online Store</uri> has increased significantly.  From posters to golf shirts to bumper stickers, now you can show off Gentoo Linux just about anywhere.  Prices have also been reduced on many items as well.  Remember that each item purchased from the official online store directly supports the continued development of Gentoo Linux.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Security</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">GLSA: ethereal</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3">GLSA: netscape-flash</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect4">GLSA: file</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect5">New Security Bug Reports</uri></li>
			</ul> 
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: ethereal</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                The ethereal network monitor application contains a string overflow vulnerability in its SOCKS dissector and
                a heap overflow in its NTLMSSP code.  These vulnerabilities could be used to crash or run arbitrary code under
                the privileges of the ethereal service by passing a carefully crafted network packet.</p>
                
                        <ul>
				<li>Severity: High - Remote DOS, code execution.</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: net-analyzer/ethereal versions prior to ethereal-0.9.10</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge ethereal, emerge clean.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=40358">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://www.ethereal.com/appnotes/enpa-sa-00008.html">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: netscape-flash</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                A patch which cumulatively resolves several buffer overflows and sandbox violations in Macromedia Flash players
                has been released.  These vulnerabilities could theoretically be used to gain remote access to a target computer.
                No exploits have been demonstrated.</p>
                
                        <ul>
				<li>Severity: High - Remote code execution.</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: net-www/netscape-flash versions prior to netscape-flash-6.0.79</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge netscape-flash, emerge clean.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=40235">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://www.macromedia.com/v1/handlers/index.cfm?ID=23821">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSA: file</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                The file(1) command contains a buffer overflow vulnerability that could be used to execute arbitrary code
                under the privileges of the target user.</p>
                        <ul>
				<li>Severity: Moderate - Privilege elevation, mitigated by requirement for target participation.</li>
				<li>Packages Affected: sys-apps/file versions prior to file-3.4.1</li>
				<li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge file, emerge clean.</li>
                                <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=40651">GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
                                <li><uri link="http://www.idefense.com/advisory/03.04.03.txt">Advisory</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New Security Bug Reports</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The following new security bugs were posted this week:</p>
			<ul>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=17386">dev-db/mysql</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=17489">net-mail/qpopper</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=17385">sys-apps/man</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>	
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Featured Developer of the Week</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Grant Goodyear</p>
<figure
link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030317_g2boojum.jpg" short="Grant Goodyear, aka g2boojum" caption="Grant Goodyear, aka g2boojum" />
<p>
<mail link="g2boojum@gentoo.org">Grant Goodyear</mail> is an old timer at Gentoo - quite possibly the only current developer who has been with the project longer is Daniel Robbins himself.  Grant, who had been using OpenBSD for scientific computing at work found out about Gentoo through Drobbins' <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/articles.xml">articles</uri> at IBM's DeveloperWorks.  At the time (about three years ago) #gentoo was a channel with only a dozen or so regulars, the 'ebuild' command existed but 'emerge', with its dependency checking did not, there were only a couple hundred packages, the gentoo-dev@gentoo.org mailing list was the bug tracker, and the only real source of information on writing ebuilds was 'man 5 ebuild'.  Like many others who eventually became developers, Grant fixed bugs and wrote packages until the lead developers (then just Achim Gottinger and Drobbins) got tired of committing his changes and asked him to become a developer.  Now he's a Senior Development Manager, a trouble shooter and occasional source of advice to younger developers.  Grant wrote the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/desktop.xml">Desktop Configuration Guide</uri> back when Gentoo upgrades meant a new install so that he could recreate his setup each time.  He also edited the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-x86-install.xml">Install Instructions</uri> which countless users have now used to set Gentoo up more or less from scratch on their machines.  
</p>
<p>
Grant is an Assistant Professor of Chemistry at Clemson University in South Carolina who publishes all his results in freely (as in speech) available, open scientific journals.  He's a theoretical chemist, so he spends a lot of his time using computers (all running Linux) to model chemical processes occurring in liquids.  He teaches Physical Chemistry 2, which comprises chemical kinetics, quantum mechanics, statistical mechanics, and spectroscopy to undergraduates who would prefer that understanding the world didn't involve so much math.  Grant is forced to run Red Hat on his 16-processor cluster, but his P4 and dual Athlon workstations, web/dns server, laptop, and home desktop all run Gentoo.  He uses Fluxbox as his WM, screen with irssi for IRC, konqueror for reading 'ebuild(5)', vim, galeon, evolution, and squirrelmail.  He feels obligated to use sendmail because he wrote the ebuild for it, but actually prefers postfix.  
</p>
<p>
Grant likes to read science fiction with good character development and happy endings.  In his less-than-copious spare time he <uri link="http://www.grantgoodyear.org/contra.html">calls Contra dances</uri>.  He just got married a few weeks ago, and has accumulated many frequent flier miles visiting his wife Sarah in Houston, Texas from his home in Greenville, South Carolina.
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Heard In The Community</title>
	<section>
	<title>Web Forums</title>
	<body>
	<p><b>Small Inconveniences</b></p>

	<p>Success can be a burden, everybody knows that. The Forums, being particularly successful, have had their shares of load problems, and solutions will have to be found rather quickly by switching to a more powerful hardware platform. While efforts are under way, site admin <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=1742">rac</uri> has put the brake on a few features that were responsible for bringing down the Forum's performance, notably the number of thread views that is no longer being updated, the list of people being simultaneously online not sorted alphabetically anymore, and a limitation to ego-searches that now includes only the last two weeks of an individual's post count:</p>
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=40767">Small inconveniences</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=40967">Where are all my posts?</uri></li>
	</ul>
	<p><b>Kernel Sources - Which Do What?</b></p>

	<p>Things were quite easy in the early days of Gentoo with just a handful of kernel source packages to choose from, but the variety of different patchsets, special purpose kernels and platforms at the end of a simple "emerge ***-sources" has grown completely out of proportion. Over the last week, a few descriptions have been put together to update the FAQ about kernel sources in Gentoo, creating a rather impressive document. Still a few blanks to be filled in if you care to add to the knowledge base:</p>
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=24634">KC6: Which sources?</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=37557">[FAQF] KC6: Which sources?</uri></li>
	</ul>

	<p><b>Embarrassing DistroWatch Cheat Attempt</b></p>

	<p>A particularly stupid git has managed to jeopardize Gentoo's reputation by rigging the page view count on DistroWatch, Ladislav Bodnar's well-known list of available Linux distributions. In Ladislav's words: "Now come on, folks! It's just a page hit ranking, it simply monitors how many times a distribution page gets viewed, nothing more! It's not meant to be taken seriously, which I've stated many times - to no avail". Some people are just hopeless:</p>
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=41214">Anyone else see this on DistroWatch? Gentoo Cheater...</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://www.distrowatch.com">DistroWatch</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</body>
	</section>
	<section>
     <title>gentoo-user</title>
     <body>
       <p class="secthead">Mozilla and Java, continued...</p>
       <p>
       The classic tale of Mozilla's distaste for a cup of joe on a Gentoo linux system has returned to the gentoo-user
       list this week. It seems that the lizard has plenty of pent up fire to warrant the use of caffeine.
       Fortunately this weeks telling contained many success stories on how Gentoo'ers managed to pair the two up.
       Examples were given for both Sun and Blackdown's JDK integration into Mozilla's plugins. These should provide
       any Gentoo'er the opportunity to take a crack at games.yahoo.com in no time.
       </p>
       <ul>
         <li><uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104725660525039&amp;w=2">Mozilla and Java</uri></li>
         <li><uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104742678404595&amp;w=2">Mozilla and Java (Again)</uri></li>
         <li><uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104726150427604&amp;w=2">Blackdown JDK Solution</uri></li>
         <li><uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104725976126661&amp;w=2">Sun JDK Solution</uri></li>
       </ul>
     </body>
	</section>
<section>
  <title>gentoo-dev</title>
  <body>
  <p><b>Portage-2.0.47-r10 Out for Testing</b></p>
  <p>Small changes to the portage system have been coming along this week. Changes include minor corrections and 
     alterations, but also additional features. All of this can be looked up in the 
	 <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-dev&amp;m=104738400107435&amp;w=2">changelog</uri>, 
	 of course. However one new option worth special mention is the change to <c>etc-update</c> that allows for
	 automerging of the config files. So from now on when the occasional 
	 <c>emerge -u world</c> is complete and all you have left to do is the <c>etc-update</c>, just let 
	 the new automerge feature do the work for you! It should be ready for tests so don't hold back on the 
	 <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-dev&amp;m=104738400107435&amp;w=2">feedback</uri>.
	 </p>
  <p>And a little reminder, if something isn't quite as it should be after the <c>etc-update</c>. Try 
     <c>env-update</c> and <c>source /etc/profile</c> both as root.</p>
  
  <p><b>GLSAs and an Automatic Security Package Tool</b></p> 
  <p>Ideas are forming about the Portage system somehow growing to include the GLSAs. This week has seen a small 
	 <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-dev&amp;m=104740560004390&amp;w=2">discussion</uri> 
	 about how it could come to life. The 
	 <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum.php?f=16">Gentoo Linux Security Announcements</uri>, 
	 as you all know, inform us when
     holes in software packages become a security hazard. And the general consensus is that it would be a 
	 very powerful tool if the portage system could not only update packages for us but also apply those 
	 very needed security patches. Or maybe even entirely mask them out and only allow for updates to packages
	 with no known security risks. Anyway, I don't think it is too much to say that it would be a most welcome
	 twist to Gentoo!
  </p>
  </body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo International</title>
    <body>

	<p class="secthead">New Dutch Forum Moderators Announced</p>

<p>Two new moderators, one Belgian, one Dutch, have been assigned to supervise <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum.php?f=36">the Netherlands forum</uri>. Long-time Forum dweller <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=3842">Garo</uri> and developer <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=8828">Foser</uri> have gracefully accepted to split the task between them. 
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Portage Watch</title>
<section>
<title>The following stable packages were added to portage this week</title>
<body>
<ul>
<li> app-emulation/stella : Stella Atari 2600 VCS Emulator <uri>http://stella.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> app-games/codebreaker : mastermind style game <uri>http://packages.debian.org/codebreaker/</uri></li>
<li> app-games/lpairs : Kids card/puzzle game <uri>http://lgames.sourceforge.net/index.php?project=LPairs</uri></li>
<li> app-games/penguzzle : Tcl/Tk variant of the well-known 15-puzzle game <uri>http://www.naskita.com/linux/penguzzle/penguzzle.shtml</uri></li>
<li> app-games/raptor2 : space shoot-em-up game <uri>http://raptorv2.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> app-games/tuxmath : Educational arcade game where you have to solve math problems <uri>http://www.newbreedsoftware.com/tuxmath/</uri></li>
<li> dev-ml/pxp : PXP is a validating XML parser library for O'Caml <uri>http://www.ocaml-programming.de/packages/documentation/pxp/index_dev.html</uri></li>
<li> dev-libs/xmlrpc-c : A lightweigt RPC library based on XML and HTTP <uri>http://xmlrpc-c.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> media-libs/dumb : IT, XM, S3M and MOD player library <uri>http://dumb.sourceforge.net/</uri></li>
<li> media-sound/hydrogen : Linux Drum Machine <uri>http://hydrogen.sourceforge.net</uri></li>
<li> media-sound/protux : Professional Audio Tools for GNU/Linux<uri>http://www.nongnu.org/protux</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Updates to notable packages</title>
<body>
<ul>
<li>sys-apps/portage - portage-2.0.47-r10.ebuild; </li>
<li>x11-base/xfree - xfree-4.3.0-r1.ebuild; </li>
<li>sys-kernel/* - ac-sources-2.4.21_pre5-r3.ebuild; gaming-sources-2.4.20-r1.ebuild; lolo-sources-2.4.20.2_pre5.ebuild; mm-sources-2.5.64-r4.ebuild; mm-sources-2.5.64-r5.ebuild; mm-sources-2.5.64-r6.ebuild; wolk-sources-4.0_rc2.ebuild; wolk-sources-4.0_rc3.ebuild; </li>
<li>dev-db/mysql - mysql-4.0.11a-r1.ebuild; </li>
<li>app-admin/gentoolkit - gentoolkit-0.1.19-r3.ebuild; </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New USE variables</title>
<body>
<ul>
<li>lirc - Adds support for lirc (Linux's Infra-Red Remote Control)</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Bugzilla</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Closed Bug Ranking</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">New Bug Rankings</uri></li>
                        </ul>                           
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Statistics</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
                bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  In the last 7 days, activity
                on the site has resulted in:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>284 new bugs this week</li>
				<li>417 bugs closed or resolved this week</li>
                                <li>6 previously closed bugs were reopened this week.</li>
				<li>2047 total bugs currently marked 'new'</li>
				<li>479 total bugs currently assigned to developers</li>
			</ul>
        <p>        There are currently 2586 bugs open in bugzilla. Of these: 66 are labelled 'blocker', 87 are labelled 'critical',
                and 185  are labelled 'major'.
		</p>
                </body>
        </section>
        <section>
		<title>Closed Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs this week are:</p>
			<ul>
				<li><mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>, with 21 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=seemant%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="mirror-admin@gentoo.org">The Mirror Administrators</mail>, with 18 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mirror-admin%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">The Gnome Team</mail>, with 18 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">The Games Team</mail>, with 15 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="carpaski@gentoo.org">Nicholas Jones</mail>, with 13 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=carpaski%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="kutsuya@gentoo.org">Jason Shoemaker</mail>, with 13 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kutsuya%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
        <section>
		<title>New Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs this week are:</p>
			<ul>				
                                <li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</mail>, with 30 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=azarah%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>						
                                <li><mail link="raker@gentoo.org">Nick Hadaway</mail>, with 20 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=raker%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>				
                                <li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">The Gnome Team</mail>, with 19 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=gnome%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>				
                                <li><mail link="carpaski@gentoo.org">Nicholas Jones</mail>, with 14 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=carpaski%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>	
                                <li><mail link="sethbc@gentoo.org">Seth Chandler</mail>, with 13 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-03-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=sethbc%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>
  
<body>
    <p class="secthead">Using a localized rsync mirror rotation.</p>
<p>
	This week's tip shows you how to take advantage of the new country and continent-specific round robin rsync mirror rotations.
</p>
<p>
The first step is to determine if your country has a round robin rotation assigned to it.
<pre caption="Using host to determine country-specific gentoo domains">
$ host rsync.no.gentoo.org
rsync.no.gentoo.org has address 80.239.42.138
</pre>
If your country doesn't have an rsync mirror rotation set up yet, you'll see something like the following:
<pre caption="Not all countries have rsync mirrors yet">
$ host rsync.mx.gentoo.org
Host rsync.mx.gentoo.org not found: 3(NXDOMAIN)
</pre>
<note>
You'll need to emerge the bind-tools package in order to use <e>host</e>
</note>
<note>
Not sure what your two-letter country code is?  <uri link="http://www.iana.org/cctld/cctld-whois.htm">Here</uri> is the official list.
</note>
</p>
<p>
Another option is to use the new continent-level rsync mirror rotations.  Currently, the following continent rotations are set up:
</p>
<ul>
	<li><e>rsync.namerica.gentoo.org</e> -- North America</li>
	<li><e>rsync.samerica.gentoo.org</e> -- South America</li>
	<li><e>rsync.europe.gentoo.org</e> -- Europe</li>
	<li><e>rsync.asia.gentoo.org</e> -- Asia</li>
	<li><e>rsync.au.gentoo.org</e> -- Australia (same as the country code)</li>
</ul>
<p>Once you have identified which rsync mirror you want to use, edit your <path>/etc/make.conf</path> file and place that value in the SYNC variable.<pre caption="SYNC set to use the rsync.us.gentoo.org rotation">
SYNC="rsync://rsync.us.gentoo.org/gentoo-portage/"
</pre>
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, Adds and Changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Patrick Kursawe (phosphan) -- bug fixes and miscellaneous stuff</li>
				<li>Sven Vermeulen (SwifT) -- Dutch documentation</li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo Linux project.</p>
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<body>
	<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Feedback</title>
	<body>
	<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make GWN better.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Other Languages</title>
	<body>
	<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
