<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20041213-newsletter.xml">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>December 13, 2004</subtitle>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="hansmi@gentoo.org">Michael Hanselmann</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="dams@gentoo.org">Damien Krotkine</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail></author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 13 December 2004.</abstract>
<summary></summary>
<version>Volume 3, Issue 50</version>
<date>13 December 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>New Chinese Gentoo Forum</title>
<body>
<p>A long-standing request has finally been fulfilled: The official Gentoo
Forums, according to our user survey the single most popular support platform,
now have <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=265378">a shiny new Chinese 
language forum</uri>. Requests for this language to be supported at the Forums had been 
brought forward for a very long time already, but were growing substantially over the past 
few weeks. </p>

<p>Enabling Chinese turned out to be trickier than anticipated. The language packs for phpBB, 
the software that powers the Gentoo Forums, are normally available in separate encodings, 
which would have mandated two forums for traditional (i.e. the Taiwanese and Hong Kong user 
base) and simplified (mainland) Chinese characters. Splitting the forum into two was out of 
the question for the Forum administrators, but thanks to Christian Hartmann (<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=15031">ian!</uri>) 
who finally set out to implement a recommendation from Chinese users, the language packages 
and headers were patched, and all files transcoded into UTF-8. ian! then released his changes 
on a few testers first, since being unable to read Chinese himself, he had to rely entirely 
on user feedback. Testing this way is similar to mooring an oil tanker using your ears only, 
but nevertheless it appears to work, didn't bring the ceiling crashing down or the Forum 
hardware to falter, and the two initial moderators are now eagerly waiting for the massive 
influx of Chinese users to put the platform under yet some more endurance tests.</p>

<p>The encoding to be used is UTF-8, which allows for both simplified and traditional 
Chinese in postings to the new forum. <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=54601">EricHsu</uri> 
and <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=82443">akar</uri>, 
will be the inaugural moderators to deal with the first wave of Chinese users to join the 
Gentoo Forums starting from today. Many Chinese Gentooists have been frequenting the <uri link="http://www.linuxsir.org/bbs/forumdisplay.php?forumid=59">Linuxsir.org</uri> 
forums, but are expected to adopt the new, officially Gentoo-driven platform, too. The 
freshly appointed moderators are able to read both character sets, but EricHsu is 
operating in GB2312 (simplified) and akar in Big5 (traditional Chinese) on their own 
PCs, and will share the supervision of forum posts accordingly. </p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20041213-chinese.png"
           short="Chinese Forum" 
           caption="Chinese Gentoo Forum editing window, with encoding set to UTF-8 and autodetection to Chinese" />

<note>While the content of the forum can be posted in either Big5 or GB2312, 
the board languages, e.g. the interface, the menu items and messages, can be 
set to each of the styles the user prefers: Both traditional and simplified Chinese are 
available as board languages now, too.</note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Future zone</title>
<section>
<title>Linux virtualization techniques</title>
<body>
<p>For some types of applications (development, service separations, simulated environments) it is preferrable to "hide" parts of the hardware or the operating system behind a virtualized machine. There are three major approaches to achieve this:</p>

<ul>
<li><b>Hardware Emulators:</b> These programs emulate the complete hardware step-by-step.
Bochs, PearPC, coLinux and QEMU belong to this group.</li>

<li><b>Hardware Virtualization:</b> VMWare, UML, plex86  and XEN do this. They only emulate certain system 
calls and Interrupts.</li>

<li><b>Limited Virtualization:</b> vServers only hide parts of the OS. Only one kernel is running, but system 
calls are intercepted and modified according to access privileges etc.</li>
</ul>

<p>All these techniques have their advantages and shortcomings, as hardware emulators for example are platform independent and just make-believe in parts or subsystems, but are extremely slow compared to hardware virtualizers. The latter are also mostly OS-independent, but limited to specific hardware (VMWare only runs on x86), and their performance isn't quite optimal yet. The limited virtualizers are optimized for speed and low overhead, and are perfectly integrated into the operating system, but of course completely dependent on it, and not all functions can be expected to work as usual. </p> 

<p>Today's future zone looks at some of the candidates for virtual machines and emulations, and sheds a little light on their availability and status in Gentoo Linux:</p>
<p><b><uri link="http://www.cl.cam.ac.uk/Research/SRG/netos/xen/">XEN</uri></b></p>

<p>This program is developed at the University of Cambridge. Guest operating systems need some changes applied, but XEN in return offers extremely high performance compared to other solutions.</p>
<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e> There are experimental ebuilds at <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=70161">Gentoo's bugzilla</uri> available.</p>
<p><b><uri link="http://user-mode-linux.sourceforge.net/">UML - User Mode Linux</uri></b></p>

<p>This is a Linux-specific virtualization. It uses a patched kernel for 
the guest OS, and needs a patched host for better performance. Some versions 
also support nested UMLs, e.g. booting a UML instance in another UML 
instance. It is completely encapsulated from the host OS and usually 
uses files for its "virtual harddisks". Therefore performance tends to 
be lower than XEN, but since it emulates a whole kernel, its uses 
tend to be different, for example honeynets, network testing, distributed 
computing testing.</p>

<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e>
The patched kernel is available as <path>usermode-sources</path> in Portage. A Howto exists at the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/uml.xml">Gentoo website</uri>.
</p>

<p><b><uri link="http://www.vmware.com/">VMWare</uri></b></p>

<p>This commercial program allows to run any x86 OS "in a window" on Linux 
and Windows. It is quite mature, and reasonably fast. Even stacked  
instances are possible, such as Linux in VMWare on Windows in VMWare on 
Linux, for example. The hardware emulation presents a S3 graphics card, so some 
special applications like Windows DirectX games will be unable to run. Different versions of VMWare are available, ESX Server targeted for  large server installations, and VMWare Workstation for desktop use.</p>
<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e>
<path>app-emulation/vmware-workstation</path> is a 30-day demo version. It can be 
upgraded to the full version by aquiring a key from VMWare.</p>

<p><b><uri link="http://maconlinux.org/">MOL - Mac-on-Linux</uri></b></p>

<p>The PowerPC equivalent of VMWare, but non-commercial and free. Near-native performance, runs Mac OS > 7.5, Mac OS X and Linux in windows or full-screen modes. Its only drawback is the inability to operate on the new G5 64-bit CPU Macintosh, but it does work on PegasosPPC, for example, even with Mac OS X.</p>

<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e>MOL is available in Portage.</p>

<p><b><uri link="http://bochs.sourceforge.net/">BOCHS</uri></b></p>
<p>BOCHS is one of the oldest emulators available. It is an x86 CPU-emulator written in C++, thus completely portable. Compared to virtualization, the performance is extremely low, but it still has its moments - or do you know any other program that allows you to boot FreeDOS on an UltraSPARC?</p>
<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e>BOCHS is available in Portage. Disk images for booting can be found on the BOCHS website.</p>

<p><b><uri link="http://pearpc.sourceforge.net/">PearPC</uri></b></p>

<p>The newcomer among the emulators. It is still in rapid development, but already allows to boot a virtual MacOS X on any supported platform (including Win32!). The speed is about 1/500th of a real processor, but the coolness factor of running bochs in pearpc in vmware is hard to beat.</p>
<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e> PearPC is available in Portage.</p>

<p><b><uri link="http://savannah.nongnu.org/projects/plex86">Plex86</uri></b></p>

<p>Plex86 wants to be seen as the Open Source alternative to VMWare. It is 
x86 only, but offers acceptable performance. The project seems to have 
little activity at the moment. A fork with slightly different goals can 
be found <uri link="http://plex86.sourceforge.net/">here</uri> but this is a Linux only 
virtualization.
</p>
<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e>
Plex86 is available in Portage.
</p>
<p><b><uri link="http://www.colinux.org/">coLinux</uri></b></p>

<p>Cooperative Linux is the first working free method for running Linux on 
Microsoft Windows natively. It can boot any Linux loopback filesystem, 
and even has limited network support through the TUN/TAP driver. It is 
not a replacement for Cygwin (which itself isn't a virtualizer, only 
an API translator), but offers the full bandwidth of Linux applications 
in Windows.</p>

<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e>A Gentoo boot image can be downloaded from the project homepage.</p>

<p><b><uri link="http://fabrice.bellard.free.fr/qemu/">QEMU</uri></b></p>
<p>This nice program is not one, but many emulators. It can emulate 
different architectures on a wide range of hardware, thus giving it the 
edge in flexibility. It is supposed to be much faster than other 
emulators, but the real performance will still be quite low. </p>
<p><e>Gentoo integration:</e>QEMU is available in portage.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>PDFlib: Multiple overflows in the included TIFF library</title>
<body>
<p>

    PDFlib is vulnerable to multiple overflows, which can potentially lead to
    the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-02.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>imlib: Buffer overflows in image decoding</title>
<body>
<p>

    Multiple overflows have been found in the imlib library image decoding
    routines, potentially allowing execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-03.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Perl: Insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

    Perl is vulnerable to symlink attacks, potentially allowing a local user to
    overwrite arbitrary files.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-04.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>mirrorselect: Insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

    mirrorselect is vulnerable to symlink attacks, potentially allowing a local
    user to overwrite arbitrary files.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-05.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PHProjekt: setup.php vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    PHProjekt contains a vulnerability in the setup procedure allowing remote
    users without admin rights to change the configuration.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-06.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>Too many mailing lists?</b></p>
<p>Are there too many (low traffic) Gentoo mailinglists? How do you get
all relevant info without subscribing to a dozen mailinglists? And
finally, is there a better solution? Find out what other Gentooists have
to say to those questions.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/23341">Too many mailing lists</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Small notes on developer policy</b></p>
<p><mail link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike Frysinger</mail> posted two
reminders on how to do things the right way: 1) Only apply patches 
arch-specific if absolutely neccessary, and 2) don't dump your bugs in 
<path>gcc-porting</path> (or some of the other defenseless bugzilla aliases).
He suggests that if everyone sticks to some basic rules, bugfixing and
updating will be easier and more efficient. And, if bugs are
assigned to the right people, they might even get fixed ...
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/23340">arch-apecific
patches</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/23314">a note about gcc-porting team</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Japan: Gentoo Bonenkai in Tokyo </title>
<body>

<p>GentooJP developer-at-large Masatomo Nakano, currently based in London, is coming back to Japan for a few days around New Year's Eve. As on previous occasions, this serves as the perfect excuse for the Japanese Gentooists to hold a Bonenkai, the usually raucous Japanese year-end party. Check the <uri link="http://ml.gentoo.gr.jp/users/">Japanese user mailing list</uri> for details on the exact location, so far the plan is to meet in Tokyo's Shibuya district on 28 December 2004, at around 18:00.</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Germany: Christmas party photos</title>
<body>

<p>The Christmas bowling event on Friday 10 December, organized by and for Germany's most weathered Gentooists in the Ruhr region that we announced two weeks ago, appears to have gone down quite well, and in perfect harmony, according to the impressive <uri link="http://www.gentoo.de/pub/pics/gum/ob/20041210/">photo gallery</uri> available at the German Gentoo website. Depicted are some of the finest developers around, but frankly, their bowling skills are not on the same level. The scorecards aren't much to write home about, but on the upside of things no harm was done to the inventory. 
</p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>
<chapter> 
<title>Gentoo in the press</title> 
<section>
<title>Heise online (7 December 2004)</title> 
<body>

<p>Germany's leading IT magazine reports about the upcoming 21c3 conference in Berlin, in an article titled <uri link="http://www.heise.de/newsticker/meldung/54008">"More than the usual suspects."</uri> Based on an interview with Gentoo developer and Chaos Computer Club spokesman <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>, the article specially mentions the Gentoo developer conference to be held during the 21c3.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 05 December 2004 and 12 December 2004, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>742 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>443 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>31 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 7590 currently open bugs: 126 are labeled 'blocker', 237 are labeled 'critical', and 548 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 36
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="tools-portage@gentoo.org" >Portage Utitilities Team</mail>, with 22
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=tools-portage@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 17
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="ppc@gentoo.org" >PPC Porters</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=ppc@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="vapier@gentoo.org" >SpanKY</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=vapier@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 23
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="perl@gentoo.org" >Perl Devs @ Gentoo</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;assigned_to=perl@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 9
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="net-mail@gentoo.org" >Net-Mail Packages</mail>, with 8
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;assigned_to=net-mail@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="mozilla@gentoo.org" >Mozilla Gentoo Team</mail>, with 8
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;assigned_to=mozilla@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="text-markup@gentoo.org" >Text-Markup Team</mail>, with 7
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;assigned_to=text-markup@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="php-bugs@gentoo.org" >PHP Bugs</mail>, with 7
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-12-05&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-12&amp;assigned_to=php-bugs@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>

<section>
<title>Fresh USE flag and profile editors</title>
<body>

<p><c>ufed</c> has served its purpose of providing an overview and editing USE flag settings in Gentoo systems for quite a while. Its ncurses-based interface wasn't exactly pretty, and it hasn't seen much development over the past few months.
</p>

<p>Enter the alternatives: <mail link="dams@gentoo.org">Damien Krotkine</mail> has just brought his new "Profuse" up to speed and into Portage. It is meant to be particularly good at dealing with cascading profiles, has a GTK+-2 interface that's generally pleasing to the eye, and is easily available by simply emerging it.</p>

<pre caption="Emerge profuse">
# echo "app-portage/profuse ~x86" >> /etc/portage/package.keywords <comment>(if necessary)</comment> 
# emerge profuse
</pre>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20041213-profuse.jpg"
           short="Profuse" 
           caption="Damien Krotkine's profuse, the profile and USE editor" />

<p><c>profuse</c> defaults to whatever is linked to <path>/etc/make.profile</path>, but it can already work on cascading profiles, too, with the profile editing GUI currently still under development:</p>

<pre caption="Invoke profuse with a cascading profile">
# profuse --profile-dir=/usr/portage/profiles/default-linux/ppc/2004.3
</pre>

<p>For Gentoo on Mac OS X users, <mail link="hansmi@gentoo.org">Michael Hanselmann</mail> has created <path>app-portage/portage-prefpane</path> that works as a plugin to the standard System Preferences
application of Mac OS X. It serves as an editor for the <path>make.conf</path> file and can manipulate USE-flags, features and mirrors. Additionally, it provides an interface to edit all variables in make.conf. It runs only on Mac OS X, of course:</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20041213-prefpane.png"
           short="portage-prefpane" 
           caption="Portage-prefpane fully integrated into Mac OS X System Preferences" />

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Michael Boman</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Torsten Veller (tove) - net-mail, net-dialup</li>
			<li>Aaron Kulbe (SuperLag) - net-mail</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo Linux project:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><e>None this week</e></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.</p>
<p>To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail> from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
