<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20041206-newsletter.xml">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>December 6, 2004</subtitle>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="bdowney@briandowney.net">Brian Downey</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="stuart@gentoo.org">Stuart Herbert</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="zypher@gentoo.org">Marc Hildebrand</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="randomaze@yahoo.it">Fabrizio Masia</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="ewagle@gmail.com">Emmet Wagle</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail></author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 6 December 2004.</abstract>
<summary></summary>
<version>Volume 3, Issue 49</version>
<date>6 December 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Developer Meeting at 21C3, 27 to 29 December 2004</title>
<body>
<p> The <uri link="http://www.ccc.de/congress/2004/">21st Chaos Communication 
Congress (21C3)</uri> is a three-day conference on technology, society and 
utopia. Traditionally held in the German capital of Berlin between Christmas 
and New Year's Eve each year, the C3 offers lectures and workshops on 
information technology, IT security, Internet, and cryptography, and offers a 
generally critical and creative debate on technology and its effects on 
society.</p>

<p>Last year's 20C3 already had plenty of Gentoo developers and users attend 
the conference, leading to the announcement of an official Gentoo Developer 
Meeting to be held concurrently at this year's event. The Gentoo Dev Meeting 
is scheduled for 28 December (the second day of the conference) at 18:00 hours, 
the guestlist and the agenda are to be announced at the 
<uri link="https://21c3.ccc.de/wiki/index.php/Gentoo">21C3's public wiki for 
Gentoo</uri>. It will serve many purposes, ranging from a simple get-together 
for (mainly European) Gentoo developers, via exploring the possibilities for 
closer co-operation, improved direct communication and more synergies in the 
network, to improvements to the Gentoo project as a whole. We will define the 
state of the European Gentoo developer network, and how we can improve 
developer relations in that network, we will discuss ways to work together and 
help each other with our efforts in maintaining and developing the Gentoo 
distribution, now and in the future.</p>

<p>Besides the developer meeting, other Gentoo highlights at the 21c3 are 
not to be missed, either, one being the Hardened Gentoo presentation of
<mail link="pappy@gentoo.org">Alexander Gabert</mail> on 28 December at 15:00, 
an introduction to the hardened toolchain, the PaX kernel, strong DAC/MAC 
control mechanisms and the project's thorough low-entry oriented user 
documentation, all-in-all providing "full scale" protection for a wide range 
of home to enterprise users. On the exhibition and activity floor of the 
conference, the traditional <uri link="http://www.ccc.de/congress/2004/">"hackcenter"</uri>, 
a Gentoo table will be set up to meet, greet and play around with Gentoo Linux.</p>

<p>Getting to know each other, sharing experience and planning future 
activities are important goals of this meeting, but we do count on its being 
fun at the same time. Please contact <mail link="zypher@gentoo.org">Marc 
Hildebrand</mail> if you like to attend or wish to add to the agenda.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New Gentoo Linux 2004.3-r1 release announced</title>
<body>
<p>Following quickly on the footsteps of the highly successful 2004.3 release, 
the Release Engineering project has put out a maintenance release for some 
architectures. Supplying a maintenance release was open to all architectures, 
but only a few found it necessary to provide one. There are very few changes 
in the release media, and this only fixes a few bugs which kept some people 
from installing. The affected architectures and their respective changes are:</p>
<ul><li><b>Alpha</b> - New LiveCD with a correct <path>aboot.conf</path>, 
<path>stages</path> and <path>livecd</path> moved to <path>/releases</path></li>
<li><b>AMD64</b> - New LiveCD with corrected Speakup support, <c>pnpbios</c> is 
turned off by default, and distfiles for <c>dhcpcd</c>, <c>slocate</c>, 
<c>usbutils</c>, and <c>pciutils</c> added to the Universal CD</li>
<li><b>HPPA</b> - This CD adds <c>lvm2</c> support to the LiveCD</li>
<li><b>x86</b> - Additions identical as for AMD64, and the x86 PackageCD was 
recompiled due to a missing <c>glib</c> dependency on <c>kdegraphics</c></li>
</ul>
<p>You can find the maintenance release media in the same location as the 
2004.3 release media on your favorite Gentoo mirror.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>UK Gentoo Developer Meeting Preannouncement</title>
<body>
<p>The UK-based Gentoo developers are pleased to announce that the Gentoo UK 2005 Conference will be held on Saturday 12th March 2005 at the University of Salford, with social events the night before and the night after. The theme for this year's Conference is "Success with Gentoo", and they will be running both a Speakers Programme and a Demonstration Programme. They're inviting developers and users alike who wish to take part in the programme to submit their proposals before 31st December 2004. For more details, see the <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~stuart/2005/">Conference website</uri></p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Future zone</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo on a 256MB USB stick: Flash Linux</title>
<body>
<note>Topics for this section may occasionally include projects that are not 
officially part of Gentoo, but affect it in one way or the other. This could be 
development in the wild that is is bound to end up being a Gentoo project in 
the future, or something that's inspired by and based on Gentoo, but heads off 
in a different direction all by itself. One of the latter is the topic for this 
week's column: </note>

<p><uri link="http://www.encryptec.net/flashlinux/">FlashLinux</uri> is a 
customized Linux variant designed to be run directly off a USB key or similar 
forms of bootable flash memory. Gareth Bult and his helpers have based their 
trimmed-to-fit binary distribution entirely on Gentoo Linux, with a special 
focus on Gnome 2.8, and the aim to to produce something that would encourage 
Windows users to give Linux a try. "The applications we included may not be a 
programmer's dream, but we're hoping they're what the average user is looking 
to get from a modern desktop system," says Gareth. Currently included are 
Evolution, XChat, Firefox, and a Ximian build of OpenOffice, along with <uri link="http://www.encryptec.net/flashlinux/flash032/index.html">many more</uri>.</p>

<p>The choice of Gentoo as the base for Flash Linux seemed obvious, even if 
generously overlooking the fact that its creator is a Gentoo user who has been
running his web servers on Gentoo Linux for the past twelve months. "I was 
looking for something as nippy as possible, and the task was to fit a quart 
into a pint pot," he explains - implicitly leaving little to no alternatives 
to FlashLinux being based on Gentoo. Provided a (x86 or AMD64) computer's 
BIOS allows for booting off a USB stick in the first place, the FlashLinux key 
fires up a 2.6.7-gentoo-r14 kernel, <c>autoconfig</c> comes from the Knoppix 
tools and provides hardware detection, and <c>mkxf86config</c> does the X 
setup. There's a GRUB based choice of either LAN or dialup configurations, at 
two different screen resolutions each. </p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20041206-fl.jpg"
           short="FlashLinux" 
           caption="Windows-swatting penguin splashscreen: FlashLinux USB key booting" />

<p>"Everybody knows the LAN setup works perfectly in the Gentoo LiveCDs, but we 
were surprised how well dialup is integrated, too," says Gareth Bult. While 
comments he received from early adopters show mostly awe that this fits onto 
a 256MB key - that even keeps 50MB of free space - the stick itself is where 
the developers identify a decisive factor. According to them, the choice of 
media is crucial for a usable configuration: "USB 1.0 keys only transfer data 
at 1Mbps and are unusable when it comes to FlashLinux. But even USB 2.0 keys do 
not really transfer data at 480Mbps, typical rates vary between 5 and 10Mbps." 
But even the more expensive recommendations in USB memory sticks are typically 
still within a 30 USD price range.</p>

<p>The FlashLinux creator has placed his work under the GPL, and hopes 
for outside help from people interested in different aspects, like making the 
USB sticks ADSL-ready, solving bootsplash issues with newer kernels, and other 
contributions or ideas that are most welcome. The contact address is <mail link="hostmaster@encryptec.net">hostmaster@encryptec.net</mail>.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>Open DC Hub: Remote code execution</title>
<body>
<p>

    Open DC Hub contains a buffer overflow that can be exploited to allow
    remote code execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200411-37.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sun and Blackdown Java: Applet privilege escalation</title>
<body>
<p>

    The Java plug-in security in Sun and Blackdown Java environments can be
    bypassed to access arbitrary packages, allowing untrusted Java applets to
    perform unrestricted actions on the host system.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200411-38.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>rssh, scponly: Unrestricted command execution</title>
<body>
<p>

    rssh and scponly do not filter command-line options that can be exploited
    to execute any command, thereby allowing a remote user to completely bypass
    the restricted shell.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-01.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>

<section>
<title>gentoo-user</title>
<body>
<p><b>udev or devfs</b></p>
<p>Systems running a 2.6 kernel now have the option of installing udev. One user notices some of the online Gentoo documentation still advises devfs and asks for suggestions on configuring udev.</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/110178">new 2004.3 system - to devfs or not to devfs, that is the question</uri> </li>
</ul>
<p><b>To opt or not to opt.  That is the question!</b></p>
<p>
A discussion regarding the location of the gentoo-rsync-mirror ebuild's install popped up this week.  Why was it
in /opt?  Shouldn't it be in /usr?  A series of (opinioned) answers came in, including some brief history of where
/opt came from in the first place.</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/110104">Local portage repository</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Gentoo... Limiting?</b></p>
<p>
One of the Gentoo provisions is that users have full control over their system.  Is this true?  One lister posed this
question on the gentoo-user mailing list this week.  It of course spawned a great discussion.  The short of it is that
Gentoo is as configurable as you want it to be, as long as you learn the tools in Portage fully.
</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/110040">Gentoo limitations</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>libperl rebuilder</b></p>
<p>After upgrading Perl packages one user asks how to update all the Perl modules.</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/109990">Upgrading Perl Modules when Upgrading Perl</uri> </li>
</ul>
<p><b>Best Digital Camera for Linux?</b></p>
<p>Nothing can be more frustrating than buying a shiny new computer toy, just to find out that it does not work with
your favorite Linux distribution.  With Christmas right around the corner; the gifts for geeks shopping season is
ramping up into full gear.  This thread has some tips for purchasing a digital camera that will work seamlessly with
Gentoo--or any Linux for that matter!
</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/109549">Suggestions for a Digital Camera under Linux</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Italy: GentooDay report</title>
<body>

<p>"Macelli Comunali", the municipal slaughterhouse, sounds a bit 
strange for a meeting in the framework of the Italian LinuxDay, but
the Gechi's contact in Prato, a nice little town near Florence, 
assured penguins of the Gentoo variety wouldn't run any danger: It's 
an old palace now, used as meeting spot and conference hall for many 
activities of non-profit organizations.</p>

<p>The place was cold, but the Gechi effectively heated it with their 
computers. Half an hour into the event, the distfiles and rsync mirror 
for people was set up, and the LAN was fully working for present Gentoo 
users to do a few happy emerges. Being curious about each other 
characterized much of the atmosphere in the morning, since it was the 
first meeting ever for many of the Gechis. While others continued to 
trickle in, <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=27023">Giulio 
Salani (zuglio)</uri> explained about his Vidalinux tests, and <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=15873">Matteo Pescarin (peach)</uri> 
showed his wonderful posters.</p>
<p>In the afternoon <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=16241">Giacomo 
Benvenuti (benve)</uri> did a ceremonial first download from the new 
experimental <uri link="http://ftp.students.cs.unibo.it/gentoo/">Italian 
Gentoo mirror in Bologna</uri>, and some people created a <c>distcc</c> 
LAN between their laptops.</p>
<p>Then it was time for the presentations, and the first was about <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=36380">Andrea 
Perotti's (deadhead)</uri> "Success stories of Gentoo in commercial 
companies". Unfortunately, Andrea had to fight the projector for an 
hour, and could only begin after that, leaving no time for <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=15873">Giovanni 
Ferri's (FonderiaDigitale)</uri>'s talk about the "Creation of a blackbox 
for securing your network environment" that was also planned for the 
afternoon slot. Giovanni's extraordinary presentation was finally held 
later that night, but ordinary visitors had all left by then, he only 
spoke to a nucleus of Gentoo activists, all well-fed with an intriguing 
local delicacy known as an F2 sandwich.</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20041206-gday.jpg"
           short="GentooDay" 
           caption="Gechi activists at the former abattoir of Prato" />
<note>Left to right: <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=48865">Cazzantoio</uri>, 
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=15368">akiross</uri>, <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=32804">oRDeX</uri>, <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=68764">lavish</uri>, 
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=32946">randomaze</uri>, <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=74185">nemesix2001</uri>, <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=36380">.:deadhead:.</uri>, and sitting in front holding the magic penguin that never falls from the table: <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=44801">genGNUbbo</uri>
</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Austria: New AGLUG website</title>
<body>

<p>The former Vienna Gentoo Linux Users Group has grown steadily over the year, and now broadened its focus to encompass an all-Austrian support group. <uri link="http://www.aglug.net">A new website</uri> has been set up that carries many new services, including a brand new Austrian Gentoo user forum, and an RSS feed for local news. Stammtisch-type regular meetings are being organized every month, with the next one to take place on 16 December. Check the <uri link="http://www.aglug.net/index.php?option=com_events&amp;Itemid=40">event calendar</uri> for details. 
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Germany: Nürnberg meeting report</title>
<body>

<p>Karl Hansl reports from the first meeting in Nürnberg last week: "Local Gentoo users met and discussed typical Linux topics, such as which motorcycle brand was faster, Kawasaki or Honda, and had some off-topic chats about programming, too. Current experience tells us that GUGN participants come from all ranges of society, self-employed, students, IT interns, and professional sysadmins. We'll definitely meet again, on 5 January 2005, and hope that others can join us then."</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter> 
<title>Gentoo in the press</title> 
<section>
<title>Linux Devices (3 December 2004)</title> 
<body>

<p>Linux Devices extensively covers the Gentoo Embedded project this week, in an article about the <uri link="http://linuxdevices.com/news/NS3119470185.html">"New kid on the embedded Linux block"</uri>. The author links to the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/base/embedded/index.xml">Gentoo Embedded web page</uri>, has friendly words for all developers involved, and even extends an official welcome to Gentoo Linux in the name of the Embedded community!</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>ZDNet UK update (3 December 2004)</title> 
<body>

<p>Based on additional information by Gentoo release engineering lead <mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>, the ZDNet editors have updated <uri link="http://news.zdnet.co.uk/software/linuxunix/0,39020390,39175014,00.htm">the article on upcoming releases of Gentoo Linux</uri> initially published last week. Details of experimental features planned, like the installer project and the option of running Gentoo Linux completely off the LiveCD, have been sorted out and are most accurately reflected in the current version.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 28 November 2004 and 05 December 2004, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>717 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>458 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>30 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 7619 currently open bugs: 130 are labeled 'blocker', 239 are labeled 'critical', and 560 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 35
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 25
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 18
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 17
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="dragonheart@gentoo.org" >Daniel Black</mail>, with 17
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=dragonheart@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="eradicator@gentoo.org" >Jeremy Huddleston</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=eradicator@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="vapier@gentoo.org" >SpanKY</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;assigned_to=vapier@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="dev-portage@gentoo.org" >Portage team</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-11-28&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-05&amp;assigned_to=dev-portage@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>

<section>
<title>Revival of the Compose Key a.k.a. Multi_Key</title>
<body>

<p>
Many users are on a keyboard layout which does not allow to type other characters than those printed on the keys. There are some workarounds with so-called "deadkeys" so that you can type characters with accents, but that does not enable you to type all characters in your locale.
</p>

<p>On many Unix-machines you can find a "Compose Key" on the attached keyboard. With that special key you can "compose" the desired
character.  For instance, typing the sequence <c>&lt;compose&gt; &lt;"&gt;
&lt;a&gt;</c> will result in the Umlaut <c>ä</c>.  Or take <c>&lt;compose&gt;
&lt;/&gt; &lt;o&gt;</c> for a danish <c>ø</c>.  With X it is no problem to declare
any key as the Compose Key, or "Multi_Key" as it is called in the internal routines.
Just remember that a keyboard sends only keycodes, and that it is unimportant which
keycode represents a given character or special key.
</p>

<p>
To enable the Compose Key you have to alter your <path>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</path>. There are other ways, like using <c>xmodmap</c>, but the global configuration with the <path>xorg.conf</path> ensures that the Compose Key will be available to all users. I recommend the
right "Windows Key" (just one of the two on your keyboard enabled should be enough):
</p>

<pre caption="Enable the Compose Key in the xorg.conf">
<comment># Your section in xorg.conf about the keyboard looks similar to this:</comment>
Section "InputDevice"
        Identifier      "Keyboard0"
        Driver          "kbd"
        Option          "XkbModel"      "pc104"
        Option          "XkbLayout"     "us"
        <comment>Option          "XkbOptions"    "compose:rwin"</comment>
EndSection
</pre>

<p>
After you restart X, you should be able to type the characters in the example
above.  A complete list of available Compose Key characters with their
description can be found in the file <path>/usr/X11R6/lib/X11/locale/&lt;your_character_enocding&gt;/Compose</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><e>None this week</e></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Joe McCann (joem) - Gnome development</li>
			<li>Michael Stewart (vericgar) - Apache</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo Linux project:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><e>None this week</e></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.</p>
<p>To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail> from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
