<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20041229-newsletter.xml">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>2nd Anniversary Issue - December 29, 2004</subtitle>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="aja@gentoo.org">AJ Armstrong</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="bdowney@briandowney.net">Brian Downey</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail></author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 29 December 2004.</abstract>
<summary></summary>
<version>Volume 3, Issue 52</version>
<date>29 December 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Second anniversary of the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<body>
<p>The inaugural edition of the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter was published on 23 December 2002,
a date conveniently placed at the end of the calendar year, henceforth to serve as a perfect excuse 
for reminiscing in major moments of the year gone by. This week's issue does contain some
of the usual sections, but we've also made room for the traditional (meaning it's happened twice
now, so it must be a tradition, right?) GWN staff and translator profiles. These are the 
people who have kept this publication alive for the past two years, and intend to keep delivering
news and insights into the Gentoo machine in the future. We're on a steady publication schedule, 
some of the abandonned translations have been picking up again (notably the Turkish, Russian 
and French versions are now available once more!). A big round of applause to everyone working 
for the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter!</p>

<p> Now, sadly, and just like last year, we have been unable to round up <e>everyone</e>, what 
with Christmas always coming as a total surprise and all, but in return we promise yet another 
incomplete list of suspects, originally intended for publication this week, but postponed to the 
next GWN issue: Watch out for a look at some of the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forum</uri> 
administration and moderator crews to satisfy your curiosity.</p>

<p>A word of gratitude to our 12,000 mail recipients and the unknown number of people flocking to 
our website each week to read the GWN: Thank you for your support, it's a pleasure working for
you! Please keep us posted about any Gentoo-related events, press cuttings, activities of all kinds
that you think would be worth covering in the GWN. If it's interesting to you, chances are others
would love to hear about it, too.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section><title>Gentoo buildtime and statistics database client</title> 
<body>
<p>After many months since the old Gentoo statistic database went away, <c>basc</c>, a new buildtime and statistics client, is now in Portage. <c>basc</c> updates information about a host running Gentoo Linux to <uri link="http://www.gentoo-stats.org/index.php?c=memstats">a central server</uri> (in this example: RAM statistics). Among other information, the client collects the kernel's <path>.config</path> and the <path>xorg.conf</path> files, and the developers involved are currently evaluating whether it is possible to have it 'suggest' configurations to new users based on previous configuration file contributions.
</p>
</body></section></chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Linux major events of 2004</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2" >Introduction</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3" >Daniel Robbins resigns as Chief Architect</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect4" >Gentoo requests NFP status</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect5" >Portage updates</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect6" >Deprecation of xfree86 in favor of xorg</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect7" >Gentoo named a finalist for the LWE product excellence awards</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect8" >Public Release of the Catalyst tool</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect9" >Release of Tenshi</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect10" >Gentoo/PPC and the PegasosPPC</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>
     <p>
       2004 has been an exciting and challenging year for the Gentoo
       community.  We've grown significantly, and few would argue that
       Gentoo is now the preeminent source distribution of Linux -
       some publications are even recognizing Gentoo as one of the
       major mainstream distros.  From major upgrades to the core
       system, through significant changes in base packages and even
       how the Gentoo community is organized, there has never been any
       shortage of news for us here at the GWN to report on.
     </p>

     <p>
       The sections below describe ten major events over the
       past year, with input from many Gentoo developers and selected 
       by the GWN editor and writers.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Daniel Robbins resigns as Chief Architect</title>
<body>
     <p>
       <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20040503-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1">Gentoo's
       founder and Chief Architect, Daniel Robbins, retired</uri> at
       the end of April.  This news came as something of a shock, but
       Daniel felt the need to move on to something new and focus on
       his family, as he stepped aside to permit the new board (see
       below) to take over the reins. He still contributes to the
       project, and has been sighted on the mailing lists and in IRC.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo requests NFP status</title>
<body>
     <p>
       In an event somewhat intertwined with Daniel Robbins'
       retirement, his plans to <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20040419-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1">transit
       Gentoo to a Not-For-Profit organization</uri> were <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20040614-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1">culminated
       in early
       June</uri>, with the creation of the Gentoo Foundation, a
       Not-For-Profit corporation.  This entrusted the copyrights to
       Gentoo technology, guidance of the project, and responsibility
       for administering the distro in the hands of a corporate entity
       with an elected board.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Portage Updates</title>
<body>
  <p>
    October saw the culmination of much of the work begun as
    portage-ng ("next generation Portage") with the <uri
    link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20041025-newsletter.xml">release
    of Portage 2.0.51</uri>.  This release added several new features,
    including initial support for GPG package validation, FHS
    compliance, and significant performance improvements - not the
    least of which is the use of lockfiles for parallel fetching and
    merging.  Of particular interest is the <path>--newuse</path> flag,
    which permits the re-emergence of affected packages after a USE
    flag change.  
  </p>
   <p>
     This culminated a long series of upgrades to portage that saw the
     shift from <path>make.conf</path> globals and command-line keywords to
     the use of configuration files in <path>/etc/portage</path> that
     permitted finer package-level control.  In particular, the use of
     the <path>package.keywords</path> file now permits the use of
     per-package keywords.
  </p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>LiveCD ISOs Available via BitTorrent</title>
<body>
     <p>
       In August, the Gentoo 2004.2 LiveCD had a parallel <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20040823-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1">release
       using BitTorrent</uri>.  This allowed more efficient downloads
       of the large files using the popular P2P protocol.  The
       experiment was a success, and it is expected that this option
       will remain available for future releases.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Release of the Gentoo Developer Handbook</title>
<body>
     <p>
       In July, we <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20040726-newsletter.xml#doc_chap2">reported</uri>
       that devrel had released of an updated and expanded <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo
       Developer Handbook</uri> that outlined not only the details of
       how to create and edit ebuilds, but the policies and
       infrastructure necessary to do so efficiently and as part of a
       team.
     </p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Deprecation of x11 in Favor of xorg</title>
<body>
     <p>
       In September, the default X11 virtual was changed from the one
       provided by <uri
       link="http://www.xfree86.org/">XFree86</uri> (<path>xfree</path>) to that
       provided by <uri
       link="http://www.x.org/">X.Org</uri> (<path>xorg-x11</path>).  This meant
       that, by default, the GUI installed on portage would be the
       version from X.Org.  This move was prompted by some changes
       made to XFree86's license for the 4.4.0 release that raised
       some question as to whether it was compatible with GPL'd
       software that linked X11 libraries. As of 31 December 2004, 
       XFree86 appears to be obsoleted and will be removed from the Portage
       tree, writes maintainer <mail link="spyderous@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholz</mail>.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo named a finalist for the LWE product excellence awards</title>
<body>
     <p>
       In January, we <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20040119-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1_sec2">reported</uri>
       that Gentoo had been named a finalist in the Linux World Expo
       Product Excellence Awards, in the category "best Open Source
       project".  Gentoo was also nominated for the same award for the
       August LWE.  Unfortunately, we lost to RealNetworks' Helix
       Player project and Firefox, respectively, but being named a
       finalist showed the recognition that Gentoo is getting in
       mainstream Linux circles.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Public Release of the Catalyst Tool</title>
<body>
     <p>
       2004 saw substantial development on and a public release of the
       <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/catalyst/">Catalyst</uri>
       tool, which is used to generate and build the stages, packages
       and LiveCDs.  The tool permits users to create their own
       architecture-specific LiveCDs, for example to create their own
       custom install builds, or to create a bootable Linux CD with a
       specific set of tools.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Release of Tenshi</title>
<body>
     <p>
       In June, we <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20040607-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1">announced</uri>
       the release of <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/tenshi/">Tenshi</uri>
       (formerly Wasabi), a log monitoring tool.  Tenshi was developed
       for use on Gentoo infrastructure servers, but rapidly became
       robust enough for general release.  Tenshi was one of the first
       software projects sponsored by Gentoo.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo/PPC and the PegasosPPC</title>
<body>
     <p>
       Since <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20041011-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1">October</uri>,
       <uri link="http://www.freescale.com/">Freescale Semiconductor,
       Inc.</uri> (a Motorola company) donated 13 PegasosPPC desktops,
       equiped with 1 GHz G4 CPUs to Gentoo developers.  This generous
       donation, to encourage development of FOSS Software on the
       platform, is an indication of the remarkable progress being
       made by the Gentoo PPC team in advancing Gentoo's support for
       that architecture.  In November, we <uri
       link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20041129-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1">reported</uri>
       that The Luxembourg-based company <uri
       link="http://www.genesi.lu/">Genesi S.à.r.l.</uri> had started
       shipping PegasosPPCs with Gentoo pre-installed.
     </p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN Staff Profiles</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect2" >Editor</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect3" >Authors</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect4" >German Translation Team</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect5" >Italian Translation Team</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect6" >Polish Translation Team</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap3_sect7" >Turkish Translation Team</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Editor</title>
<body>
  <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_plate.jpg"
	  short="Ulrich Plate" caption="Ulrich Plate" />
  <p>
       <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail> has been with the GWN ever since
       its inaugural issue two years ago, but only recently took over the role of its editor 
       from Yuji Carlos Kosugi who left in September 2004 to concentrate on his studies. Ulrich
       makes no secret of significant deficits in mastering the technicalities of publishing a 
       newsletter, but can fall back on his training as a journalist and PR specialist for IT
       companies going back 20 years to yield acceptable results, as far as presenting content is 
       concerned. Each weekend the process of editing the GWN is under close surveillance by 
       his family who try to make sure he doesn't spend too much time on it, with the actual 
       publication on Monday morning 0:00 UTC providing little comfort - as a non-English
       speaker he's very much afraid of inadvertently saying "Belgium" some day.   
  </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Authors</title>
<body>
  <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_aja.jpg"
	  short="AJ Armstrong" caption="AJ Armstrong" />
  <p>
       <mail link="aja@gentoo.org">AJ Armstrong</mail> began working
       on the GWN when it first began in 2002.  He recently returned
       to working on it from several months' hiatus that followed the
       birth of his first child.  AJ teaches Computer Engineering
       Technology at the Northern Alberta Institute of Technology,
       including courses in Embedded Linux and Operating Systems
       theory.  He also practices Karate and enjoys SCUBA diving, but
       most of his time is currently spent trying to figure out his
       son, who unfortunately arrived without any man pages.
  </p>
  <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_bdowney.jpg"
	  short=">Brian Downey" caption="Brian Downey" />
  <p>
        <mail link="bdowney@briandowney.net">Brian Downey</mail> began
        working on the community section of the GWN in September 2003.
        Other than breaking his Linux servers and Mac workstation
        computers, he spends his time with his wife Phaedrah and their
        cat Millie.  This summer, he's planning on teaching an
        introductory Linux college course in between running a Linux
        consulting business and playing guitar and drums in his
        band.
  </p>

  <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_patrick.jpg"
	  short="Patrick Lauer" caption="Patrick Lauer" />
  <p>
        <mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail> Patrick Lauer 
	has been writing the summaries for the <path>gentoo-dev</path>
	mailing list, some Tips and Tricks and other miscellaneous bits of
	news since he joined the GWN team in September 2004. He is a student 
	of Computer Science at the RWTH Aachen in Germany, with most of his spare 
	time being wasted between IRC (where he is known as bonsaikitten) and 
	the Gentoo mailing lists where he is rumored to be building up
	a somewhat trollish reputation. Patrick's focus in Gentoo is on
	hunting bugs, and he intends to get a fully automated compile 
	farm in the near future. Apart from that he's a busy Gentoo evangelist and
	tries to convert everybody he knows to the one true Linux. 
 </p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>German Translation Team</title>
<body>
    <p><b>German Translators</b></p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_herren.png"
short="Marc Herren" caption="Marc Herren" />
<p>
<mail link="dj-submerge@gentoo.org">Marc Herren aka dj-submerge</mail>
is 27 years old and lives in Bern (Switzerland). He's using Linux
since 1998 and Gentoo for about 3 years. Currently he's working as a
project leader in a networking company mainly dealing with HP-UX and
Linux. Besides computers he plays volleyball a lot and spins the turntables.
</p>

<figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_scherbaum.jpg"
short="Tobias Scherbaum" caption="Tobias Scherbaum" />
<p>
<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>  is 23 years
old and lives in Oberhausen (Germany). A Gentoo user for about two
and a half years, he is responsible for German translations within the
<uri link="http://gdp.gentoo.org">Gentoo Documentation Project</uri>.
Sometimes he also contributes some "Tips &amp; Tricks" to the GWN.</p>

<figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_brandstetter.jpg"
short="Matthias F. Brandstetter" caption="Matthias F. Brandstetter" />
<p><mail link="haim@gentoo.org">Matthias F. Brandstetter</mail> is 21 and
lives in Vienna (Austria). When he isn't translating the GWN into German, 
he is working as a freelancing Linux IT Consultant. In his spare
time, Matthias likes to party with friends or read an interesting book.
</p>

<figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_hansen.jpg"
short="Tobias Hansen" caption="Tobias Hansen" />
<p><mail link="tph@gentoo.org">Tobias Hansen</mail>, 24 years old, lives in 
Frankfurt am Main. He works as a computer scientist for end-to-end 
performance and availability measurements, and has been using Gentoo since 2002.</p>

<p><mail link="nadi@gentoo.org">Nadi Sarrar</mail> is 23 years old, lives in
Berlin and is a Computer Science student at the Technical 
University of Berlin. A Gentoo Linux user since about 1.5 years, he enjoys 
making and listening to music besides functional programming.</p>

<p><mail link="mluisser@gentoo.org">Markus Luisser</mail>is 29 years old and
works at the Institute of Chemical Engineering at the Vienna University 
of Technology, finishing his PhD thesis in the field of mechanical engineering. 
His job at the university carries the advantage of exclusively using Gentoo since more
than two years. He spends his spare time mostly training Aikido.</p>

<figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_ebner.jpg"
short="Martin Ebner" caption="Martin Ebner" />
<p><mail link="martin@gentoo.org">Martin Ebner</mail>is 29 years and lives in
Salzburg, Austria. He is employed as a software developer in a company for 
access solutions - mainly in a Microsoft environment. As compensation he 
works with Linux for some years now at home. He is using Gentoo Linux 
since 1.5 years on his home server which is used as video server based 
on MythTV beside other typical server functions. Aside from computers he plays 
the trumpet and participates in folkloristic activities like the "Biergemeinschaft 
Gaisberg" (beer-community Gaisberg).</p>

<figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_matzat.jpg"
short="Tobias Matzat" caption="Tobias Matzat" />
<p><mail link="SirSeoman@gentoo.org">Tobias Matzat</mail>is 24 years old,
lives in Trier and studies computer science at
the Trier University of Applied Sciences. He's been using Linux and Gentoo for
several years now, playing basketball, reading a good book and listening to loud 
music in his spare time.</p>

<figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_raschbacher.jpg"
short="Thomas Raschbacher" caption="Thomas Raschbacher" />
<p>Austrian <mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail> aka LordVan is
22 years old and moved to the UK in October this year. He's using Linux since 1995
and Gentoo for about 3 years. Currently looking for a job in the UK, he is a Gentoo 
developer since December 2002. When he's not coding or translating the GWN he's 
usually listening to music, studying Japanese, reading Mangas or watching Animes.</p>

<figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_gerholdt.jpg"
short="Daniel Gerholdt" caption="Daniel Gerholdt" />
<p><mail link="sputnik1969@gentoo.org">Daniel Gerholdt</mail>, also know as
Sputnik1969 is 35 years old and lives in Germany's capital Berlin. 
He uses Linux since 1998 and discovered Gentoo in 2002. He is also looking for a new job, and has returned to studying at school whenever he's not mistreating his computer.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Italian Translation Team</title>
<body>
     <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_marco.jpg"
	  short="Marco Mascherpa" caption="Marco Mascherpa" />
     <p>
       Marco Mascherpa is 25 and lives in Milan, Italy. This year,
       after completing his degree in Computer Engineering, he has
       started working for a small consulting company. His
       contributions to the Gentoo project began at the end of 2002,
       translating the GWN, now he leads the Italian translators
       team. He loves to travel with his beautiful girlfriend,
       Raffaella, and he spends his spare time watching movies and
       reading.
     </p>
     <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_rossi.jpg"
	  short="Stefano Rossi" caption="Stefano Rossi" />
     <p>
       Stefano Rossi is 25 years old, born and living in Rome,
       Italy. He has been on the Italian translation team for more
       than a year. He is studying Economics at the University Roma
       Tre. His favourite hobby is to follow the matches of AS Roma's
       soccer team everywhere in Italy, when possible.
     </p>
     <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_lucidi.jpg"
	  short="Stefano Lucidi" caption="Stefano Lucidi" />
     <p>
       Stefano Lucidi 24 years old and lives in Rome, Italy. He works 
       as an IT consultant and studies computer science at the same
       time. Stefano started using Gentoo 3 years ago because a friend 
       talked him into it, and but it was love on first sight, eventually
       making him the founder and administrator of 
       <uri link="http://www.gentoo-italia.net">Gentoo-Italia</uri>, a 
       web site with news for the Italian community, and 
       <uri link="http://wiki.gentoo-italia.net">the new wiki</uri>
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Polish Translation Team</title>
<body>
     <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_jbozanowski.jpg"
	short="Kuba Bo&#x017c;anowski" caption="Kuba Bo&#x017c;anowski" />
     <p>
       <mail link="jbozanowski@gmail.com">Kuba 'fixxxer'
       Bo&#x017c;anowski</mail> is a 24 year old CS student, living in
       Opole, Poland (although that's probably going to change once
       he's done with his thesis). Apart from computers he loves
       riding his mountain bike and playing guitar in a heavy metal
       band.  He also enjoys a good read and good food (We've heard
       that he makes a pretty good pizza).
     </p>
     <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_dziwisz.jpg"
	  short="Jakub Dziwisz" caption="Jakub Dziwisz" />
     <p>
       <mail link="dziwisz@icslab.agh.edu.pl">Jakub Dziwisz</mail>
       lives in Krakow, Poland.  He studies Computer Science at
       AGH-University of Science and Technology.  His main field of
       interest and subject of his Master's Thesis is Grid
       computing. Recently, he started a portal devoted to these issues,
       <uri
       link="http://www.grid-scape.org/">www.grid-scape.org</uri>. He
       has used Gentoo as his default OS since 2002, and since May he
       has helped to translate the GWN into Polish.
     </p>
     
     <p>
       <mail link="gooroo@gentoo.pl">Karol G&#x00f3;ralski</mail> lives in
       Radom, Poland, and works as system administrator. He maintains
       the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.pl">gentoo.pl</uri> server,
       providing many services for Polish Gentoo users. He has been
       involved in translation of the GWN for several months.
     </p>
     
     <p>
       <mail link="lucass@gentoo.or">&#x0141;ukasz Strzygowski</mail>
       is a 16 year old high school student, born and living in
       Kielce, Poland. He has used Gentoo for about two years. He is
       coordinator of Polish translation for the GWN, and was also
       involved in translation of the Gentoo Handbook. He was recently
       named a a member of the Gentoo development team and maintains
       some python-related packages.  In his spare time he reads and
       learns programming.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Turkish Translation Team</title>
<body> 
  <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_bahadir.jpg"
	  short="Bahad&#x0131;r Kandemir" caption="Bahad&#x0131;r Kandemir" />
     <p>
       <mail link="bahadir@gentoo.org">Bahad&#x0131;r Kandemir</mail> is
       a 22 year old Computer Engineering student, born and living in
       Turkey. On his last year in college, he started working on
       Gentoo Handbook translations. After seeing its customizability
       and performance, he switched to Gentoo Linux. Bahad&#x0131;r has
       been translating GWN to Turkish since October 2004. He also
       works part-time for an automotive factory as an Intranet
       Applications Developer, but unfortunately he works with
       non-Unix operating systems.
     </p>
     <figure link="/images/gwn/20041229_erkan.jpg"
	  short="Erkan Kaplan" caption="Erkan Kaplan" />
     <p>
       <mail link="erkan@linux-sevenler.org">Erkan Kaplan</mail> is a
       34 year-old Management Economist, born in Turkey, living in
       Germany since 1992. He previously administrated Gentoo Handbook
       Turkish translations, and now he works on many translation
       projects including GWN, Gentoo Handbook and Mozilla. He has
       been a Linux addict since 1995, and a Gentoo Linux user since
       2003. In his spare time, Erkan plays with his AS400 and analog
       electronic circuits. Now he's interested in Java, and will
       start studying "Software Programming with Java" at VW-Akademie
       in January.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Future zone</title>
<section>
<title>Closing in on Qt 4.0</title>
<body>
<p>Qt 4.0 beta1 is now available in portage (hard masked, and still under 
development). <uri link="http://www.trolltech.com">The Trolls</uri> have been hard at work to provide this major upgrade to the already 
popular Qt3 based desktop.  New features include:</p>
<ul><li>Tulip, a new set of template container classes.</li>
<li>Interview, a model/view architecture for item views.</li>
<li>Arthur, the Qt 4 painting framework.</li>
<li>Scribe, the Unicode text renderer with a public API for performing low-level 
text layout.</li>
<li>Mainwindow, a modern action-based mainwindow, toolbar, menu, and docking 
architecture.
</li>
</ul>
<p>In addition, the following modules have been significantly improved since Qt 
3:
</p>
<ul>
<li>A fully cross-platform accessibility module, with support for the emerging 
SP-API Unix standard in addition to Microsoft and Mac Accessibility.</li>
<li>The SQL module, which is now based on the Interview model/view framework.</li>
<li>The network module, with better support for UDP and synchronous sockets.</li>
<li>The style API, which is now decoupled from the widgets, meaning that you can 
draw any user interface element on any device (widget, pixmap, etc.).</li>
<li>Enhanced thread support, with signal-slot connections across threads and 
per-thread event loops.</li>
</ul>
<p>The code is not production ready yet - there are still bugs to be worked out  
and ebuild installation issues to work through.  However, software writers 
who are using the Qt3 library may be interested in upgrading to see what the 
latest offerings are, and begin looking at migrating their codebase.  
Upgrading to Qt4 should not interfere with an existing Qt3 installation.
</p>
<p>More details can be found <uri link="http://doc.trolltech.com/4.0/">here</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>kfax: Multiple overflows in the included TIFF library</title>
<body>
<p>

    kfax contains several buffer overflows potentially leading to execution of
    arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-17.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>abcm2ps: Buffer overflow vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    abcm2ps is vulnerable to a buffer overflow that could lead to remote
    execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-18.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>phpMyAdmin: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    phpMyAdmin contains multiple vulnerabilities which could lead to file
    disclosure or command execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-19.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>NASM: Buffer overflow vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    NASM is vulnerable to a buffer overflow that allows an attacker to execute
    arbitrary code through the use of a malicious object file.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-20.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>MPlayer: Multiple overflows</title>
<body>
<p>

    Multiple overflow vulnerabilities have been found in MPlayer, potentially
    resulting in remote executing of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-21.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>mpg123: Playlist buffer overflow</title>
<body>
<p>

    mpg123 is vulnerable to a buffer overflow that allows an attacker to
    execute arbitrary code through the use of a malicious playlist.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-22.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Zwiki: XSS vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    Zwiki is vulnerable to cross-site scripting attacks.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200412-23.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Overclockers: The day after...</b></p>
<p>What happens if you meticulously apply all tricks in the GCC book to your compilations, include all CFLAGS recommended by Acovea and known to man, and try to break all records of optimizations for packages in Gentoo? Exactly, you get to keep the pieces: </p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=271084">Acovea analysis results against real world programs</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-user</title>
<body>
<p><b>Package Manager Debate!</b></p>
<p>
Emacs versus vim.  Intel versus AMD.  Now, portage versus RedHat's up2date.  What are the 
fundamental differences, advantages, and disadvantages of up2date and Portage?  The Gentoo
community pipes up honest opinions and great information, as usual.  Let the debate begin!</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/linux.gentoo.user/browse_thread/thread/222eac5c2ad82bbe/03265c7b784e038f#03265c7b784e038f">Gentoo's Portage vs. Redhat's up2date</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Building Custom Kernels and Portage</b></p>
<p>
How does one build a custom kernel with specific options, outside of Portage but then at the same time notify
the system that the said packages are already installed?  In this thread, one user installs the ALSA
sound system manually, and several other list memebers offer suggestions and guidance to get Portage to 
behave as requested.
</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://groups-beta.google.com/group/linux.gentoo.user/browse_thread/thread/e6706fb81d0f3cb2/aead1a0b5c042219?_done=%2Fgroup%2Flinux.gentoo.user%2Fthreads%3Fstart%3D30%26order%3Drecent%26&amp;_doneTitle=Back&amp;&amp;d#aead1a0b5c042219">ALSA and my own kernel</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter> 
<title>Gentoo in the press</title> 
<section>
<title>Linux Weekly News (23 December 2004)</title> 
<body>

<p>In its <uri link="http://lwn.net/Articles/116694/">yearly distro roundup</uri>,
the Linux Weekly News (to whom we owe much gratitude for redistributing the GWN 
to their own readers each week!) mentions Gentoo: "Following a dramatic growth in 
popularity during the previous two years, the source-based Gentoo Linux has now 
matured into a mainstream, yet unique distribution that appeals to many technical 
users. Its adoption might be slowing down, though - not because Gentoo's founder 
Daniel Robbins is no longer with the project, but rather because most binary
distributions have improved their package management to the point that
dependency issues are no longer as annoying as they used to be. Also,
some users have found that maintaining and updating a Gentoo system is
time-consuming and not entirely fool-proof. Still, Gentoo has emerged
(pun intended) as one of the most prominent and innovative Linux
community projects, with unparalleled documentation, active community
involvement, and ongoing work on support for new hardware architectures."</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Linux Weekly News (16 December 2004)</title> 
<body>

<p>One week before, Ladislav Bodnar of <uri link="http://www.distrowatch.com">Distrowatch</uri> 
fame wrote <uri link="http://lwn.net/Articles/114992/">an article</uri> for the same Linux Weekly 
News about his experiences with installing and running Gentoo Linux on the AMD64 platform. Having
done the same exercise with Debian and Fedora in earlier LWN issues, he admits to having "cursed 
profusely" everytime compile errors delayed a successful installation, but closes with 
the observation that "while the effort required to achieve that goal was far 
greater than with the other two distributions, there is little doubt that Gentoo Linux 
is an elegant operating system with powerful package management and truly superb documentation."</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla 2004</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed Bug Ranking</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  For 2004, between 1 January and 26 December, activity
     on the site resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>38691 new bugs this year</li>
	  <li>22004 bugs closed or resolved this year</li>
	  <li>263 previously closed bugs were reopened this year</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 7810 currently open bugs: 114 are labeled 'blocker', 229 are labeled 'critical', and 553 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed Bug Rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs this year are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 1534
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 915
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 780
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 759
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="eradicator@gentoo.org" >Jeremy Huddleston</mail>, with 679
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=eradicator@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 664
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java Team</mail>, with 647
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="dev-portage@gentoo.org" >Portage Team</mail>, with 559
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=dev-portage@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="ppc64@gentoo.org" >PPC64 Architecture Team</mail>, with 515
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=ppc64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="vapier@gentoo.org" >Mike Frysinger</mail>, with 442
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=vapier@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 396
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="net-mail@gentoo.org" >Net-Mail Packages</mail>, with 381
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=net-mail@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >Media-Video herd</mail>, with 358
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="swift@gentoo.org" >Sven Vermeulen</mail>, with 349
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=swift@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="ppc@gentoo.org" >PPC Porters</mail>, with 314
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=ppc@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows Packagers</mail>, with 298
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="mozilla@gentoo.org" >Mozilla Gentoo Team</mail>, with 281
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mozilla@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x86-kernel@gentoo.org" >x86 Kernel Team</mail>, with 279
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=x86-kernel@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="mirror-admin@gentoo.org" >Mirror Admins</mail>, with 239
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mirror-admin@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="perl@gentoo.org" >Perl Devs</mail>, with 234
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=perl@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gcc-porting@gentoo.org" >GCC Porting Team</mail>, with 229
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gcc-porting@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sci@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Science Related Packages</mail>, with 225
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sci@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="python@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Python Team</mail>, with 221
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=python@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 218
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="text-markup@gentoo.org" >Text-Markup Team</mail>, with 202
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2004-01-01&amp;chfieldto=2004-12-26&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=text-markup@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><e>None this week</e></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Matthew Marlowe (MattM) - Apache</li>
			<li>Ming Zhao (ming) - tcltk herd, Gnome, CJK</li>
			<li>Marcus Hanwell (cryos) - Scientific herd, AMD64</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo Linux project:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Jochen Maes (SeJo) - Recruiters (additional role)</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.</p>
<p>To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail> from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
