<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050418-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>April 18th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="w.haas@xover.htu.tuwien.ac.at">Wernfried Haas</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="pvdabeel@gentoo.org">Pieter Van den Abeele</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 18 April 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 17</version>
<date>2005-04-18</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Documentation project updates</title>
<body>

<p>
<mail link="fox2mike@gmail.com">Shyam Mani</mail>'s excellent <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/usb-guide.xml">"USB Guide"</uri> for Gentoo
Linux is among the highlighted additions to the ever-growing collection of in-house 
documentation, which also includes a paper on <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/fluxbox-config.xml">configuring Fluxbox</uri> this month. 
Complementing the existing Gnome and KDE documentation, this new Fluxbox window 
manager configuration aide was written by <mail link="smith.jonathan@gmail.com">Jonathan 
Smith</mail>.
</p> 

<p>
Meanwhile, an announcement in the "Gentoo on Sparc" section of the Gentoo Forums <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-162259.html">points to 
recently added documentation</uri> for Gentoo Linux on Sun hardware. <mail 
link="ciaranm@gentoo.org">Ciaran McCreesh</mail>, <mail link="todd@gentoo.org">Todd 
Sunderlin</mail> and <mail link="peitolm@gentoo.org">Colin Morey</mail> have
written the guides that should improve both installation and usability of Gentoo
Linux on Sparcs: 
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-sparc-quickinstall.xml">Quickinstall</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-sparc-faq.xml">FAQ</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-sparc-netboot-howto.xml">Netboot Howto</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
  <title>2005.0 aftermath releng meeting</title>
  <body>

    <p>On Thursday 14 April the Gentoo Releng Team had a meeting to discuss the
    good and bad things during the 2005.0 release and find new strategies for
    the next release.  First the good things should be named, like building a CD
    that works well on a lot of systems and architectures, what was caused by
    not rushing the release, so that we had time to <uri
      link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/20050303-2005.0-secrebuild.xml">fix
      bugs</uri>.  One part of the release that first went wrong was
    communication, but with the security-rebuilding communication improved a lot
    and the different arches worked pretty well together with the Release
    Management.  And now to the bad things: We had that big delay of the release
    with more than six weeks after the first discussed release date.  Then there
    were some md5sums which were not up to date with the LiveCDs, the
    announcement of the Release through our PR-team has not been covered well,
    the Handbook has now several updates which are not in the offline-version on
    the CD itself and finally the community didn't accepted the pre-orders by
    the store.</p>

    <p>In order to resolve the issues, several strategies have been discussed.
      So the Release-team will make better use of the <uri
        link="http://devwiki.gentoo.org/">devwiki</uri> (devwiki means, that it
    is for developers only), where we will place our documention for the Release
    and create a Release-checklist, where every arch can note, which step has
    been passed.  Every arch should build a testing LiveCD that will hit the
    mirrors in the experimental branch, so that users with special hardware can
    test new improvements and tell us about them in bug-reports.  Common
    profiles and scripts should make the different arche's LiveCDs more
    similary, so that users can find the same utilities on every kind of
    LiveCD. And finally we want to do a better PR-work for the next release.</p>

    <p>As a last point the next release date has been discussed.  We don't want
    to force it on a special date, as we want to release a LiveCD without major
    bugs, although the 2005.1 release should be just a refresh of the 2005.0
    release with newer software and less bugs.  XLiveCDs with the <uri
      link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/installer/index.xml">Installer</uri>
    included are in discussion, but not mandatory for the next Release.  The
    release date will be about late July or August.</p>

  </body>
</section>
<section>
  <title>New official Gentoo IRC channels</title>
  <body>

    <p>Two new Gentoo IRC channels were recently added to the <uri
        link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/irc.xml">Gentoo IRC channel
        list</uri>:</p>

    <ul>
      <li><b>#gentoo-netmon</b>: Network Monitoring Packages</li>
      <li><b>#gentoo-voip</b>: Voice over IP related Discussion</li>
    </ul>

  </body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Future Zone</title>
<section>
<title>Luminocity X-LiveDVD for PPC released</title>
<body>
<note>
It started harmlessly as a development project for automatic X configuration
by the Gentoo/PPC team. All they wanted back then was to showcase the new 
configurator in a couple of X-enabled LiveCDs. But what <uri 
link="http://www.metadistribution.org/blog">Pieter Van den Abeele</uri> did 
release last week went more than just slightly beyond the initial 
scope of the project...
</note>
<p>
A Gentoo-based PowerPC Altivec-Optimized LiveDVD with a long feature list has
been released last week. It runs on Genesi's PegasosPPC Open Desktop Workstations, 
and its most unique feature is probably Luminocity, an 
OpenGL-based experimental window manager technology testbed. The medium allows 
you to try out Luminocity without having to compile or install any experimental 
software from the Gnome CVS repository. But the 1.8GB DVD is jock-full of other
exciting features, too:
</p>
<ul>
<li><b>Smartcard integration:</b> Gentoo sponsor company Genesi Inc. donated
a number of smartcard readers, complete with media, cards . The LiveDVD supports authentication
via smartcard for users to try it out, without the need to personalize the card
at first -- to be done later, using <uri link="http://www.opensc.org/">opensc</uri>.</li>
<li><b>GRID support:</b> Sun Grid Engine 6 (SGE) core ported to PowerPC, Apple's XGRID
engine agent and standalone LAM-MPI, PVM libraries. These features enable users to
develop their own grid-enabled applications.</li>
<li><b>Eclipse SDK:</b> Much in demand, finally available from disk.</li>
<li><b>Video conferencing:</b> Compatible with QuickCam webcams from Logitech,
cross-platform audio and video conferencing that even works with Microsoft's
"net-meeting" is available directly from the LiveDVD.</li>
<li><b>3D desktop switching:</b> OpenGL technology to make use of 3D graphics 
features, including three-dimensional window managers.</li>
<li><b>Text to Speech,</b> Blender, Ardour, and many more...</li>
<li>And last but not least, <b>Gentoo's version of Xautoconfig on Apple machines</b></li></ul>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050418_livedvd.png"
short="Smartcard" 
caption="Gentoo LiveCD/DVD image asking for smartcard authentication " />

<p>
The Luminocity X-LiveDVD is available <uri 
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~pvdabeel/torrents/ppc-livedvd.torrent">via bittorrent</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Search sucketh less</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="tomk@forums.gentoo.org">Tom Knight</mail> spent ample time 
improving the search function of the Forums, concerning both speed and selection
criteria. Apart from getting results faster than before, the default settings 
of a search now exclude the entire Off The Wall section, the dustbin and all 
international forums, a feature that had been requested by many users, and since
a long time. As an unpleasant side effect, searching for posts by specific users 
also excluded the same forums -- a few complaints and even fewer hours later, 
tomk had fixed this issue, too. 
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-323916.html">New search function</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Return of the avatars</b></p>
<p>Avatars not belonging to the default gallery of the forums were recently 
disabled due to a vulnerability in <c>php</c>. While some users already feared they 
would never come back, the avatars were actually reinstalled after less than a day. 
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-322136.html">[solved]No more avatars?</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>InternetNews.com (14 April 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Last week InternetNews published an article titled <uri 
link="http://www.internetnews.com/dev-news/article.php/3497931">"Non-Commercial 
Linux Use on The Rise"</uri>, reporting that "new data released this 
week from research firm Evans Data indicates non-commercial Linux distribution 
use has passed the inflection point and is now more widely used by developers 
than commercial Linux distributions." Counting Gentoo Linux among those worth
mentioning as examples for community distributions that have left RedHat and 
SuSE behind as preferred platforms for development, author Sean Michael Kerner
quotes the research firm to explain why Gentoo et al. are more popular with
developers than their commercial cousins: "As the general knowledge base of 
Linux has increased, developers are less reliant on formal models of support.",
states the study by Evans Data.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PC Inpact (13 April 2005, in French)</title>
<body>
<p>
A complete guide to installation and usage of a popular first-person shooter
game for Linux, World of Warcraft, has been published by French "mégazine"
PC Inpact in <uri link="http://www.pcinpact.com/articles/d/51/1.htm">an 
article</uri> published last week. Interesting to note: Much of the content
of the guide has been taken from the Gentoo Forums, which are credited in 
the article as one of its major sources.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and tricks</title>
<section>
  <title>Bootup with the Gentoo 2005.0 logo</title>
  <body>

    <p>When you boot from the 2005.0 LiveCD you see an awesome Gentoo bootlogo
      and progress-bar -- and you wish you could impress your friends with it
      during your usual bootup?  Here we go:</p>

    <note><c>splashutils</c> only work on x86 and amd64 architectures perfectly 
      at the moment. Support for ppc is in progress.</note>

    <p>First of all, we need to emerge <c>splashutils</c> and
      <c>splash-themes-livecd</c>:</p>

    <pre caption="emerge splashutils and splash-themes-livecd">
# <i>emerge splash-themes-livecd</i>
<comment>splashutils is a dependency of splash-themes-livecd</comment>
    </pre>

    <p>Now we have to create an initial boot-disk.  You are free to change the
      resolution to your choice, but choose one that is available as a config
      file in <path>/etc/splash/livecd-2005.0/</path>:</p>

    <pre caption="Creation of an initrd with the 2005.0-splash">
<comment>Be sure that /boot is mounted before you call the command</comment>
# <i>splash_geninitramfs -v -g /boot/splash-livecd-2005.0-1024x768 \
  -r 1024x768 livecd-2005.0</i>
    </pre>

    <p>Check your kernel-config to make sure that <path>"Initial RAM disk (initrd) support"</path>
      is built in.  You can find the option in <path>"Device Drivers" --&gt; "Block
        devices" --&gt; "RAM disk support"</path>.  Furthermore check that you are
      using an appropriate framebuffer for your video-card (<path>"Graphics
        Support"</path>) or stick with the VESA-framebuffer.  Usually
      <c>splashutils</c> should do the checks during the emerge-progress, but we
      want to be sure.  Now tell your bootloader that it should load the initrd
      with the 2005.0-splash:</p>

    <pre caption="Configure the bootloader">
# <i>nano -w /boot/grub/menu.lst</i>
<comment>First change your kernel-boot-line to something like this (depends on</comment>
<comment>your used framebuffer and further kernel-parameters):</comment>
kernel /boot/kernel-2.6.11-r6 root=/dev/hda3 video=vesafb:1024x768-32@72
  splash=silent,theme:livecd-2005.0 quiet CONSOLE=/dev/tty1
<comment>You must use more than 8bpp (in this example it is 32,</comment>
<comment>specified by 1024x768-32@72).</comment>

<comment>Add the following line to your kernel-config:</comment>
initrd /boot/splash-livecd-2005.0-1024x768
    </pre>

    <p>Now we have that nice bootup-splash installed.  Finally we want a
      permanent Gentoo statusbar at the bottom of our terminal-session, like on
      the LiveCD.  Therefore we have to change the default theme in
      <path>/etc/splash</path>:</p>

    <pre caption="Change the default splash">
# <i>cd /etc/splash</i>
# <i>rm default</i>
# <i>ln -s livecd-2005.0 default</i>
    </pre>

    <p>This splash should be started after bootup has finished:</p>

    <pre caption="Add splash to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add splash default</i>
    </pre>

    <p>If you want to finetune the splash-theme, you should have a look at
      <path>/etc/conf.d/splash</path>.  Happy Gentooing!</p>

    <p>Thanks to <mail link="spock@gentoo.org">Michael Januszewski</mail> for
      his work on splashutils and <mail link="blackace@gentoo.org">Nicholas D.
        Wolfwood</mail> for the 2005.0-theme.</p>

  </body>
  </section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<e>None this week</e>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Harald van Dĳk (truedfx) - Portage
</li>
<li>
Vibhav Garg (vgarg) - Java
</li>
<li>
Diego Pettenò (Flameeyes) - FreeBSD, AMD64, video
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Nicholas Jones (carpaski) - Left the Portage team (and its lead position)
</li>
<li>
Marius Mauch (genone) - New Portage co-lead
</li>
<li>
Brian Harring (ferringb) - New Portage co-lead
</li>
<li>
Jason Stubbs (jstubbs) - New Portage co-lead
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>phpMyAdmin: Cross-site scripting vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    phpMyAdmin is vulnerable to a cross-site scripting attack.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-08.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Axel: Vulnerability in HTTP redirection handling</title>
<body>
<p>

    A buffer overflow vulnerability has been found in Axel which could lead to
    the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-09.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gld: Remote execution of arbitrary code</title>
<body>
<p>

    Gld contains several serious vulnerabilities, potentially resulting in the
    execution of arbitrary code as the root user.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-10.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>JunkBuster: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    JunkBuster is vulnerable to a heap corruption vulnerability, and under
    certain configurations may allow an attacker to modify settings.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-11.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>rsnapshot: Local privilege escalation</title>
<body>
<p>

    rsnapshot allows a local user to take ownership of local files, resulting
    in privilege escalation.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-12.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>OpenOffice.Org: DOC document Heap Overflow</title>
<body>
<p>

    OpenOffice.Org is vulnerable to a heap overflow when processing DOC
    documents, which could lead to arbitrary code execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-13.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>monkeyd: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Format string and Denial of Service vulnerabilities have been discovered in
    the monkeyd HTTP server, potentially resulting in the execution of
    arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-14.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PHP: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Several vulnerabilities were found and fixed in PHP image handling
    functions, potentially resulting in Denial of Service conditions or the
    remote execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-15.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 10 April 2005 and 17 April 2005, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>835 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>436 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>27 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8583 currently open bugs: 90 are labeled 'blocker', 237 are labeled 'critical', and 641 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="recruiters@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Recruiting Team</mail>, with 34
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=recruiters@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="neysx@gentoo.org" >Xavier Neys</mail>, with 30
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=neysx@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 30
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 12
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="gdesklets@gentoo.org" >GDesklets packages</mail>, with 44
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;assigned_to=gdesklets@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 22
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 22
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 20
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="hanno@gentoo.org" >Hanno Boeck</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;assigned_to=hanno@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="netmon@gentoo.org" >Netmon Herd</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;assigned_to=netmon@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="php-bugs@gentoo.org" >PHP Bugs</mail>, with 9
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-04-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-17&amp;assigned_to=php-bugs@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and 
help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
