<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050314-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>March 14th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="dsd@gentoo.org">Daniel Drake</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 14 March 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 11</version>
<date>2005-03-14</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Planet Gentoo launched</title>
<body>
<p><uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org">Planet Gentoo</uri> has been launched 
last week, a <uri link="http://www.planetplanet.org/">Planet</uri>-driven 
website that aggregates all Gentoo-related entries from the weblogs of over 50 
contributing developers. The new resource is intended to improve communication 
between the user and developer communities, and enhance communication 
internally between developers.
</p>
<p>
Contributing developers write articles to their weblogs, which will then 
automatically be published on Planet Gentoo, providing a good overview of what 
is being developed and where things are going. At time of launch, the Planet 
has over 50 contributing developers, and will grow further as more and more 
developers add their feeds to the list of those already available.
</p>
<p>
Planet Gentoo started life as an <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0030.html">enhancement 
proposal</uri>. Following an extensive testing phase, it is now buzzing with 
activity. All official Gentoo developers qualify for inclusion of their feed, 
provided it's in English and either entirely about Gentoo matters, or allowing 
for categorized feeds that can be limited to those. Developers who haven't been 
listed yet can get set up by sending an email to Daniel Drake, even if they 
don't have a blog of their own yet: A weblog to start with can be provided to 
those who need one.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo UK Conference</title>
<body>
<p>
Big turnout for the Gentoo UK conference last Saturday: around 40 Gentoo 
developers and users had flocked to the University of Salford (near Manchester) 
to attend this year's event, organized for the second time in a row by <mail 
link="reuben.finch@btinternet.com">Reuben Finch</mail> and <mail 
link="stuart@gentoo.org">Stuart Herbert</mail>. Presentations included talks by
<mail link="tigger@gentoo.org">Rob Holland</mail> about code auditing, <mail 
link="dsd@gentoo.org">Daniel Drake</mail> on the kernel and user-relation 
projects, <mail link="slarti@gentoo.org">Tom Martin</mail> with his successful 
attempt at showing how to get the most out of a command line interface (and 
making <c>zsh</c> a little more popular), and guest speakers Harry Moyes of the 
<uri link="http://www.manchesterwireless.net">Manchester Wireless network 
initiative</uri>, and Gareth Bult and his <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20041206-newsletter.xml#doc_chap2">Flash 
Linux project</uri> presentation rounded off a densely packed, mostly technical, 
and highly enjoyable presentation track. But bringing developers together under 
real life conditions has other advantages, too: <mail link="plasmaroo@gentoo.org">Tim 
Yamin</mail>and Daniel Drake sat and worked through a few <c>genkernel</c> 
embellishments, and <mail link="spb@gentoo.org">Stephen Bennett</mail> got a chance 
to demonstrate Gentoo/FreeBSD with the Gentoo init script system to some fellow devs. 
Photos were unavailable at the time of writing, but the organizers have promised to 
edit a video of the event. Thanks a lot to the sponsors of the conference, the 
<uri link="http://www.linx.net/">London Internet Exchange (LINX)</uri> and the <uri 
link="http://www.salford.ac.uk/">University of Salford</uri>, for making it 
possible to offer this conference free for all! And since after the show is in 
fact before the show,  plans for the 2006 edition of the Gentoo UK conference are 
already under way. 
</p> 
<note>Collated from blog entries by <uri link="http://www.reactivated.net/weblog/archives/2005/03/gentoo-uk-2005-meet/">Daniel Drake</uri>, <uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/slarti">Tom Martin</uri> and <uri link="http://blog.cryos.net/index.php?/archives/21-Gentoo-UK-2005.html">Marcus D. Hanwell</uri>.</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo preloaded: Pegasos Open Desktop Workstation sale begins</title>
<body>
<p>A few days later than the date <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20050124-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1_sect3">announced 
in the GWN</uri>, Genesi's ODW with Gentoo installed is now available for 
online ordering. After receiving a lot of expressions of interest to the 
temporary mail address, Gentoo has now the ability to proceed orders for 
the machines. For each workstation that is sold via the new <uri 
link="http://vendors.gentoo.org">vendors.gentoo.org</uri> site, the Foundation 
will receive a 100 USD donation from Genesi. A detailed description of the 
hardware you buy is available <uri 
link="http://vendors.gentoo.org/index.cgi?page=1&amp;comGroup=1">at the ODW 
page</uri>, from where you can register and place your order via the Freescale 
online shop.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>GLEP talk</b></p>
<p>
The last weeks have seen lots of discussion on the Gentoo Linux Enhancement 
Proposals, and how the system as it is now can be improved:
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25967">USE groups (and negatives) [GLEP 29]</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25879">Metapackages    [unnumbered]</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25950">Eclass Restructure/Redesign [GLEP 33]</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26016">uid/gid handling [GLEP 27]</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26165">Per-Category metadata.xml Files [unnumbered]</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26106">Subversion for Gentoo hosted projects [unnumbered]</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26158">GLEP system worthwile? [meta-discussion]</uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>Metastructure/organizational idea</b></p>

<p>
<mail link="iggy@gentoo.org">Brian Jackson</mail> presents a new approach to 
handling inactive developers: "I think we should institute a monthly 
survivor-esque vote to get rid of developers that are useless. I think this 
would help much more than needlessly reorganizing management once again. Once 
we vote off all the useless people that just seem to complain about management, 
we can all live happily ever after."
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26081">Metastructure/organizational idea</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Keywording policy</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="weeve@gentoo.org">Jason Wever</mail> has some advice for other devs:
"I'd like to ask that you all take the time to review the keywording
policy in the Developer Handbook.  In particular, I'd like to draw
your attention to the section on "Upgrading Ebuilds" People have been getting 
good lately at either dropping keywords for no reason and/or failing to notify 
or file a bug with the arches dropped as to why."
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26030">Keywording policy</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Germany: IT/Linux Days Lörrach</title>
<body>
<p>
The "REGIO Messe" is an annual event in a region known as "Trirhenia",
with French, Swiss and German constituencies all sitting on the banks 
of the river Rhine. The four-day IT/Linux Days in Lörrach are part
of the larger REGIO event, and Gentoo has been present at this fair
for the second time in a row. The booth was manned by a team of 
supporters and developers of the Gentoo project, Sebastian Müller (dakjo), 
Timo Antweiler (aZZe), <mail link="stkn@gentoo.org">Stefan Knoblich</mail> 
(stkn), and <mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail> 
(dertobi123). The same LiveDVD and CD already sold at FOSDEM in Brussels 
and the Linuxtage in Chemnitz last week were available again (and can 
still be had <uri link="http://tracker.netdomination.org">via Bittorrent</uri>. 
At the booth, questions about Gentoo Linux on "alternative" architectures 
dominated the dialogue with visitors, with one of the more frequent requests, 
interestingly enough, being a Sparc32 port. Next year's ITLD will be 
rebaptized to "Minibit", and chances are that Gentoo will be present again.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050314_itld.jpg"
	short="Impressions" 
	caption="Impressions from the IT/Linux Days" />
<note>Left: maddog giving the keynote speech, center: Tobias Scherbaum 
installing Gentoo on a Mac Mini, right: Sebastian Müller hacking away at a 3GHz P4 (</note>
<p>
Some people may have trouble finding the small South-German town of Lörrach on 
a map. Not so Jon "maddog" Hall, open-source evangelist and legendary executive
director of Linux International: Not only did he know where Lörrach is, he stayed
for the entire duration of the event, and he also identified its most interesting 
spots right away.</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050314_maddog.jpg"
	short="Loerrach" 
	caption="Embracing the future: maddog visits the Gentoo booth" />
<note>Left to right: Gentoo developer <mail link="stkn@gentoo.org">Stefan Knoblich</mail>, 
Jon "maddog" Hall, booth staffers Timo Antweiler and Sebastian Müller</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Japan: The future of software engineering</title>
<body>
<p>
<mail link="hagi@p1d.com">Yoshiaki Hagihara</mail>, former lead translator on the 
Japanese GentooJP team, has written a book on the future of software engineering in 
Japan. <uri link="http://www.seshop.com/detail.asp?pid=5819">日本のSEはこれからどうなるのか</uri> 
(What's to become of Japan's software engineering?) is a collection of interviews with a 
wide range of people, from manga artists to Japanese SE companies, and several 
professional foreign and Japanese hackers, including three Gentooists: Ion Mudreac, 
the man behind the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.ro">Romanian Gentoo website</uri>, 
Gentoo developer <mail link="nakano@gentoo.org">Masatomo Nakano</mail>, spiritus 
rector of the GentooJP project, and GentooJP co-founder <uri 
link="http://senri.homelinux.com/">Hiroshi Senri</uri>. The book, published by <uri 
link="http://www.shoeisha.co.jp/">Shoeisha</uri>, is sold online for 1575 JPY (15 USD).</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050314_book.jpg"
	short="SE book" 
	caption="Cover of Yoshiaki Hagihara's book" />
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Germany: Gentoo introduction for LUUSA</title>
<body>
<p>
Despite appearances, the members of <uri link="http://www.luusa.org">LUUSA</uri> 
are quite knowledgeable folk: the acronym stands for "Linux and Unix Users Sankt 
Augustin", the resident LUG of a community near Bonn, the former German capital. <mail 
link="sebastian@gentoo.org">Sebastian Bergmann</mail> had the honour of holding 
a talk about Gentoo in general at a meeting last Thursday, 10 March 2005, at Bonn's 
community center "Netzladen", in front of about 30 LUUSAs in the audience. Two fellow 
Gentoo developers, <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail> and <mail 
link="zypher@gentoo.org">Marc Hildebrand</mail>, had stopped by to support 
Sebastian. His slides (including screen shots from the Gentoo Installer project) 
are available in <uri link="http://www.sebastian-bergmann.de/talks/2005-03-10-Gentoo.pdf">PDF</uri>, 
<uri link="http://www.sebastian-bergmann.de/talks/2005-03-10-Gentoo.swf">Flash</uri> 
and <uri link="http://www.sebastian-bergmann.de/talks/2005-03-10-Gentoo.sxi">Openoffice 
Impress format</uri>.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050314_luusa.jpg"
	short="LUUSA" 
	caption="The LUUSA audience at the Netzladen in Bonn" />
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Linux Format (Issue 65)</title>
<body>
<p>
The UK Linux Format magazine has awarded its annual reader selection of the best
projects in the open-source realm. Gentoo received the palmares in two of the 
three categories it was nominated in: "Best support" went to the Gentoo Forums,
according to Linux Format "no doubt boosted by the canvassing that Gentoo did
on those very pages," and the award for "Best distro" in 2004 was won by Gentoo,
beating the usual suspects Mandrake, Fedora and SuSE. Linux Format notes that
"by a reasonable margin, this year's spoils go to a relative newcomer who has 
picked up a lot of supporters in the last twelve months -- Gentoo. Well done!"</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>FAZ (7 March 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Anticipating this week's Cebit IT fair in Hannover, one of Germany's major daily 
newspapers had an article on "Programming for the benefit of mankind" in last 
monday's edition, written by free-lancer Detlef Borchers. "When a trade fair has 
established itself as the world's largest computer fair, it doesn't really have
to be afraid of an immediate loss of importance. But Cebit has a problem, the 
same problem as Microsoft. And they're not the only ones," writes Borchers about 
the rise of open-source development. The article mentions Gentoo in a paragraph about
the highlights at this year's FOSDEM in Brussels, which Borchers considers "a
traditional major hacker event," exemplifying the ways of the open-source movement
that look strange to people who only know Microsoft environments. To him,
Gentoo and the other "clans" who were present with DevRooms of their own, sound "like
Spanish villages, but hiding behind those names are vital software constructs." 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<e>None this week</e>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Carlos Silva (r3bak) - Kernel</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<e>None this week</e>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>mlterm: Integer overflow vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    mlterm is vulnerable to an integer overflow, which could potentially allow
    the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-13.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>KDE dcopidlng: Insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

    The dcopidlng script is vulnerable to symlink attacks, potentially allowing
    a local user to overwrite arbitrary files.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-14.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>X.org: libXpm vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    A new vulnerability has been discovered in libXpm, which is included in
    X.org, that can potentially lead to remote code execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-15.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Ethereal: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Multiple vulnerabilities exist in Ethereal, which may allow an attacker to
    run arbitrary code or crash the program.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-16.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>libexif: Buffer overflow vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    libexif fails to validate certain inputs, making it vulnerable to buffer
    overflows.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-17.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 06 March 2005 and 13 March 2005, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>765 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>405 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>26 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8238 currently open bugs: 97 are labeled 'blocker', 229 are labeled 'critical', and 598 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 34
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 26
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 22
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 18
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="perl@gentoo.org" >Perl Devs @ Gentoo</mail>, with 18
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=perl@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="web-apps@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Web Application Packages Maintainers</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;assigned_to=web-apps@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 9
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 9
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 9
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 8
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 8
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-13&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter? Send us an <mail 
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and 
help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
