<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050228-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>February 28th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="vericgar@gentoo.org">Michael Stewart</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 28 February 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 9</version>
<date>2005-02-28</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>First European Gentoo developer meeting</title>
<body>
<p>
Twentythree Gentoo developers from the European Union, Norway, Switzerland and 
the U.S.attended the first official Gentoo developer meeting organized in Brussels,
borrowing the location and the occasion from the FOSDEM event held last weekend. 
For two hours on Sunday morning, the Gentoo DevRoom in one of the historic 
buildings of Université Libre de Bruxelles was reserved for the internal meeting
that for the first time brought together people who have been working as a team
for months or years, but had never met in person. After a short round of 
introductions, the discussion quickly centered on structural issues of Gentoo 
development. When infrastructure provisioning and development was done by just a 
handful of key persons, it was usually sufficient to holler requests into their
general direction, and they'd get the job done. Today, with a headcount of over 
350 developers and a great diversity of needs and ambitions, the Brussel meeting 
unanimously suggested renovating the project's internal structure, to reflect changes 
in its scope, to make active developers feel better represented, and to prepare 
the ground for future scalability. The result of the discussion will be drafted
as a proposal to submit to Gentoo's project managers and developers at large.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050228_fosdem-devs.jpg"
	short="Dev-Meeting" 
	caption="First Pan-European Gentoo developer meeting" />
<note>
Standing, from left to right:  cryos, foser, tantive, pYrania, ian, jaevorsz, 
koon, SeJo, pvdabeel, hansmi, lu_zero. Sitting in front: beejay, luckyduck, plate, 
Pylon, zypher, Ferdy, BaSS, karltk, tove, bonsaikitten, Kugelfang, KingTaco. 
Invisibly present (helping out at the booth): stkn.
</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>FOSDEM 2005 expo and conference</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo's presence at the biggest open-source developer meeting in Europe for the
third year in a row was an outstanding experience for everyone who attended. At 
an estimated 3500 participants, FOSDEM has outgrown its old target audience of 
just developers from Benelux countries, and an impressive line-up of presenters
attracts open-source developers from all over Europe and beyond to come to Brussels 
each year. Learning from previous experience prevented the toilets from overflowing
and sandwiches from being sold out before everyone was fed, and with speakers like
Alan Cox and Richard Stallman in the main track and dozens of projects -- including
Gentoo -- organizing their own developer rooms, the three buildings entirely occupied
by FOSDEM 2005 were buzzing with activity for both days of the conference.
</p>  
<p>
The DevRoom booked for the duration of the entire conference was densely packed 
with Gentoo users and others interested in the twelve presentations held by 
the Gentoo developers. Attendance fluctuated between a few dozen and
80 people sitting and standing around the room, and the range of topics covered
general descriptions of the Gentoo project as well as highly technical papers
on specific development. Portage and Java development were at the center of the
attention, but even more exotic presentations like the GNAP work of <mail 
link="koon@gentoo.org">Thierry Carrez</mail> in the embedded space attracted 
highly focussed crowds. Most DevRoom presentations are available for download from a <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/pr/docs/presentation-listing.xml">central 
repository</uri>. Outside of the DevRoom, <mail link="dams@gentoo.org">Damien 
Krotkine</mail> held a "lightning talk" about his <uri 
link="http://www.libconf.net/">libconf project</uri> (the base for Gentoo's 
USE flag editor GUI <c>profuse</c>, among other things), and last but not least, <mail 
link="genone@gentoo.org">Marius Mauch</mail> had the honour of addressing the larger 
main track audience with his presentation of Gentoo's Portage system.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050228_fosdem-keynote.jpg"
	short="sejo" 
	caption="Jochen Maes giving the keynote speech at the Gentoo DevRoom" />
<p>
Detached from the DevRoom in a separate building, Gentoo had a double-sized booth 
in the hallway, located between the Mozilla table celebrating the first anniversary 
of Firefox, and a project for converting inexpensive Korean Gameboy clones (<uri 
link="http://www.gp32linux.com/">"Gamepark"</uri>) into fully-fledged Linux-PDAs. 
On display at the Gentoo stand were four of Genesi's PegasosPPC Open Desktop 
Workstations (two of them demoing the new <uri 
link="/news/en/gwn/20050131-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1_sect3">Cube LiveCD for PPC</uri>),
several x86 and PPC notebooks, and TGL's exotic <uri 
link="/news/en/gwn/20050221-newsletter.xml#doc_chap2">Kuro-Box</uri> running as an
MP3 streaming server. Visitors were jostling through the narrow hallway, stopping
for a chat with the Gentooists on duty, grabbing stickers or sweets (from a box 
labeled "<path>/dev/snack</path>"), or to buy T-shirts and other Gentoo paraphernalia.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050228_fosdem-booth.jpg"
	short="FOSDEM Booth" 
	caption="Busy hours at the Gentoo booth" />

<p>
The inofficial, yet popular "Fizzlewizzle" releases collated by <mail 
link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>, were completely sold out 
within a few hours. Special FOSDEM editions of Gentoo Linux CDs have become a 
tradition of their own, but this year's "Fizzlewizzle" was available for the 
first time on both LiveCD and -DVDs. The ISOs had been updated with the latest 
Portage snapshot just three days before FOSDEM opened its gates, spin in a 
default English environment as opposed to earlier German localizations, and contain 
a full KDE 3.3 installation that can be run directly from the media, without 
installing on harddisk first. The DVD encompasses 2.2GB worth of sources on top 
of the usual CD image contents, and both images continue to be available via <uri 
link="http://tracker.netdomination.org">bittorrent</uri>, for x86 or PPC, along 
with the Cube LiveCD for PPC.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050228_fosdem-dvd.jpg"
	short="DVD cover" 
	caption="Brussels landmark monument, the Atomium, on Gentoo's FOSDEM edition LiveDVD cover" />
<note>Artwork by <mail link="ian@gentoo.org">Christian Hartmann</mail>, download 
the full-size cover art for printing DVD and CD labels, for <uri link="http://download.iansview.com/gentoo/artwork/ian/livecds/ppc/fosdem/2005/">PPC</uri> and <uri link="http://download.iansview.com/gentoo/artwork/ian/livecds/x86/fosdem/2005/">x86</uri>.</note>
<p>
FOSDEM's famous quantum singularity, first spotted by Daniel Robbins during his 
visit to the 2003 conference and rediscovered on the floor of Brussel's youth 
hostel last year, had migrated to one of Europe's most famous techno clubs, Fuse, 
where a group of Gentoo developers claims to have seen it hovering over the 
dance floor on Saturday night. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Apache unmasked</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo Apache Team has unmasked package updates that have been in the works 
for a while. Thanks to additional help from developers who joined the team over
the past few months, the announcement many Apache users have been waiting for
could finally be made last Sunday. Some of the major changes include:</p>
<ul>
<li>
New configuration and configuration locations to more closely match
upstream and reduce confusion for users coming from other
distributions.
</li>
<li>
Modules now use a centralized <c>eclass</c> that builds, installs, and
displays standard information on enabling the module. This allows
easier maintenance of existing modules, and allows us to more rapidly
develop ebuilds for modules that are not yet in the tree.
</li>
<li>
Expanded <path>USE</path> flags to customize your apache installation now let you
choose multiple MPMs to build and make it easy to switch between
them.
</li>
<li>
A new <path>gentoo-webroot</path> that will eventually provide a gentoo-themed
icon-set, error documents, and default website. This has been put in
its own package, and includes a <path>USE</path>-flag to not install the
<path>gentoo-webroot</path> into <path>/var/www/localhost</path> - useful if 
you put your own website there.
</li>
<li>
And much more, including many bug fixes.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
When upgrading Apache, necessary steps will include merging customizations 
in <path>/etc/apache2/httpd.conf</path> and updating all currently used 
modules to revisions that support the new <c>eclass</c>. <uri 
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~vericgar/doc/apache-package-refresh.html">Detailed 
documentation</uri> is available, and if you have any questions or problems 
during migration, talk to the Apache team on <path>#gentoo-apache</path> at 
irc.freenode.net or via the mailing list, <path>gentoo-web-user@gentoo.org</path>. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New Gentoo/FreeBSD documentation available</title>
<body>
<p>
Since our <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20050207-newsletter.xml">recent 
article</uri> about the Gentoo/FreeBSD project in the GWN's Future Zone, Gentoo 
developer <mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail> has taken over 
maintenance of the related documentation. The <uri 
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~citizen428/doc/gentoo-freebsd.html">new document</uri> 
is based on Aaron Walker's original installation instructions, and contains lots of 
contributions by Gentoo/FreeBSD project lead <mail link="angusyoung@gentoo.org">Otavio 
R. Piske</mail>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>PuTTY: Remote code execution</title>
<body>
<p>

    PuTTY was found to contain vulnerabilities that can allow a malicious SFTP
    server to execute arbitrary code on unsuspecting PSCP and PSFTP clients.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-28.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Cyrus IMAP Server: Multiple overflow vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    The Cyrus IMAP Server is affected by several overflow vulnerabilities which
    could potentially lead to the remote execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-29.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>cmd5checkpw: Local password leak vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    cmd5checkpw contains a flaw allowing local users to access other users
    cmd5checkpw passwords.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-30.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>uim: Privilege escalation vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    Under certain conditions, applications linked against uim suffer from a
    privilege escalation vulnerability.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-31.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>UnAce: Buffer overflow and directory traversal vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    UnAce is vulnerable to several buffer overflow and directory traversal
    attacks.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-32.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-catalyst</title>
<body>
<p><b>Catalyst vs Knoppix Confusion</b></p>

<p>This week a user asked if Catalyst can be used to build
a Knoppix-like LiveCD based on Gentoo Linux. General consensus was 
that the tool isn't really there yet, but improvements are under way 
to enhance its functionality into this direction. <mail 
link="rpaskowitz@confucius.ca">Robert Paskowitz</mail> pointed out 
a Catalyst-made LiveCD, <uri 
link="http://zaheer.merali.org/mediawiki/index.php/Caster">Caster</uri>, 
that provides a good example of what's already possible today.
</p>

<note>Until popular mailing list archives like <uri 
link="http://www.gmane.org">Gmane</uri> pick up the gentoo-catalyst 
mailing list, <mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail> 
keeps a regularly updated <uri 
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~citizen428/hypermail/gentoo-catalyst/">archive</uri> 
in a temporary home at his developer webspace.</note>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~citizen428/hypermail/gentoo-catalyst/0502/0233.html">Catalyst vs Knoppix Confusion</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>eWeek (28 February 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
ZiffDavis analyst Jason Brooks summarizes eWeek Lab's <uri 
link="http://www.eweek.com/article2/0,1759,1770228,00.asp">evaluation</uri> of
Gentoo Linux for enterprise use. The article opens stating that "Gentoo Linux 
has quickly grown into one of the world's most popular Linux distributions", 
and "the system's source code-based software installation mechanism makes (it) a 
good fit for testing the latest versions of key open-source software components." 
However, "its reputation as a bleeding-edge distribution (...) has so far dimmed 
its prospects for enterprise adoption." and Brooks therefore "hesitates to 
recommend" Gentoo for wide adoption in production environments. The
article walks through some basic pros and cons of source-based distributions, and
finds a few potential problems in all-free Linux distributions as opposed to 
commercial vendors, but when testing the installation of VMWare as an example for 
non-free software packages, the author readily acknowledges that "Gentoo makes 
the process of obtaining the software more elegant than any other Linux distribution 
we've tested."
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>OSdir.com (22 February 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
O'Reilly's online magazine on operating systems finds unusually harsh words 
for Linux distributor RedHat's attitude of the past. In the article titled <uri 
link="http://www.osdir.com/Article4265.phtml">"Best of Linux World 
Coverage: The Redhat Mistake"</uri>, Gentoo is mentioned as stepping in "where they 
messed up" by "abandoning their 'freebie' Redhat version two years ago to 
focus exclusively on their enterprise 'pay up big time' version," a move that 
was "not exactly the wisest thing to do," says OSdir.com's managing editor 
Steve Mallett. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>ZDNet (18 February 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
In <uri link="http://news.zdnet.com/2100-3513_22-5582945.html?tag=nl.e539">a 
similar article</uri> about RedHat's "misstep in its relations with technology 
enthusiasts" and the plan to "rectify the situation with a more aggressive 
Fedora project," CNET author Stephen Shankland observes that "Red Hat has ample 
competition. Projects such as Gentoo lure hard-core Linux programmers, while 
Sun Microsystems is trying to build its own community of programmers around 
its OpenSolaris project."
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 20 February 2005 and 27 February 2005, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>789 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>443 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>33 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8054 currently open bugs: 100 are labeled 'blocker', 233 are labeled 'critical', and 595 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 49
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 24
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="mozilla@gentoo.org" >Mozilla Gentoo Team</mail>, with 17
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mozilla@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="www-proxy@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Web Proxy Developers</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=www-proxy@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="pam-bugs@gentoo.org" >PAM Gentoo Team</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=pam-bugs@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="so@gentoo.org" >so</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=so@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="netmon@gentoo.org" >Netmon Herd</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=netmon@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 36
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 21
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sci@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Science Related Packages</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;assigned_to=sci@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="php-bugs@gentoo.org" >PHP Bugs</mail>, with 12
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-27&amp;assigned_to=php-bugs@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<e>None this week</e>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
David Gümbel (ganymede) - wine
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<e>None this week</e>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter? Send us an <mail 
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and 
help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">french</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">portuguese (brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">portuguese (portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>