<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050207-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>February 7th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="spb@gentoo.org">Stephen Bennett</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="absinthe@gentoo.org">Dylan Carlson</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="angusyoung@gentoo.org">Otavio R. Piske</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 7 February 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 6</version>
<date>2005-02-07</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo at the Linux World Expo, Boston edition</title>
<body>
<p>
With just a week to go before the U.S. east coast version of the <uri 
link="http://www.linuxworldexpo.com">LWE</uri> opens its gates, the Gentoo line-up 
is complete. Gentoo developers manning the booth will include Mike Frysinger, Chris 
Gianelloni, Dylan Carlson, Daniel Ostrow, Luke Macken, Jeffrey Forman, Rajiv Aaron 
Manglani and Chris Aniszczyk, aided by local organiser Andrew Fant who's been busy 
preparing everything to go smoothly at booth #6  on the exhibition floor at Boston's
Hynes Convention Center. Visitors to the Gentoo stand will find Sparcs and x86, and 
a Mac Mini running Gentoo Linux/PPC among the architectures on display. The exhibition 
starts on Tuesday 15 February and lasts until Thursday 17, open daily from 10:00 to 
17:00 (16:00 on Thursday).
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Two million posts</title>
<body>
<p>Yet another record for the Gentoo Forums: The 2,000,000th post since the creation 
of Gentoo's phpBB user support forum was registered last Monday. While dozens
of Forum regulars were watching the total post count move up towards the magic number,
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=56608">Naib</uri> 
from Birmingham in the United Kingdom finally hit the submit button at 
exactly the right time. His post, combining both clarity of expression and 
snotty Brum poetry, was in reply to someone asking for fullscreen capabilities
in terminal programs. Naib's answer, scheduled for immortality: <uri 
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?p=2041272#2041272">"Ctrl-Alt-F1"</uri>
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050207_forum.png"
short="2Mposts" caption="Post counter on forums.gentoo.org, 31 January 2005 at around 20:15 UTC" />
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New IRC channel, mailing list for Gentoo media packages</title>
<body>
<p><mail link="luckyduck@gentoo.org">Jan Brinkmann</mail> announced two new support 
platforms for the evergrowing number of packages in Portage dealing with audio and 
video applications. <path>#gentoo-media</path> is a new channel on irc.freenode.net where media 
package maintainers congregate, and a new mailing list, <path>gentoo-media@gentoo.org</path>, 
has also been created to improve the communication between the developers in media 
related herds. "We also intended to make it easier for desktop users to get in touch with 
maintainers of software which is related to these herds," says Jan Brinkmann, hoping both the new 
IRC channel and mailing list will soon become both "popular and populated," especially
in view of recruiting additional developers for the understaffed media herds. To subscribe
to the mailing list, send a blank email to <mail 
link="gentoo-media-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-media-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>. If you
would like to help with development on sound and video applications, contact Jan Brinkmann 
directly.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Future Zone</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo/FreeBSD</title>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo/FreeBSD project officially started in August 2004 as a set of 
system ebuilds based on FreeBSD 5.2.1 and a portage overlay provided by 
Grant Goodyear (g2boojum). As the release of FreeBSD 5.3 became imminent, the 
project slowly ported base system ebuilds to this new version, which is the 
actual base for our project.</p> 
<p>The Gentoo/FreeBSD project, as its name implies, is an effort to have 
the whole set of Gentoo components running on top of a FreeBSD base system. 
This means that, for example, instead of having a Linux kernel and GNU LibC, one
will have FreeBSD's kernel and FreeBSD's LibC. In  addition, the project is
also working on porting baselayout to Gentoo/FreeBSD in such a way that makes
the management of startup services as easy as in Gentoo Linux.
</p>
<p>Although this project is fairly young, a fair amount of progress
has been achieved. The most important accomplishments include:
</p>
<ul><li>Portage now runs without needing to be patched.</li>
<li>the set of ebuilds that downloads and install specific FreeBSD system packages 
is now almost stable and the process of building it is, in general, painless.</li>
<li>we have defined a system profile as well as some non-FreeBSD packages that 
should be available.</li>
</ul>
<p>At this moment, we are working on stabilizing the content of source
tarballs in such a way that they provide all the reasonable things for
their category (system sources tarballs, in Gentoo/FreeBSD are separated by
category, like <path>freebsd-lib</path>, <path>freebsd-usbin</path>, etc).
</p>
<p>Our efforts with baselayout have mainly been oriented towards getting
Gentoo's dependency-based init system working with FreeBSD's userland.
Unsurprisingly, certain parts (mainly involving <c>gawk</c>) have been
problematic, but we currently have a package that can bring up a
functional FreeBSD system, and should allow the initscripts in the main
Portage tree to work unchanged. More work is needed to write initscripts
for the less common parts of the FreeBSD system, and possibly to update
the system to baselayout 1.11 when that becomes stable.
</p> 
<p>
Goals for the immediate future include a set of stages that will be used to 
install Gentoo/FreeBSD, completion of the baselayout port, and finally, a release.
</p>
<p> 
In a separate effort we are also looking into porting the <c>glibc</c> and GNU userland 
to the FreeBSD kernel. If you are interested in working on this, contact 
<mail link="absinthe@gentoo.org">Dylan Carlson</mail>. (see also the post by 
Robert Millan to the <path>gentoo-dev</path> mailing list referenced below).</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>Gallery: Cross-site scripting vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    Gallery is vulnerable to cross-site scripting attacks.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-45.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>ClamAV: Multiple issues</title>
<body>
<p>

    ClamAV contains two vulnerabilities that could lead to Denial of Service
    and evasion of virus scanning.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-46.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>ncpfs: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    The ncpfs utilities contain multiple flaws, potentially resulting in the
    remote execution of arbitrary code or local file access with elevated
    privileges.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-44.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>FireHOL: Insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

    FireHOL is vulnerable to symlink attacks, potentially allowing a local user
    to overwrite arbitrary files.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-01.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>UW IMAP: CRAM-MD5 authentication bypass</title>
<body>
<p>

    UW IMAP contains a vulnerability in the code handling CRAM-MD5
    authentication allowing authentication bypass.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-02.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>enscript: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    enscript suffers from vulnerabilities and design flaws, potentially
    resulting in the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-03.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Squid: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Squid contains vulnerabilities in the code handling WCCP, HTTP and LDAP
    which could lead to Denial of Service, access control bypass, web cache and
    log poisoning.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-04.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Newspost: Buffer overflow vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    A buffer overflow can be exploited to crash Newspost remotely and
    potentially execute arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-05.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>LessTif: Multiple vulnerabilities in libXpm</title>
<body>
<p>

    Multiple vulnerabilities have been discovered in libXpm, which is included
    in LessTif, that can potentially lead to remote code execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-06.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>Gentoo/kFreeBSD</b></p>
<p>
Visiting Debian developer <mail link="rmh@debian.org">Robert Millan</mail> 
posted to announce his work on porting the glibc and GNU userland to the 
FreeBSD kernel: "I started from the existing Gentoo FreeBSD system and gradually 
migrated it to Glibc." 

</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/24990">Gentoo GNU/kFreeBSD</uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>GWN independence?</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="g2boojum@gentoo.org">Grant Goodyear</mail> tries to come to
terms with the status of the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter: "Is the GWN an 
official Gentoo newsletter that promotes Gentoo, or is it a 
quasi-independent newsletter that is free to criticize as well as 
evangelize?" How much influence should developers have on its content?

</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25156">GWN
independence?</uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>Proper if/else blocks in bash</b></p>
<p>
Once again, <mail link="ciaranm@gentoo.org">Ciaran McCreesh</mail> gives
some important info on <c>bash</c> syntax. This should be especially
interesting for those among you that contribute ebuilds.
Also, he does not point us at the not existing draft of <uri
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~ciaranm/docs/IGNORE_the-doc/#multiple-selection">
the doc</uri> which, if it existed, would be a good ressource for all
ebuild questions.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25115">Proper
if/else blocks in bash</uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>gcc-4 support in Gentoo</b></p>
<p>
For all Gentooists who like new ans shiny toys, <mail
link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike Frysinger</mail> has added gcc-4 ebuilds to
portage. They are masked at the moment and totally unsupported, so if
you wish to use them it's at your own risk! First reports are quite
mixed, from random segfaults to flawless working everything seems to be
possible. Enjoy!
</p><ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25098">gcc-4
support in Gentoo</uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>autotools confusion</b></p>
<p>
Some time ago, the <c>autoconf</c> / <c>automake</c> / <c>libtool</c> ebuilds were modified.
Many users now complain that portage wants to install all available
versions, but as <mail link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike Frysinger</mail>
explains: "The old ebuilds (<path>autoconf-2.59-r5</path> / <path>automake-1.8.5-r1</path> /
<path>libtool-1.5.2-r7</path>) actually downloaded and installed multiple versions
of each package. You <e>thought</e> you had just one <c>autoconf</c>, but boy oh boy
were you wrong !"
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25020">autotools
confusion</uri></li>
</ul>

</body></section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Germany: Oberhausen GUM on Friday 11 February</title>
<body>
<p>
Oberhausen, home to the "Friends of Gentoo e.V." and several
active developers, is again the venue for a Gentoo User Meeting
at the Gasthof Harlos, itself on the way to become an institution
in the German Gentoo microcosmos. This week, preparations for the
FOSDEM conference in Belgium later this month are on the agenda,
as is the notorious Schnitzelplatte, a copious amount of meat 
traditionally served at Oberhausen GUMs. The organisers are also 
trying to bring one of the used <uri 
link="http://sunsolve.sun.com/handbook_pub/Systems/SunBlade100/SunBlade100.html">Sun 
Blade 100</uri> that have been bought recently by several German 
developers from a Swiss university to the meeting, which is going
to take place on 11 February, starting at around 19:00 CET. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Linux Magazin (Issue 3/2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
The German Linux Magazin carries an article by Gentoo developer
<mail link="citizen428">Michael Kohl</mail> in its latest number. 
Michael explains the <c>catalyst</c> release engineering tool
and the release process for Gentoo Linux on three pages full of
interesting details, mentioning examples for using <c>catalyst</c>
to create variant LiveCDs like the German "Fizzle Wizzle" release
that includes a complete KDE environment running Knoppix-like from
the CD without the need to install on the harddisk. The printed
magazine is available at newsstands in Germany since Thursday
last week, and also includes an additional Gentoo installation 
rundown by editor Oliver Frommel.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>David Berlind's blog (31 January 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
CNET columnist David Berlind posted a clarification to his earlier 
article on Gentoo and OpenSolaris <uri 
link="/news/en/20050131-newsletter.xml#doc_chap5">we referenced 
last week</uri>. In his new article <uri 
link="http://blogs.zdnet.com/BTL/index.php?p=988">"Gentoo: We're 
not the Napster of Open Source"</uri> he quotes from mails going
back and forth between Gentoo developer Pieter Van den Abeele and
himself, acknowledging that "the folks at Gentoo are disputing my 
characterization of their Portaris and Portage technologies as being 
Napster-like facilitators that can grease the wheels of open source 
license violation." 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 31 January 2005 and 07 February 2005, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>875 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>661 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>28 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8006 currently open bugs: 105 are labeled 'blocker', 245 are labeled 'critical', and 601 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="osx@gentoo.org" >osx porters</mail>, with 173
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=osx@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 33
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 30
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 23
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 21
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 20
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="neysx@gentoo.org" >Xavier Neys</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=neysx@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 37
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 21
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 17
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="mozilla@gentoo.org" >Mozilla Gentoo Team</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;assigned_to=mozilla@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="marduk@gentoo.org" >marduk</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;assigned_to=marduk@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="xfce@gentoo.org" >XFCE Team</mail>, with 7
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-31&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-07&amp;assigned_to=xfce@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
	<section>
	<title>Moves</title>
	<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>
			Alexander Gabert
		</li>
		<li>
			Andrew Bevitt (temporary leave)
		</li>
		</ul>
	</body>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Adds</title>
	<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Stefano Rossi (so) - Documentation</li>
		<li>Andreas Pokorny (DieMumiee) - AMD64</li>
		<li>Shigehiro Idani (idani) - Japanese translation</li>
		</ul>
	</body>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Changes</title>
	<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
		Gentoo Linux project:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>Chris Gianelloni (wolf31o2) - Changed from Release Engineering Operational to Strategic Lead</li>
		<li>Tim Yamin (plasmaroo) - New Release Engineering Operational Lead</li>
		</ul>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<section>
	<body>
		<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?
		Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN feedback</title>
	<section>
	<body>
		<p>Please send us your <mail
		link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make
		the GWN better.</p>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN subscription information</title>
	<section>
	<body>
		<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank
		email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.</p>
		<p>To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank
		email to <mail
		link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
		from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Other languages</title>
	<section>
	<body>
		<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
		following languages:</p>
		<ul>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
		</li>
		<li>
			<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
		</li>
		</ul>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
</guide>


