<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20051114-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>November 14th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 14 November 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 45</version>
<date>2005-11-14</date>

<!-- Gentoo News -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo news</title>
<section>
<title>Switched to stage3 as the default installation method</title>
<body>
<p>
During the last week the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/index.xml">Gentoo Documentation
Project</uri> changed the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/index.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>
in a way, that the installation of a stage3 will be default.  Prior to this
change the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/index.xml">Release
Engineering team</uri> asked for the change, as the number of users increased,
who messed up their base-system due to unrecommended changes during a stage1 or
stage2 install or not following the handbook completely.
</p>
<p>
The adviced method now is to do a stage3 installation and optionally recompile
the system after the installation.  That will create an optimized system as
well.  How to proceed a real stage1 or stage2 installation is still described in
the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/faq.xml#stage12">FAQ</uri>.
</p>
<p>
For further reading you can have a look at the <uri
link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.documentation/2327">full
discussion</uri> about the change on the gentoo-doc mailing list, see the
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-x86-medium.xml?hidecvsroot=1&amp;search=&amp;hideattic=0&amp;sortby=file&amp;r2=1.41&amp;logsort=date&amp;root=gentoo&amp;diff_format=h&amp;r1=1.40">real
changes</uri> in our viewcvs or read <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/105809">bug #105809</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Future zone -->
<!-- User Stories -->

<chapter>
<title>User stories</title>
<section>
<title>Interview with Douglas Robertson from Zymeta Corporation</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20051114_zymeta-jukebox.jpg" short="Zymeta Video
  Jukebox"
caption="The Zymeta Video Jukebox in action" />

<p><e>A few words about you. Who are you, where do you work?</e></p>

<p>My name is Douglas Robertson and I'm the Director of Technology at <uri
  link="http://www.zymeta.com/">Zymeta Entertainment.</uri></p>

<p><e>What is your "product"?</e></p>

<p>Zymeta is an entertainment systems company. We have developed an on demand
  touch screen media delivery platform for public venues complete with a backend
  system for updating and managing the platform. And we can manage the platform
  as a whole or make changes for a single location.  Our first very successful
  product is a music video entertainment system called the "Video Jukebox" which
  is typically installed in pubs and bars.  The venues patrons are able to
  choose their music selections using a touchscreen and then watch the music
  videos on the bars televisions and advertisers can pin point their promotions
  to specific locations or groups of locations.   The service is completely
  licensed by the music industry.   It's flashy, it's interactive and it's built
  on top of Gentoo Linux.</p>

<p>If anyone wants to see the jukebox in action, our <uri
    link="http://www.zymeta.com/files/corporate-video-small.mov">corporate
    video</uri> also has a lot of cool shots.</p>

<p><e>How does Gentoo fit in there? Why did you decide to use it?</e></p>

<p>As far as technology is concerned, Zymeta is a Gentoo-driven company.  The
  development team all run Gentoo on their desktops, our servers are all running
  Gentoo and, most importantly, our jukeboxes all run Gentoo.   I brought Gentoo
  into Zymeta and mandated it be the distro used; trying to support multiple
  distributions is too much hassle. I chose Gentoo because of it's flexibility;
  it's a source-based distro with a great packaging system and a great
  user-base.</p>

<p>We update the jukebox client software over the Internet but we haven't been
  updating the Operating System on the jukeboxes. We haven't updated the OS
  because Gentoo has been so stable and as such there's been no real need to
  change anything.  We looked at setting up our own portage tree but decided
  that the best route to any major updates would be to build a new tarball of
  the OS and use that to update the jukeboxes. In the future we may look at
  doing minor updates of individual packages using a portage tree. This would
  allow us to keep the jukeboxes up to date in case of any security flaws
  found.</p>

<p>That said, we recently upgraded the software so that it works flawlessly on
  the 2.6 kernel and I have spent the last two days setting up a CD that boots
  the jukebox, mounts the hard drive and then updates the OS files.  The Gentoo
  community was very helpful with this, and as I mentioned, there is a tonne of
  documentation, which make it simple for me to modify the Gentoo 2005.1 LiveCD
  so that it is Zymeta branded and does the required updating.</p>

<p><e>What did Gentoo replace?</e></p>

<p>Prior to Gentoo, Zymeta was running Red Hat for servers and Debian on the
  jukeboxes.</p>

<p><e>Any experiences with other distributions? How do they compare?</e></p>

<p>I initially tried Gentoo in 2003 at my previous job because a co-worker
  decided to try it and then complained about how much trouble it was to set up
  and how it took him two days to get it working.  To prove him wrong I tried it
  and had a working Gentoo, complete with KDE, on my Dell laptop within the day.
  It was love at first sight with Gentoo so I never went back to my old Red Hat
  install.</p>

<p>A lot of people had issues with Red Hat's RPM system, but I loved it.  At
  least until I started needing the latest packages of various things (such as
  PostgreSQL and some networking tools) and the RPM wouldn't work because it was
  built on a different version of Red Hat. Or it would require updating three
  other packages, which in turn had their own dependencies.  Gentoo's package
  system is the real shining star as far as I'm concerned, and while updates
  take longer since packages are compiled, it's well worth it.</p>

<p><e>What are the big advantages? Where does it shine?</e></p>

<p>Gentoo offers flexibility. Don't need IPv6 support is your packages?  Just
  change your USE flags. No ebuild for a package you need? Just create your own
  ebuild and add it into your Portage overlay. How sweet is that for
  flexibility?</p>

<p><e>What do you see as problematic? Where could things be improved?</e></p>

<p>My only complaint is that sometimes it takes a long time to stabilize
  packages. I like that the maintainers ensure that packages compile and work
  properly before marking a package as stable, especially given that we run
  Gentoo on production/enterprise systems, but sometimes it seems to take a bit
  too long. But we get around that using Portage's flexibility (ie. USE flags
  and Portage overlays).</p>


<p><e>There are many projects like the installer, Gentoo/Alt (BSD,...).  What do
    you think of this expansion into new fields? How about different
    architectures?</e></p>

<p>I think that the more people using Gentoo the better. Part of the reason I'm
  excited about this interview is that I want to help spread the word that
  Gentoo can be used in any environment, whether it's on a desktop or on an
  enterprise server running a mission-critical database. Stability is key in
  most environments but I don't think that you necessarily need to use six month
  old packages to get that stability.</p>

<p><e>How do you see the community? What is the general perception of Gentoo in
    your company?</e></p>

<p>I love the Gentoo community.  There's a lot of support available and tonnes
  of documentation. And because at this stage it seems like the majority of
  Gentoo users have a fairly technical background, there's a different feel to
  the Gentoo forums as compared to say the old Red Hat forums.</p>

<p>As for Zymeta, everyone in the company knows Zymeta's product is built on top
  of Gentoo. And since our switch to Gentoo, the stability of our product has
  increased. Part of that is due to Gentoo and part of that is due to an updated
  kernel. But the end result is that the Zymeta team and our customers associate
  Gentoo with stability.</p>

<p><e>How can you be contacted?  And what can we expect in the near future?</e></p>

<p>If anyone wants to talk to me about deploying Gentoo in the enterprise, they
  can contact me at dr@zymeta.com. Also, I believe that Gentoo developer Corey
  Shields wants to create a Gentoo case study out of Zymeta so people should
  look soon for that.</p>

<p>Oh, and there's a Gentoo easter egg in an upcoming version of the Zymeta
  Jukebox client so if anyone wants to know how to do that, they can email me
  about that too.</p>

<p><e>Thanks for the interview!</e></p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo Stories -->
<!-- Developer of the week -->
<!-- Heard in the community: gentoo-dev, gentoo-user, forums -->
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>GLEP 43: GLEP file hosting</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="ciaranm@gentoo.org">Ciaran McCreesh</mail> publicized a <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0043.html">new GLEP</uri> this
week to allow (future) GLEPs to have attached code in a subdirectory instead of
inlined or placed externally. This should allow for better GLEP readability and
easier maintenance.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/32769">GLEP 43:
GLEP file hosting </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>Creation and handling of virtual/tar</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="flameeyes@gentoo.org">Diego 'Flameeyes' Pettenò</mail> tells us
about the creation of virtual/tar which at the moment can be satisfied by GNU
tar and bsdtar. Creating this virtual will mostly help <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gentoo-alt/index.xml">Gentoo/Alt</uri> at
the moment.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/32732">virtual/tar
</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Gentoo international -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo international</title>
<section>
<title>Germany: LWE and DevCon in the Frankfurt/Main area</title>
<body>
<p>
This week the area around Frankfurt/Main will be the events-location for Gentoo.
First there is the <uri link="http://www.linuxworldexpo.de/">Linux World
Conference &amp; Expo</uri> in Hall 4 of Frankfurt's Fairground.  From Tuesday,
November 15, until Thurdsday, November 17, you have the ability to meet Gentoo
Developers at their booth in the .org-Pavilion (G06).  A little highlight will
be the <uri
link="http://www.linuxworldexpo.de/04_03_01.php?Termin_ID=154&amp;ID=97">lecture
about Gentoo</uri> at Wednesday evening.
</p>
<p>
Right after the three days on the Fairground, Gentoo Weekly Newsletter Editor
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail> invited to the <uri
link="http://conference.gentoo-ev.org/">European Gentoo developer meeting</uri>
at his residence Kransberg Castle, 40km north of Frankfurt.  More than 20
developers and some users declared their attendance.  Some lectures and
workshops round up by nice catering and a get-together will fill the day.
</p>
<p>
If you are interested in attending the conference, please use the <uri
link="http://conference.gentoo-ev.org/cgi-bin/registration.pl">online
registration form</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Gentoo in the press -->
<!-- Tips and Tricks -->
<!-- Gentoo developer moves -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo developer moves</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo project:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Jesper Brodersen (broeman) - Danish translations</li>
<li>Arne Mejholm (aaby) - Danish translations</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo project:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Michael Schönbeck (thoand) - video disc recorder</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo project:</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo security -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Security</title>
<!-- paste from the script -->
<section>
<title>PHP: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>
    PHP suffers from multiple issues, resulting in security functions bypass,
    local Denial of service, cross-site scripting or PHP variables overwrite.
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200511-08.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Lynx: Arbitrary command execution</title>
<body>
<p>
    Lynx is vulnerable to an issue which allows the remote execution of
    arbitrary commands.
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200511-09.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>RAR: Format string and buffer overflow vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>
    RAR contains a format string error and a buffer overflow vulnerability that
    may be used to execute arbitrary code.
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200511-10.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>linux-ftpd-ssl: Remote buffer overflow</title>
<body>
<p>
    A buffer overflow vulnerability has been found, allowing a remote attacker
    to execute arbitrary code with escalated privileges on the local system.
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200511-11.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<!-- end of paste from the script -->
</chapter>

<!-- Bugzilla -->
<!-- paste from the script -->
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
      The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri
      link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
      bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the
      development team.  Between 06 November 2005
      and 13 November 2005, activity on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>711 new bugs during this period</li>
          <li>315 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
          <li>31 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8960 currently open bugs: 107 are labeled 'blocker', 195 are labeled 'critical', and 558 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
       The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
      <li><mail link="docs-team@gentoo.org">Docs Team</mail>, with 21
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=docs-team@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org">Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 20
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org">Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 10
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="security@gentoo.org">Gentoo Security</mail>, with 9
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="achumakov@gentoo.org">Alexey Chumakov</mail>, with 9
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=achumakov@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="svyatogor@gentoo.org">Sergey Kuleshov</mail>, with 8
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=svyatogor@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="perl@gentoo.org">Perl Devs @ Gentoo</mail>, with 8
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=perl@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="ppc-macos@gentoo.org">Gentoo for Mac OS X</mail>, with 6
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=ppc-macos@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
       The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
      <li><mail link="maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for New Packages</mail>, with 56
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 49
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="perl@gentoo.org">Perl Devs @ Gentoo</mail>, with 42
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;assigned_to=perl@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="amd64-test@gentoo.org">AMD64 Testing Team</mail>, with 10
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;assigned_to=amd64-test@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 9
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org">Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 9
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="mozilla@gentoo.org">Mozilla Gentoo Team</mail>, with 7
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;assigned_to=mozilla@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org">Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 6
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-11-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-11-13&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- end of paste from bugzilla script -->
<!-- GWN feedback information -->
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and
help make the GWN better.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- GWN subscription information -->
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p> To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Other Languages -->
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following
languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ko/gwn/gwn.xml">Korean</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
