<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050404-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>April 4th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="w.haas@xover.htu.tuwien.ac.at">Wernfried Haas</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 4 April 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 15</version>
<date>2005-04-04</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>April fools</title>
<body>
<p>
Impossible to catch all IT-related April fool's jokes this year, they were 
everywhere, on Google, OpenBSD, some even found their way into Gentoo ebuilds. 
One seems to have qualified for the 2005 best of April fool's shortlist at many 
publications: The <uri link="http://gentooexperimental.org/nt">GeNToo project</uri>, 
Gentoo for the NT kernel, alas, is a complete and utter joke. If you believed a word 
of it, you've been had.
</p>
<p>
Of the <uri link="#doc_chap3_sect2">several pranks played at Gentoo</uri> this year, 
the GeNToo plot was the most elaborate, and actually dating back to a group of three 
developers splitting away from the rest of the lot at FOSDEM in February for a 
spontaneous hacking and belgian fries session: <mail link="karltk@gentoo.org">Karl 
Trygve Kalleberg</mail>, <mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail> and <mail 
link="genone@gentoo.org">Marius Mauch</mail>. Under the influence of too many Belgian 
fries, karltk was the first to point out the epiphany hidden in the name of the project: 
"You see, when you write 'Gentoo', it has NT in the middle," said the Norwegian developer. 
And thinking aloud: "Now if one took the NT kernel ... there <e>is</e> a POSIX 
layer for it ... put Portage on it ..." As he drew the surreal picture in increasingly shrill 
colors, the three devs quickly realized that the only possible release date for this 
particularly fine piece of vaporware would have to be the first of April.
</p> 
<p>
So, with the idea floating since February, there was time to back the story up with
ample documentation and even screenshots (which were taken from VMware during a 
regular boot of Windows 2000 in "Safe Mode"), with a coating of a handmade bootlog 
text that was a rather good approximation of how <c>emerge info</c> might actually 
look on such a system.
</p>
<p>
When the announcement was posted to the website and the topics of two IRC channels 
almost simultaneously around noon UTC, the traffic statistics on the website where 
the project description was hosted went simply through the ceiling. An amazingly 
constant stream of traffic, weighing in at around one hit per second or 100MB per hour, 
was sustained over almost the entire day -- considering that the whole website is  only 
165KB, estimations are that the GeNToo hoax got around 600 visitors per hour. 
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050404_bonsai.png"
	short="Screenshot" 
	caption="Traffic load on the fake GeNToo project pages: Right after the announcement" />
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050404_slashdot.png"
	short="Screenshot" 
	caption="Traffic load on the fake GeNToo project pages: Slashdot effect after 22:00" />
<p>
To make the illusion even more believable, a channel on Freenode was created, too: 
<path>#gentoo-nt</path>, the perfect place to discuss something that didn't even 
exist. An interesting twist came about when some of the first to be fooled later 
turned into devoted GeNToo evangelists, perpetuating the myth in the IRC channel 
and taking the charade even further: One produced "a patched NT kernel" and offered 
it online at his own website. When looked at closely, it bore a striking familiarity 
with a 2.6.11 Linux kernel, but nevertheless -- declared as a "GeNToo binary" -- found 
many curious downloaders.
</p>
<p>
While the <path>#gentoo-nt</path> channel on Freenode was still continuing 
its makebelief stance well past the dateline into Saturday 2 April, nobody 
was sad when the atrocities behind the other prominent Gentoo April fool's joke 
were taken down again. People who had followed <uri 
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-317053.html">the announcement</uri> in 
the Gentoo forums that the redesign had now been finished and could be applied by 
simply switching the user profile, quickly complained about headache, sudden bursts 
of claustro- and other phobia. Small wonder, looking at the effect the "redesign" 
had on posts:</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050404_forum.png"
	short="Screenshot" 
	caption="Kallamej's announcement, rendered in the freshly redesigned Forum layout" />
<p>
Reactions were mixed, while some people figured out the joke pretty fast, others 
complained about eyestrain. While moderators were watching and merging duplicated spawn to <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-317056.html">the central thread</uri>, they 
decided to create even more confusion by renaming moderators to "Ninjas" and administrators to "Ninja Masters". Bodhisatvas (the rank for ex-mods and -admins) decided not to follow this trend -- and were renamed to HAL 9000. How subtle moderator interference at the forums really is was best displayed by the fact that it took almost all day before people <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-317461.html">started noticing</uri> the change!
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>emerge webrsync reloaded</title>
<body>
<p>
Portage developer <mail link="ferringb@gentoo.org">Brian Harring</mail> has
implemented a more resource-friendly version of <c>emerge webrsync</c>.
Instead of pulling in the whole tarball, it only uses compressed patches
between (daily) versions. That way a user can keep up-to-date with only
minimal overhead even when <c>rsync</c> is not available (firewalls and dialup
users mostly). A description and howto can be found at <uri
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~ferringb/blog/archives/2005-03.html#e2005-03-29T17_14_42.txt"> his blog</uri>. 
First estimates give up to 99% bandwidth saved compared to <c>webrsync</c>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Donations surpassing expectations</title>
<body>
<p>
Last week's announcement of the return of PayPal donations has triggered a
delightful response from the community, as Corey Shields, one of the trustees 
of the Gentoo Foundation, has reported last week.</p>
<p>The opening balance for the bank account was spontaneously paid in full 
by Gentoo sponsor Genesi, who wired an advance payment on commissions for the
sales of PegasosPPC Open Desktop Workstations.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>"Why Gentoo? It's cool." -- Michael Hanselmann (hansmi)</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050404_hansmi.jpg"
	short="hansmi" 
	caption="Michael Hanselmann aka hansmi" />

<p>
This weeks featured dev is Michael Hanselmann, known to most as <mail 
link="hansmi@gentoo.org">hansmi</mail>. He does "various stuff" 
in Gentoo/PPC, Gentoo/HPPA and the <c>qmail</c> herd, which mostly 
boils down to marking packages stable, fixing bugs and hanging out 
on IRC a lot. He is the administrator of a hosting experiment (a project 
called <uri link="http://www.forkbomb.ch">forkbomb.ch</uri>), has
written <uri link="http://www.hansmi.ch/software">some software of his own</uri>, 
used to do some work with <c>fli4l</c> and still does busy himself
with the <c>m0n0wall</c> project, but his greatest contributions he still 
sees in Gentoo, including a stint on the Mac OS X team where he contributed a
Mac OS panel application for setting Portage preferences.
</p>
<p>
Currently he is doing a programmer apprenticeship in Liechtenstein which 
will be finished this summer -- job offers in Switzerland are therefore 
highly appreciated! His favourite applications are the <c>vim</c>, <c>mutt</c> 
and <c>qmail</c>, which all runs somewhere on a heterogenous mix of 
<path>x86</path>, <path>sparc</path>, <path>hppa</path> and <path>ppc</path>, 
with <c>fluxbox</c> quite possibly being the only element that binds them all 
together. Asked what the first application to launch after he boots his systems,
he insists on an appropriately geeky answer: "Technically, <path>/sbin/init</path> 
is the first application I (or my kernel) launches at startup. Or maybe you mean 
<c>bash</c> when logging in. In a graphical environment, it's <c>aterm</c> and 
<c>ssh</c>." 
</p>
<p>
In those rare moments when he is not attached to computer peripherals he fiddles 
with electronics, building or breaking stuff, and sometimes really considers "real" 
life less interesting than computers.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Banned from OTW</b></p>
<p>A new feature, originally introduced by ex-developer Christian Hartmann and 
available to forum administrators since about a month ago has now been officially 
announced to the public. The OTW ban button provides the forum admins with a 
finer-grained ability to ban someone for disregarding the guidelines for postings 
in Off the Wall, while leaving their ID intact and activated for posts in the 
technical support forums. People can be hotheads and still eager (and competent) 
to help others with their Linux problems. Until the new feature was introduced, 
banning resulted in a full ban from the forums altogether.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-317818.html">Bans from OTW</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>The Pluggable Hell - PAM</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="flameeyes@users.berlios.de">Diego Pettenò</mail> explains
his work with getting PAM (Pluggable Authentication Modules) to behave
the same on non-Linux Gentoos as on normal Linux. For anyone interested
in porting software this should be an interesting read, showing how
small differences can make you life really difficult when trying to get
something to work properly ...
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26664">Pluggable Hell Part 1 </uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26726">Pluggable Hell Part 2 </uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26731">pam_console headaches </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>GTK / GTK2 USE flag madness</b></p>
<p>
As it happens every 6 months or so, a discussion on the (ab)use and the
combinations of GTK and GTK2 USEflags was started. There are many ideas
to improve the situation, but no real consensus on what "-gtk gtk2"
would mean has been reached (yet)
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26681">GTK und GTK2 Use Flag </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>ApRiL FoOlS!!!</b></p>
<p>
As it happens every year, a few jokes were sent to the -dev mailinglist
on April 1. Here's a list of those messages:
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26744">Uniting x86 and AMD64 keywords </uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26752">New "warez" useflag </uri></li>

<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26756">GeNToo, Gentoo with Microsoft NT kernel </uri></li>

<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26760">new dev mr_t </uri></li>

</ul>
</body></section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>NewsForge (28 March 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Bruce Byfield discusses the upcoming OpenOffice.org version 2.0 and the 
implications of its move towards Java: "Since Java's license is neither free 
nor open source, a small but vocal minority has responded both strongly and 
negatively," says Byfield, and explains in detail why there are fears of 
platform support for OOo falling apart (FreeBSD and Linux for PPC, for example, 
currently "have no official version of Java," as he notes), and of alienating 
users. In his article with the provocative title <uri 
link="http://software.newsforge.com/article.pl?sid=05/03/22/204244&amp;tid=93">"Java 
fallout: OpenOffice.org 2.0 and the FOSS community"</uri>, he looks at the 
plans at major distributors of how to go about the issue of OOoand Java 
inclusion, he quotes Gentoo developer <mail link="pauldv@gentoo.org">Paul de 
Vrieze</mail> as preferring an open-source implementation of Java such as GCJ, 
but being open to include Java proper if no alternative is available.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Summary of release coverage (28 March 2005 and later)</title>
<body>
<p>
The long-awaited release of 2005.0 received a lot of attention throughout the 
week, here's a compilation of some major sightings:</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://osnews.com/story.php?news_id=10121">OS News</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.internetnews.com/dev-news/article.php/3493541">InternetNews.com</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://bloggeditnews.blogspot.com/2005/03/new-gentoo-release.html">Blogged IT News</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.desktoplinux.com/news/NS2703815206.html">Desktop Linux</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.linuxelectrons.com/article.php/20050328065233355">Linux Electrons</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://linuxfr.org/2005/03/29/18615.html">LinuxFR</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://derstandard.at/?id=1995209">Der Standard (Austrian daily newspaper, in German)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.golem.de/0503/37161.html">Golem.de (German)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.dslteam.de/news2538.html">DSL Team (German)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.pro-linux.de/news/2005/7960.html">Pro-Linux (German)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.linuxhelp.it/modules.php?name=News&amp;file=article&amp;sid=2781">LinuxHelp (Italian)</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Chris White
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Joe Sapp (nixphoeni) - gDesklets
</li>
<li>
Jory Pratt (anarchy) - qmail
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>mpg321: Format string vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    A flaw in the processing of ID3 tags in mpg321 could potentially lead to
    the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-34.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Smarty: Template vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    Smarty's "Template security" feature can be bypassed, potentially allowing
    a remote attacker to execute arbitrary PHP code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-35.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>netkit-telnetd: Buffer overflow</title>
<body>
<p>

    The netkit-telnetd telnet client is vulnerable to a buffer overflow, which
    could allow a malicious telnet server operator to execute arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-36.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>LimeWire: Disclosure of sensitive information</title>
<body>
<p>

    Two vulnerabilities in LimeWire can be exploited to disclose sensitive
    information.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-37.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>telnet-bsd: Multiple buffer overflows</title>
<body>
<p>

    The telnet-bsd telnet client is vulnerable to two buffer overflows, which
    could allow a malicious telnet server operator to execute arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-01.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sylpheed, Sylpheed-claws: Buffer overflow on message display</title>
<body>
<p>

    Sylpheed and Sylpheed-claws contain a vulnerability that can be triggered
    when displaying messages with specially crafted attachments.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-02.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 27 March 2005 and 03 April 2005, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>911 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>489 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>32 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8410 currently open bugs: 87 are labeled 'blocker', 235 are labeled 'critical', and 633 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 48
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 36
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 27
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="livecd@gentoo.org" >Gentoo LiveCD Team</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=livecd@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="ppc@gentoo.org" >PPC Porters</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=ppc@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 12
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 23
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="toolchain@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Toolchain Maintainers</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;assigned_to=toolchain@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kernel@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Kernel Bug Wranglers and Kernel Maintainers</mail>, with 12
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;assigned_to=kernel@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-27&amp;chfieldto=2005-04-03&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter? Send us an <mail 
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and 
help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
