<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050328-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>March 28th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="ramereth@gentoo.org">Lance Albertson</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="cherry@trombik.mine.nu">Tomoyuki Sakurai</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="cshields@gentoo.org">Corey Shields</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 28 March 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 14</version>
<date>2005-03-28</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo 2005.0 released</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo Linux is proud to bring you the long awaited Gentoo Linux 2005.0
release!
</p>
<p>
This release has had a few setbacks including a complete security
rebuild, but with the help of the many teams within the Gentoo developer
community, we believe that this release will be one of the best that we
have ever had.
</p>
<p>
This release includes new installation media from Alpha, AMD64, PPC,
PPC64, SPARC, and x86 and includes stages for IA64 and SPARC32.  Please
check out our <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri> 
to find the closest one to you.  As with 2004.3, you will be able to download 
optimized PackageCD images for x86 and PPC via our <uri 
link="http://torrents.gentoo.org">bittorrent</uri> server, and also our 
"unofficial" <uri link="http://tracker.netdomination.org">secondary 
bittorrent</uri> server, provided by Friends of Gentoo e.V. in Germany.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Donations to Gentoo via Paypal</title>
<body>
<p>
The <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/">Gentoo Foundation</uri> is 
pleased to announce the return of the Paypal donation link on the www.gentoo.org 
pages. This link allows you to donate any amount you wish directly to the 
Foundation. One of the responsabilities of the Foundation is to handle the 
financial needs of Gentoo and to help fund the further development of Gentoo 
Linux. More information about funding needs can be found <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/funds.xml">at the Gentoo website</uri>.
</p>
<p>
The most immediate funding need that the Foundation has is to raise the 
500 USD opening balance for the Foundation's bank account (and this will 
remain in the account as the minimum balance).  We challenge users and 
organizations to donate if they can, even the smallest amount counts! 
Thank you for your continued support of Gentoo Linux!
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Bugzilla now supports SSL</title>
<body>
<p>
As of 24 March 2005, Gentoo's <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org">Bugzilla</uri>
now supports SSL for encrypted communications. This will help people who reside in 
highly unprotected networks (such as a university or an unencrypted wireless 
connection) and want to have a more secure connection to our Bugzilla. 
Authentication and bug submission can now be done securely, without threat of
your password being sniffed or patch data being altered while in transit. Happy 
bug fixing!
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>"Gentoo represents choice and freedom for every user to build their
computing environment to their individual needs, by giving them the
tools to do it." -- Marcus D. Hanwell (cryos)</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050328_cryos.jpg"
	short="cryos" 
	caption="Marcus D. Hanwell aka cryos" />

<p>This weeks featured developer is Marcus D. Hanwell, aka cryos. He is a
PhD student at the University of Sheffield, studying "the structure of
metal-organic nanosystems and their sensing applications", as he puts
it. He also runs a small IT consultancy firm specialized in deploying
Gentoo-based solutions for local businesses.
</p>
<p>
Initially recruited for work with the science herd, he now also supports
the AMD64 herd since his work and home systems are AMD64-based. Further
interests include, but are not limited to, the www-proxy herd and web
apps in general. "I would like to see Gentoo recognised as the best platform
for scientific applications," states Marcus who works a lot on getting new
scientific applications into Gentoo - concentrated in the areas of
physics, mathematics and analysis packages/language extensions. 
Gentoo is his first real open-source project, but he has used Linux since
the stone age (which translates roughly to 1996). The motivation to work
on Gentoo came from it being his favourite distribution.
</p>
<p>
His favourite tools are Thunderbird, Firefox, <c>kdevelop</c>, <c>vim</c> 
and <c>gvim</c>,<c> kvirc</c>, <c>irssi</c>, <c>kopete</c>, <c>povray</c>, 
<c>gimp</c>, <c>screen</c>, <c>konsole</c> and <c>amarok</c>, proving that
the K*/G* split in Gentooland is not absolute. His main machine is, of 
course, an Athlon64 3200+, featuring lots of goodies: 1GB Corsair LL RAM, 
NEC DVD writer, nVidia GeForce FX5900XT 128MB graphics, Creative Audigy 2 
sound, Dolby 5.1 speakers and two 17" LG TFT screens using nVidia TwinView.
His desktop environment of choice is KDE (especially 3.4), and on booting 
up he usually starts <c>konsole</c> or Thunderbird first. <c>kvirc</c> fills 
his need for an IRC client.
</p>
<p>
When he isn't glued to his computers he takes his German shepherd for walks
and does some amateur photography with the cameras he owns. He has an 
extensive life away from computers, much of it devoted to his fiancee (which 
he intends to marry in July). But other activities are becoming rare since 
working on Gentoo is so much fun... He enjoyed meeting other developers at 
the FOSDEM Gentoo developer conference in February and the UK conference in 
March very much. His motto is borrowed from Albert Einstein: "<e>Two things are 
infinite: the universe and human stupidity; and I'm not sure about the 
universe.</e>"
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Forkbombing Gentoo</b></p>
<p>
An article on SecurityFocus (see Gentoo in the press section) triggered a 
heated debate about the sanity of setting <c>ulimit</c> by default. Common 
sense dictates that system administrators have to take care of this themselves, 
but many people point to the broad base of non-professional Gentoo users for 
reasons why setting a "safe" limit to the number of processes in a user shell 
may be a good idea. Check the companion bug report for developer opinions, and 
the Gentoo documentation on tightening security.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-309944.html">No forkbomb protection by default !?!</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=85656">Bug report: Default limits.conf allows system crash</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-security.xml#doc_chap6">Gentoo Linux Security Guide: Setting ulimit</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>alternative tree sync methods?</b></p>
<p>
From a <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-p-2218914.html">Forum thread</uri>
comes an idea for an optimized <c>sync</c> method that might fill the void
between <c>rsync</c> (which many firewalls filter) and <c>webrsync</c> (one huge
tarball, no easy updating, not updated that often).
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26527">Alternative tree sync methods? </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>GLEP 34 implemented</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="ciaranm@gentoo.org">Ciaran McCreesh</mail> informs us that
GLEP 34 (category metadata) has been implemented. This gives users some
more metadata to search, and it can even be done in multiple languages!
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0034.html">GLEP 34 </uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26567">GLEP34 implemented </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>glibc update problems</b></p>
<p>
Among the most difficult problems in Gentoo are toolchain bugs. If your
compiler doesn't work, you can't update. Not as bad, but still very
annoying are problems like this one: "When trying to upgrade my glibc 
[...] it does nothing but [an] infinite loop." If you find such bugs, 
please don't post to the mailinglists, <uri 
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri> is a much better 
place for that. But we appreciate precise bugreports that allow us to 
track down the problem and give you a better Gentoo experience!
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/26570">glibc update problems </uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/84640">emerge segfaulting on gcc update</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Japan: Open Source Conference 2005</title>
<body>
<p>
We had more than 30 participants, from Linux newbies to Gentoo users, 
at the Gentoo Installfest event on the second day of the Open Source 
Conference at Tokyo's Japan Electronics College in Okubo. Starting with 
a short explanation of the latest Gentoo release, <uri 
link="usata@gentoo.org">Mamoru Komachi</uri> introduced the power of 
distributed computing: <c>distcc</c> bootstrapping. With <c>distccd</c> 
as build helpers, it was expected that at least some of the 15 machines
in the room -- rather than none, as it turned out -- would be 
Gentooified within the two hours of the session. Despite the result, 
people enjoyed this exotic installation procedure. After the session, 
GentooJP members and a few participants had lunch together, discussing 
some new GentooJP projects. 
</p>
<p>
For Usata, this event was the last one in Tokyo: He is moving to the 
Kansai area to attend Graduate School. We appreciated his contribution, 
thanks and good luck, Usata!
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050328_osc.jpg"
	short="GentooJP" 
	caption="GentooJP installfest at the Japan Electronics College in Tokyo" />
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>SecurityFocus (16 March 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Author Jason Miller produces a "deer-in-headlight look" on his own face by
running a forkbomb script on his own Mandrake desktop, then goes on to have
his friends spawn enough processes to crash their Gentoo and RedHat 
installations. Amid displays of happiness about his BSD machines and Debian 
not faltering under the DoS attacks his script triggers, <uri 
link="http://www.securityfocus.com/columnists/308?ref=rss">his article</uri>
doesn't quite explain what default <c>ulimit</c> settings and kernel security 
have to do with each other, but has collected a fairly large number of comments 
questioning the method or asking for additional information, and even more 
active are the discussions Miller's article triggered on the <uri 
link="#doc_chap3_sect1">Gentoo Forums and Bugzilla</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Linux Journal (24 March 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Dovid Kopel, a Gentoo user and Forum regular, has written a detailed howto
for synchronizing the Treo 650 smartphone via Bluetooth, using a Gentoo Linux
desktop. <uri link="http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/8185">His article</uri> 
describes the necessary modifications to the kernel configuration in order to
access the USB bluetooth adapter he uses, installation and configuration of
packages, and using the phone to hotsync applications like calenders and 
addresses, but also to connect the Linux host to the Internet via bridged 
networking through the Palm OS 5 device!
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Software Design (Issue 4/2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo developer and PPC strategic lead <mail link="pvdabeel@gentoo.org">Pieter
Van den Abeele</mail> gave an interview in a Japanese magazine, <uri 
link="http://www.gihyo.co.jp/magazines/SD">Software Design</uri>, with his 
answers embedded in this month's cover story about the business ramifications 
of OpenSolaris and its relation to Linux. The article, titled "Solaris Perfect 
Guide 2005", is not available online, but copies of the magazine's April issue 
can be bought at newsstands in Japan.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Christian Hartmann
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Marcelo Góes (vanquirius) - netmon, crypto, Brazilian translations
</li>
<li>
John N. Laliberte (allanonjl) - Installer team, GLSR, libconf
</li>
<li>
Luis F. Araujo (araujo) - Haskell
</li>
<li>
Zaheer Abbas Merali (zaheerm) - gstreamer
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li>Danny van Dyk (kugelfang) - Release coordinator for the AMD64 project</li>
<li>Lars Weiler (pylon) - PPC release coordinator</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>Xzabite dyndnsupdate: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Xzabite's dyndnsupdate software suffers from multiple vulnerabilities,
    potentially resulting in the remote execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-27.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sun Java: Web Start argument injection vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    Java Web Start JNLP files can be abused to evade sandbox restriction and
    execute arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-28.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>GnuPG: OpenPGP protocol attack</title>
<body>
<p>

    Automated systems using GnuPG may leak plaintext portions of an encrypted
    message.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-29.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mozilla Suite: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    The Mozilla Suite is vulnerable to multiple issues ranging from the remote
    execution of arbitrary code to various issues allowing to trick the user
    into trusting fake web sites or interacting with privileged content.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-30.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mozilla Firefox: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Mozilla Firefox 1.0.2 fixes new security vulnerabilities, including the
    remote execution of arbitrary code through malicious GIF images or
    sidebars.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-31.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mozilla Thunderbird: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Mozilla Thunderbird is vulnerable to multiple issues, including the remote
    execution of arbitrary code through malicious GIF images.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-32.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>IPsec-Tools: racoon Denial of Service</title>
<body>
<p>

    IPsec-Tools' racoon is affected by a remote Denial of Service vulnerability.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200503-33.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 20 March 2005 and 27 March 2005, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>853 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>544 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>19 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8307 currently open bugs: 98 are labeled 'blocker', 222 are labeled 'critical', and 625 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 63
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="swift@gentoo.org" >Sven Vermeulen</mail>, with 20
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=swift@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 20
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="mozilla@gentoo.org" >Mozilla Gentoo Team</mail>, with 18
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mozilla@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 18
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 23
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 23
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="mozilla@gentoo.org" >Mozilla Gentoo Team</mail>, with 20
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;assigned_to=mozilla@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="svyatogor@gentoo.org" >Sergey Kuleshov</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;assigned_to=svyatogor@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="toolchain@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Toolchain Maintainers</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;assigned_to=toolchain@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-03-20&amp;chfieldto=2005-03-27&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter? Send us an <mail 
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and 
help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
