<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050509-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>May 9th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="">Cory Oldford</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 9 May 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 20</version>
<date>2005-05-09</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Recruiting printing experts</title>
<body>

<p>
The printing herd is looking for help with some of their packages, particularly
to close some of the <uri link="http://shorl.com/gunygraprifatra">more than a 
hundred bugs</uri> that have accumulated because the team is severely understaffed. 
People with considerable experience in both Gentoo and applications or utilities 
like CUPS, Ghostscript, <path>gimp-print</path>, <c>xpdf</c>, <c>acroread</c> and 
more, are vigorously encouraged to approach <mail 
link="lanius@gentoo.org">Heinrich Wendel</mail> directly, or contact the <mail 
link="recruiters@gentoo.org">Gentoo developer relations</mail> with a short 
self-introduction including a few words on your experiences in the field.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>News from the Forums</title>
<body>
<p>
Staff shuffle at the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Forums</uri> again. 
Administrator <mail link="ian@gentoo.org">Christian Hartmann</mail> is back in 
play after a timeout of several weeks. During his absence, fellow admin <mail 
link="tomk@forums.gentoo.org">Tom Knight</mail> has updated the forum software 
to the latest phpBB version 2.0.15, and made some useful changes to the search 
function. The collection of these and other announcements can always be found 
in the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-16.html">News &amp; 
Announcements forum</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>"There must be no barriers to freedom of inquiry." -- Danny van Dyk (kugelfang)</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050505_kugelfang.jpg"
short="kugelfang" 
caption="Danny van Dyk aka kugelfang" />

<p>
This weeks featured develeoper is <mail link="kugelfang@gentoo.org">Danny 
van Dyk</mail>, the Operational Lead (with <mail 
link="kingtaco@gentoo.org">Mike Doty</mail>) and Gentoo/AMD64 Release 
Coordinator, as well as a member of the Gentoo Scientific Project. "My 
work as operational lead developer for Gentoo/AMD64 mainly requires
me to be update on the things the other devs do, coordinate their work,
and apart from that I try to fix as many open bugs as possible, which is
how I was recruited onto the team in the first place."
</p>
<p>
Gentoo is Danny's first OSS project, and he takes quite some pride in the 
work he has done for Gentoo Linux on AMD64. He is a student of physics at
the University of Dortmund and spends a lot of his time on Gentoo.
When he isn't busy studying himself he works as a tutor and helps other
students with trivial things such as mathematics, physics and
programming languages, although he is for hire at the moment since his
tutor job has ended.
</p>
<p>
He was appointed as release coordinator for AMD64 quite recently. <mail 
link="jhuebel@gentoo.org">Jason Huebel</mail> had him step in to make the
2005.0 release media (LiveCDs, stages, package-CD). His computers all have 
greek letters as host names to make them more interesting, and his collection
of machine covers most of x86, ppc and amd64. His most important tool seems 
to be a HP LaserJet 4+, while on the software side he shows how open-minded
he can be by using KDE along with Mozilla Thunderbird and XMMS, showing off
the friendly coexistence of things Qt and Gtk.
</p>
<p>
Even more amazingly he plays the flute and loves to cook, especially new
and untested meals that show what real hackers can do in real life.
To any females in the appropriate age range in Witten (where Danny
lives:) He is single, and has an impressive set of skills. Danny's motto
is borrowed from Robert Oppenheimer, and there's more to it than just the 
headline above: <e>"There is no place for dogma in science. The scientist is 
free, and must be free to ask any questions, to doubt any assertion, to seek 
for any evidence, to correct any errors."</e> 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Sudden strictness catching users unaware</b></p>
<p>
<path>FEATURES="strict"</path> was enabled several weeks ago, but the
number of people who've been confused by new error messages and outright
installation errors hasn't declined. Maybe that's because there was no 
"official" announcement of the change? This thread has been made sticky
to allow for quick referral of people with the same errors:
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-325007.html">Portage does more security checks? Digest verification fails</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Next generation</b><path>init</path><b>replacement</b></p>
<p>
Yet another <uri link="http://jw.dyndns.org/initng/">community project</uri> 
originating from the apocryphic sidelines of the greater Gentoo realm has 
attracted not only hundreds of replies to the original thread in the Forums, 
it's already carried on Freshmeat and getting some media coverage. Swedish 
forum user Jimmy Wennlund has devised this "replacement for the old and in 
many ways deprecated sysvinit" that just made it into the official Portage 
tree last weekend:
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-331844.html">Beta test New Init system, realy improved boot time.</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/ebuilds/?initng-0.0.10">Initng in Portage</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Inofficial install media released</b></p>
<p>
Together with <uri link="http://jackass.homelinux.org/">a small team of 
contributors</uri>, Bob Perdaina (a forum regular and author of a popular 
howto on installing Gentoo with an underlying NPTL structure) has released 
a series of bootable CDs containing stage 3 tarballs made to work as if you 
were installing from stage 1. The name of the project takes some getting 
used to, though:
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-334276.html">Jackass! 2005.0 is Released!</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-319349.html">Installing Gentoo 2005.0: Stage 1 NPTL on a Stage 3 Tarball</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>Splitting up dev-perl (phase one of a million)</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="mcummings@gentoo.org">Michael Cummings</mail> brings good
news from the perl camp:
"This weekend I intend to start splitting dev-perl into sub
categories, starting with perl-core. If anyone doesn't think there are
enough packages in the current dev-perl, resync your tree because it's
been years since the last time you did :)

perl-core will contain ebuilds for those modules that are also
distributed with the core installs of perl (though versions and patches
may vary from the version you have installed).

Anyone wishing to provide input on this multi-phased migration can
always post on <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=75435">bug 75435 </uri>"

</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/27699">Splitting
up dev-perl
</uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>Certified Gentoo?</b></p>
<p>
An interested Gentooist who works with IBM hardware asks what can be
done to get Gentoo IBM-certified. Other Gentooists join in with their
questions how to get Gentoo certified for other commercial software.

It seems that IBM will only certify distributions that have a commercial
backend (because of Service Level Agreements etc.), but it is always
good to see people trying to take Gentoo to the next level.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/27626">Certified
Gentoo? </uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Portage as a secondary package manager</b></p>
<p>
Since Portage can do software management quite well, why not use it on
other distros for your own customizations? A similar thought must have 
motivated this GLEP draft that wants to enhance portage to be able to 
install and manage software in arbitrary locations, and also as a 
secondary package manager when <c>rpm</c> just isn't good enough.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/27569">Portage as
a secondary package manager </uri></li>
</ul>
</body></section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Belgium: Gentoo website brought online</title>
<body>
<p>
Last Sunday, Gentoo developer <mail link="sejo@gentoo.org">Jochen 
Maes</mail> has set up a server that hosts <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.be/">Gentoo's regional Belgian web presence</uri>. 
As many of the other country-specific Gentoo community sites, this one also 
has a number of features besides syndicalised content from the official 
Gentoo website, including a user forum, photo gallery and other 
community functions. The site is so new that it doesn't even have a logo
of its own yet, hence a call for contributions to a logo contest held 
until the end of the month. A special section in the forum has been
set aside for this purpose, check the site for instructions.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Canada: Elementary school Gentoo LTSP installation</title>
<body>
<p>
Cory Oldford is the vice-president of <uri link="http://plug.ca">Prairie Linux 
User Group</uri> and manager for a remarkable community project in Winnipeg. His 
group was approached <uri link="20050110-newsletter.xml#doc_chap5">some time ago</uri> 
to switch a lab at a local private elementary school to Gentoo Linux. The lab consisted of 
about 30 workstations ranging from a P75 with 16MB RAM to a handful of PIII 667mhz with 
128MB RAM. The machines were constantly plagued with issues caused by hardware 
failures and outdated operating systems and software. 
</p>
<p>
It was originally thought the PIIIs wouldn't be able to handle the workload, 
and that administering several LTSP servers would be too cumbersome. The 
solution devised by the <uri 
link="http://plug.ca/article.php?story=20050410105433363">HC-Linux team </uri> 
(as in "Holy Cross", the name of the school) was an openMosix-enabled LTSP, 
Gentoo Linux server. After the server's filesystem was built, however, the 
administrator at the school scraped up much more suitable server hardware, an 
AMD Sempron 2500 with 1.2GB of RAM. 
</p>
<p>
openMosix worked great for a time, says Cory, but in the class room environment it 
turned into a liability, because students would insist on powering off the machines. 
Currently openMosix is disabled, but could be fired up anytime simply by starting 
the service. The diskless clients don't share their own load, so they just 
wait for openMosix on the server to farm out processes anyway.
</p>
<p>
<uri link="http://ltsp.org">LTSP</uri> functioned as expected after a few 
network issues were resolved, but the desired desktop environment presented a 
challenge at first: The memory requirements of up to 30 instances of KDE and 
Konqueror caused the server to start swapping under load. With only one slow 
40GB IDE drive, the performance of the server went down dramatically when 30 
students were working in the lab. Switching to <c>icewm</c> and a simplified 
(kludged) ROX-Filer resolved this. The switch to a less voracious desktop 
environment also left enough RAM to precache the major applications and related 
libraries on a RAM disk for a greater performance boost.
</p>
<p>
The HC-Linux PLUGgers get called in for minor issues from time to time, but the 
server has been running reliably for months now. Cory is grateful for the 
support he received from the community: "Thanks to <mail 
link="tantive@gentoo.org">Michael Imhof</mail> and the rest of the cluster team, 
and to all the other Gentoo developers for their hard work."
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/200505009_winnipeg.jpg"
short="PentiumI" 
caption="Gentoo on historic hardware - Pentium 75MHz with 16MB RAM" />
<note>Photo courtesy of Cory Oldford</note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Coyotegulch (2 May 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Last week <mail link="scott.ladd@coyotegulch.com">Scott Robert Ladd</mail>, 
the author of a tool for compiler analysis called <uri 
link="http://www.coyotegulch.com/products/acovea/index.html">Acovea</uri>, 
conducted a <uri link="http://www.coyotegulch.com/reviews/gcc4/index.html">benchmarking 
test</uri> to compare the performance of both compilation and compilate using 
the GNU C compiler (<c>gcc</c>) version 3.4.3, and the new 4.0 that Was 
released just two weeks ago. "No matter which compiler options I choose, 
someone is likely to send me e-mail telling me I got it all wrong," says the 
author of the review, fully aware of the pitfalls of benchmarking, and he also 
refrains from comparing <c>gcc</c> with Intel's or other commercial C 
compilers. The platforms he uses for the benchmark test are an AMD64 Dual 
Opteron and a plain x86 Pentium 4 host -- both running Gentoo Linux, which he's 
unlikely to recompile with 4.0 right away: "Version 4.0.0 is laying a foundation 
for the future, and should be seen as a technological step forward with new 
internal architectures and the addition of Fortran 95. If you compile a great 
deal of C++, you'll want to investigate GCC 4.0," says Scott Ladd. If that's not 
the case, looks like the 3.4 series is still the way to go.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Desktoplinux (8 May 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
The <uri link="http://www.desktoplinux.com/articles/AT2127420238.html">survey 
results</uri> of Desktoplinux' annual reader poll show a remarkable decline
in the number of respondents, an inexplicable disappearance of about two
thirds of the Debian user community, and a comfortable growth of Gentoo
to about twice the market share of 2003, up at 10 percent of all desktop
Linux installations chez Desktoplinux readers. There is, however, room for
belief that there may be a fairly large portion of market reality not covered 
by this particular research.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<e>None this week</e>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Duncan Coutts (dcoutts) - Haskell
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li>
Tobias Scherbaum (dertobi123) - joined the PPC team
</li>
<li>
Bryan Ostergaard (kloeri) - new Alpha architecture co-lead
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>Sylpheed, Sylpheed-claws: Buffer overflow on message display</title>
<body>
<p>

Sylpheed and Sylpheed-claws contain a vulnerability that can be triggered
when displaying messages with specially crafted attachments.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-02.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Dnsmasq: Poisoning and Denial of Service vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

Dnsmasq is vulnerable to DNS cache poisoning attacks and a potential Denial
of Service from the local network.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-03.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>mit-krb5: Multiple buffer overflows in telnet client</title>
<body>
<p>

The mit-krb5 telnet client is vulnerable to two buffer overflows, which
could allow a malicious telnet server operator to execute arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-04.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gaim: Denial of Service issues</title>
<body>
<p>

Gaim contains multiple vulnerabilities that can lead to a Denial of
Service.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-05.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>sharutils: Insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

The unshar utility is vulnerable to symlink attacks, potentially allowing a
local user to overwrite arbitrary files.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200504-06.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 01 May 2005 and 08 May 2005, activity
on the site has resulted in:
</p>
<ul>
<li>833 new bugs during this period</li>
<li>433 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
<li>27 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
</ul>
<p>
Of the 8576 currently open bugs: 95 are labeled 'blocker', 219 are labeled 'critical', and 629 are labeled 'major'.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 25
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 25
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 21
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 19
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="php-bugs@gentoo.org" >PHP Bugs</mail>, with 17
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=php-bugs@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="eradicator@gentoo.org" >Jeremy Huddleston</mail>, with 14
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=eradicator@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 13
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="neysx@gentoo.org" >Xavier Neys</mail>, with 13
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=neysx@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 31
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 16
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 15
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="sci@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Science Related Packages</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;assigned_to=sci@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="release@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Release Team</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;assigned_to=release@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="python@gentoo.org" >Python Gentoo Team</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;assigned_to=python@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="netmon@gentoo.org" >Netmon Herd</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-01&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-08&amp;assigned_to=netmon@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and 
help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
