<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050509-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>May 23th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="conspiracy@gentoo.de">“German Conspiracy”</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="w.haas@xover.htu.tuwien.ac.at">Wernfried Haas</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 23 May 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 21</version>
<date>2005-05-23</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Last week's GWN…</title>
<body>
<p>
…got lost due to the Whitsun holiday and an illness of the GWN Editor <mail
  link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>.  This week's GWN is a kind of
'emergency issue' published by long-time GWN-authors and -contributors.  We are
glad that we could collect enough articles to present you a well-stuffed GWN
that fits for two weeks!
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Foundation's Trustees Election for 2005-2006</title>
<body>
<p>
The first election of the 13 <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/#doc_chap4">Gentoo Foundation's
  Trustees</uri> by the Developers have gone off well!  With the help of <mail
  link="agriffis@gentoo.org">Aron Griffis</mail> <path>votify</path> and
<path>countify</path> scripts, the developers who are active for at least one
year had the possibly to vote their favourite <uri
  link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~slarti/misc/nominees.html">candidates</uri>.
About 45% of the nearly 200 Foundation members took the chance for voting.  The
mathematical election method the Gentoo Foundation uses is called the <uri
  link="http://electionmethods.org/CondorcetEx.htm">Condorcet Voting</uri>.
</p>
<p>
The developers didn't had to wait long for the <uri
  link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.nfp/252">official trustees
  2005 election result</uri> published by the election officals Aron Griffis,
Mike Frysinger and Tom Martin:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><mail link="g2boojum@gentoo.org">Grant Goodyear</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="cshields@gentoo.org">Corey Shields</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="spyderous@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholz</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="ramereth@gentoo.org">Lance Albertson</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="dmwaters@gentoo.org">Deedra M. Waters</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="carpaski@gentoo.org">Nicholas Jones</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="dostrow@gentoo.org">Daniel Ostrow</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="jhuebel@gentoo.org">Jason Huebel</mail></li>
  <li><mail link="kumba@gentoo.org">Joshua Kinard</mail></li>
</ul>
<p>
With the results given, Gentoo devoloper Ciaran McCreesh created nice <uri
  link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~ciaranm/docs/trustees-2005-vote-distribution.txt">popularity
  charts</uri> for all nominees.
</p>
<p>
<e>Congratulations to the newly-elected Trustees!</e>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New mailing list: gentoo-perl</title>
<body>
<p>
A new mailing list has been set up: <path>gentoo-perl@gentoo.org</path>, for
discussing perl in gentoo, enhancments, g-cpan, etc.
</p>
<p>
How to subscribe and other mailing-lists information are available at <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml" />.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>User stories</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo at Open Source Development Labs (OSDL)</title>
<body>
<p>
The GWN-team received a story from Leann Ogasawara and other members of the <uri
  link="http://www.osdl.org/">Open Source Development Labs (OSDL)</uri>, of how
Gentoo is used at the laboratory.  We would like to present you the full story
in this week's GWN:
</p>
<p>
“OSDL is utilizing Gentoo for various projects here at the lab.  One such
project is the BRT (Binary Regression Testing) project.  The purpose of the BRT
project is to execute suites of regression tests focused towards specific
application binaries on a specific set of software packages.  The goal is to
make it easier for application developers to run regression tests on the latest
open source software stack and to capture the results. The need to build a
customizable set of software packages from the bottom up is what initially drew
our interest towards Gentoo, and more specifically, the Portage package
management tool.  We needed a tool that would not only automate a package's
build and installation process, but also be in sync with the latest package
release as well as older versions.  The tool also needed to be able to track
build dependencies for a package and handle their installations smoothly.  The
only additional functionality we would maybe like to see in Portage is the
ability to automatically remove a package's build dependencies but keep the run
time dependencies installed (an ebuild DEPENDS vs RDEPENDS thing).  That way
our test system would only have the absolute necessary set of packages that we
want installed and the extraneous packages wouldn't have a chance to possibly
interfere with our tests we want to run.  Other than that, we've been very
pleased with the Portage tool and Gentoo in general.  Since we first started
playing with Gentoo and researching what it could provide for us, we've been
using it on a daily basis and it has played an integral role in the development
of our project.  Other developers at OSDL have also started using Gentoo in
their day to day tasks and often prefer to use it as their test platform of
choice.”
</p>
<p>
Thanks for this nice story!
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>"An eye for an eye will make the whole world blind" (Ghandi)</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050523_slarti.jpg"
short="slarti" 
caption="Tom Martin aka slarti" />

<p>
This week's dev-of-the week is Tom Martin, better known as Slarti. He is an
AMD64 keyworder, maintainer of some net-mail packages, part of the shell-tools
herd and recruiter. His next "big thing" will be testing Mono on AMD64 with the
help of the Mono maintainer Peter "latexer" Johanson. As with many Gentoo devs,
Gentoo is his first OSS project and also the software project he's most proud of
(to be more precise, his work on mailer-config and the <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/utf-8.xml">UTF-8 guide</uri>). He also
enjoys recruiting new developers and seeing that they do “the Right Thing”™.
</p>
<p>
Although he appears to be more, he is still at school in Guernsey, Channel
Islands, where he'll soon have his final GCSE exams. Guernsey is a small island
with about 65000 permanent residents and about 24 square miles large.
</p>
<p>
His favourite programs are a wild mix: “Zsh is about the coolest thing I've ever
seen. I think imagemagick, LaTeX, rubber, mpd and t-prot are all very useful
programs, too.” Those usually run within Openbox, accompanied by mutt, vim,
irssi and their helper programs. Of course, they all run on a self-built AMD64
box, accompanied by a newly bought Sun Ultra 2. For programming usually Ruby is
(ab-)used (since it has a “great concept of OOP”), running within rxvt-unicode.
</p>
<p>
When not glued to a computer he enjoys playing rugby and guitar, but
also listening to diverse kinds of music.  If you wish to find even more
information, check <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~slarti/">slarti's developer
  webspace</uri>.
</p>
<p>
“‘Gentoo is all about choice!’<br />
Haha.  No, really, I think Gentoo is <e>not</e> all about choice, it's all
about flexibility. You can make it work for you.”
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Gentoo mentioned in books</b></p>
<p>
Forums user <uri
  link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=40001">radulucian</uri>
reported that he found Gentoo mentioned in about 27 published books and posted
what one of them had to say about Gentoo. The review in "Linux Transfer for
Windows Power Users: Getting Started with Linux for the Desktop" seems to be
quite fair, pointing out the big community behind Gentoo, but that it might not
be the best choice for new Linux users. Gentoo is among the six most important
distributions of the author.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-338900.html">Gentoo mentioned in various books, 27 found so far</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Gentoo Foundation Website Redesign Contest</b></p>
<p>
Forums Moderator <uri
  link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=16020">M Curtis
  Napier (curtis119)</uri> posted some current screenshots from his work on the
Website Redesign.  If you want to catch a glimpse at how the Gentoo-Website will
look like in the future, you should read this posting.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-p-2421342.html#2421342">Gentoo Foundation Website Redesign Contest -- the vote</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>elibtoolize failures</b></p>
<p>
If an emerge fails on you with "Portage patch failed to apply (ltmain.sh
version 1.3.4)!" or similar, you might have hit a known bug. Please
don't panic, it'll be fixed soon, as <mail link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike
Frysinger</mail> tells us.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/27955">elibtoolize failures</uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>bugs.gentoo.org upgraded</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="jforman@gentoo.org">Jeffrey Forman</mail> of Gentoo's infrastructure
team upgraded our bugzilla on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/" />.  The new
features are listed in his e-mail.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/28044">UPGRADE complete bugs.gentoo.org</uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>New category proposal</b></p>
<p>
What started as a proposal for a "cellphone" category for all
applications that help with mobile phones drifted away into a discussion
wether portage should support multiple categories per ebuild.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/27893">New category proposal </uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>New profuse version available</b></p>
<p>
Our <path>libconf</path> and <path>profuse</path> hacker <mail link="dams@gentoo.org">Damien
Krotkine</mail> has released a new version of <path>profuse</path>, a Use-flag editor
and possible <path>ufed</path> replacement.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/27972">New profuse version available </uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>death to underquoted M4 definitions</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="ka0ttic@gentoo.org">Aaron Walker</mail> writes:
“I'd like to propose a new function for <path>eutils.eclass</path> that fixes m4
files so that aclocal doesn't produce those annoying underquoted definition
warnings when invoked.”<br />
That should reduce the amount of (harmless) warnings which happen quite a lot.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/28113">death to underquoted M4 definitions</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Austria: Grazer Linuxtage was a success</title>
<body>
<p>
Thanks to the organisation team of the <uri link="http://linuxtage.at/">Grazer
  Linuxtage</uri> the event at Saturday 14th May was a success.  It was not only
a chance to tell people about Gentoo and give away flyers and LiveCDs, but also
to get to know each other.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050523_graz.jpg"
  short="Grazer Linuxtage"
  caption="Left: Gentoo folks, right: Gentoo, Debian and Grml teams" />
<p>
In the left picture some of the Gentoo folks who mostly had not ever seen each
other in real life are shown: Gregor Perner, forums admin Wernfried Haas (amne),
Gregor's brother Philip, Gentoo developer Roger Miliker (roger55), forums user
nephros and Markus Lang.  In the right picture you see the Gentoo team meet
other distributions teams: <uri link="http://www.debian.org/">Debian</uri> and
<uri link="http://www.grml.org/">grml</uri>. Once the Linuxtag was over most of
them also joined a social event which was a nice completion of the day.
</p>
<note>Pictures taken from the <uri
    link="http://dufo.tugraz.at/glt05/graz/index.html">Grazer Linuxtage
    gallery</uri>.</note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>MyOSS (May 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Ow Mun Heng from Kuala Lumpur has published the first issue of his brand new
<uri
  link="http://mag.my-opensource.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=22&amp;Itemid=49">"Malaysian
  OSS Magazine"</uri>, a monthly publication. The inaugural number contains an
article on <path>swsuspend2</path>, the power management application for
notebook Linux users, based on the editor's distribution of choice, Gentoo
Linux.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Emediawire (11 May 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
<uri link="20050221-newsletter.xml#doc_chap2">Remember the Kuro-Box</uri> we
covered in our Future zone a few months ago? Well, a small company based in
Illinois called <uri link="http://www.sumocomputer.com/">Sumo Computer</uri>
seems to have liked the idea so much they transformed it into something
marketable: A press release issued last week announces a Kuro-Box equipped with
an extra 250GB Maxtor disk and Gentoo Linux pre-installed, now shipping to
customers interested in a "more user friendly, ready to go system" that will set
them back 549 USD. Sumo Computer's Melody Bornheimer says they chose Gentoo
Linux because of “its ease of administration, and over 9,000 ported open-source
applications.”
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Distrowatch (9 May 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Everybody's favorite website for Linux distribution news and information,
Ladislav Bodnar's <uri link="http://distrowatch.com">Distrowatch</uri>, also
carries a highly informative newsletter published each week on the same day as
the GWN. Last Monday, the Distrowatch newsletter opened with a <uri
  link="http://distrowatch.com/weekly.php?issue=20050509#1">mini-review of
  Gentoo Linx 2005.0</uri>, written by Robert Storey and recounting his
experiences during a first-time Gentoo Linux installation. “Not for aunt Tilly,”
but otherwise quite positive…
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><e>John Davis (zhen)</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><e>Benjamin Smee (strerror) (net-mail)</e></li>
  <li><e>Daniel Gryniewicz (dang) (amd64)</e></li>
  <li><e>René Nussbaumer (Killerfox) (hppa)</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
  <li><e>Brian Jackson (iggy) - left the devrel team</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>gzip: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    gzip contains multiple vulnerabilities potentially allowing an attacker to
    execute arbitrary commands.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-05.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>TCPDump: Decoding routines Denial of Service vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    A flaw in the decoding of network packets renders TCPDump vulnerable to a
    remote Denial of Service attack.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-06.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>libTIFF: Buffer overflow</title>
<body>
<p>

    The libTIFF library is vulnerable to a buffer overflow, potentially
    resulting in the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-07.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>HT Editor: Multiple buffer overflows</title>
<body>
<p>

    Two vulnerabilities have been discovered in HT Editor, potentially leading
    to the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-08.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gaim: Denial of Service and buffer overflow vulnerabilties</title>
<body>
<p>

    Gaim contains two vulnerabilities, potentially resulting in the execution
    of arbitrary code or Denial of Service.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-09.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>phpBB: Cross-Site Scripting Vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    phpBB is vulnerable to a cross-site scripting attack that could allow
    arbitrary scripting code execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-10.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mozilla Suite, Mozilla Firefox: Remote compromise</title>
<body>
<p>

    Several vulnerabilities in the Mozilla Suite and Firefox allow an attacker
    to conduct cross-site scripting attacks or to execute arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-11.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PostgreSQL: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    PostgreSQL is vulnerable to Denial of Service attacks and possibly allows
    unprivileged users to gain administrator rights.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-12.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>FreeRADIUS: SQL injection and Denial of Service vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    The FreeRADIUS server is vulnerable to an SQL injection attack and a buffer
    overflow, possibly resulting in disclosure and modification of data and
    Denial of Service.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-13.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Cheetah: Untrusted module search path</title>
<body>
<p>

    Cheetah contains a vulnerability in the module importing code that can
    allow a local user to gain escalated privileges.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-14.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gdb: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Multiple vulnerabilities have been discovered in the GNU debugger,
    potentially allowing the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-15.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>ImageMagick, GraphicsMagick: Denial of Service vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    ImageMagick and GraphicsMagick utilities can be abused to perform a Denial
    of Service attack.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-16.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
    <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri
       link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the
     development team.  Between 08 May 2005 and 22 May 2005, activity on the
     site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
       <li>1650 new bugs during this period</li>
       <li>987 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
       <li>48 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8469 currently open bugs: 89 are labeled 'blocker', 221 are labeled 'critical', and 621 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 65
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 43
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 38
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 35
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 33
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 33
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="perl@gentoo.org" >Perl Devs @ Gentoo</mail>, with 31
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=perl@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="jforman@gentoo.org" >Jeffrey Forman</mail>, with 28
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=jforman@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 37
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 27
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kernel@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Kernel Bug Wranglers and Kernel Maintainers</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;assigned_to=kernel@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="toolchain@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Toolchain Maintainers</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;assigned_to=toolchain@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="svyatogor@gentoo.org" >Sergey Kuleshov</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;assigned_to=svyatogor@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="graphics@gentoo.org" >media-gfx herd</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_stamp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;assigned_to=graphics@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-08&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-22&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and
help make the GWN better.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
  link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
