<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050530-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>May 30th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="expose@luftgetrock.net">Daniel Herzog</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dams@gentoo.org">Damien Krotkine</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 30 May 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 22</version>
<date>2005-05-30</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Hardware donation at OSU</title>
<body>
<p>
Thanks to Gentoo AMD64 <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/base/amd64/tests/index.xml?part=1&amp;chap=1">archtester</uri> 
Chris Parrot, a developer at <uri link="http://www.amd.com">AMD</uri>'s Austin 
plant, the Open Source Laboratory of Oregon State University received a 
surprise package this month. What was originally announced as a forthcoming 
donation of one disused AMD64 architecture PC turned out to be three dual-CPU 
motherboards complete with six CPUs and 3GB worth of registered DDR RAM. 
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050530_amd64.jpg"
	short="mobos" 
	caption="Fresh out of the box: donated AMD64 motherboards" />
<p>
One machine goes to the Gentoo release engineering team and will be used for 
the production of future releases, including LiveCDs, stages and more. The 
other two are to be used as a general development platform for the Gentoo/AMD64 
team and will be made accessible to both Gentoo and outside developers upon 
request. Thanks a lot to Chris Parrott and AMD for this generous donation!</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation status update</title>
<body>
<p>
A fun game to play for aspiring Gentoo documentation authors: If you'd like to 
try out your abilities in writing good clean XML code for the Gentoo 
documentation, why not go over the "magnificently ugly" <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/doc/fix-me.xml.txt?passthru=1">disfigured 
document</uri> prepared by the documentation team as part of a quiz? If you can 
fix that one, continue reading the <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-policy.xml">updated policy</uri> 
for becoming a member of the documentation task force, and help them do some 
more of the things they do: Some of last month's highlights of which include 
the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/kde-config.xml">KDE configuration 
guide</uri> that is catching up with several applications in the split ebuilds of 
KDE above 3.4, updates to the <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoolkit.xml">Gentoolkit</uri> and <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-x86.xml?part=2&amp;chap=1">Portage 
introduction</uri> guides that have been made over to reflect changes and 
additions, and many more new bits and pieces making the Gentoo documentation 
even better than it is. See the complete status update for the past month at 
the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/status/status_20050529.xml">documentation 
status page</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>"Gentoo -- Damien Krotkine</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050530_dams.jpg"
short="dams" 
caption="Damien Krotkine aka dams" />

<p>
<mail link="dams@gentoo.org">Damien Krotkine</mail> or dams is officially 
one of the PPC monkeys, maintaining a few ebuilds of programs he uses, but 
he actually spends most of his Gentoo-time on coding configuration tools 
and related stuff.  He used to be the lead of the - currently dormant - Gentoo 
Desktop Research Project. Outside of Gentoo he has designed the official logo 
of the <uri  link="http://plf.zarb.org/">PLF</uri> (Penguin Liberation Front) 
and has done some perl hacking in his time, including crazy things like trying 
to use Mozilla's internal objects from perl with perl-XPCOM. Since he is a 
rather quiet and modest character, he isn't especially proud of his work, but the 
combination of Perl and gtk in his hands can do some really neat tricks. 
</p>
<p>
He went to school in different places like Frankfurt and Paris, even studied
Computer Science, although his opinion of school seems rather low. His
real life work is not as much about Gentoo as one could wish for, but
developing software based on Mozilla and an OSS search engine at a
French company is quite acceptable as a line of work. 
</p>
<p>
He recently reduced the number of computers at home, but it remains an 
impressive collection, including an Athlon, a PegasosPPC and an iBook. 
His predilection for <c>perl</c> and <c>emacs</c> makes him lose most flame war battles, 
but he's good at avoiding those, too. Other applications he likes are 
<c>screen</c>, <c>zsh</c> and Firefox which are almost always within reach on one or all
of his computers. <c>icewm</c> and <c>enlightenment</c> are his window managers of choice, 
his mail client is currently Thunderbird instead of <c>gnus</c> - dams enjoys
using the right tool for the right job.
</p>
<p>
Since he is a really cool cat, he does snowboarding, rollerskating and
climbing. He used to be "famous TM of the Sporks Of Chaos official team,
hey that's actually something I'm proud of", and when he doesn't work or
code, he tries to be at OSS events. Living in Paris (which makes
him very French), he enjoys reinforcing stereotypes by being a slick
seductive Frenchman - but hasn't met the right girl to get married yet. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>keeping ebuilds fresh</b></p>
<p>
As time goes by some ebuilds are not maintained as well as one could
wish. In this thread many ideas were thrown around how to give users the
possibility to help with testing and maintaining new versions of
programs in the portage tree.

</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/28240">keeping
ebuilds fresh </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>Bashrc mini HOWTO</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="chriswhite@gentoo.org">Chris White</mail> has written a nice
mini-howto on the use of a bashrc file with portage - if you don't know
what this means, this howto might not yet be for you, but in short it
shows the awesome power of the newest portage cvs versions.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/28299">Bashrc
mini HOWTO </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>baselayout request for testers</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike Frysinger</mail> asks for some
testing on the new baselayout 1.11.12-r2, a new and hopefully much
better version of the baselayout scipts. Since many things have changed
and some things have been modularized there might be some breakage - so
if you don't mind potentially wrecking your system and want to help,
read Mike's announcement and have fun with it.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/28317">baselayout
request for testers </uri></li>
</ul>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Canada: Ottawa Linux Symposium</title>
<body>
<p>
The <uri link="http://www.linuxsymposium.org">Ottawa Linux Symposium</uri> 
(OLS) will be held from 20 to 23 July 2005. Gentoo PPC64 developer <mail 
link="omkhar@gentoo.org">Omkhar Arasaratnam</mail> is going, if you would 
like to join a meet-up of Gentoo users and developers in Ottawa on this
occasion, please contact him directly.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Japan: Open Source Party with GentooJP</title>
<body>
<p>
About 50 Japanese Gentoo developers and power users will meet on 3 June at
an Open Source Party marking the occasion of the Linuxworld in Tokyo. Starting
at 19:00 hours, it will be held at the Ginza franchise of a T.G.I. Friday's. <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.gr.jp">GentooJP</uri> founder Masatomo Nakano, on a 
visit from London, is said to attend the meeting, too. No need to report back 
to the GentooJP mailing list to announce your intentions to come, simply sign  
up in advance at the <uri 
link="http://utage.org/enkai/menu.cgi?ENKAI_CODE=osp2005">reservation page</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>LinuxUser (May/June 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
The German magazine LinuxUser recently published a "Gentoo-Mini-Series".
The first part was about the proper installation of a Gentoo system:
"Gentoo Linux provides a made-to-measure product: The clever
distribution can be perfectly customized to the user's requirements."
Within the second and last part, published in their current issue, the
system maintenance using Portage is concerned. An English version is 
expected to be released in the UK/US-edition of the LinuxMagazine in 
about two months. As a first success of the Gentoo articles published 
by LinuxUser, its editor in chief got infected with the "Gentoo virus" 
and could no longer resist the sweet temptation: He installed Gentoo 
Linux himself.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Triangle (20 May 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
In an article titled <uri link="http://www.thetriangle.org/media/paper689/news/2005/05/20/SciTech/Debate.Pits.Open.Source.Linux.Against.Microsoft-953266.shtml?page=1">Debate pits open source Linux against Microsoft</uri>, the student 
newspaper of Drexel university, reports from an event organized by Drexel's 
<uri link="http://society.cs.drexel.edu/">Math and Computer Science Society</uri>. 
Towards the end of a thorough account of the debate between a Microsoft academic 
relations manager and a member of the local Linux user group. Gentoo is mentioned 
as an example for 64-bit computing as it should be, with not just the kernel, but 
also applications compiled for this architecture.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
  <title>Coding Session</title>
  <section>
    <title>Preface</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        A short presentation of dams' configuration tools: (code indentation might
        be broken. In case of questions ask <mail
          link="dams@gentoo.org">dams</mail>)
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Libconf</title>
    <body>
      <note>
        website: <uri link="http://libconf.net">http://libconf.net</uri><br />
        what is it: it allows you to read/write easily config tools
      </note>
      <p>OK let's say you want to edit your gdm configuration, and set the
        autologin user. Let's see if libconf provides something for that.
        Launch simply on a console:</p>
      <pre caption="launch libconf">
libconf
      </pre>
      <figure link="/images/gwn/sc_libconf1.png"
        short="sc_libconf1"
        caption="libconf command line" />
      <p>Now let's call the built-in help:</p>
      <pre caption="libconf help">
help
      </pre>
      <p>as suggested, you'll see the 'list_templates' command. Type</p>
      <pre caption="list_templates">
list_templates
      </pre>
      <figure link="/images/gwn/sc_libconf2.png"
        short="sc_libconf2"
        caption="list of available high level templates" />
      <p>Generic/Shell is the one the most used, but there are some others. As
        you can see, there is a 'X/Gdm' template. Now let's see what options
        it offers:</p>
      <pre caption="options for X/Gdm">
list_template_options X/Gdm
      </pre>
      <figure link="/images/gwn/sc_libconf3.png"
        short="sc_libconf3"
        caption="X/Gdm options" />
      <p>You can see it asks you to launch <c>man Libconf::Glueconf::X::Gdm</c>. If
        you do that it'll tell you there is no such documentation, that because
        it's not yet written. Too bad, huh? Nevermind, you'll see it's easy
        enough.</p>
      <p>Now let's do a bit perl:</p>
      <pre caption="gdm_autologin.pl">
#!/usr/bin/perl
# first of all, include the libconf template module
use Libconf::Glueconf::X::Gdm;
# then use the template
my $gdm_conf = Libconf::Glueconf::X::Gdm->new({ filename =>
'/etc/X11/gdm/gdm.conf' });
# now we would like to see what the structure looks like
use Data::Dumper;
print Dumper($gdm_conf) . "\n";
# that will print the content of the structure
      </pre>
      <p>write this in a file called <path>gdm_autologin.pl</path>, set it
        executable and launched it:</p>
      <pre caption="launch gdm_autologin.pl">
./gdm_autologin.pl
      </pre>
      <figure link="/images/gwn/sc_libconf4.png"
        short="sc_libconf4"
        caption="dumped structure with gdm_autologin.pl" />
      <p>It's easy to understand how it is structured. Now what we want, is take
        a username in argument, and set it to the autologin. That is done
        with:</p>
      <pre caption="take username in argument and set it to the
        autologin">
$gdm_con->{daemon}{AutomaticLogin} = $user;
      </pre>
      <p>Now here is the complete script:</p>
      <pre caption="complete script for autologin">
#!/usr/bin/perl
# first of all, include the libconf template module
use Libconf::Glueconf::X::Gdm;
# get the first argument
my $user = $ARGV[0] or die 'please give me one parameter';
# use the template
my $gdm_conf = Libconf::Glueconf::X::Gdm->new({ filename =>
'/etc/X11/gdm/gdm.conf' });
# change the autologin field
$gdm_conf->{daemon}{AutomaticLogin} = $user;
# then write the structure back to the file
$gdm_conf->write_conf();
      </pre>
      <p>And it'll do the job. You can see that libconf has indented the file,
        which is easier to read. But if you don't want that, simply add the
        following line before writing the file:</p>
      <pre caption="don't let libconf intend the file">
$Libconf::Templates::Indentspaces = '';
      </pre>
      <note>
        more doc (sorry it's not complete): http://libconf.net/documentation/html/Libconf.html
      </note>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Gtk2Fu</title>
    <body>
      <note>
        website: <uri link="http://libconf.net/gtk2-fu/">http://libconf.net/gtk2-fu/</uri><br />
        what is it: it's a layer on top of perl-gtk2, that make it simplier and
        better.
      </note>
      <p>gtk2fu is actually simple: it provides more power and easiness. There
        is also <uri
          link="http://search.cpan.org/~dams/Gtk2Fu-0.07/Gtk2Fu.pm">full
          documentation</uri> available.</p>
      <p>Now, if you have read the documentation, you should be able to create
        some simple stuff. Here is a small application that is fully
        functional, and display a GUI to edit the Automatic Login facility of
        gdm, based of what we previously did with libconf:</p>
      <pre caption="GUI for Automatic Login facility of gdm based on
        libconf">
#!/usr/bin/perl

# first of all, include the libconf template module
use Libconf::Glueconf::X::Gdm;
my $gdm_conf = Libconf::Glueconf::X::Gdm-&gt;new({ filename =&gt;
'/etc/X11/gdm/gdm.conf' });
$Libconf::Templates::Indentspaces = '';

# include Gtk2Fu
use Gtk2Fu qw(:all);
# initialize Gtk2;
Gtk2-&gt;init;

# create the window
my $main_window = create_window();
my $entry;
# create the menubar
my ($menubar, $item_factory) = $main_window-&gt;create_full_menubar(
   [
     [ '/_File', undef, undef , 0, '&lt;Branch&gt;' ],
     [ '/File/_Save', '&lt;control&gt;S', sub { $gdm_conf-&gt;write_conf();
Gtk2-&gt;main_quit }, 0, '&lt;StockItem&gt;', 'gtk-save' ],
     [ '/File/_Quit', '&lt;control&gt;Q', sub { Gtk2-&gt;main_quit }, 0,
'&lt;StockItem&gt;', 'gtk-quit' ],
   ]
   );
# create the widgets, handlers, and actions
$main_window-&gt;signal_connect_(destroy =&gt; sub { Gtk2-&gt;main_quit } )
  -&gt;add_(Gtk2::VBox-&gt;new(0,0)
         -&gt;gtkpack_(0, $menubar,
                    1, Gtk2::VBox-&gt;new(0, 0)
                       -&gt;gtkpack_(1, Gtk2::HBox-&gt;new(0, 0)
                                     -&gt;gtkpack_(0, 'Gdm AutomaticLogin',
                                                1, $entry =
Gtk2::Entry-&gt;new()

- -&gt;set_text_($gdm_conf-&gt;{daemon}{AutomaticLogin})

- -&gt;signal_connect_(changed =&gt; sub {

$gdm_conf-&gt;{daemon}{AutomaticLogin} = $entry-&gt;get_text();
                                                                     } )
                                               )
                                  )
                      -&gt;set_border_width_(5),
                    0, Gtk2::HSeparator-&gt;new(),
                    0, Gtk2::HButtonBox-&gt;new()
                       -&gt;set_spacing_default_(10)
                       -&gt;set_layout_('end')

- -&gt;gtkpack(Gtk2::Button-&gt;new_from_stock('gtk-cancel')
                                 -&gt;set_border_width_(5)
                                 -&gt;signal_connect_(clicked =&gt; sub {
Gtk2-&gt;main_quit; }),
                                 Gtk2::Button-&gt;new_from_stock('gtk-ok')
                                 -&gt;set_border_width_(5)
                                 -&gt;signal_connect_(clicked =&gt; sub {
$gdm_conf-&gt;write_conf(); Gtk2-&gt;main_quit; })
                                )
                   )
        )
  -&gt;show_all();
Gtk2-&gt;main;
      </pre>
      <p>Save this in a <path>test.pl</path>, set it executable, and launch it,
        it'll display something like:</p>
      <figure link="/images/gwn/gtk2fu_gwn.png"
        short="test.pl"
        caption="gtk2fu autologin test-window" />
      <p>The application is functional, if you run it as root and change the
        content of the entry and save, it'll work. I use the similar approach
        with perl-ncurses to build text mode GUIs.</p>
      <p>That's it for today, this is just a presentation of what is possible
        with libconf+gtk2fu+ncurses. I hope it gives some of you some
        ideas/directions to look into. And if you are willing to join the
        configuration tool deployment force, contact me.</p>
  </body>
  </section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li>Mike Doty (kingtaco) - AMD64 strategic lead (replacing Jason Huebel)</li>
<li>Simon Stelling (blubb) - AMD64 operational co-lead (with Danny van Dyk)</li>
<li>David Holm (dholm) - PPC strategic lead</li>
<li>Luca Barbato (lu_zero) - PPC operational lead</li>
<li>Lars Weiler (pylon) - PPC release engineering (formerly assigned to the post of tactical lead)</li>
<li>Markus Rothe (corsair) - PPC64 Security</li>
<li>Daniel Ostrow (dostrow) - PPC profile maintainer</li>
<li>Joseph Jezak (josejx) - PPC documentation lead</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>Qpopper: Multiple Vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

Qpopper contains two vulnerabilities allowing an attacker to overwrite
arbitrary files and create files with insecure permissions.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-17.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Net-SNMP: fixproc insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

Net-SNMP creates temporary files in an insecure manner, possibly allowing
the execution of arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-18.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gxine: Format string vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

A format string vulnerability in gxine could allow a remote attacker to
execute arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-19.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mailutils: Multiple vulnerabilities in imap4d and mail</title>
<body>
<p>

The imap4d server and the mail utility from GNU Mailutils contain multiple
vulnerabilities, potentially allowing a remote attacker to execute
arbitrary code with root privileges.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200505-20.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 22 May 2005 and 29 May 2005, activity
on the site has resulted in:
</p>
<ul>
	<li>835 new bugs during this period</li>
	<li>474 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	<li>35 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
</ul>
<p>
Of the 8480 currently open bugs: 85 are labeled 'blocker', 217 are labeled 'critical', and 615 are labeled 'major'.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 29
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 28
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 24
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 21
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 19
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 18
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 17
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 15
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 16
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 15
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 13
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="mobile@gentoo.org" >Mobile Herd</mail>, with 12
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;assigned_to=mobile@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 12
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="net-p2p@gentoo.org" >Gentoo net-p2p team</mail>, with 10
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;assigned_to=net-p2p@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="hardened@gentoo.org" >The Gentoo Linux Hardened Team</mail>, with 10
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;assigned_to=hardened@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 10
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-05-22&amp;chfieldto=2005-05-29&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
  link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
