<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050718-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>July 18th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="dsd@gentoo.org">Daniel Drake</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="plasmaroo@gentoo.org">Tim Yamin</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 18 July 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 28</version>
<date>2005-07-18</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Discontinuing Gentoo-2.4-sources</title>
<body>
<p>
  The Gentoo kernel maintainers are considering to discontinue the
  gentoo-sources-2.4 kernel series.
</p>
<p>
  <c>gentoo-sources-2.4</c> is a kernel based on the older 2.4 series kernel
  which is no longer under active development. x86 is the only supported
  architecture, and several feature-style patches are included.
</p>
<p>
  Since January, <c>gentoo-sources-2.6</c> has become the default kernel, and
  full migration documentation has been produced. Linux 2.6 is under active
  development and includes many of the feature patches which were included in
  <c>gentoo-sources-2.4</c>.
</p>
<p>
  This only concerns the removal of <c>gentoo-sources-2.4</c>, a 'clean' Linux
  2.4 kernel will still be provided through <c>vanilla-sources</c>.
  <c>gentoo-sources-2.6</c> will also continue as normal.
</p>
<p>
  If you have input on this subject, please mail <mail
    link="kernel@gentoo.org">kernel@gentoo.org</mail> with your opinion. We're
  especially interested to hear from current gentoo-sources-2.4 users. Do you
  depend on gentoo-sources-2.4 specifically, or are you able to migrate to
  vanilla-sources-2.4 with minimal hassle? We would especially like to know if
  there is anything preventing you from upgrading to gentoo-sources-2.6. Your
  input is appreciated!
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Hardware Donations</title>
<body>
<p>
  The last weeks have brought two hardware donations to Gentoo.  First is a SUN
  E250 from the Loyola University of Chicago and Mike Doty (kingtaco). It's a
  dual-processor 400Mhz UltraSparc2 box with 2GB RAM and 2x36GB disks, available
  for Gentoo Development from now on.
</p>
<p>
  The second donation received is a Hewlett Packard management processor which
  has allowed remote testing and development of LiveCDs, which has not happened
  until now due to the rarity and lack of physical access to the hardware. In
  addition, HP has included a 73Gb 15,000rpm U320 SCSI drive with this donation,
  giving developers much needed space for testing applications in the Portage
  tree.
</p>
<p>
  Additional thanks are directed to the Open Source Laboratory, at the
  University of Oregon (OSUOSL) - where Corey Shields and Michael Marineau
  provided invaluable assistance installing the newly donated hardware. Lance
  Albertson is also kindly acknowledged for allowing the use of other Gentoo
  infrastructure to access the serial consoles on the IA64 system.
</p>
<p>
  These machines are a welcome addition to the existing <uri
    link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/dev-machines.xml">development
    machines</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>First IA64 LiveCD finished</title>
<body>
<p>
  Thanks to very generous hardware donations from Hewlett Packard, the
  Gentoo/IA64 team has finally been able to build a working LiveCD for systems
  based on the Itanium (IA64) architecture. The new LiveCD will allow users to
  quickly and painlessly deploy Gentoo on an IA64 platform, where previously
  another distribution was required to jumpstart the bootstrap process for a
  Gentoo installation. The CD is planned to be released as part of Gentoo
  2005.1, and anyone who is interested in helping test the product should
  contact the IA64-Developer <mail link="plasmaroo@gentoo.org">Tim Yamin</mail>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bugzilla Upgrade</title>
<body>
<p>
  Shortly before the release of this GWN, infrastructure-developer <mail
    link="jforman@gentoo.org">Jeffrey Forman</mail> upgraded <uri
    link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/">Gentoo's Bugzilla</uri> from version 2.18.1
  to 2.18.3.  This update gives beside some security bugs an end to the
  duplicate-bugs-fiasco which was introduced in an earlier update.  Furthermore
  there is a new autolink feature: just like being able to cite "bug #XXXX" and
  a link is created, now "glsa #XXXX-Y" will be active so that our security
  folks can more easily reference GLSA's.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>“For the first impression there is no second chance” — Sven Wegener (swegener)</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050718_swegener.jpg"
short="swegener" 
caption="Sven Wegener aka swegener" />
<p>
  This weeks victim is <mail link="swegener@gentoo.org">Sven Wegener</mail>, one
  of the German devs. He's living near Hamelin, the city of the Pied Piper of
  Hamelin saga.
</p>
<p>
  Most people might know him from his QA efforts (he was promoted to QA lead
  recently), but he also maintains the net-irc, net-news and shell-tools herds.
  In general he does bugfixing, package maintenance and looks out for tree
  breakage.  One of his newest toys is ‘autorepoman’, an automated checker that
  sends mails whenever someones commit causes a problem. Like many other devs he
  never got to work on other OSS projects before being absorbed into the Gentoo
  collective.
</p>
<p>
  He used to have a day job as a system administrator, but since that contract
  expired he's looking for new sources of income. About his education he says “I
  studied at the University of Cooperative Education in Hamelin and graduated as
  business data processing specialist. After a law change I was able to
  post-graduate as Bachelor of Science”, noting that it's quite difficult to
  translate these titles from German.
</p>
<p>
  Right now Sven mostly uses his AthlonXP workstation and several computers in
  the basement (nothing fancy, all x86) for development. He adds: “I use
  gnome-light for my daily work, but occasionally switch to plain console.  Mail
  is done via a mixture of mutt, pine and evolution, all connected to my IMAP
  server. My workstation is normally left running all time, but I count firefox
  and several terminals, to access my servers and other development computers,
  to the apps I normally start after login. irssi, centericq, mutt and pine are
  permanently running on a server outside of my house.” Speaking of outside:
  Whenever he finds some spare time he enjoys bowling.
</p>
<p>
  Quote: “Gentoo makes easy things difficult, impossible things easy, but it also
  gives you enough rope to hang yourself.”
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>Another Spam victim</b></p>
<p>
After different kinds of spam in the last week this week saw some really weird
spam with a win32 executable as attachment. Even mailinglists seem to be an
acceptable target to some spammers now.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29811">Re: Re:
Hello </uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Proposal: pre-emerge advisories</b></p>
<p>
Since sometimes breakage happens during updates, an interested user suggests to
add functionality to portage to warn about known issues before upgrading.
Although this would be very interesting to have it is unlikely to become a
portage feature in the foreseeable future.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29799">pre-emerge
advisories </uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>upcoming portage changes</b></p>
<p>
As portage continues to grow in CVS (which is not yet available for general
consumption) the portage hackers warn of things to come: At some point in the
future the ebuild format will change in a non-compatible way. To make any
transition easier there will be a new EBUILD_FORMAT variable so that old and
new ebuild can be distinguished.  Also, the RDEPEND=DEPEND assumption that
portage does right now will change.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29512">EBUILD_FORMAT</uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29509">RDEPEND=DEPEND
changes </uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>devfs is dead, let's move on</b></p>
<p>
Our resident kernel hacker and udev maintainer GregKH explains some of the
changes that the removal of devfs from the 2.6 kernel series will cause.  Also,
a slight reorganization in the udev namespace might save some RAM for all
involved.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29504">devfs is
dead </uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Proposed security policy for web-based apps</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="stuart@gentoo.org">Stuart Herbert</mail> offers a proposal for
handling security bugs for web-apps. This should reduce the reaction time for
Gentoo whenever there are such bugs (and thanks to sloppy coding there are more
than enough of those).
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29447">Proposed
security policy for web-apps </uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Canada: Gentoo at the Ottawa Linux Symposium</title>
<body>
<p>
The annual <uri link="http://www.linuxsymposium.org">OLS</uri> is coming
up this week, held from 20 to 23 July at the Ottawa Congress Centre
(preceded by a desktop developer's conference at the same venue starting
today, 18 to 19 July, open to anyone arriving early for the main event). At
the OLS, Gentoo's Linux kernel developer and <c>udev</c> maintainer Greg
Kroah-Hartman will be given a device upon the start of the class, and by the
end, they will have created a kernel driver that controls the
device that will be acceptable for inclusion in the main Linux kernel tree!
Seating for Greg's tutorial is limited to 30 spaces, so please reserve now.
He also hosts a birds-of-a-feather (BOF) session about  "Linux device
persistant naming policy", and fellow Gentoo developer <mail
  link="omkhar@gentoo.org">Omkhar Arasaratnam</mail> will organize an
impromptu Gentoo BOF session for any Gentoo user, developer or afficionado
who happens to be in Ottawa. Please email Omkhar directly to announce your
interest in participating.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Germany: Gentoo introductory talk at Oberhausen LUG</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo Developer <mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail> held
a presentation about Gentoo including a demonstration how fast Gentoo can be
installed using GRP packages last Wednesday at the monthly meeting of his local
<uri link="http://www.lugor.de">LUG</uri> in Oberhausen/Germany. First he
introduced the concepts behind Gentoo, then how everyone can utilize Gentoo for
his personal needs and finally Gentoo's big plus: our strong and manifold
community.
</p>
<p>
Subsequent to his presentation the attendees got a practical introduction to
Gentoo: Tobias installed Gentoo on a quite new HP notebook using the 2005.0
installation media and explained the necessary installation steps, including
the usage of GRP packages to get a system quick set up.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Benchmarking AMD64 and P4 with Gentoo on linuxhardware</title>
<body>
<p>
  Linuxhardware did a current <uri
    link="http://www.linuxhardware.org/article.pl?sid=05/07/11/185212&amp;mode=thread">benchmark
    between different AMD64 and P4 machines</uri>.  The interesting stuff: They
  used Gentoo/AMD64 for both platforms.  Find out the winner!
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
  <title>Tips and Tricks</title>
  <section>
    <title>Fullscreen task-switching: skippy</title>
    <body>
      <p>You know the problem: Too many applications open, too many windows open,
        and you are searching for one window you can't find in your taskbar or
        with the taskswitcher.  That's the point when <c>skippy</c> becomes
        handy:</p>

      <figure link="/images/gwn/20050718_skippy.png"
        short="skippy"
        caption="fullscreen task-switching with skippy" />

      <p>For installation just run <c>emerge skippy</c> and start it with
        <c>skippy</c>.  Now you can switch your tasks with <c>F11</c>.  Or show
        the windows of the current application only with <c>Alt-F11</c>.  Use
        your mouse for selecting the window or cycle through all windows with
        <c>Alt-Tab</c>.</p>

      <p>You can customize the keys by copying the file
        <path>/usr/share/skippy-0.5.0/skippyrc-default</path> into
        <path>~/.skippyrc</path> and change it to your preferences.</p>

      <p>And finally there is a <uri
          link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-173949.html">skippy
          thread</uri> in the forums with some customized config-files.</p>

    </body>
  </section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>New staff member: Wernfried Haas (amne) (forum moderator)</li>
  <li>New developer: Francesco Riosa (vivo) (MySQL)</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
  <li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>Adobe Acrobat Reader: Buffer overflow vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    Adobe Acrobat Reader is vulnerable to a buffer overflow that could lead to
    remote execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-09.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Ruby: Arbitrary command execution through XML-RPC</title>
<body>
<p>

    A vulnerability in XMLRPC.iPIMethods allows remote attackers to execute
    arbitrary commands.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-10.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>MIT Kerberos 5: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    MIT Kerberos 5 is vulnerable to a Denial of Service attack and remote
    execution of arbitrary code, possibly leading to the compromise of the
    entire Kerberos realm.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-11.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bugzilla: Unauthorized access and information disclosure</title>
<body>
<p>

    Multiple vulnerabilities in Bugzilla could allow remote users to modify bug
    flags or gain sensitive information.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-12.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>pam_ldap and nss_ldap: Plain text authentication leak</title>
<body>
<p>

    pam_ldap and nss_ldap fail to restart TLS when following a referral,
    possibly leading to credentials being sent in plain text.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-13.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mozilla Firefox: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Several vulnerabilities in Mozilla Firefox allow attacks ranging from
    execution of script code with elevated privileges to information leak.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-14.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PHP: Script injection through XML-RPC</title>
<body>
<p>

    PHP includes an XML-RPC implementation which allows remote attackers to
    execute arbitrary PHP script commands.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-15.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>dhcpcd: Denial of Service vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    A vulnerability in dhcpcd may cause the dhcpcd daemon to crash.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-16.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
      The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri
      link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
      bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the
      development team.  Between 10 July 2005
      and 16 July 2005, activity on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>634 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>561 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>22 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 8131 currently open bugs: 104 are labeled 'blocker', 185 are labeled 'critical', and 552 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
       The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="dev-portage@gentoo.org" >Portage team</mail>, with 117
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=dev-portage@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 20
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="genkernel@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Genkernel Maintainers</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=genkernel@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 18
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 17
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="ppc@gentoo.org" >PPC Porters</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=ppc@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="apache-bugs@gentoo.org" >Apache Herd - Bugzilla Reports</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=apache-bugs@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
       The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org" >Default Assignee for New Packages</mail>, with 206
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org" >Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 44
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 9
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 8
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 8
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 8
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11-drivers@gentoo.org" >X11 External Driver Maintainers</mail>, with 7
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-07-10&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-16&amp;assigned_to=x11-drivers@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and
help make the GWN better.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
  link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
