<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050214-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>February 14th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="mike@mikefetherston.ca">Mike Fetherston</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 14 February 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 7</version>
<date>2005-02-14</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Forums platform and software switch</title>
<body>
<p>
As anticipated in a <uri link="/news/en/gwn/20050124-newsletter.xml#doc_chap2">Future 
zone</uri> article three weeks ago, the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo 
Forums</uri> have switched to a new hardware platform and an upgraded version 
of phpBB, now running on a clean codebase, normalizing all the patches that had 
been applied to the old version, and more feature-rich than the release that was
powering the Forums before. Among the embellishments are better language packs 
for the non-English forums, new URI styles with absolute links that enable 
search engine spiders to index the entire Forum, and a few things of lesser 
visibility, like the moderators' new ability to join threads -- displacing 
posts from threads where they're out of context to a more appropriate location 
was never possible before. A few glitches aside, the changeover went so 
smoothly that none of the users realized it until it was all over and done. 
Congratulations to <mail link="ian@gentoo.org">Christian Hartmann</mail> and <mail 
link="ramereth@gentoo.org">Lance Albertson</mail> for a flawless migration!
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo event calender for February/March 2005</title>
<body>
<p>
Busy days for Gentoo evangelists: Their schedule has never been so packed with 
shows, conferences and presentations as over the next four weeks. Here's a list 
of the upcoming events, with a last reminder for tomorrow's LWE in Boston at 
the top. 
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="http://www.linuxworldexpo.com/live/12/events/12BOS05A/">Linux World 
Expo</uri> - 15-18 February in Boston, MA: Hynes Convention Center
</li>
<li>
<uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~pylon/fosdem-2005.html">FOSDEM</uri> - 26 and 
27 February in Brussels, Belgium: Université Libre de Bruxelles
</li>
<li>
<uri link="http://cplug.net/conference">CPLUG Security Conference</uri> - 5 
March in Grantham, PA: Messiah College
</li>
<li>
<uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~dertobi123/clt2005">Chemnitzer Linux-Tage</uri> - 
5 and 6 March in Chemnitz, Germany: Technische Universität
</li>
<li>
<uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~stuart/2005/">Gentoo UK Conference</uri> - 12 
March in Manchester, UK: University of Salford
</li>
</ul>
<note>
Links point to official event websites or -- if available -- Gentoo developer pages 
organizing our own presence.
</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux Security Team -- Interview with Thierry Carrez</title>
<body>

<p>If you have a habit of watching the pattern of security issues and
responses in the Linux world, you've probably noticed that Gentoo's
alerts and responses to those issues tend to follow rapidly on the
heels of initial discovery. In fact, Gentoo Linux Security
Announcements (GLSAs) are a frequently cited resource for security
notifications and fix status even outside the Gentoo community.  This
reputiation of responsiveness is a remarkable feat for a community 
which does not have a commercial arm supporting a dedicated security
response center.</p>

<p><mail link="koon@gentoo.org">Thierry Carrez</mail> (koon), one of
the Operational Managers for Gentoo's <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/security/index.xml">Security
Team</uri>, was kind enough to take a few minutes to explain some of
the practices that have allowed the team to be so efficient in
identifying and responding to security issues.</p>

<p><e>Could you give us a rough overview of the process involved in
identifying and fixing security flaws?  What steps are involved?  Who
performs them?  What tools are used?</e></p>

<p>We follow the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/vulnerability-policy.xml">Vulnerability
Treatment Policy</uri> to handle security bugs.  In brief, public
vulnerabilities get submitted by users, our security scouts or the
security developers, whoever finds it first. Sometimes we get notified
by confidential channels (the vendor-sec list or direct contact from
the upstream developers or auditors). Then the security bug progresses
through <e>upstream</e> status (where we wait for a fix from upstream
maintainers); <e>ebuild</e> status (where we call the Gentoo
maintainer for the package and ask for a fixed ebuild); <e>stable</e>
status, where we ask all security-supported arches to test and mark
the fixed package stable; and finally to <e>glsa</e> status where we
issue a GLSA if necessary. Sometimes we get stuck at one of those
intermediate statuses and have to work out a patch ourselves.
Sometimes we don't find a solution and we mask the package because
it's a security risk to leave it in the tree without a fix.</p>

<p>Security bug handling is mostly calling the right people at the
right time to try to get the ball rolling at all times. This task is
performed by the GLSA coordinators, and it's not automated. We rely
heavily on the other Gentoo developers (package maintainers and arch
teams) to do the patching and testing.</p>

<p><e>Where do you find out about security flaws?  Mailing lists?
Alerts?  Do we do testing ourselves?</e></p>

<p>We rely on our user base to submit as many public vulnerabilities
as they can. The security team tries to get all those that go
unnoticed.  Security flaws come from public mailing-lists like BugTraq
or Full-Disclosure, and also upstream security advisories and other
distribution advisories. We are more and more accepted as part of the
general Linux security community and therefore we get notice of some
vulnerabilities before they go public. To contribute back we have
recently set up a Security Audit subproject to find vulnerabilities by
ourselves, and our package maintainers also find a lot of
vulnerabilities in their testing.</p>

<p><e>When a flaw is identified, how is it documented?</e></p>

<p>Most of the time we just copy the public advisory information, and
then proceed in verifying that it applies to Gentoo Linux, and rate
its severity. This severity seeds priorities, as we try to respect the
delays indicated in the Vulnerability Treatment Policy.</p>

<p><e>Is there a formal process where the resolution of a flaw is
assigned to someone?  How are priorities set?  How is the fix
documented and tested?</e></p>

<p>Each GLSA Coordinator can take a bug and be tasked to ensure the
ball keeps rolling on this bug at all times. But if a bug gets stuck,
every security developer can intervene to unstick it. Priorities are
set by severities, following the rules described in the Vulnerability
Treatment Policy.</p>

<p><e>When a fix is available, how is it documented?  Who does the
GLSA?  How are GLSA's transmitted?  How are they archived or
stored?</e></p>

<p>We document the fix in a GLSA draft, which must get at least two
positive peer-reviews before getting released. We use a tool called
GLSAMaker to help in ensuring consistency between all GLSAs. The GLSA
is written by the GLSA Coordinator or sometimes by one of our Security
Apprentices (GLSA coordinators in training). GLSAs are sent by mail to
gentoo-announce and other security lists, automatically appear in a
live <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/rdf/en/glsa-index.rdf">RDF
feed</uri> and on the <uri link="http://security.gentoo.org">Gentoo
Security page</uri>.  Finally, they get copied by forum moderators to
appear as forum announcements. GLSA XML sources are part of the
portage tree (in metadata/glsa) and get synced on all user boxes, to
enable the use of the (for the moment still experimental) glsa-check
tool (which is part of the gentoolkit package).</p>

<p><e>Who are the upstream consumers of GLSA's?  Other than Gentoo
users, are there other organizations that are alerted?</e></p>

<p>We warn linuxsecurity.com so that they include GLSA in their <uri
link="http://www.linuxsecurity.com/content/blogcategory/0/76/">advisories
page</uri>. The <uri
link="http://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvekey.cgi?keyword=GENTOO">MITRE
CVE dictionary</uri> also includes GLSA references.</p>

<p><e>Are there any automated tools or scripts that the team uses to
manage these jobs?</e></p>

<p>We use GLSAMaker, a tool written by <mail
link="plasmaroo@gentoo.org">Tim Yamin</mail> (plasmaroo), to help in
writing GLSA XML source and the text counterpart.</p>

<p><e>What's the status of "emerge security" functionality to identify
and fix security issues using portage?</e></p>

<p>"Emerge security" functionality is currently under testing with the
"glsa-check" tool, part of the gentoolkit package. It allows us to
identify which GLSAs affect your system and to automatically fix the
vulnerable packages.  When this is ready, the portage tool team will
integrate this into mainline tools like emerge. Users are encouraged
to use the latest glsa-check and report any oddities using <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugzilla</uri>.</p>

<p><e>Where can users get information about the security team?</e></p>

<p>Our main page is the Gentoo Security portal at <uri
link="http://security.gentoo.org">security.gentoo.org</uri>.  It
contains all the pointers to our policy documents, the latest GLSAs
and lots of useful information. People that would like to join the
Gentoo Security project should read the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/security/">Security project
webpage</uri>, and in particular the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/coordinator_guide.xml">GLSA
Coordinators guide</uri> and the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/padawans.xml">Security
padawans page</uri> to get a feel of what we need.</p>

<p><e>What are some of the initiatives the security team have
undertaken recently?</e></p>

<p>In the last year, we put procedures in place so that all unwritten
rules followed by the team have a reference policy document. We also
put together a new team that will ensure that we keep a consistent
security watch at all times.</p>

<p><e>What did we forget to ask that we should know about?</e></p>

<p>Maybe our management structure. <mail
link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail> (klieber) is our
strategic manager, <mail link="jaervosz@gentoo.org">Sune Kloppenborg
Jeppesen</mail> (jaervosz) and myself are the operational
managers.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Future Zone</title>
<section>
<title>Open-Xchange in Gentoo Linux</title>
<body>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.open-xchange.org">Open-Xchange (OX)</uri> is the 
open-source groupware server on which Novell's SuSE Linux Openexchange Server 
<uri link="http://www.novell.com/products/openexchange">(SLOX)</uri> is based. 
Open-Xchange was closed source until 30 August 2004 when it was released under 
the GNU Public License. OX leverages popular open-source server technology by 
integrating existing projects (SMTP, IMAP, LDAP, Apache, Tomcat, and 
PostgreSQL) to deliver a powerful messaging and collaboration environment. Some 
features of interest include e-mail, project management, a versioning document 
store, shared calendaring, and a knowledge base. It can be accessed via both a 
web interface or through fat clients such as Evolution, the Mozilla suite 
(Thunderbird and Sunbird) and any other third party application that supports 
WebDAV. Currently, Open-Xchange is in development with a slated stable release 
(v0.8) in March 2005. If you want to see what OX is like before undertaking the 
somewhat daunting install, you can try it out using the <uri 
link="http://mirror.open-xchange.org/ox/EN/community/online.htm">online demo</uri>.
</p>
<p><b>Installation and support</b></p>
<p>
There are currently two ways to install OX in Gentoo Linux: using the <uri 
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=62197">ebuild from Bugzilla</uri> 
(not currently in the Portage tree), or manually installing it. A <uri 
link="http://gentoo-wiki.com/HOWTO_Open-Xchange">Wiki page</uri> explains 
the installation using the ebuild, but for most of the necessary steps to get OX 
successfully running, an additional <uri link="http://www.mikefetherston.ca/OX/">manual 
installation HOWTO</uri> covers the prerequisite configurations as well as 
extending and enhancing Open-Xchange. For Gentoo-specific questions <uri 
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-233291.html">a Gentoo Forum thread</uri> 
with several hundred posts has most of the answers that are available so far.
</p>
<p>
If you are not already familiar with the servers that OX uses be prepared for a 
steep learning curve and to do a lot of reading. A majority of the problems 
experienced so far involve LDAP configuration, Apache/Tomcat integration, and 
SASL authentication. All of the servers that OX relies on need to be properly 
configured and working before you can proceed with the actual Open-Xchange install.
</p>
<note>
Author <uri link="http://www.mikefetherston.ca">Mike Fetherston</uri> was a dedicated 
Slackware user who turned to Gentoo in early 2004. Upon <uri 
link="http://mirror.open-xchange.org/ox/EN/community/netline.htm">Netline's</uri> 
release of SuSE's SLOX server under the GPL he covered his initial installation 
experiences and tremendous feedback from the Gentoo user community in a document of 
currently more than 40 pages.
</note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>OpenMotif: Multiple vulnerabilities in libXpm</title>
<body>
<p>

    Multiple vulnerabilities have been discovered in libXpm, which is included
    in OpenMotif, that can potentially lead to remote code execution. <e>(NB: This
    is the same vulnerability that was fixed in xorg-x11 last November)</e>
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-07.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PostgreSQL: Local privilege escalation</title>
<body>
<p>

    The PostgreSQL server can be tricked by a local attacker to execute
    arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-08.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Python: Arbitrary code execution through SimpleXMLRPCServer</title>
<body>
<p>

    Python-based XML-RPC servers may be vulnerable to remote execution of
    arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-09.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>pdftohtml: Vulnerabilities in included Xpdf</title>
<body>
<p>

    pdftohtml includes vulnerable Xpdf code to handle PDF files, making it
    vulnerable to execution of arbitrary code upon converting a malicious PDF
    file.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-10.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mailman: Directory traversal vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    Mailman fails to properly sanitize input, leading to information
    disclosure.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-11.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Webmin: Information leak in Gentoo binary package</title>
<body>
<p>

    Portage-built Webmin binary packages accidentally include a file containing
    the local encrypted root password.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-12.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Perl: Vulnerabilities in perl-suid wrapper</title>
<body>
<p>

    Vulnerabilities leading to file overwriting and code execution with
    elevated privileges have been discovered in the perl-suid wrapper.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-13.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>mod_python: Publisher Handler vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    mod_python contains a vulnerability in the Publisher Handler potentially
    leading to information disclosure.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200502-14.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>Remove no [insert feature here] USE-flags from the tree</b></p>
<p>

<mail link="m.debruijne@hccnet.nl">Michiel de Bruijne </mail> writes:
"There are quite a few ebuilds in the tree that make use of a no [insert
feature here] USE-flag. So basically by disabling the USE-flag you get
more features. Pulling in extra dependencies by disabling the USE-flag is a
possibility. This has some nasty side effects ..."
The following discussion shows quite well why these USE-flags are not
good.
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25197">Remove
no [insert feature here] USE-flags from the tree</uri>
</li>
</ul>

<p><b>Automatic stabilization of packages</b></p>
<p>
Approximately every 6 months the same discussion comes up:
How can the packages in portage be kept up to date? The naive approach
would be automatic stabilization after a certain period of time.
This thread shows why for the most part that is not a good idea ...
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25254">Automatic
stabilization of packages</uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>Closing or resolving bugs, which is it?</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="genone@gentoo.org">Marius Mauch</mail> writes:
"I noticed a new trend lately introduced by a few new devs: changing bug
status from RESOLVED to CLOSED. Personally I just find it annoying and
completely useless. Can we agree to not do that unless there is a
technical reason? Don't see any benefit in this, just means that closed
bugs are now split between two "categories" with no actual difference."
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/25168">should we close bugs?</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>USA: Gentoo Bugday event at Oregon State University LUG</title>
<body>
<p>
<uri link="http://bugday.gentoo.org/">Gentoo Bugdays</uri> are regularly held 
every first Saturday of each month, with developers and users everywhere gathering 
on IRC and skimming Gentoo's bugzilla for anything that looks like it needs 
fixing. On 5 February, the Linux User Group of Oregon State University took the 
opportunity and turned the virtual event into <uri 
link="http://lug.oregonstate.edu/wiki/index.cgi?GentooBugDay">a real one</uri>. 
Twelve OSLUG members met at Weatherford Hall, the OSU residential college 
building. Aided by a precompiled list of bugs prepared by Gentoo's Bugday
organizers for this occasion, they kept squashing bugs from 9:00 to 16:00, with 
the official IRC channel <path>#gentoo-bugs</path> being projected overhead, 
and assorted computers scattered around the classroom, each with a determined 
Gentoo bug hunter in front of the screen. 
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050214_oslug.jpg"
           short="GentooBugDay" 
           caption="The Klendathu, OR bughunt: Deedra Waters, Dunbar (background) and Micheal Clay" />
<note>
More photos are available at <uri link="http://lug.oregonstate.edu/gallery/GentooBugDay">the OSLUG website</uri>.
</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Germany: Storage tool release for Gentoo Linux</title>
<body>
<p>
Commercial releases of Linux applications with official support outside the 
RedHat/SuSE/Mandrake realm are scarce and far between. A German company, <uri 
link="http://www.sep.de">SEP AG</uri>, has now announced the availability of 
their storage management product "SEP sesam" for Gentoo Linux. "We're 
traditionally tied to SuSE Linux, but had Gentoo on our radar ever since we 
watched the impressive installation <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars 
Weiler</mail> did on an HP Proliant cluster at last year's LinuxTag in 
Karlsruhe," recalls SEP's sales manager Johann Krahfuss (cf. <uri 
link="/news/en/gwn/20040628-newsletter.xml">GWN report 28 June 2004</uri>). 
"So when our first customers demanded an adaptation of SEP sesam to 
Gentoo Linux, it didn't exactly take us by surprise." The German federal 
research institution <uri link="http://www.fhg.de">Fraunhofer Gesellschaft</uri> 
were the first to request a SEP sesam installation inside a Gentoo 
Linux environment, "and since we didn't encounter any problems whatsoever, we 
feel it's ready for official release," says Krahfuss. A 30-day-test version 
(including support) can be downloaded from the corporate website's download 
section. SEP sesam is designed for data storage management in heterogenous 
networks, including Linux, BSD, Solaris, TRU/64, OpenVMS, Windows and Mac OS X. 
The company will be present at next week's <uri 
link="http://www.solutiondays.de/storage">CRN Storage Solution Days 2005</uri> 
in Neuss (link in German only).
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Newsforge (8 and 9 February 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Newsforge published an article in two parts about <uri 
link="http://software.newsforge.com/software/04/12/27/1238216.shtml">using 
MySQL to benchmark OS performance</uri>, as analyzed and written by <uri 
link="http://vegan.net/tony/">Tony Bourke</uri>. The performance check
spans server operating systems Open-, Net- and FreeBSD, Solaris 10, and Linux 
as platforms for MySQL database execution, and "among a multitude of 
distributions" Gentoo was chosen for the Linux part of the test, running both 
2.4 and 2.6 kernels (<path>gentoo-sources</path>) on ReiserFS. "With Gentoo it 
was also relatively easy to install NPTL for 2.6, which I used in the 2.6 tests," 
says Tony Bourke, "although they didn't make any difference when compared to 
non-NPTL 2.6 results." While the first part just explains the tools and 
the methodology, the actual performance comparison is published in <uri 
link="http://www.newsforge.com/article.pl?sid=04/12/27/1243207">a separate 
article</uri> - with amazing results, Gentoo Linux clearly winning all individual
benchmark tests. Funnily enough, Gentoo's outstanding performance even triggered 
complaints about the <uri link="http://www.newsforge.com/comments.pl?sid=43141&amp;op=&amp;threshold=0&amp;commentsort=0&amp;mode=thread&amp;tid=152&amp;pid=106968#106970">"unfair 
advantage"</uri> of using a source-based, possibly processor-optimized Linux 
distribution as a platform for the comparison.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>CNET (7 February 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Sun's President Jonathan Schwartz nods his head to Gentoo's OpenSolaris
effort in an interview published on CNET last week. While explaining the
OpenSolaris governance model to interviewer Stephen Shankland, he claims <uri 
link="http://news.com.com/Suns+open-source+gamble/2008-1082_3-5564283.html">"Solaris 
is now officially platform-neutral"</uri> and expects "10 or more" non-Sun 
OpenSolaris distributions to appear in the market.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Security Focus (2 February 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Columnist Jason Miller says Linux kernel security handling is broken,
"and it needs to be fixed right now." The <uri 
link="http://www.securityfocus.com/columnists/296">article at 
securityfocus.com</uri>, a publication mainly read by security professionals, 
is highly critical of the way security bugs in the Linux kernel are being
addressed. But the author, a self-proclaimed "huge follower of BSD-based operating 
systems," has some good news, too: "Once we start looking at actual distributions 
of the Linux kernel as a complete operating system, we find some distributions 
with official security contacts, as well as security-related pages similar to 
those provided by the major BSD-based operating systems. Gentoo Linux Security is 
a good example of that." 
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Réseaux &amp; Télécoms (3 February 2005, in French)</title>
<body>
<p>
Directly responding to the Security Focus column by Jason Miller, the French 
network and telco magazine looks beyond the kernel as a security issue: Both 
flaws in individual applications not depending on the kernel, and the 
distribution of security-related information are identified as equally important
fields of activity for the "bug hunters of open source." The article <uri 
link="http://www.reseaux-telecoms.com/cso_btree/05_02_03_194507_984/CSO/Newscso_view">"Noyau 
Linux : Mais où est la sécurité ?"</uri> acknowledges Miller's conclusion 
of "things changing, fast and in the right direction," and praises Thierry 
Carrez (see our <uri link="/news/en/gwn/20050214-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1_sect2">interview 
above</uri>) as an example for "impressive work." With the current pace of 
discussion around the structure of security handling and the distribution of 
information, it's "time to show some optimism," says author Marc Olanie, 
pointing out that it took Microsoft eighteen years to standardize their own 
security procedures -- "or have they?"
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Sun blogs (31 January 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Eric Boutilier, an engineer at Sun, Inc. is gearing up for Gentoo development 
on OpenSolaris, and posted his first attempts at familiarizing himself with Portage
on Linux to <uri link="http://blogs.sun.com/roller/page/eric_boutilier/20050131">
his blog at the Sun website</uri>. While his choice of installation material is 
peculiar - Gentoo-clone Vidalinux rather than a standard install, and on a five-year-old
Portégé laptop - he quickly falls in sync with normal Portage user behaviour for lengthy
compiles: "Oh well. I left it happily building away and went to work."
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 06 February 2005 and 13 February 2005, activity
on the site has resulted in:
</p>
<ul>
<li>860 new bugs during this period</li>
<li>699 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
<li>37 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
</ul>
<p>
Of the 8036 currently open bugs: 102 are labeled 'blocker', 243 are labeled 'critical', and 600 are labeled 'major'.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="osx@gentoo.org" >osx porters</mail>, with 179
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=osx@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 53
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 30
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 24
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 23
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 19
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 19
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="text-markup@gentoo.org" >Text-Markup Team</mail>, with 17
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=text-markup@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 30
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 18
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 15
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="net-mail@gentoo.org" >Net-Mail Packages</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;assigned_to=net-mail@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="mobile@gentoo.org" >Mobile Herd</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;assigned_to=mobile@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="dev-portage@gentoo.org" >Portage team</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-02-06&amp;chfieldto=2005-02-13&amp;assigned_to=dev-portage@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and tricks</title>
<section>
<title>Portage magic: Identify obsolete packages</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo developer <mail link="ferringb@gentoo.org">Brian Harring</mail> designed
a clever way to identify all merged versions of packages not available 
in Portage anymore -- both the official tree and packages from 
<path>PORTDIR_OVERLAY</path>. Here is the method he came up with, packing
as much Python neatness as fits on a single command line:
</p>
<pre caption="Python scriptlet #1">
python -c 'import portage; print [x for x in portage.db["/"]["vartree"].getallcpv() \ 
if len(portage.portdb.xmatch("match-all","="+x))==0]'
</pre>
<p>
If that just went a little over your head, let's look at what exactly it does. For example,
if a package, say, <path>foo-1.2.3</path> is merged, and that version 1.2.3 is no longer in the 
tree, the script will point it out. A simple check for packages that aren't available any 
longer regardless of versions, would look like this:
</p>
<pre caption="Python scriptlet #2">
python -c 'import portage; print [x for x in portage.db["/"]["vartree"].getallcpv() \ 
if len(portage.portdb.xmatch("match-all",portage.pkgsplit(x)[0]))==0]'
</pre>
<p>
Finally, if you want to ignore package <path>foo-1.2.3</path> even if it isn't in the tree 
any longer, but a revision <path>foo-1.2.3-r1</path> is, the following script will ignore 
the package, only triggering on installed applications that have completely vanished from 
Portage. </p>
<pre caption="Python scriptlet #3">
python -c 'import portage; print [x for x in portage.db["/"]["vartree"].getallcpv() \ 
if len(portage.portdb.xmatch("match-all","~"+"-".join(portage.pkgsplit(x)[:2])))==0]'
</pre>
<p>Lastly, none of the above take injected packages into consideration, only those that
were installed from an available tree. Now, suppose you'd like to ignore those, too, here's
what to do:</p>
<pre caption="Python scriptlet #3">
python -c 'import portage; print [x for x in portage.db["/"]["vartree"].getallcpv() \ 
if len(portage.portdb.xmatch("match-all",portage.pkgsplit(x)[0]))==0 \ 
and not portage.db["/"]["vartree"].dbapi.isInjected(x)]'
</pre>
<p>Yes, we knew you'd like this. All of the above do work for individual packages you keep 
in an overlay tree, for example at <path>/usr/local/portage</path>, those are being evaluated 
along with packages in the official Portage tree. Try it out, you can't break anything, it 
just notifies you about whatever it finds, leaving it up to the user to decide what to do 
with that information.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
<e>None this week</e>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
Sebastian Bergmann (sebastian) - PHP
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<e>None this week</e>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter? Send us an <mail 
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and 
help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">french</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">portuguese (brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">portuguese (portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>