<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050711-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>July 11th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="buanzo@buanzo.com.ar">Arturo 'Buanzo' Busleiman</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="w.haas@xover.htu.tuwien.ac.at">Wernfried Haas</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 11 July 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 27</version>
<date>2005-07-11</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>2.5 million posts</title>
<body>
<p>
With the ascension of Gentoo Forum moderators to official staff membership progressing 
nicely, their area of activity has just passed yet another impressive milestone: On 6 July, 
the magic number of 2.5 million posts was reached. Since finding out who the poster of this 
historic submission was is fiendishly difficult and involves major operations on the 
underlying database, suffice for now to show visual proof of the moment:
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050711_postcount.png"
short="Postcount" 
caption="Passing the 2.5 million mark: Total number of Forum posts on 6 July 2005" />
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation project update</title>
<body>
<p>
Recent addition to the Documentation team <mail link="fox2mike@gentoo.org">Shyam 
Mani</mail> has rewritten the heavily outdated ALSA Guide, and converted Daniel 
Robbins' articles from IBM DeveloperWorks to the standard GuideXML format and 
made them available <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/articles/">at the 
Gentoo website</uri>. A completely new piece of documentation is 
<mail link="hollow@gentoo.org">Benedikt Boehm's</mail> contributed <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/vserver-howto.xml">vserver Howto</uri>, while 
major revamping has been applied to the <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/">Gentoo Handbook</uri> (now with an 
improved description of <c>lspci</c> and an update on <c>devfsd</c> versus <c>udev</c>. 
A new part on network configuration that covers Gentoo's current <path>baselayout</path> 
and includes wireless networks has been added to the handbook, and the NVidia, 
Gentoo Security and Printing Guides have also been updated. The complete status
update can be viewed <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/status/status_20050630.xml">at 
the Gentoo website</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Greek translator team looking for new members</title>
<body>
<p>
The Greek translators of the Gentoo documentation are recruiting new team 
members to reinforce their ability to cover the material in its entirety.
If your Greek is up to the task and you would like to join the other 
translators, contact <mail link="deathwing00@gentoo.org">Ioannis 
Aslanidis</mail>, please.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>"It's done when it's done" -- Tobias Scherbaum (dertobi123)</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050711_dertobi123.jpg"
short="dertobi123" 
caption="Tobias Scherbaum aka dertobi123" />
<p>
This week's featured dev is Tobias Scherbaum, better known to most as
<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">dertobi123</mail>. He lives in
Oberhausen in Germany's industrial Ruhr region, and is one of the 
veterans among German developers. As with many other Gentoo developers 
he associated himself with Gentoo well before he could get involved with 
any other OSS project.
</p>
<p>
Tobias is the German lead translator, but recently started HPPA stage
building and PPC stable keywording, too. Probably his best-known project,
one he has spent a lot of time on, are the FizzleWizzle XLiveCDs that see
new releases shipping just in time for most of Europe's major Linux events,
like FOSDEM, LinuxTag or the German edition of the Linux World Expo.
At the moment he is undergoing an apprenticeship for "Fachinformatiker
Systemintegration", which essentially boils down to becoming a highly 
trained monkey for fixing cabling and computer problems. Before that he 
passed his German "Abitur" (graduation after 12 or 13 years of school) and
studied Economy for two years. 
</p>
<p>
Like many Gentooists he owns an impressive hardware collection, spanning many 
architectures, including SGI, SUN and HPPA, plus an iBook and some obsolete 
x86 machines. Some platforms are still missing, but one of Tobias' ambitions 
in life is to decorate his home with at least one specimen of every single 
architecture that Gentoo runs on.
</p>
<p>His normal working environment is the Gnome, with <c>ssh</c> and <c>screen</c> 
as the main helpers for administration and remote connections. About the first 
application he fires up in the morning is usually Evolution, followed by a 
sufficiently large amount of terminals to accomodate all his <c>screen</c> 
sessions. Contrary to popular opinion he has a life outside the computers, 
with more exotic hobbies such as gardening (with barbecues as an important
subset), reading computerbooks and cycling, but he is currently void of a 
female companion. 
</p>
<p>
Tobias is one of the founders of the "Friends of Gentoo e.V.", the
German NFP association, and a regular booth staff member at German Linux 
happenings. Just a few weeks ago he passed the ebuild quiz and is now a 
fully enabled ot wreak havoc in the Portage tree, and he maintains the GTK+-2
frontend for CD/DVD burning, <c>graveman</c>. Tobias has so far completely and 
utterly failed to break the tree as such, but on the upside of things he's 
managed to get a number of overdue packages to stable status, most importantly
Gnome 2.10 for PPC. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>Keywording problems</b></p>
<p>
Just a few minutes apart two threads were started in response to some
violations of our keywording policy. As it seems some devs were a bit
optimistic and broke a few things on SPARC. This shouldn't happen, but
somehow it does every now and then. To quote Monty Python: "We apologise
for that. The people responsible have been sacked"
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29230">Keys and
words: ways to fail your team </uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29220">Brainless
keywording </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>GLEP 38: Status of forum moderators</b></p>
<p>
For the longest time the forum moderators that are not already
developers were not considered official staff while the forums were
official. To rectify this situation GLEP 38 was proposed in which the
global moderators would become official Gentoo staff by taking the staff
quiz. Due to some suboptimal wording this was slightly misunderstood and
caused a minor flamewar, but in the end an agreement was reached.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29139">Glep 38:
Status of forum moderators in The Gentoo project </uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/29219">Glep 38:
round two </uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Argentina: Ututo-E 2005.1 release</title>
<body>
<p>
The <uri link="http://e.ututo.org.ar">Ututo-e</uri> Core Team announces the 
release of its Gentoo-based GNU/Linux Distribution, Ututo XS 2005.1. Ututo-e is 
a Gentoo-based distribution for desktop users that keeps compatibility with 
Gentoo and enjoys endorsement by the FSF and Richard M. Stallman himself as 
the <uri link="http://kerneltrap.org/node/4484">"only free GNU/Linux 
distribution"</uri> he knows.
</p>
<p>
The new release XS 2005.1 is aiming for ease of migration from proprietary
operating systems. Ututo-e provides a per-processor globally-optimized software 
packages repository, processor-optimized downloadable ISO images for 
installation, and a soon-to-be released LiveCD. Additionally, Ututo-e is 
supporting the x86_64 architecture. You can download the different flavors of 
Ututo-e's XS 2005.1 directly from the <uri 
link="http://ftp.gnu.org/pub/gnu+linux-distros/ututo-e/">GNU Project's 
servers</uri>, or from any of the <uri 
link="https://e.ututo.org.ar/xp/modules/mydownloads/">nine mirrors</uri> 
available worldwide, or <uri link="http://www.linuxtracker.org/">via
BitTorrent</uri>. The Ututo-e XS 2005.1 installation system is available in 
English, Italian, Portuguese and Spanish, and comes with a GUI- or console-based 
(ncurses) administration system.
</p>
<p>
Ututo-e's core team would like to join an expression of their gratitude to this 
announcement: a huge thank you goes to every and each person that has contributed 
to the Gentoo Project. People, base your projects on Gentoo. It's a wonderful 
metadistribution. Again, thank you.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Japan: Visiting European devs get shown around</title>
<body>
<p>
UK-based Gentoo dev <mail link="cryos@gentoo.org">Marcs D. Hanwell</mail>, returning 
from a conference in Sapporo, stayed in Tokyo for a week. Enough excuse for 
Tomoyuki Sakurai, the GWN lead translator, to organise a night out and about 
for cryos and his English friends: They went to Tokyo's traditional and popular 
downtown area of Asakusa, enjoyed the basic pleasures of Japanese food 
including <uri link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Okonomiyaki">Okonomiyaki and 
Monjayaki</uri>, then went on to a genuine spa, one of the few hotsprings right 
in the heart of Tokyo. The long day was rounded off at a typical Izakaya, a 
Japanese style pub offering yet some more snacks, and the four Englishmen who 
hadn't heard of anything but Sushi and Sashimi went home quite pleasantly 
surprised at the wide range of foods in Japan.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050711_cryos.jpg"
short="Cryos" 
caption="Cryos (right) and friends at Ueno train station" />
<p>
Just a few days later, on 7 July, the GentooJP lot held a party in honor of yet 
another visiting Gentoo dev, <mail link="lu_zero@gentoo.org">Luca Barbato</mail> 
and his Italian friends. A Japanese family of Gentooists, Japan-based <mail 
link="jstubbs@gentoo.org">Jason Stubbs</mail> and Mudrii joined the 
crowd, adding the benefit of both being weathered foreigners living in Japan:
very helpful resources, particularly as guides to undocumented rules in Japanese 
society for Italian travellers. The type of information Luca and his companions 
got is impossible to be had from books, and available to other Gentooists if they 
happen to make it all the way to Japan. Next time you do, remember to drop a line 
to the <path>gentoojp-misc@ml.gentoo.gr.jp</path> mailing list, or <path>/join</path> 
the <path>#gentoo-ja</path> IRC channel on Freenode.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050711_luzero.jpg"
short="Luca and friends" 
caption="Mudrii, jstubss and lu_zero at a pub in Tokyo" />
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Linux Weekly News (28 June 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo dev and regular GWN contributor <uri link="http://lwn.net/Articles/141886/">Patrick 
Lauer's article</uri> about the Gentoo community was published two weeks ago, 
but has only now been made available to non-subscribers of the Linux Weekly 
News. He provides an overview of the community, with fellow Gentoo devs <mail 
link="spyderous@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholz</mail> and <mail link="g2boojum@gentoo.org">Grant 
Goodyear</mail> chiming in for the ensuing discussion.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Brent Baude (ranger) - PPC/PPC64</li>
<li>Jan Hendrik Grahl (grahl04) - Documentation translator</li>
<li>Joshua Baergen (Josh_B) - X11</li>
<li>Kahtryn Kulick - commonbox, net-im, X11 themes</li>
<li>Michael Curtis Napier (curtis119) - WWW redesign</li>
<li>Scott Shawcroft (tannewt) - Bugday team</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li>Tobias Scherbaum (dertobi123) - Adds HPPA release engineering to his other duties</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>Clam AntiVirus: Denial of Service vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

Clam AntiVirus is vulnerable to a Denial of Service attack when processing
certain Quantum archives.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-23.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Heimdal: Buffer overflow vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

Multiple buffer overflow vulnerabilities in Heimdal's telnetd server could
allow the execution of arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-24.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PEAR XML-RPC, phpxmlrpc: PHP script injection vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

The PEAR XML-RPC and phpxmlrpc libraries allow remote attackers to execute
arbitrary PHP script commands.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-01.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>WordPress: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

WordPress contains PHP script injection, cross-site scripting and path
disclosure vulnerabilities.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-02.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>phpBB: Arbitrary command execution</title>
<body>
<p>

A vulnerability in phpBB allows a remote attacker to execute arbitrary
commands with the rights of the web server.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-03.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>RealPlayer: Heap overflow vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

RealPlayer is vulnerable to a heap overflow that could lead to remote
execution of arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-04.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>zlib: Buffer overflow</title>
<body>
<p>

A buffer overflow has been discovered in zlib, potentially resulting in the
execution of arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-05.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>TikiWiki: Arbitrary command execution through XML-RPC</title>
<body>
<p>

TikiWiki includes PHP XML-RPC code, making it vulnerable to arbitrary
command execution.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-06.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>phpWebSite: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

phpWebSite is vulnerable to the remote execution of arbitrary PHP script
code and to other, yet undisclosed, vulnerabilities.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-07.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>phpGroupWare, eGroupWare: PHP script injection vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

phpGroupWare and eGroupWare include an XML-RPC implementation which allows
remote attackers to execute arbitrary PHP script commands.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200507-08.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 26 June 2005 and 10 July 2005, activity
on the site has resulted in:
</p>
<ul>
	<li>1437 new bugs during this period</li>
	<li>840 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	<li>35 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
</ul>
<p>
Of the 8392 currently open bugs: 103 are labeled 'blocker', 200 are labeled 'critical', and 597 are labeled 'major'.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 44
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 41
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="web-apps@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Web Application Packages Maintainers</mail>, with 36
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=web-apps@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 33
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="smithj@gentoo.org" >Jonathan Smith</mail>, with 31
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=smithj@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="neysx@gentoo.org" >Xavier Neys</mail>, with 30
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=neysx@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 29
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 28
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
	</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org" >Default Assignee for New Packages</mail>, with 103
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org" >Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 59
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 25
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 21
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="stuart@gentoo.org" >Stuart Herbert</mail>, with 20
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;assigned_to=stuart@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 17
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 17
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 15
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-26&amp;chfieldto=2005-07-10&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
	</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and
help make the GWN better.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
  link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
