<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050613-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>June 13th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="dholm@gentoo.org">David Holm</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="angusyoung@gentoo.org">Otavio R. Piske</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 13 June 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 24</version>
<date>2005-06-13</date>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>New PegasosPPC Open Desktop Workstations with Gentoo preinstalled</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050613_odw.jpg"
short="ODW" 
caption="New design, performance boost, Gentoo inside: The new Open Desktop Workstation" />

<p>
Back in January we reported on Genesi's PegasosPPC, the PowerPC-based 
platform marketed as the "Open Desktop Workstation" (ODW) -- and being sold 
with Gentoo preinstalled. In order to better match Apple's Mac Mini the 
Open Desktop Workstation has just received a face lift, not only in case 
design but also in terms of hardware inside, and at a lower price than 
before. The ODW now sports twice the RAM, double the storage space of the 
previous model, and it includes a dual-layer DVD±RW drive, all for 799 USD 
(650 EUR). For each unit sold via Gentoo's <uri 
link="http://vendors.gentoo.org/">vendors page</uri>, 50 USD is donated to 
the Gentoo Foundation.
</p>
<p>
With Apple turning their back on a growing community of PowerPC users, <uri 
link="http://www.genesi.lu/">Genesi</uri> and IBM remain committed to selling
affordable, high-quality PowerPC machines for desktop and server use.
</p>
<ul>
<li>Pegasos II with 1GHz G4 processor</li>
<li>512MB DDR RAM</li>
<li>80GB Hard Disk</li>
<li>Dual-Layer DVD±RW Drive</li>
<li>ATI Radeon 9250 graphics</li>
<li>Low Profile Small Footprint Case - Tower or Desktop Orientation</li>
</ul>
<p>
The system comes with one AGP slot, in use by the Radeon 9250, and three
PCI slots. The CPU-card is replaceable and CPU-upgrades will be made
available at a later date.
</p>
<p>
A few of the new ODWs have found their way to Gentoo developers already,
with one machine donated to Oregon State University currently being used by 
the Hardened Gentoo team, and yet another donated mainboard assembled to
serve by <mail link="cshields@gentoo.org">Corey Shields</mail>. A second 
board is scheduled to be put in a crystal case and displayed at the Gentoo 
booth in San Francisco at the Linux World Expo in August. Another of the 
double RAM, double HDD space machines went to PPC developer <mail 
link="josejx@gentoo.org">Joseph Jezak</mail>, bringing the total number of
donated Genesi ODWs of both generations that have been brought to use in 
Gentoo development to almost twenty.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New Gentoo/MIPS SGI LiveCD</title>
<body>
<p>
The first iteration of the SGI LiveCD worked only on a few assorted systems. 
Several months down the line, <mail link="kumba@gentoo.org">Joshua Kinard</mail> 
now has the pleasure of announcing a new one that not only supports most
SGI hardware available, but also autodetects what system and CPU is present,
loads the right kernel and passes every parameter needed to get your Indy,
Indigo2, Octane or O2 booted successfully.
</p>
<p>
While still being labeled experimental, the new CD benefits from the awesome new
bootloader for SGI systems called ARCLoad, developed by <mail 
link="sskowron@et.put.poznan.pl">Stanislaw Skowronek</mail>, replacing the older
<c>arcboot</c>. ARCLoad itself will be made available in Portage soon those wanting
to boot directly off their hard disks. The compressed LiveCD image is slim enough 
to fit in 15MB of <uri 
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~kumba/mips/releases/livecd-rc4/">Kumba's devspace</uri> 
where it's available for download along with instructions for the different types 
of SGI machines.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>GuideXML editor released</title>
<body>
<p>
<mail link="ian@gentoo.org">Christian Hartmann</mail> (ian!) has 
released a new version of his Perl-driven WYSIWIG editor for Gentoo's 
documentation, <c>gendocedit</c>. Originally written to help ease the process 
of translating documents from English to other languages, the current version 
is able to output clean GuideXML that's fit for inclusion on the Gentoo 
website. Since accurate, up-to-date documentation is one of the most valuable 
assets for the Gentoo project, a tool that helps authoring it is a welcome 
addition by anyone's standard. Speaking of documentation, a user manual for 
<c>gendocedit</c> isn't available yet, but it's pretty much self-explanatory, 
and is entirely governed by a GPL2 license, free for anyone to mend and bend 
and make better in the process. Downloads for version 0.4 can be made from <uri link="http://download.iansview.com/gendocedit/releases/gendocedit-0.40.tar.gz">ian!'s 
own website</uri>. Currently not for the faint at heart yet, since dependencies 
require highly unstable environments, including a package-masked MySQL version.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>"Gentoo is LinuxFromScratch on acid" -- Michael Cummings</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050613_mcummings.jpg"
short="mcummings" 
caption="Michael Cummings aka mcummings" />

<p>
This week's victim for the featured developer column is <mail 
link="mcummings@gentoo.org">Michael Cummings</mail>, a self-proclaimed 
prankster and Gentoo Perl Monkey. The latter has him hacking all things Perl 
(especially the package splits in <path>perl-*</path>), the former mostly 
making fun of users in ways that don't offend them. He's had quite some 
competition for that role lately, so Michael has to do more Perl work to 
compensate for that. 
</p>
<p>
Like most other devs Michael got pulled in through fixing a few bugs and
trying to help with things that were not working as planned - Gentoo is
his first open-source project. Some of the things that came from working
on Perl are "bugger" (a command-line bugzilla tool) and <c>g-cpa</c>n, a Perl
module managment tool for Gentoo.</p>
<p>
In real life Michael graduated in 97 from Virginia Tech with a degree in
Political Science (with a minor in Philosophy), from where he got to his
job of "web application administration, installation, troubleshooting, 
securing, fixing breaking" for an undisclosed employer. Surprisingly he 
uses Perl a lot, but after a long time of using <c>blackbox</c> he has 
recently changed to KDE 3.4 because the integration of applications is just 
right for him. Unsurprisingly his main computer is a run-of-the-mill Pentium4 
box, and there's also a SPARC machine doing a few things.</p>
<p>
Outside of Gentoo his greatest hobby is his family: a wife, two
daughters and a dog. They live in the US-state of Virginia, on the "south side" 
of Fredericksburg. His work is about 45 minutes to an hour away, meaning he 
gets up, drives for a long time, slacks and works a bit, drives back and plays 
with the kids. That doesn't leave very much time, but the progress in Perl he's 
made for Gentoo is still more than respectable. His choice of favourite quotes
shows a high degree of reliability, too: "If the apocalypse comes, page me," as
Buffy the vampire slayer puts it.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Having fun with automation</b></p>
<p>
Bekker, a new user on the Gentoo Forums, saw a Ubuntu feature he liked 
and tried to reproduce the experience in Gentoo: on insertion of a memory 
stick an icon appears on the desktop, without even mounting it. One way
to get this to work is with udev, d-bus, HAL and gnome-volume-manager,
says the friendly helper crowd. The thread is in Dutch, but setting this 
up is quite easy, and documentation exists in many other places.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-347194.html">Having fun with
automation</uri> (in Dutch)</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>Minimal perl install</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="mcummings@gentoo.org">Michael Cummings</mail> tells of a
reduced-size Perl base package. It's experimental right now and doesn't
play nice with the rest of perl, but at 930k (instead of 12300) it might
be a nice alternative for LiveCDs and other constrained areas of Gentoo.

</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/28648">Minimal
perl install </uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=95038">Bug with a
minimal perl ebuild</uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>Where goes Gentoo?</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="agriffis@gentoo.org">Aron Griffis</mail> starts a really
long thread about where Gentoo is today, where it might go in the future
and all the other questions that pop up in Gentooland. Parts of it might
be inflammatory, but it's a recurring theme that never got fully
answered in previous discussions.

</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/28633">Where goes
Gentoo? </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>ekeyword and ordering</b></p>
<p>
In the past the policy on keyword ordering in ebuilds was never fully
agreed on and formalized. So while at one point the keywords were added
in chronological order, others were added in alphabetical order. What
happens when those two ideas clash is this amazingly long thread that
elaborates all advantages and disadvantages that could arise from a
change in policy.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/28628">ekeyword
and ordering </uri></li>
</ul>
</body></section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo International</title>
<section>
<title>Brazil: 6° Fórum Internacional Software Livre</title>
<body>
<p>
As happened last year, the Brazilian Gentooists held a meeting during
the 6th edition of <uri link="http://fisl.softwarelivre.org/6.0/">International 
Free Software Forum</uri>, in Porto Alegre, south of Brazil. Thanks to their 
big banner, the Gentooists' booth could be easily indentified in the middle 
of the crowd thus making it easy for the visitors to come and get support, 
installation CDs and chat with the local Gentoo community.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050613_fisl.jpg"
short="FISL" 
caption="Brazilian Gentooists mounting the booth at FISL" />
<note>Left to right: Gustavo R. Piske (AngusYoung), Diego R. Grein
(AngrA), Vanessa Sabino (Bani), Wagner Martins (Chatoo), Eric Raymond,
Luiz Agostinho (fl0cker) and Santos (santos). Photo credit: Vanessa Sabino</note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Linux Magazine Brazilian Edition (June 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
The <uri link="http://www.linux-magazine.com.br/">Brazilian edition of Linux 
Magazine</uri> has an i686 Gentoo Linux 2005.0 installation CD (with stages) 
in its brandnew June issue. Not only that, but they also provide a step-by-step 
stage1 installation tutorial written by Marcelo V. Lima and William Ferraz.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>PC Magazin (8 June 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
In <uri link="http://www.pc-magazin.de/common/nws/einemeldung.php?id=38503">an 
interview</uri> with the German general interest computing magazine PC Magazin,
former Debian project leader Martin Michlmayer speaks out about the reasons for 
the longish Sarge delay, the relationship with Ubuntu, and other things over at 
Debian that could use some refurbishing. "Gentoo has a number of good ideas," 
acknowledges the Debian veteran of ten years, "For example the easy adaptation 
of configuration variables to the user's needs will hopefully find their way 
into Debian, too."
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Linuxfr.org (8 June 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
The French Linux site posted an <uri 
link="http://linuxfr.org/2005/06/12/19095.html">announcement</uri> for a 
reverse proxy based on Apache and mod_perl called "VultureNG", mentioning that 
it's already in Portage. The proxy integrates authentication at remote sites 
and makes them available to various applications.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Process of Elimination (4 June 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
Matt T. Proud shares a few of his <uri 
link="http://process-of-elimination.net/?q=kde_3_5_observations">KDE 3.5 
observations</uri>, including plenty of screenshots. For the purpose of checking 
out the new features in the upcoming version of KDE, he built it from the 
latest subversion snapshots on a "Gentoo stable" host.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Shyam Mani (fox2mike)  - Documentation</li>
<li>Chris Hotchkiss (chotchki) - Installer project</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>Mailutils: SQL Injection</title>
<body>
<p>

GNU Mailutils is vulnerable to SQL command injection attacks.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-02.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Dzip: Directory traversal vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

Dzip is vulnerable to a directory traversal attack.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-03.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Wordpress: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

Wordpress contains SQL injection and XSS vulnerabilities.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-04.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>SilverCity: Insecure file permissions</title>
<body>
<p>

Executable files with insecure permissions can be modified causing an
unsuspecting user to run arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-05.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>libextractor: Multiple overflow vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

libextractor is affected by several overflow vulnerabilities in the PDF,
Real and PNG extractors, making it vulnerable to execution of arbitrary
code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-06.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Ettercap: Format string vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

A format string vulnerability in Ettercap could allow a remote attacker to
execute arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-07.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>GNU shtool, ocaml-mysql: Insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

GNU shtool and ocaml-mysql are vulnerable to symlink attacks, potentially
allowing a local user to overwrite arbitrary files.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-08.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gedit: Format string vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

gedit suffers from a format string vulnerability that could allow arbitrary
code execution.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-09.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>LutelWall: Insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

LutelWall is vulnerable to symlink attacks, potentially allowing a local
user to overwrite arbitrary files.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-10.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gaim: Denial of Service vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

Gaim contains two remote Denial of Service vulnerabilities.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200506-11.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 05 June 2005 and 12 June 2005, activity
on the site has resulted in:
</p>
<ul>
<li>746 new bugs during this period</li>
<li>437 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
<li>28 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
</ul>
<p>
Of the 8435 currently open bugs: 86 are labeled 'blocker', 214 are labeled 'critical', and 599 are labeled 'major'.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="printing@gentoo.org" >Printing Team</mail>, with 29
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=printing@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 21
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 19
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 18
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 15
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 12
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="mobile@gentoo.org" >Mobile Herd</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mobile@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="neysx@gentoo.org" >Xavier Neys</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=neysx@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 16
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 13
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="toolchain@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Toolchain Maintainers</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;assigned_to=toolchain@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="sci@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Science Related Packages</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;assigned_to=sci@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="svyatogor@gentoo.org" >Sergey Kuleshov</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;assigned_to=svyatogor@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="x11-drivers@gentoo.org" >X11 External Driver Maintainers</mail>, with 6
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;assigned_to=x11-drivers@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="robbat2@gentoo.org" >Robin Johnson</mail>, with 6
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-06-05&amp;chfieldto=2005-06-12&amp;assigned_to=robbat2@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and
help make the GWN better.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail
  link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the
following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
