<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20060703-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
  <title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
  <subtitle>03 July 2006</subtitle>
  <author title="Editor">
    <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="mark_alec@gentoo.org">Mark Kowarsky</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="nichoj@gentoo.org">Josh Nichols</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="anpereir@gentoo.org">Andrés Pereira</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="musikc@charter.net">Chrissy Fullam</mail>
  </author>
  <abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 03 July
    2006.</abstract>
  <summary/>
  <version>Volume 5, Issue 24</version>
  <date>2006-07-03</date>
  
  <!-- Gentoo News -->
  <chapter>
    <title>Gentoo news</title>
    <section>
      <title>Modular X.Org stable</title>
      <body>
      <p>
        The Gentoo <uri link="/proj/en/desktop/x">X11</uri> team has marked
        the modular X.Org stable. The amd64 and x86 architectures will update
        to 7.0, due to planned changes in the ABI (Application Binary
        Interface) that have broken binary drivers, and other architectures
        will update to 7.1. This allows for quicker upgrades in the event of
        bugs and also security problems as well as reducing the on-disk and
        in-memory footprint of the X implementation. This also allows for
        X-based packages to be installed on headless servers without
        requiring that all of X be installed, too.
      </p>

      <p>
        There is a <uri link="/proj/en/desktop/x/x11/modular-x-howto.xml">
        guide</uri> for upgrading to modular X, as well as giving information
        on the design behind the changes. As usual, bug reports are filed to
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">http://bugs.gentoo.org</uri>.
      </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New Knowledge Base (KBase) project</title>
      <body>
      <p>
        The Gentoo <uri link="/proj/en/kbase">Knowledge Base</uri> project has
        been formed to provide a facility for informing users about specific
        information on packages. Unlike a wiki, the Gentoo Knowledge Base will
        be written by the developers exclusively. This ensures that the
        information is accurate. Like ebuilds in the tree, topics in the
        knowledge base will be maintained by a specific developer, to keep
        information from becoming outdated. While the actual postings will be
        limited to developers, users are encouraged to participate in the
        project both by proofreading and also by giving their valued input. If
        you would be interested in helping with the project, please subscribe
        to the <c>gentoo-kbase@lists.gentoo.org</c> mailing list. Archives are
        online at both <uri
        link="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.knowledge-base">
        Gmane</uri> and <uri
        link="http://www.mail-archive.com/gentoo-kbase%40lists.gentoo.org/">
        Mail-Archive.com</uri>.
      </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>New Java system</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          The <uri link="/proj/en/java">Gentoo/Java</uri> team is pleased to
          announce that the new Java system is now unmasked in the tree.
        </p>

        <p>
          To begin using it, you will need to follow the <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/java/java-upgrade.xml">upgrade
          guide</uri>.
        </p>

        <p>
          For those not familar with that this means, here are some highlights:
        </p>

        <ul>
          <li>Ability to switch the current VM on the fly</li>
          <li>Changes to the user and system VM take effect immediately, and no
          longer are tied to the shell environment, which means you no longer
          have to run env-update followed by source /etc/profile when you
          switch the system VM</li>
          <li>Now has the concept of a "build VM", which is used to emerge
          packages and is configured independently of the system VM</li>
          <li>For each version of Java, ie 1.3, 1.4, 1.5, etc, the build VM can
          be configured as to which vendor and version of a VM to use</li>
          <li>The VM at emerge time will be switched on the fly according to its
          configuration, as well as the dependency of the package. For example,
          some packages won't compile with 1.5. In these cases, a 1.4 VM will be
          used at build time</li>
          <li>Java packages which build with ant will have their build.xml
          rewritten at build time in order to ensure that the correct version of
          Java bytecode is compiled</li>
          <li>Will be able to unmask Java 1.5 soon and be able to handle Java
          1.6 when it comes out this fall</li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Spanish GWN translators</title>
      <body>
      <p>
        Since its reemergence in earlier 2005, the Spanish Gentoo Weekly
        Newsletter has continued to be published thanks to the hard work of a
        few active translators. In order to ensure its constant publishing the
        Spanish GWN translation team is looking for new members to help with
        the task. If you are an advanced speaker of both English and Spanish
        (native not required) and you are interested in collaborating with us,
        please send an e-mail to <mail link="gwn-feedback-es@gentoo.org">
        gwn-feedback-es@gentoo.org</mail> or visit us in <c>#gentoo-gwn-es</c>
        on <c>irc.freenode.net</c>. Many thanks in advance!
      </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Developer of the week</title>
    <section>
      <title>"I'm a crazy mad Russian. Dig it." - Tim Yamin (plasmaroo)</title>
      <body>
      <figure link="/images/gwn/20060703_plasmaroo.jpg"
        short="plasmaroo" caption="Tim Yamin, aka plasmaroo" />

      <p>
        Developer Tim Yamin, better known as plasmaroo, resides in the UK. At
        17, he can recall moving from Russia about 10 years ago. He lives with
        his family and has no pets. There's no wonder why as he refers to them
        as "furry cretins."
      </p>

      <p>
        Tim is studying mathematics and plans to obtain a degree in Computer
        Science. He does not currently work as it's hard to find a flexible
        part-time job to compliment his study schedule. Looking towards the
        future, his dream job would involve lots of blinking LEDs, funky
        hardware, and lots of dollar signs. (Need those dollar signs to fund
        his Gentoo hardware habit.) Not working allows him to devote most of
        his time to Gentoo and coffee ice cream. Who could blame him - it's
        coffee and ice cream!
      </p>

      <p>
        As he describes it, he is often found babbling on IRC, but does manage
        to get in a bit of gaming as he really enjoys playing Enemy Territory.
        He likes to listen to funky music, usually progressive
        DnB/House/Trance/Hip-hop. While plasmaroo doesnt travel much yet, he
        would enjoy going through national parks and the like.
      </p>

      <p>
        When asked what he likes most about Gentoo, plasmaroo replied, "It does
        what I want, and if it doesn't, it will after a five-minute cluebatting
        session." Plasmaroo has worked on Gentoo for three years now. He
        started off working on kernel stuff (gentoo-sources) and then branched
        into other areas. He is part of several teams, including, Release
        Engineering, Documentation, Developer Relations, Kernel, Security,
        Gentoo/IA64, genkernel, and sci-electronics. The contribution that he
        is most proud of is the GLSAMaker system, which has been used for over
        two years now and has pushed out over 700 GLSAs.
      </p>

      <p>
        Plasmaroo's home machines, while obviously all running Gentoo, consist
        of a dual Opteron workstation with 4GB of RAM, a P4 box that compiles
        stuff at an amazingly slow pace and acts as a very overpowered router,
        and four SGI boxes that he plans on using for kernel work. He'd like to
        say that he's using all of these systems as a compile cluster, but he
        has had some rather uncooperative motherboards that keep him busy.
        After his first cup of coffee ice cream, the first application
        plasmaroo launches is konsole and his preferred shell is zsh.
      </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>Heard in the community</title>
    <!-- forums -->
    <section>
      <title>forums</title>
      <body>
      <p><b>Moving away from Freenode?</b></p>
      <p>
        Currently, some users dislike the Freenode IRC network and are
        discussing moving all of the gentoo channels to another network, such
        as OFTC. Would this be something that others would be willing to do or
        are we happy with the service Freenode provides to Gentoo?
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-475821.html">
        Gentoo and "freenode"</uri></li>
      </ul>

      <p><b>How often do you --sync?</b></p>
      <p>
        Is it easier to manage Gentoo if you <c>emerge --sync</c> daily, or is
        it more productive to wait a few weeks or until a package you want
        appears on <uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org">
        http://packages.gentoo.org</uri> before you sync? Post how often you
        <c>emerge --sync</c> in this forum thread.
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-474863.html">
        How often do you sync?</uri></li>
      </ul>
      </body>
    </section>

    <!-- planet.gentoo.org -->
    <section>
      <title>planet.gentoo.org</title>
      <body>
      <p><b>GUADEC</b></p>
      <figure link="/images/gwn/20060703_gentoo-lunch.jpg" short="Gentoo
	    developers" caption="From left to right: foser, suka, dsd, zaheerm" />
      <p>
        A group of Gentoo developers attended the 7th annual GNOME User and
        Developer European Conference (GUADEC), taking place in Spain this year.
        <mail link="suka@gentoo.org">Andreas Proschofsky</mail> was looking
        forward to listening a talk about <uri
        link="http://www.beatniksoftware.com/gimmie/">Gimmie</uri>, a
        next-generation panel for the GNOME desktop, and a speech by Michael
        Meeks about OpenOffice.org. Meeting many interesting people, seeing an
        <uri link="http://laptop.org/">OLPC</uri> prototype and several parties
        were <mail link="dsd@gentoo.org">Daniel Drake's</mail> highlights.
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li><uri
        link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~suka/blog/archives/2006/06/#e2006-06-22T09_07_53.txt">
        Heading to GUADEC</uri></li>
        <li><uri
        link="http://www.reactivated.net/weblog/archives/2006/07/back-from-guadec/">
        Back from GUADEC</uri></li>
        <li><uri
        link="http://zaheer.merali.org/articles/2006/07/02/guadec-is-about-people">
        GUADEC is about people</uri></li>
      </ul>

      <p><b>User Representatives</b></p>
      <p>
        <mail link="mark_alec@gentoo.org">Mark Kowarsky</mail> was busy getting
        in touch with the nominees to be elected as Gentoo user representatives
        during the past week. Some of them declined the nomination, but more
        than fifteen accepted their nomination and provided the necessary
        information.
      </p>

      <ul>
        <li><uri
        link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/mark_alec/2006/06/29/user_representatives_part_1">
        User Representatives</uri></li>
      </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <!-- Gentoo International-->
  <chapter>
    <title>Gentoo International</title>
    <section>
      <title>France: Libre Software Meeting, Nancy</title>
      <body>
      <p>
        The 7th Rencontres Mondiales du Logiciel Libre, also known as Libre
        Software Meeting, will be held on July 4th-8th, 2006, in
        Vandoeuvre-les-Nancy, in the "1er cycle" building of the Faculte des
        Sciences, campus of Henri Poincare - Nancy 1 University. Gentoo will
        have a booth at the event, so be sure to stop by and say hello to
        Damien Krotkine (dams) and Boris Fersing (kernelsensei).
      </p>

      <p>
        You can find more information on the <uri
        link="/proj/en/pr/events/lsm2006-france/index.xml">
        Gentoo Events</uri> project page for the event, and also on the event's
        <uri link="http://www.rmll.info/?lang=en">official homepage</uri>.
      </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>UK: Gentoo UK 2006 Conference, London</title>
      <body>
      <p>
        The 3rd annual Gentoo UK Conference will be held on July 8th in central
        London, at The Resource Centre. Anyone interested in Gentoo is welcome
        to attend. The conference will feature a series of presentations mostly
        given by Gentoo developers, as well as some general discussion and help
        sessions. This is a chance to foster positive relations between users
        and developers of the distribution.
      </p>

      <p>
        You can find more information on the event in Daniel Drake's <uri
        link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~dsd/gentoo-uk-2006/">devspace</uri>.
      </p>
      </body>
    </section>

  </chapter>

<!-- Gentoo in the press -->

<!-- Tips and Tricks -->

<!-- Gentoo developer moves -->
  <chapter>
    <title>Gentoo developer moves</title>
    <section>
      <title>Moves</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          The following developers recently left the Gentoo project:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li><e>none this week</e></li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Adds</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          The following developers recently joined the Gentoo project:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li><e>none this week</e></li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Changes</title>
      <body>
        <p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
          Gentoo project:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Sven Vermeulen (swift) KBase</li>
          <li>Josh Saddler (nightmorph) KBase</li>
          <li>Andrés Pereira (anpereir) KBase</li>
          <li>Łukasz Damentko (rane) KBase</li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

<!-- Gentoo security -->
  <chapter>
    <title>Gentoo security</title>
  <!-- paste from the script -->
<section>
<title>Hashcash: Possible heap overflow</title>
<body>
<p>

    A heap overflow vulnerability in the Hashcash utility could allow an
    attacker to execute arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200606-25.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>EnergyMech: Denial of Service</title>
<body>
<p>

    A Denial of Service vulnerability was discovered in EnergyMech that is
    easily exploitable via IRC.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200606-26.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mutt: Buffer overflow</title>
<body>
<p>

    Mutt contains a buffer overflow that could result in arbitrary code
    execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200606-27.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Horde Web Application Framework: XSS vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    The Horde Web Application Framework is vulnerable to a cross-site scripting
    vulnerability.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200606-28.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Tikiwiki: SQL injection and multiple XSS vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    An SQL injection vulnerability and multiple XSS vulnerabilities have been
    discovered.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200606-29.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Kiax: Arbitrary code execution</title>
<body>
<p>

    A security vulnerability in the iaxclient library could lead to the
    execution of arbitrary code by a remote attacker.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200606-30.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>


  </chapter>
  <!-- Bugzilla -->
  <!-- paste from the script -->
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
      The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri
      link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
      bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the
      development team.  Between 24 June 2006
      and 01 July 2006, activity on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>865 new bugs during this period</li>
          <li>443 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
          <li>30 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 10319 currently open bugs: 53 are labeled 'blocker', 136 are labeled 'critical', and 533 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
       The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
      <li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">Gentoo Games</mail>, with 37
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org">AMD64 Project</mail>, with 27
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org">Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 26
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 23
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="security@gentoo.org">Gentoo Security</mail>, with 20
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="java@gentoo.org">Java team</mail>, with 20
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="dev-portage@gentoo.org">Portage team</mail>, with 12
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=dev-portage@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org">Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 11        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
      </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
       The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
      <li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 29
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for New Packages</mail>, with 25
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org">AMD64 Project</mail>, with 15
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org">Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 11
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="treecleaner@gentoo.org">Gentoo TreeCleaner Project</mail>, with 9
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;assigned_to=treecleaner@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org">Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 9
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
      <li><mail link="java@gentoo.org">Java team</mail>, with 7
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>      </li>
      <li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org">media-video herd</mail>, with 6
        <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-06-24&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-01&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
      </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

  <!-- GWN feedback information -->
  <chapter>
    <title>GWN feedback</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
          Please send us your <mail
          link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN
          better.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <!-- GWN subscription information -->
  <chapter>
    <title>GWN subscription information</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
          To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
          <mail
            link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
        </p> 
        <p>
          To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
          <mail
            link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
          from the e-mail address you are subscribed under.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <!-- Other Languages -->
  <chapter>
    <title>Other languages</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
          The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following
          languages:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/ko/gwn/gwn.xml">Korean</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
          </li>
          <li>
            <uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</guide>
