<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20060731-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>31 July 2006</subtitle>

<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="jkt@gentoo.org">Jan Kundrát</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="kloeri@gentoo.org">Bryan Østergaard</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="nichoj@gentoo.org">Josh Nichols</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="musikc@hotmail.com">Chrissy Fullam</mail>
</author>

<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 31 July
2006.</abstract>
<summary/>

<version>Volume 5, Issue 28</version>
<date>2006-07-31</date>

<!-- Gentoo News -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo news</title>

<section>
<title>Catalyst 2.0 released</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo <uri link="/proj/en/releng/index.xml">Release Engineering</uri>
project is pleased to announce that catalyst 2.0 has been released. The new
catalyst version is a complete re-write from the aging 1.x code base, and
includes several new features and updates, including:
</p>

<ul>
<li>autoresume - attempts to resume a failed build</li>
<li>kerncache - caches the build of the kernels to speed up livecd-stage2</li>
<li>seedcache - use the build output of a previous target if it exists to speed
up the copy</li>
<li>snapcache - cache the snapshot so that it can be bind-mounted into the
chroot</li>
<li>DIGESTS - creates digests in any format supported by <c>shash</c></li>
</ul>

<p>
This version is currently masked in portage under <c>package.mask</c> and will
be unmasked this week for ~arch users. Users of the 2.0_pre series of catalyst
builds will need to perform some steps to ensure a clean upgrade, especially
if you wish to keep your package caches.
</p>

<pre caption="Renaming catalyst directories">
(Rename the cache directory)
# mv -i /var/tmp/catalyst2 /var/tmp/catalyst
Rename the configuration directory)
# mv -i /etc/catalyst2 /etc/catalyst
# cd /etc/catalyst
# sed -i -e 's/catalyst2/catalyst/' *.conf
</pre>

<p>
The online documentation is being written for catalyst 2.0 and will be in place
before 2.0 is marked stable. For now, the example spec templates installed to
<c>/usr/share/doc/catalyst-2.0/examples</c> are the best documentation.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Third anniversary of Gentoo's Bugday</title>
<body>

<p>
Saturday 5th August is the third anniversary of the Gentoo/Bugday project.
This marks a major milestone, and it will be celebrated appropriately
with contests and prizes!
</p>

<p>
Bugday first started out life as <uri link="/proj/en/glep/glep-0006.html">GLEP
6</uri>. From the very beginning the bugday project had the potential to be a
big influence on Gentoo. It has certainly proved its worth in its first 3
years. Lots of new developers have been recruited directly from their Bugday
involvement as users, and others have had their first ebuild experiences from
past Bugdays and have since joined Gentoo projects unrelated to Bugday.
</p>

<p>
Besides being a powerful recruitment tool, users and developers have cooperated
on fixing an astonishing number of bugs on Bugdays. Bugday is one of the
important cornerstones of the Gentoo community. Certainly, Bugday has helped
bridge the often talked about gap between users and developers and the Bugday
IRC channel has long since turned into a channel where ebuild issues and fixes
are discussed daily.
</p>

<p>
Contests:
To celebrate the third anniversary, they will have a number of contests. Users
will battle each other for most solved bugs, most Gentoo knowledge, etc.
</p>

<p>
They are still working on finalizing contests and prizes, but all details should
be announced on the <uri link="http://bugday.gentoo.org">Bugday site</uri>
later this week.
</p>

<p>
Good luck to everybody. The Bugday project hopes that this will be the best
Bugday yet. A big thank you to everybody who's participated in the last three
years -- you've truly helped make Bugday the big success it is today.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo/Java staffing needs</title>
<body>

<p>
As has been the case for some time, the Java team is still atrociously
understaffed. Below, they'll outline a few 'positions' that they would like see
filled. The term 'filled' is used really loosely, and it is meant more as in
the sense of 'these are things we would like people to be working on'. If
current developers are interested, that would be great, but they are also
willing to mentor some fresh blood for the team.
</p>

<ul>
<li>Java generalists</li>
</ul>

<p>
The Gentoo/Java team has tons of Java packages. At last count, it was around
400 or so packages. As one can imagine, this kind of number generates a pretty
constant stream of bug reports and version bump requests.
</p>

<p>
So, basically, the Java team is looking for some people to help out with general
maintenance of their packages. They would expect them to be familiar with Gentoo
and Java (surprise!). If they are not already, they will need to become
familiar with the ins and outs of how Java is handled on Gentoo.
Familiarity with ant, which is used for a large majority of their
packages, would also be very useful.
</p>

<ul>
<li>JBoss maintainer</li>
</ul>

<p>
JBoss is a pretty important app in the enterprise world of Java. It has
been pretty unmaintained for some time now, and could use some love.
Because of the nature of this beast, the Java team would want someone that uses
JBoss on a daily basis, preferably in an enterprise setting, to be the
type of person to maintain this.
</p>

<ul>
<li>Jetty maintainer</li>
</ul>

<p>
Jetty is a web container, like tomcat and resin. It also has been pretty
unmaintained in recent times. Preferably, the person who picks this
fella up uses jetty on a daily basis in an enterprise type setting.
</p>

<ul>
<li>Free Java Hackers</li>
</ul>

<p>
One of illustrious users has been working on working away at getting GCJ
usable as a JDK, in the sense that it can be used to build our packages.  The
Java team does have a handful of other free Java VMs in portage, like kaffe,
sablevm, jamvm, etc. If people were interested, it would be great if
they could get their packages building using these other VMs.
</p>

<ul>
<li>Eclipse / Netbeans maintainers</li>
</ul>

<p>
Eclipse and Netbeans are the primary IDEs for Java. Eclipse is well kept
for the moment, but the plugins haven't been. Netbeans needs a bit of
love though, as it hasn't been updated in awhile.
</p>

<p>
So, if one or more of these sounds interesting and like something you'd
want to do? For starters, you should take a gander over at the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/java">project page</uri>, and check out
various documentation they have. If you are still interested, then contact
<mail link="nichoj@gentoo.org">Josh Nichols</mail>.
</p>

<p>
Other things you can do:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Join the mailing list, <c>gentoo-java</c>. It is pretty low-traffic.</li>
<li>Lurk in the IRC channel, <c>#gentoo-java</c> on irc.freenode.net. It is
also fairly low-traffic, so don't expect immediate responses.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Czech translation of Gentoo documentation finally official</title>
<body>

<p>
After more than one year of hard work, Czech translation team is proud
to announce that they have finally made the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/cs/">Czech translation</uri> official.
That means that interested Czech-speaking users can read the
documentation in their <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/cs/">native
language</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Everyone who can write Czech and understand written English (yeah,
that's you if you read this :) ) is more than welcome to help with our
efforts. All the applicants who want a shiny @gentoo.org e-mail address and
aren't afraid of endless months of tedious work are requested to hang on
at #gentoo-doc on freenode or just drop a mail to <mail
link="jkt@gentoo.org">Jan Kundrát</mail>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Developer of the Week -->

<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>

<section>
<title>Joshua Kinard</title>
<body>

<figure link="/images/gwn/20060731_kumba.jpg"
  short="kumba" caption="Joshua Kinard, aka kumba" />

<p>
Developer Joshua Kinard, known as Kumba, resides in Waldorf, MD, a short drive
outside Washington, D.C. He lives with his parents and has several pets,
including a family dog, two cats, Isis and Leto, and oddly enough, a mouse. The
cats obviously love the mouse. The mouse must not mind either as Kumba said his
family has tried to release the mouse but he just won't leave. At 24, Joshua can
still vividly recall some of the places he and his family have been stationed
throughout his father's Air Force career. Perhaps most memorable were the few
years they lived in Spain, on a military base outside of Madrid.
</p>

<p>
Kumba's interests include some rather uncommon music tastes, such as
Irish/Celtic tunes (especially good bagpipes), Gregorian chants, and some
sub-genre's of metal like therion and blind guardian. He also moderates about
13 IRC channels, mostly Gentoo, and still finds the time to fit in a game of
Diablo 2 now and then.
</p>

<p>
Joshua currently works as a System Administrator for a non-profit organization
near Washington, D.C. The environment ranges among Netware, HP-UX, Linux, and
even Windows. As for the future, he admits that he's not the biggest fan of the
corporate world and has considered pursuing grad school or even a career change.
</p>

<p>
As for Kumba's start with Gentoo, he claims a rather simple beginning. While
using various flavors of Linux, he looked for something that he could use on
his recently acquired 64-bit SPARC, and that search quickly led to Gentoo. He
has been a Gentoo developer since 2004 and currently is the team lead for the
MIPS team, though he also enjoys helping with baselayout, toolchain, and SPARC
teams.
</p>

<p>
The rumors are true, Kumba's home Workstation, a Dual Pentium III, is indeed
running Windows Server 2003 and boasts a hot-swappable RAID5 SCSI array. The
first application any IRC moderator launches is obviously mIRC and Kumba
follows that with AIM/DeadAIM, Winamp, and Firefox. He's also know to track
unusual weather events using Stormlab and to dabble inside of NASA's WorldWind
application. Kumba's other home machines include a dual Athlon MP 2000, acting
as a web server, an old SPARC machine, used for testing, and several SGI boxes:
an Octane used for development, two O2's, one for package testing and one for
kernel testing, and an IP28. He even has an old SGI Indy, from the early 90's,
which he still uses to do kernel testing!</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>

<!-- forums -->

<!-- planet.gentoo.org -->

<section>
<title>planet.gentoo.org</title>
<body>

<p><b>#gentoo-db</b></p>

<p>
Another IRC channel has just opened its (virtual) doors. <c>#gentoo-db</c> is
intended to provide a platform for discussions and development around database
support within Gentoo. Currently MySQL and PostgreSQL people hang out there,
developers maintaining other database-related packages for Gentoo and users are
encouraged to join the channel.
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="http://chtekk.longitekk.com/?p=25">#gentoo-db</uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>State of Gentoo in 5 minutes</b></p>

<p>
<mail link="dberkholz@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholz</mail> held a lightning talk
about Gentoo's current state at this year's <uri
link="http://conferences.oreillynet.com/os2006/">OSCON</uri> covering Portage
2.1, the upcoming 2006.1 release (including a new Installer version) and support
for multiple overlays. His talk is also mentioned in a recent <uri
link="http://business.newsforge.com/article.pl?sid=06/07/27/161239">NewsForge</uri> article.
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="http://spyderous.livejournal.com/77772.html">State
of Gentoo in 5 minutes</uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>Wanted: PowerPC Release Testers</b></p>

<p>
The call for <uri
link="/news/en/gwn/20060626-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1_sect1">Release
Testers</uri> about a month ago wasn't that successful for Gentoo's PowerPC
team. Only less then a handful of people with supported machines responded.
<mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail> now started another call for
Release Testers - if you can help out (he listed a list of supported machines
in his blog entry) please contact <mail link="roger55@gentoo.org">Roger
Miliker</mail>.
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/pylon/2006/07/27/wanted_powerpc_release_testers">
Wanted: PowerPC Release Testers</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo International-->

<!-- Gentoo in the press -->

<!-- Tips and Tricks -->

<!-- Gentoo developer moves -->

<chapter>

<title>Gentoo developer moves</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Henrik Brix Andersen (brix)</li>
<li>Michael Kohl (citizen428)</li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Wolf Giesen (frilled) Security</li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo security -->

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>

<!-- paste from the script -->

<section>
<title>Wireshark: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>

<p>
Wireshark (formerly known as Ethereal) is vulnerable to several security
issues, potentially allowing the execution of arbitrary code by a remote
attacker.
</p>

<p>
For more information, please see the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200607-09.xml">GLSA
Announcement</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Samba: Denial of Service vulnerability</title>
<body>

<p>
A large number of share connection requests could cause a Denial of Service
within Samba.
</p>

<p>
For more information, please see the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200607-10.xml">GLSA
Announcement</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>TunePimp: Buffer overflow</title>
<body>

<p>
A vulnerability in TunePimp has been reported which could lead to the
execution of arbitrary code.
</p>

<p>
For more information, please see the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200607-11.xml">GLSA
Announcement</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>OpenOffice.org: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>

<p>
OpenOffice.org is affected by three security vulnerabilities which can be
exploited to allow the execution of arbitrary code by a remote attacker.
</p>

<p>
For more information, please see the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200607-12.xml">GLSA
Announcement</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Audacious: Multiple heap and buffer overflows</title>
<body>

<p>
The adplug library included in Audacious is vulnerable to various overflows
that could result in the execution of arbitrary code.
</p>

<p>
For more information, please see the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-200607-13.xml">GLSA
Announcement</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Bugzilla -->

<!-- paste from the script -->

<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>

<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">New bug rankings</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the
development team.  Between 23 July 2006
and 30 July 2006, activity on the site has resulted in:
</p>

<ul>
<li>679 new bugs during this period</li>
<li>289 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
<li>19 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
</ul>

<p>
Of the 10687 currently open bugs: 52 are labeled 'blocker', 134 are labeled
'critical', and 533 are labeled 'major'.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>

<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>

<ul>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">Gentoo Games</mail>, with 22
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org">Java team</mail>, with 19
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="dev-portage@gentoo.org">Portage team</mail>, with 15
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=dev-portage@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 14
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org">Gentoo KDE team</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org">Gentoo Security</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="python@gentoo.org">Python Gentoo Team</mail>, with 6
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=python@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">Xavier Neys</mail>, with 6
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=neysx@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>

<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this
period are:
</p>

<ul>
<li><mail link="maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for New Packages</mail>, with 33
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org">Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org">AMD64 Project</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kernel@gentoo.org">Gentoo Kernel Bug Wranglers and Kernel Maintainers</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;assigned_to=kernel@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org">media-video herd</mail>, with 7
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 7
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="netmon@gentoo.org">Netmon Herd</mail>, with 6
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;assigned_to=netmon@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">Gentoo Games</mail>, with 6
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-07-23&amp;chfieldto=2006-07-30&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- GWN feedback information -->
<chapter>

<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Please send us your <mail
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN
better.
</p>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

<!-- GWN subscription information -->
<chapter>

<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p> 

<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the e-mail address you are subscribed under.
</p>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Other Languages -->
<chapter>

<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following
languages:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/zh_cn/gwn/gwn.xml">Chinese (Simplified)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ko/gwn/gwn.xml">Korean</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

</guide>
