<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20070723-newsletter.xml" disclaimer="draft" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>23 July 2007</subtitle>

<author title="Editor">
<mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Assistant Editor">
<mail link="musikc@gentoo.org">Chrissy Fullam</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="cla@gentoo.org">Dawid Weglinski</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="john.m.alberts@gmail.com">John Alberts</mail> 
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="davide.italiano@gmail.com">Davide Italiano</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="jtp@nc.rr.com">James</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="yoswink@gentoo.org">Jose Luis Rivero</mail>
</author>

<!-- Be sure to add yourself if you write an article -->

<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 23 July
2007.</abstract>
<summary/>

<version>Volume 6, Issue 30</version>
<date>2007-07-23</date>

<!-- Gentoo News -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>

<section>
<title>Gentoo Realtime Guide</title> 
<body>
<p>
<mail link="flameeyes@gentoo.org">Diego Pettenò</mail> completed a <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/desktop/sound/realtime.xml">guide</uri> on enabling realtime support for multimedia processes. If you were playing with a MIDI instrument connected to a software synthesizer, a high latency would yeild improper results. However, if you use multimedia process only to play songs while doing other tasks such as surfing the web, you don't need realtime support.</p>
<p>
This guide was written for people who need the maximum priority for multimedia support. The beauty of this guide is that it will show you a simple method to get realtime support, without any exrta software: you have only to set up <c>PAM</c> correctly.</p>
<p>
Thanks a lot to Diego for this nice guide and also to <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Josh Saddler</mail> for editing the guide.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Compilation Optimization Guide</title> 
<body>

<p>
<mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Josh Saddler</mail> completed writing the Compilation Optimization <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gcc-optimization.xml"> guide</uri>, which has been added to the Gentoo documentation repository. This guide is an introducition to optimize your compiled code using sane <c>CFLAGS</c> and <c>CXXFLAGS</c> and also includes an introduction to optimization in general. This guide was highly requested from users on the forums, Bugzilla, and IRC. Thanks to Josh, Gentoo has a Compilation Optimization Guide.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo Artwork Project looking for volunteers</title>
<body>
<p>
<mail link="cla@gentoo.org">Dawid Weglinski</mail> has recently kicked off a new <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/desktop/artwork/index.xml">project</uri> aimed at officially maintaining all Gentoo-related artwork and Gentoo desktop themes. The team is looking for new members and would appreciate any artwork contributions from the community.</p>
<p>
Qualifications for interested contributors should be a base knowledge on creating artwork, use of the related programs, as well as a sense of esthetics. There is particular interest for people with experience in configuring graphic environments (kde, gnome, xfce), especially with gtk based applications. If anyone is interested, join #Gentoo-desktop for discussions.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo Alpha Project Status Update</title> 

<body>
<p>
A new <uri link="/proj/en/base/alpha/status/status-20070721.xml">Gentoo Alpha Status Update</uri> has been released. Check out the update to find out more about the changes in core system packages (kernel, gcc, glibc), general port overview and even the latest news on the new aboot revision and security improvements. 
</p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>
<!-- Developer of the Week -->

<!-- Heard in the community -->

<!-- forums.gentoo.org -->

<!-- planet.gentoo.org -->

<!-- gentoo-user -->

<!-- gentoo-dev -->

<!-- gentoo-catalyst -->

<!-- gentoo-cluster -->

<!-- gentoo-embedded -->

<!-- gentoo-security -->

<!-- Gentoo International-->

<!-- Gentoo in the press -->

<!-- Tips and Tricks -->
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>

<section>
<title>New update script</title>
<body>

<p>
Back in the December 4th issue of the GWN, a nice update script called update-world was featured in the Tips and Tricks section.  Since December, several more update scripts have been posted by budding developers. One such script is simply called update.</p>
<p>
Update was started based on conversations around guenther's <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-494331.html">upgrade</uri> and count_zero's <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-p-3798148.html#3798148">update-world</uri>. It has been in testing since mid-January, 2007, and one such tester event boasts on its "flawless" performance.</p>
<p>
So, what exactly does this script do?  Update is similiar to other update scripts in that it will automatically skip failed packages and continue to emerge the rest of an emerge list.  In addition, it has built-in support for automatically running revdep-rebuild, auto-mounting a tmpfs to speedup emerges, sync first, fetch files first, special options for updating a server via a cron job, and more. Another great feature is that it automatically hides most of the cruft from compiling packages, which makes it much easier to see einfo and ewarns.  You can also further reduce or even increase the log output with the use of the -q and -v options.</p>
<p>
Click <uri link="http://phpfi.com/214168">here</uri> to view a sample output from a gcc compile.</p>
<pre caption="Getting the script">
# wget -O /sbin/updatescript.sh
# chmod +x /sbin/updatescript.sh
</pre>
<p>
Most users may likely find this script as an easy way to update their entire system.</p>
<pre caption="This is easily done with:">
# updatescript.sh
or, if you want to sync the portage tree first
# updatescript.sh -s
</pre>
<p>
The original forum thread and a download link for the script can be found <uri link=" http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-546828.html">here</uri>.
Thanks to steveL for providing this script.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo developer moves -->

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo developer moves</title>

<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo security -->

<!-- paste from the script -->

<!-- Gentoo package moves -->

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo package moves</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>
This section lists packages that have either been moved or added to the tree
and packages that have had their "last rites" announcement given to be removed
in the future. The package removals come from many locations, including the <uri
link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners">Treecleaners</uri> and various developers. Most
packages which are listed under the Last Rites section are in need of some love
and care and can remain in the tree if proper maintainership is established.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- paste from the script -->

<section>
<title>Last Rites:</title>
<body>

<!-- paste from email -->

<table>

<tr>
<th>Package:</th>
<th>Removal date:</th>
<th>Contact:</th>
</tr>

</table>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Bugzilla -->

<!-- paste from the script -->

<!-- GWN feedback information -->

<chapter>

<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The GWN is staffed by volunteers and members of the community who submit ideas
and articles.  If you are interested in writing for the GWN, have feedback on an
article that we have posted, or just have an idea or article that you would
like to submit to the GWN, please send us your <mail
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN
better.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- GWN subscription information -->

<chapter>

<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p> 

<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the e-mail address you are subscribed under.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Other Languages -->

<chapter>

<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following
languages:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/zh_cn/gwn/gwn.xml">Chinese (Simplified)</uri>
</li>
<!-- <li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li> -->
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/el/gwn/gwn.xml">Greek</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ko/gwn/gwn.xml">Korean</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/sk/gwn/gwn.xml">Slovak</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

</guide>
