<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" disclaimer="draft" link="20070820-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>20 August 2007</subtitle>

<author title="Editor">
<mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor">
<mail link="musikc@gentoo.org">Chrissy Fullam</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="dsnider@thesniderpad.com">David Snider</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="john.m.alberts@gmail.com">John Alberts</mail>
</author>

<author title="Contributor">
<mail link="matt@matt.net.nz">Matt Courtney</mail>
</author>

<!-- Be sure to add yourself if you write an article -->

<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 20 August
2007.</abstract>
<summary/>

<version>Volume 6, Issue 34</version>
<date>2007-08-20</date>

<!-- Gentoo News -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>

<section>
<title>Interview with the Council Nominees</title>

<body>

<p>
In response to the upcoming Council elections, the GWN staff wanted to 
highlight our Council nominees. Our goal is to aid in the voting decision 
process by highlighting their current roles as well as provide insight by means
of the below interview questions.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<th>Nominee</th>
<th>Current roles</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>Wernfried Haas (amne)</ti>
<ti>Forums Lead</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>Petteri Räty (betelgeuse)</ti>
<ti>Java Lead, Developer Relations (Recruiters Lead)</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Christel Dahlskjær (christel)</ti>
<ti>User Relations Lead (Adopt-a-Dev), PR Lead, Developer Relations (Recruitment, Conflict Resolution Lead), Gentoo/Alpha, Gentoo/Mips, QA, Bugday</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Donnie Berkholz (dberkholz)</ti>
<ti>Desktop lead, X, Science, clustering</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Tobias Scherbaum (dertobi123)</ti>
<ti>Gentoo/PPC, Gentoo/HPPA</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Diego Pettenò (flameeyes)</ti>
<ti>Gentoo/Alt</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Sune Kloppenborg Jeppesen (jaervosz)</ti>
<ti>security</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Markus Ullmann (jokey)</ti>
<ti>Overlays Lead, Sunrise Co-Lead, UserRel, Arches: arm and x86, ldap, net-irc, netmon herd maintainer</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Luca Barbato (lu_zero)</ti>
<ti>Gentoo/PPC, Video Lead</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Roy Marples (uberlord)</ti>
<ti>Gentoo/FreeBSD Lead, baselayout, basesystem,networking</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Mike Frysinger (vapier)</ti>
<ti>Games Lead, Toolchain, Base System, Embedded</ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>Peter Weller (welp)</ti>
<ti>Gentoo/AMD64, Bugday, Xfce, Gentoo/FreeBSD, Gentoo/*BSD, net-irc, www-servers</ti>
</tr>

</table>

<!-- Question 1 -->
<p>
<b>In what way do you see yourself helping to fulfill the role of the 
council?</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li><c>Wernfried Haas (amne):</c> Communication, decision making, having a 
strong council, and resolving the Code of Conduct situation. Communication: 
While the council is the governing body of Gentoo, it is important to stay in 
touch with the people who voted for the council in the first place. That means 
announcing meetings, posting logs and summaries thereof so people know what you
are doing. If no one else does, I would be willing to take care of this. 
Decision making: As I see it, the council is supposed to make decisions, but 
not work them out by itself. The best way to do so is gathering input from the 
whole community and decide what's best instead of having a closed process that 
only involves the council members and a select few. Having a strong council: I 
think the council should be strong in its decisions, but they should be made 
based on the input from the community. Get the CoC situation fixed: Without 
specifics, I'm interested in finally having a solution that enforces the CoC on
both users and developers and has clearly defined roles and authorities without
overlaps between different projects. That doesn't mean moderating opinions, but
clearly saying no to abusive behaviour, from whomever it's coming. I also think
that social problems should and cannot be solved with technical solutions 
alone, but only human interaction.</li>
<li><c>Petteri Räty (betelgeuse):</c> For the most part, taking part in the 
discussions and actively pushing things forward as needed.</li>
<li><c>Donnie Berkholz (dberkholz)</c> declined to answer, alternatively he 
suggests that you read his 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/council/voting-logs/council-2007-nominees.xml">manifesto</uri></li>
<li><c>Tobias Scherbaum (dertobi123):</c> As I'm a silent-guy who's following 
lists and discussions constantly, I do not take part in most of them; however, 
I recognize the pro's and con's of suggestions from an other point of view than
people have when they're actually involved with this specific discussion. This 
allows me to make decisions based on what's good for Gentoo or on what's a 
better technical implementation.</li>
<li><c>Diego Pettenò (flameeyes):</c> I really don't, as it is, as the past 
council's have had no actual role, just one more bureaucratic organ. I hope 
things change this time, but I won't count on it.</li>
<li><c>Markus Ullmann (jokey):</c> As being part of the dev crowd for about one
and a half year now, including being lead of a project for more than a year, I 
think I have seen enough tops and flops to know what is good for Gentoo and 
what is bad.</li>
<li><c>Roy Marples (uberlord):</c> By providing level headed judgement in 
technical decisions. I may also brandish a large stick when necessary.</li>
<li><c>Luca Barbato (lu_zero):</c> I don't think there is much in particular, I
try to be balanced and I think that's probably what a council member should be.
I try to keep a cool mind and have others not lose their temper. I don't mind 
being wrong and I try to take the input from everybody, no matter how rude they
could be, I'm interested in the content, I couldn't care less about the form in
which it is delivered.</li>
<li><c>Sune Kloppenborg Jeppesen (jaervosz):</c> My role in Gentoo is a bit 
different than most other devs I believe. I've never taken on the 
responsibility of maintaining ebuilds. I've been helping out mostly on the 
Security Team over the years, primarily with GLSA coordination. When I have 
time I also try to help out with GNAP development and very rarely I get time to
do a bit of documentation. For the Security Team it has always been important 
to have good relations with ebuild maintainers, arch teams and upstream to 
ensure that we get things fixed as quick as possible. So my main areas of 
interest (also for the council) is a bit less technical and I try to focus more
on the community side. I will try to keep Gentoo as open and friendly as 
possible.</li>
</ul>

<!-- Question 2 -->
<p>
<b>What drives you to run for the Gentoo Council?</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li><c>Wernfried Haas (amne):</c> Because I care. I guess some people may 
disagree with what I'm suggesting or what I did before, e.g. as the proctors 
lead. Feel free to do so, no offence taken. In any case my motivation is that I
care about Gentoo and its future. If you think my ideas are bad and I suck, 
feel free to vote for someone who sucks less.</li>
<li><c>Petteri Räty (betelgeuse)</c> declined to answer, alternatively he 
suggests that you read his 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/council/voting-logs/council-2007-nominees.xml">manifesto</uri></li>
<li><c>Donnie Berkholz (dberkholz)</c> declined to answer, alternatively he 
suggests that you read his 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/council/voting-logs/council-2007-nominees.xml">manifesto</uri></li>
<li><c>Tobias Scherbaum (dertobi123):</c> The time I've spent with Gentoo in 
the past few years has shown my involvement. Starting as a user, helping others
in the forums and on mailing-lists, I quickly started contributing. First with 
German translations of GWN and documentation, for which I became responsible 
quite fast. Afterwards I took the ebuild quiz and helped our PPC team in 
maintaining the stable-tree and started building the release-media for HPPA, 
plus I'm maintaining several packages. Running for the council is another 
logical step of involvement.</li>
<li><c>Diego Pettenò (flameeyes):</c> I made clear in the past, in my blog, 
what I think of the council and the way it's currently useless; if my fellow 
developers will decide to vote for me, it would be a clear sign that enough of 
them wants to see something done, for good or bad.</li>
<li><c>Markus Ullmann (jokey):</c> In the opensource community you don't moan 
about others not doing the right thing, you simply do it yourself.</li>
<li><c>Roy Marples (uberlord):</c> I didn't run for Council, I was nominated by
more people than I thought possible. So you could say I'm driven by the 
community.</li>
<li><c>Luca Barbato (lu_zero):</c> I hope to help getting stuff delivered. Last
year we started lots of interesting stuff, we are slowly improving, BUT 
sometimes we've got too many heated discussions that made us archiving less 
than expected. I'd like to have the next year have more code implemented and 
less angry feelings around.</li>
<li><c>Sune Kloppenborg Jeppesen (jaervosz):</c> First of all a desire to help 
and try to make a difference. Secondly the latest round of controversy have 
both scared and encouraged me.</li>
</ul>

<!-- Question 3 -->
<p>
<b> What qualifications do you have for running a large open source 
project?</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li><c>Wernfried Haas (amne):</c> I've been one of the Gentoo Forums leads for 
a while, and so far they haven't kicked me from that job. I think I understand 
the social processes within Gentoo quite well, including integrating the forums
mods officially into Gentoo, and some first hand experience from spending some 
time in devrel and the proctors project.</li>
<li><c>Petteri Räty (betelgeuse)</c> declined to answer, alternatively he 
suggests that you read his 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/council/voting-logs/council-2007-nominees.xml">manifesto</uri></li>
<li><c>Donnie Berkholz (dberkholz)</c> declined to answer, alternatively he 
suggests that you read his 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/council/voting-logs/council-2007-nominees.xml">manifesto</uri></li>
<li><c>Tobias Scherbaum (dertobi123):</c> I was responsible for managing German
documentation translations within Gentoo a while ago, but no real experience in
running a large OSS project.</li>
<li><c>Diego Pettenò (flameeyes):</c> None, I suppose; I'm not one of the 
longest time developers, I don't have much experience with leading projects, 
opensource or otherwise, I'm more a simple jack, and I like being one. But 
jacks might be something the council needs more, to stop caring about the 
"political" views and start tackling technical issues.</li>
<li><c>Markus Ullmann (jokey):</c> As already pointed out in the first 
question, I am lead of more than one project already and they seem to work out 
nice so it must be okay how I handle things. Other than that, I've lead and 
organized some larger projects with 60-80 people, so even managing larger 
groups of people is not completely new to me.</li>
<li><c>Roy Marples (uberlord):</c> 2.5 years of Gentoo baselayout development I
lead the Gentoo/FreeBSD effort. Both of these involve a large amount of 
interaction with other Gentoo projects and our user community.</li>
<li><c>Luca Barbato (lu_zero):</c> I have some experience being in the 
management of the early gentoo, I was and I'm still involved in other projects 
like ffmpeg and MPlayer, I'm the current leader of a smaller university project
that I'm striving to make bloom, LScube. And I have the will and passion to 
keep doing what I start.</li>
<li><c>Sune Kloppenborg Jeppesen (jaervosz):</c> As for similar jobs in the 
past I've had years of experience with Gentoo, I've been on several boards for 
volunteer organizations, I'm the treasurer of one of them with an annual budget
of 10k+, I've been sysadminning Linux/Gentoo full time for 3+ years and I've 
been running my own full time one man company.</li>
</ul>

<!-- Question 4 --> 
<p>
<b>How do you think that your participation will help Gentoo resolve it's 
problems or attain its goals?</b>
</p>
<ul>
<li><c>amne</c> declined to answer but suggests you reference his answers to 
question #1.</li>
<li><c>Petteri Räty (betelgeuse):</c> I am usually cool headed and base 
decisions on facts, not emotions. As for the goals, they should be defined 
first.</li>
<li><c>Donnie Berkholz (dberkholz):</c> By proposing solutions to the problems 
and concrete suggestions for reaching our goals, then putting them into action.
I've already begun some of this on my blog with a recent post on improving our 
code quality.</li>
<li><c>Tobias Scherbaum (dertobi123):</c> Gentoo doesn't have any general goals
we're trying to achieve. Based on the input I got after my talk at the Gentoo 
UK Meeting, defining such general goals and getting people to agree on them is 
nearly impossible, or at least very difficult. Defining goals within projects 
(and lots of projects already do this!) will help Gentoo much more in my 
opinion. But we need to be more open about this. The problems include 
gentoo-dev flamefests and the constant lack of manpower. The first one is 
partly resolved with splitting up -dev into the -dev, -project, and 
-dev-announce mailinglists. The other part of that particular problem isn't 
solvable, we'll always have to deal with - lets call them - "special" people, 
they're part of our community like everyone else. We can't change them, we need
to change or way of interaction and communication with them. The second one can
only be solved by being more open and trying to get even more people involved 
with Gentoo. Sunrise was a good start, we need more projects and ideas like 
this! I'm aware that we have some other problems as well, but yeah .. I've 
chosen these two.</li>
<li><c>Diego Pettenò (flameeyes):</c> Not by being in the council: goals are 
attained by doing what needs to be done, not by discussing no one knows what. 
Most of the problems of Gentoo are technical and are usually solved by 
analysing the issue and implementing a solution. Up to now most of the issues 
were analysed and over-analysed, solutions were proposed, and discussed 
"ad nauseam", but never actually implemented. I know, it sounds harsh and 
negative, but I made myself clear before on thinking the Council hasn't been 
doing anything good, me included, so it shouldn't come as a surprise.</li>
<li><c>Markus Ullmann (jokey):</c> People seek for goals to work towards. We 
have both users and developers with quite good ideas which just either sit 
around or are dropped due to inabilities or no motivation. I'd like to pick 
those up and motivate people to get back to them or find other options like 
involving others. From what I see, at the moment, we just lack motivation. We 
have many really skilled devs already and the group still grows more. So the 
aim for me is obvious.</li>
<li><c>Roy Marples (uberlord):</c> My participation with solve neither, but 
hopefully make the eternal journey smoother.</li>
<li><c>Luca Barbato (lu_zero):</c> The main perceived problem in Gentoo is the 
lack of new stuff on a side and how slow things get delivered. I think about 
half of it is just a wrong perception and the other half is due to the flames 
led by the first half. I'll try to help on both sides.</li>
<li><c>Sune Kloppenborg Jeppesen (jaervosz):</c> I hope that my participation 
will be able to cool things down a bit and further volunteer cooperation within
Gentoo.</li>
</ul>

<!-- No response yet -->
<p>
The GWN staff received no reply to inquiries, no interview is available as a 
result for the following nominees:
</p>
<ul>
<li><c>Christel Dahlskjær (christel)</c></li>
<li><c>Mike Frysinger (vapier)</c></li>
<li><c>Peter Weller (welp)</c></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
<!-- Developer of the Week -->

<!-- Heard in the community -->

<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>

<!-- forums -->

<!-- planet.gentoo.org -->

<section>
<title>planet.gentoo.org</title>
<body>

<p>
<b>Java stabilization plans</b>
</p>

<p>
Gentoo's Java Team is out for stabilization of some major packages, namely
Java 1.6 and Netbeans 5.5. The latter one has been already marked stable
for x86, the former one has been held back by a Javadoc bug - which is now
fixed. <mail link="betelgeuse@gentoo.org">Petteri Räty</mail> filed bugs
for the x86 and AMD64 architecture teams to let them spread out their
stable keywords.
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/betelgeuse/2007/08/17/java_1_6_going_stable">Java 1.6 going stable</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/betelgeuse/2007/08/17/netbeans_5_5_stabilization">Netbeans 5.5 stabilization</uri></li>
</ul>

<p>
<b>git-lkml</b>
</p>

<p>
Proposing patches for the Linux kernel isn't that simple, like 
<mail link="phreak@gentoo.org">Christian Heim</mail> discovered. Being used to
the easiness of Subversion handling git is somewhat different hence he
decided to document the necessary steps in his blog.
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="http://blog.barfoo.org/2007/08/16/git-lkml-for-stupid-people-like-me/">git-lkml for stupid people (like me)</uri></li>
</ul>

<p>
<b>We are flooded with bugs!</b>
</p>

<p>
<mail link="opfer@gentoo.org">Christian Faulhammer</mail> plotted a graph
out of old GWN Bugzilla statistics showing the growing number of open bug
reports in Gentoo's bugzilla since 2003. While 10.000 open bugs is an
impressive amount though, about 2.500 of these bugs are requests for new
packages, thus not affecting packages currently in Gentoo's Portage Tree.
</p>

<p>
In a follow-up mail to the <mail>gentoo-project@gentoo.org</mail>
mailing-list <mail link="dberkholz@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholz</mail> posted
links to Bugzilla functions which can also be used to plot Bugzilla stats.
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.faulhammer.org/index.php?option=com_content&amp;task=view&amp;id=194&amp;Itemid=99999999">We are flooded with bugs!</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.project/145">
Re: Bug statistics and your opinion/facts</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- gentoo-user -->

<!-- gentoo-dev -->

<!-- gentoo-catalyst -->

<!-- gentoo-cluster -->

<!-- gentoo-embedded -->

<!-- gentoo-security -->

<!-- Gentoo International-->

<!-- Gentoo in the press -->

<!-- Tips and Tricks -->

<!-- Gentoo developer moves -->

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo developer moves</title>

<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>Jason Smathers (jsin) net-ftp herd</e></li>
<li><e>Christian Hoffmann (hoffie) PHP herd</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo security -->

<!-- paste from the script -->

<!-- Gentoo package moves -->

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo package moves</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>
This section lists packages that have either been moved or added to the tree
and packages that have had their "last rites" announcement given to be removed
in the future. The package removals come from many locations, including the <uri
link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners">Treecleaners</uri> and various developers. Most
packages which are listed under the Last Rites section are in need of some love
and care and can remain in the tree if proper maintainership is established.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- paste Add/Removes from the script -->
<section>
<title>Removals:</title>
<body>

<table>

<tr>
<th>Package:</th>
<th>Removal date:</th>
<th>Contact:</th>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>kde-base/kworldwatch</ti>
<ti>16 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="keytoaster@gentoo.org">Tobias Heinlein</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>dev-java/javahelp-bin</ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="betelgeuse@gentoo.org">Petteri Räty</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>x11-misc/fsv</ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="drac@gentoo.org">Samuli Suominen</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>www-misc/libapreq2</ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="hollow@gentoo.org">Benedikt Boehm</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>dev-ruby/mod_ruby</ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="phreak@gentoo.org">Christian Heim</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti>dev-python/mod_python</ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="phreak@gentoo.org">Christian Heim</mail></ti>
</tr>

</table>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Additions:</title>
<body>

<table>

<tr>
<th>Package:</th>
<th>Addition date:</th>
<th>Contact:</th>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-ruby;name=id3lib-ruby">dev-ruby/id3lib-ruby</uri></ti>
<ti>13 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="omp@gentoo.org">David Shakaryan</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=net-im;name=telepathy-mission-control">net-im/telepathy-mission-control</uri></ti>
<ti>13 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="coldwind@gentoo.org">Santiago M. Mola</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=net-im;name=empathy">net-im/empathy</uri></ti>
<ti>13 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="coldwind@gentoo.org">Santiago M. Mola</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=media-gfx;name=raw-thumbnailer">media-gfx/raw-thumbnailer</uri></ti>
<ti>13 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="angelos@gentoo.org">Christoph Mende</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=x11-misc;name=xnee">x11-misc/xnee</uri></ti>
<ti>13 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="drac@gentoo.org">Samuli Suominen</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=games-arcade;name=whichwayisup">games-arcade/whichwayisup</uri></ti>
<ti>13 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="coldwind@gentoo.org">Santiago M. Mola</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-php;name=roadsend-php">dev-php/roadsend-php</uri></ti>
<ti>14 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="hkbst@gentoo.org">Marijn Schouten</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-ruby;name=haml">dev-ruby/haml</uri></ti>
<ti>15 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="trapni@gentoo.org">Christian Parpart</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-perl;name=RTF-Writer">dev-perl/RTF-Writer</uri></ti>
<ti>15 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="ian@gentoo.org">Christian Hartmann</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=games-puzzle;name=amoebax">games-puzzle/amoebax</uri></ti>
<ti>15 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="mr_bones_@gentoo.org">Michael Sterrett</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-python;name=pygsl">dev-python/pygsl</uri></ti>
<ti>16 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="bicatali@gentoo.org">Sebastien Fabbro</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=app-misc;name=irtrans-irclient">app-misc/irtrans-irclient</uri></ti>
<ti>16 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="hd_brummy@gentoo.org">Joerg Bornkessel</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=app-misc;name=irtrans-irserver">app-misc/irtrans-irserver</uri></ti>
<ti>16 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="hd_brummy@gentoo.org">Joerg Bornkessel</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=kde-base;name=kworldclock">kde-base/kworldclock</uri></ti>
<ti>16 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="keytoaster@gentoo.org">Tobias Heinlein</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=media-libs;name=libdiscid">media-libs/libdiscid</uri></ti>
<ti>17 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="coldwind@gentoo.org">Santiago M. Mola</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=media-sound;name=picard">media-sound/picard</uri></ti>
<ti>17 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="coldwind@gentoo.org">Santiago M. Mola</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-php;name=PEAR-Mail_mimeDecode">dev-php/PEAR-Mail_mimeDecode</uri></ti>
<ti>17 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="hoffie@gentoo.org">Christian Hoffmann</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=app-dicts;name=aspell-pt-br">app-dicts/aspell-pt-br</uri></ti>
<ti>17 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="philantrop@gentoo.org">Wulf Krueger</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=net-ftp;name=cmdftp">net-ftp/cmdftp</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="jsin@gentoo.org">Jason Smathers</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=app-misc;name=geneweb">app-misc/geneweb</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="tupone@gentoo.org">Alfredo Tupone</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=gnustep-base;name=gnustep-back-cairo">gnustep-base/gnustep-back-cairo</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="grobian@gentoo.org">Fabian Groffen</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=virtual;name=gnustep-back">virtual/gnustep-back</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="voyageur@gentoo.org">Bernard Cafarelli</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=app-dicts;name=aspell-la">app-dicts/aspell-la</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="philantrop@gentoo.org">Wulf Krueger</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=app-dicts;name=aspell-lt">app-dicts/aspell-lt</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="philantrop@gentoo.org">Wulf Krueger</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-util;name=mpatch">dev-util/mpatch</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="robbat2@gentoo.org">Robin H. Johnson</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=sys-block;name=fio">sys-block/fio</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="robbat2@gentoo.org">Robin H. Johnson</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=sys-block;name=seekwatcher">sys-block/seekwatcher</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="robbat2@gentoo.org">Robin H. Johnson</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=media-sound;name=tunapie">media-sound/tunapie</uri></ti>
<ti>18 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="drac@gentoo.org">Samuli Suominen</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-perl;name=GSSAPI">dev-perl/GSSAPI</uri></ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="ian@gentoo.org">Christian Hartmann</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=www-apache;name=libapreq2">www-apache/libapreq2</uri></ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="hollow@gentoo.org">Benedikt Boehm</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=www-apache;name=mod_python">www-apache/mod_python</uri></ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="phreak@gentoo.org">Christian Heim</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=dev-ruby;name=text-hyphen">dev-ruby/text-hyphen</uri></ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="graaff@gentoo.org">Hans de Graaff</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=www-apache;name=mod_ruby">www-apache/mod_ruby</uri></ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="phreak@gentoo.org">Christian Heim</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=sys-fs;name=archfs">sys-fs/archfs</uri></ti>
<ti>19 Aug 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="jokey@gentoo.org">Markus Ullmann</mail></ti>
</tr>

</table>

</body>
</section>

<!-- paste Last Rites from the script -->
<section>
<title>Last Rites:</title>
<body>
<table>

<tr>
<th>Package:</th>
<th>Removal date:</th>
<th>Contact:</th>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=mail-filter;name=spamassassin-ruledujour">mail-filter/spamassassin-ruledujour</uri></ti>
<ti>14 Sep 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="robbat2@gentoo.org">Robin H. Johnson</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=www-apps;name=ids">www-apps/ids</uri></ti>
<ti>15 Sep 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="wrobel@gentoo.org">Gunnar Wrobel</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=media-sound;name=usbmidi">media-sound/usbmidi</uri></ti>
<ti>17 Sep 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="drac@gentoo.org">Samuli Suominen</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=media-video;name=xmps">media-video/xmps</uri></ti>
<ti>17 Sep 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="drac@gentoo.org">Samuli Suominen</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=media-sound;name=mp3kult">media-sound/mp3kult</uri></ti>
<ti>19 Sep 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="drac@gentoo.org">Samuli Suominen</mail></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
<ti><uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=net-misc;name=ebayagent">net-misc/ebayagent</uri></ti>
<ti>20 Sep 2007</ti>
<ti><mail link="ian@gentoo.org">Christian Hartmann</mail></ti>
</tr>

</table>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Bugzilla -->

<!-- paste from the script -->
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>

<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#bugs-stats">Statistics</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#bugs-closed">Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#bugs-new">New bug rankings</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section id="bugs-stats">
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the
development team.  Between 12 August 2007
and 18 August 2007, activity on the site has resulted in:
</p>

<ul>
<li>519 new bugs during this period</li>
<li>303 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
<li>22 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
<li>111 closed as NEEDINFO/WONTFIX/CANTFIX/INVALID/UPSTREAM during this period</li>
<li>110 bugs marked as duplicates during this period</li>
</ul>
<p>
Of the 9873 currently open bugs: 12 are labeled 'blocker', 101 are labeled
'critical', and 350 are labeled 'major'.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section id="bugs-closed">
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>

<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>

<ul>
<li><mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">Xavier Neys</mail>, with 22
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=neysx@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org">Java team</mail>, with 20
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">Gentoo Games</mail>, with 15
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org">AMD64 Project</mail>, with 14
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org">Gentoo Security</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="strerror@gentoo.org">Benjamin Smee (strerror)</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=strerror@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="hanno@gentoo.org">Hanno Boeck</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=hanno@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org">media-video herd</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section id="bugs-new">
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>

<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this
period are:
</p>

<ul>
<li><mail link="maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for New Packages</mail>, with 12
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org">AMD64 Project</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">Gentoo Games</mail>, with 7
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 6
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org">Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 6
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="toolchain@gentoo.org">Gentoo Toolchain Maintainers</mail>, with 4
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;assigned_to=toolchain@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="net-irc@gentoo.org">Packages in net-irc</mail>, with 4
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;assigned_to=net-irc@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kernel@gentoo.org">Gentoo Kernel Bug Wranglers and Kernel Maintainers</mail>, with 4
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2007-08-12&amp;chfieldto=2007-08-18&amp;assigned_to=kernel@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- GWN feedback information -->

<chapter>

<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The GWN is staffed by volunteers and members of the community who submit ideas
and articles.  If you are interested in writing for the GWN, have feedback on an
article that we have posted, or just have an idea or article that you would
like to submit to the GWN, please send us your <mail
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN
better.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- GWN subscription information -->

<chapter>

<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p> 

<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the e-mail address you are subscribed under.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Other Languages -->

<chapter>

<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following
languages:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/zh_cn/gwn/gwn.xml">Chinese (Simplified)</uri>
</li>
<!-- <li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li> -->
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/el/gwn/gwn.xml">Greek</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ko/gwn/gwn.xml">Korean</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/sk/gwn/gwn.xml">Slovak</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

</guide>
