<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20070205-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>5 February 2007</subtitle>

<author title="Editor">
<mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>

<!-- Be sure to add yourself if you write an article -->

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="diox@gentoo.org">Dimitry Bradt</mail>
</author>

<!-- <author title="Author">
<mail link="thirtyyearswar@mindspring.com">Chris Atkinson</mail>
</author> -->

<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 5 February
2007.</abstract>
<summary/>

<version>Volume 6, Issue 6</version>
<date>2007-02-05</date>

<!-- Gentoo News -->

<!-- Developer of the Week -->

<!-- Note: Please add the pictures used in this article to the
gentoo/xml/htdocs/img/gwn folder -->
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>Matthias Schwarzott, aka zzam</title>
<body>

<!-- Please scale this image down (convert -> imagemagick failed on jpg :/) -->
<figure link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~diox/temp/dotw/zzam/20070205_zzam.jpg"
 short="zzam" caption="Matthias Schwarzott, aka zzam" />

<p>
I don't think zzam needs introducing. Though for those who don't know who he
i and/or what he does, here is a small summary:
</p>

<p>
Matthias Schwarzott, also known as zzam, is a 25 year old developer from
<!-- please create a tinyurl for this url : 
<uri link="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=d&hl=en&saddr=&daddr=n%C3%BCrnberg&ie=UTF8&om=1&z=12&iwloc=addr">Erlangen,
Germany</uri> -->
<uri link="http://tinyurl.com/2va8ys">Erlangen,Germany</uri>. He lives there
with his lovely girlfriend Charlotte on the 8th floor of a tall <uri
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~diox/temp/dotw/zzam/20070205_outside.jpg">Apartment</uri>.
The view he looks outside from the balconies, is -by the way- splendid (<uri
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~diox/temp/dotw/zzam/20070205_view1.jpg">view1</uri>
<uri
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~diox/temp/dotw/zzam/20070205_view2.jpg">view2</uri>).
So far Matthias doesn't own pets, though he's pity he lives in an apartment with
limited space for a cat.
</p>

<p>
Matthias studies technomathematics, which is basicly an expensive word for
mathematics and technology, at the <uri
link="http://uni-erlangen.de">Friedrich Alexander University of
Erlangen-Nuremberg</uri>. Most of the technology is programming in java,
working with algorithms and programming computer graphics in c++. He also get
technical background about electronical engeneering. To give an example of a
practical technical aspect of his studies: Matthias recently finished a
thesis on model integrated circuits in VHDL (Very High Speed Integrated Circuit
Hardware Description Language), a language to model ICs. He implemented
<e>PONG</e> in our practica on an fpga, some kind of configurable hardware.
</p>

<p>
While he studied, he already achieved some pratical experrience at Siemens,
where He was a c/c++ programmer. Though Matthias recently started working
part-time as an systems administrator at a small company which operates
web-games. When zzam is done with these studies, which are still one semester,
Matthias hopes to be able to start working somewhere as a programmer.
</p>

<p>
Matthias started using linux in the summer of '97 when he was tired of
Windows 3.11 . At that time, he bought suse 5.0 at a local book store after
reading about it in a magazine. He also tried Debian before he finally decided
to start to work with Gentoo Linux. He started using our operating system
around the 1.4 version, which he has used ever since.
</p>

<p>
He only started to get interests of joining the developers team, after buying
his dvb-card to set up a vdr-box. At first he used to compile the programs by
hand, though a bit later on he started using a few ebuilds from
<uri>http://www.gentoo.de</uri>. After that he started contributing, under
<mail link="genstef@gentoo.org">Stefan Schweizer</mail>'s keen eye. After
his recruitment-proces, Matthias became vdr-lead. Since then vdr has grown a
lot! Though he's still looking for active contributors, since he wants to
implement some patches and someone to help him maintain the patchsets he
collected yet.
</p>

<p>
After a while it's fun to see how dvb on windows isn't that great compared to
the raw power of vdr. This, and off course seeying happy users, is exactly
what gives zzam stamina to go on with his work.
</p>

<p>
Though he's pretty busy with his studies, his part-time job and gentoo,
Matthias still (fortunately) got some free time left for his hobbies, which
are practising classic dances (e.g. cha-cha/waltz/etc.), cooking and baking
and doing fitness, which he only started doing recently. zzam started dancing
at the end of his school time. At that time he took dancing classes, which he
has recently restarted doing with his girlfriend at the jugendclub. There he
tries to improve his skills.
</p>

<p>
As mentioned before, Matthias also likes baking and cooking. His favorite
recipe's are streusel cake and self made pizza, which look very
<e>yummie</e>.
</p>

<figure link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~diox/temp/dotw/zzam/20070205_cake.jpg"
 short="zzam_cake" caption="zzam's streusel cake." />

<p>
At the end we asked Matthias how he things gentoo will look like in 10 years.
After a minute, he answered the following: "I think in 10 years (if no hard
break occured) gentoo will have a high number of devs. Though gentoo is in
need of a better team management, to let teams work better together. Also I
think that gentoo needs an improved version of bugday."
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Heard in the community -->

<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>

<!-- forums.gentoo.org -->

<!-- planet.gentoo.org -->

<section>
<title>planet.gentoo.org</title>
<body>

<p><b>More fancy desktops: Metisse</b></p>

<!-- add http://www.hboeck.de/uploads/metisse.png to the
gentoo/xml/htdocs/images/gwn/ folder please. Maybe resizing might be a good
thought. -->

<figure link="/images/gwn/20070129_metisse.png" short="Metisse" caption="Metisse
X-Server screenshot" />

<p>
<mail link="hanno@gentoo.org">Hanno Boeck</mail> recently added <uri
link="http://insitu.lri.fr/metisse/">Metisse</uri> to his svn overlay. Metisse
is the answer from <uri link="http://www.mandriva.com">Mandriva</uri> to compiz,
and the whole 3d-desktop thing.
</p>

<p>
Metisse has some some features that gives the possibility to transform the
natural shape of windows. A few examples of this are: rotating, scaling, zooming
your windows. You can even make a parallellogram from your window! Mettisse runs
on its own native X-Server, which is luminocity/xgl-alike and a modified variant
of fvwm.
</p>

<p>
Unfortunately Metisse is still missing an amd64 version, but that is taken care
of upstream. Also we're patiently waitint for a new version where the coders
should fix some known bugs. For more information on where to get the sources,
and how to start the environment, please read the original blog post which
listed below.
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri>http://www.hboeck.de/item/433</uri></li>
<li><uri>http://www.mandriva.com/en/projects/metisse/download</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<!-- gentoo-user -->

<!-- gentoo-dev -->

<!-- gentoo-catalyst -->

<!-- gentoo-cluster -->

<!-- gentoo-embedded -->

<!-- gentoo-security -->

</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo International-->

<!-- Gentoo in the press -->

<!-- Tips and Tricks -->

<!-- Gentoo developer moves -->

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo developer moves</title>

<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
<li><e>none this week</e></li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo security -->

<!-- paste from the script -->

<!-- Gentoo package moves -->

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo package moves</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>
This section lists packages that have either been moved or added to the tree
and packages that have had their "last rites" announcement given to be removed
in the future. The package removals come from many locations, including the <uri
link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners">Treecleaners</uri> and various developers. Most
packages which are listed under the Last Rites section are in need of some love
and care and can remain in the tree if proper maintainership is established.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- paste from the script -->

<!-- <section>
<title>Last Rites:</title>
<body> -->

<!-- paste from email -->

<!-- </body>
</section> -->

</chapter>

<!-- Bugzilla -->

<!-- paste from the script -->

<!-- GWN feedback information -->

<chapter>

<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The GWN is staffed by volunteers and members of the community who submit ideas
and articles.  If you are interested in writing for the GWN, have feedback on an
article that we have posted, or just have an idea or article that you would
like to submit to the GWN, please send us your <mail
link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN
better.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- GWN subscription information -->

<chapter>

<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p> 

<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the e-mail address you are subscribed under.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- Other Languages -->

<chapter>

<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following
languages:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/zh_cn/gwn/gwn.xml">Chinese (Simplified)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/el/gwn/gwn.xml">Greek</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ko/gwn/gwn.xml">Korean</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/sk/gwn/gwn.xml">Slovak</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

</guide>
