<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20060522-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>22 May 2006</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="sebastian@gentoo.org">Sebastian Bergmann</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="amne@gentoo.org">Wernfried Haas</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="halcy0n@gentoo.org">Mark Loeser</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="deadhead@gechi.it">Andrea Perotti</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 22 May 2006.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 5, Issue 19</version>
<date>2006-05-22</date>

<!-- Gentoo News -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo news</title>
<section>
<title>GCC 4.1 on its way into Portage</title>
<body>
<p>
The long awaited moment of GCC 4.1 being unmasked has almost arrived.  The
toolchain team will be unmasking gcc-4.1.1 this week after it is released.
The upgrade should be incredibly easy and require no additional work to
install and use.  The number of applications that do not compile with gcc-4.1
is extremely small now, and most users should not experience any problems
with <path>~arch</path> packages not compiling.  To upgrade to the new version (assuming
you are using gcc-3.4), all that is required is to upgrade GCC and then select
the new profile using gcc-config.  If you are upgrading from an earlier version
of GCC, please refer to our <uri link="/doc/en/gcc-upgrading.xml">GCC Upgrading 
Guide</uri> for more detailed instructions.
</p>
<p>
If you run into any applications that do not compile, and they do not have a
bug currently open, please file a "GCC Porting" bug and assign it to
<mail link="gcc-porting@gentoo.org">gcc-porting@gentoo.org</mail> so that 
the GCC Porting team can look into it.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Summer of Code</title>
<body>
<p>
There were over 6400 applications from students, almost 90 mentoring
organizations - in almost every respect the Summer of Code program from
Google has grown a lot since last year. This year Gentoo will be one of 
the mentoring organizations, with the UserRel project acting as organizer. 
While the final numbers will be released on Monday the 22nd
we can already say that Gentoo got 130 applications. Out of these around
13 will be sponsored by Google. We are very happy to see such a great
interest in Gentoo and hope that all sponsored projects will be
successful! 
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Old-style PHP packages removed from Portage</title>
<body>
<p>
After being <path>package.mask</path>ed for quite some time, the old-style PHP
packages (<path>dev-php/php, dev-php/php-cgi, dev-php/mod_php</path>, and friends)
have been removed from the Portage tree. The new-style PHP packages
(<path>dev-lang/php, dev-php4/*, dev-php5/*</path>, and friends) are now stable on
most architectures.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Future zone -->
<!-- User Stories -->
<!-- Gentoo Stories -->
<!-- Developer of the week -->

<!-- Heard in the community: gentoo-dev, gentoo-user, forums -->
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>et_EE locale and language of error messages</b></p>
<p>
The Gentoo bugwranglers often have to wrangle bugs that have error
messages in other languages. This makes it difficult to understand and
to find duplicates. A workaround for this issue would be to set the
default language used by portage to "C", which is (through historic
precedents) English and the default when nothing else is set.
A different class of bugs comes from the estonian locale, et_EE: As
their alphabet ordering is different some "silly" buildsystems stumble
as [a-z] no longer matches all letters. While these bugs can be really
annoying they should be fixed. Setting the locale to another language
would prevent these bugs, but it is recommended to fix it so that future
problems are avoided.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/38378">et_EE
locale and language of error messages </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>New eclasses</b></p>
<p>
As there are many different Revision Control Systems and it is often
useful to have ebuild support to check out files directly from a
repository this week gives us a few eclasses that help with managing
darcs, git and mercurial. Those three are relatively new RCS that are
already used by many projects instead of CVS or subversion.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/38364">New
eclasses </uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>Signing everything, for fun and for profit</b></p>
<p>
The first recorded discussions about signing all Gentoo-provided files
to avoid tampering go back to 2003. Since then there have been a few
tries to get a Gentoo-wide system to cryptographically sign all files,
but there was never a consensus, and in the end it never got fully
implemented. <mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
revives the discussion in the hope of getting it finally done.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/38363">Signing
everything, for fun and for profit </uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>RFC - Gentoo Knowledge Base</b></p>
<p>
A new Gentoo project gets kickstarted by <mail
link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>. The goal is to create a
knowledge base that "[...] provides answers to specific questions and problems
that users (or developers) might encounter. It is easily searchable and
maintained by developers who are knowledgeable in the topic. The
knowledge base entries ("topics" as I like to call them) are not
documentation guides, but very specific to a particular environment and
question."
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/38030">RFC -
Gentoo Knowledge Base </uri></li>
</ul>

<p><b>Paludis profiles yay or nay?</b></p>
<p>
What started as a simple question by <mail link="spb@gentoo.org">Stephen
Bennett</mail> whether there were any objections to adding profiles for the
Paludis package manager into the mainline Gentoo tree became one of the
fastest and most heated email exchanges to happen on the <path>gentoo-dev</path>
mailinglist. With around 300 messages in the main thread and three
forked subthreads this is an impressive debate:
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/38016">Paludis
and Profiles </uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/38231">Alternative
Gentoo package managers discussion request (for the council) </uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/38342">RFC:
etiquette enforcement </uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/38351">259
paludis-profile messages. ENOUGH! </uri></li>

</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Planet Gentoo</title>
<body>
<p><b>Baselayout 1.12 going stable?</b></p>
<p>
Asked by many users Roy Marples now announced that there is only one 
unionfs bug left before he starts building baselayout's 1.12.0 tarball. 
If there don't occur any show-stopping bugs it will take another month 
before baselayout-1.12.0 can be marked stable by our ARCH-teams.
</p>
<ul>
<li>Baselayout 1.12 going stable?</li>
</ul>
<p><b>Apache 2.0.58 now available</b></p>
<p>
Later than expected Apache 2.0.58 finally made it into the tree, including 
some changes how Apache works within Gentoo. Most notable is the deprecation 
of net-www/gentoo-webroot-default as discussed in Bug #90748. As of 2.0.58 
the /var/www/localhost directory will be left untouched if it exists. If 
it doesn’t exist, it will be created and populated.
</p>
<ul>
<li>Apache 2.0.58 now available</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Gentoo international -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo international</title>
<section>
<title>Austria: Gentoo at the Grazer Linuxtage</title>
<body>
<p>
As announced in last week's GWN, Gentoo was present at the Linuxtag in Graz. 
Markus Lang, <mail link="roger55@gentoo.org">Roger Miliker</mail>, Gregor 
Perner and <mail link="amne@gentoo.org">Wernfried Haas</mail>
were present at the Gentoo booth, handing out LiveCDs on request, selling
case badges and chatting with users about Portage features, and giving away 
stickers.
As usually, the grml folks (who were next to Gentoo) asked if we still were 
compiling stuff, which was promptly answered by demonstrating the installer.
Of course this was just poking fun at each other between the different
distributions, the teams from Funkfeuer, Gentoo, grml and Debian had a good
time with each other. Wernfried Haas also held a workshop introducing people 
to IRC with focus on the popular IRC client <c>irssi</c> and the Freenode 
network. Both visitors as well as the exhibitors had fun at the GLT,
thanks to the organisation team and see you in 2007.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20060522_glt.jpg"
short="GLT"
caption="Amne readjusting the word order" />
<note>More pictures of the event can be found on http://dufo.tugraz.at/glt06/</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Italy: Gentoo at the Linux World Summit in Milano</title>
<body>
<p>
Fellows from GeCHI (Gentoo CHannel Italia www.gechi.it) spent two
intense days at the Linux World Summit in Milan. Compared to past
years, the spaces reserved by the organization at the Marriot Hotel for 
the event were small, which is probably why few commercial vendors were
represented in the exhibition hall. Stands managed by associations were 
bigger, more colorful and funnier. As predicted in the last GWN, the GeCHI
showed a Sun Fire V120 and an OpenMosix cluster composed of four Via Epia 
motherboards, both systems running Gentoo Linux. In the cluster only the 
first node is connected to the two SATA disks, while the remaining three 
nodes boot from network and are diskless. Due to its unusual casing, the 
cluster was at the center of the public's attention on both days of the 
exhibition. The GeCHI had also prepared a Gentoo brochure distributed at 
the stand, and matching penguins and cows (as in: Larry) on offer.
</p>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20060522_gechi.jpg"
short="Gechi"
caption="One Larry, four Tuxes: The GeCHI at work" />
<note>Left to right, in the back: deadhead, blackman, ElDios, front: mouser, 
riquitoi. More pictures of the event can be viewed at <uri 
link="http://dev.gechi.it/gallery/v/Eventi/lws06">the GeCHI website</uri></note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo in the press -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Dot KDE (16 May 2006)</title>
<body>
<p>
In a series of interviews with businesses that benefit from KDE -- 
or vice-versa -- the KDE Dot News magazine spoke with Gentoo developer 
<uri link="http://dot.kde.org/1147698188/">Caleb Tennis</uri> in his 
professional quality as system designer at AEI, a company in Columbus,
Indiana, specializing in diesel engine durability assessment, exhaust
research, performance development and numerous other services. Caleb
sees reliability as a key element in AEI's decision to run Linux and 
KDE, as everything else "may be liveable on your girlfriend's computer, 
but for one that's monitoring a $1,000,000 development engine, it becomes 
pretty important to not have problems because 'Windows crashed'."
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Newsforge (19 May 2006)</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo trustee and infrastructure lead <mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt 
Lieber</mail> gets his say in an article about Gentoo sponsor OSUOSL titled
<uri link="http://mobile.newsforge.com/mobility/06/05/05/2018250.shtml">"Oregon 
lab plays Web host to the stars of open source."</uri> Setting the backdrop
for the following interview with OSUOSL's Scott Kveton, Kurt points out how
fabulous the open-source lab's services to Gentoo have been: "in fact, it's 
better than what I would expect from commercial vendors in a lot of respects."
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Tips and Tricks -->
<chapter>
<title></title>
<section>
<title>Managing your overlays with layman</title>
<body>
<note>
This is the first tips and tricks section in a while. If you have tips and 
tricks you would like to share with the Gentoo community please drop us a 
mail at <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">gwn-feedback@gentoo.org</mail>. 
</note>
<p>
<c>layman</c> is a small and nifty Python application written by Gentoo 
developer <mail link="wrobel@genoo.org">Gunnar Wrobel</mail> which allows
to easily use and synchronize several Portage overlays on your local
machine.
</p>

<p>
As of now there is no stable <c>layman</c> version available, so you
need to add <c>layman</c> to your <path>package.keywords</path> file
before installing.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing layman">
# echo "app-portage/layman" >> /etc/portage/package.keywords
# emerge layman
</pre>

<p>
To include the overlays managed by <c>layman</c> to your
<c>PORTDIR_OVERLAY</c> variable you have to source a file where all
layman-managed overlays listed. Note that you can still add other
overlays to the <c>PORTDIR_OVERLAY</c> variable in
<path>/etc/make.conf</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Sourcing layman overlays">
# echo "source /usr/portage/local/layman/make.conf" >> /etc/make.conf
</pre>

<p>
Configuring <c>layman</c> is as easy as riding a bike ;) First you
fetch a list of available overlays and then start adding overlays you
would like to use.
</p>

<pre caption="Configure layman">
<comment>Fetch list of available overlays</comment>
# layman -f

<comment>Add the 'gentoo-de' overlay</comment>
# layman -a gentoo-de
</pre>

<p>
<c>layman -l</c> gives you a list of all available overlays, using the
<c>-a</c> switch you can add other overlays.
</p>

<p>
The <c>-s</c> switch allows you to synchronize the local overlay
copies. You can choose between syncing one specific overlay or all
overlays you added.
</p>

<pre caption="Synchronizing overlays">
<comment>Synchronize the 'gentoo-de' overlay</comment>
# layman -s gentoo-de

<comment>Synchronize all overlays</comment>
# layman -s ALL
</pre>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<!-- Gentoo developer moves -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo developer moves</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo project:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Rob Holland</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo project:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Steve Dibbs (beandog) - Planet</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo project:</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo security -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Security</title>
<!-- paste from the script -->
<section>
<title>libextractor: Two heap-based buffer overflows</title>
<body>
<p>
libextractor is vulnerable to two heap overflow vulnerabilities which could
lead to the execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200605-14.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Quagga Routing Suite: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>
Quagga's RIP daemon allows the injection of routes and the disclosure of
routing information. The BGP daemon is vulnerable to a Denial of Service.
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200605-15.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<!-- end of paste from the script -->
</chapter>
<!-- Bugzilla -->
<!-- paste from the script -->
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the
development team.  Between 14 May 2006
and 21 May 2006, activity on the site has resulted in:
</p>
<ul>
<li>653 new bugs during this period</li>
<li>323 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
<li>24 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
</ul>
<p>
Of the 10139 currently open bugs: 56 are labeled 'blocker', 149 are labeled 'critical', and 524 are labeled 'major'.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 21
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="emacs@gentoo.org">GNU Emacs Herd</mail>, with 16
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=emacs@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org">Gentoo Security</mail>, with 15
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">Gentoo Games</mail>, with 14
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="robbat2@gentoo.org">Robin Johnson</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=robbat2@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="dev-portage@gentoo.org">Portage team</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=dev-portage@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="apache-bugs@gentoo.org">Apache Herd - Bugzilla Reports</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=apache-bugs@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="ppc64@gentoo.org">ppc64 architecture team</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=ppc64@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for New Packages</mail>, with 22
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org">AMD64 Project</mail>, with 17
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="squinky86@gentoo.org">Jon Hood</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;assigned_to=squinky86@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org">Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="flameeyes@gentoo.org">Diego Pettenò</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;assigned_to=flameeyes@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org">Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 7
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2006-05-14&amp;chfieldto=2006-05-21&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- end of paste from bugzilla script -->
<!-- GWN feedback information -->
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and
help make the GWN better.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- GWN subscription information -->
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p> 
<p> To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the e-mail address you are subscribed under.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Other Languages -->
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following
languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ko/gwn/gwn.xml">Korean</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
