<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>May 19th, 2003</subtitle>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of May 19th, 2003.</abstract>
<summary>Announcing Gentoo Games, Inc.  Gentoo Linux attends E3.</summary>
<version>Volume 2, Issue 20</version>
<date>19 May 2003</date>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="nesta@iceburg.net">Brice Burgess</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
	<mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="david@phrixus.net">David Narayan</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="mail@psharp.uklinux.net">Peter Sharp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="kim@thinkit.dk">Kim Tingkaer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
        <mail link="matje@lanzone.be">Mathy Vanvoorden</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
        <mail link="Hendrik.Eeckhaut@UGent.be">Hendrik Eeckhaut</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
        <mail link="sephiroth@quicknet.nl">Jorn Eilander</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
        <mail link="bernieke@bernieke.com">Bernard Bernieke</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
        <mail link="peter@daborg.nl">Peter Ter Borg</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
        <mail link="linux@sejo.be">Jochen Maes</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
        <mail link="rgoessen@home.nl">Roderick Goessen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
        <mail link="gerard@steelo.net">Gerard van den Berg</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
    <mail link="mat@frheaven.com">Matthieu Montaudouin</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
    <mail link="riverdale@linuxmail.org">Martin Prieto</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="madeagle@gentoo.org">Steffen Lassahn</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="haim@gentoo.org">Matthias F. Brandstetter</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="yanestra@gentoo.org">Klaus-J. Wolf</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="mush@monrif.net">Marco Mascherpa</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="paper@tiscali.it">Claudio Merloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="bsolar@bluewin.ch">Christian Apolloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="kage-chan@gentoo.org">Daniel Ketel</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="hagi@p1d.com">Yoshiaki Hagihara</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="andy@billydpro.com">Andy Hunne</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="yasunori@mail.portland.co.uk">Yasunori Fukudome</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
    <mail link="088@t.email.ne.jp">Takashi Ota</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="venturasbarbeiro@ig.com.br">Ventura Barbeiro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="blueroom@digitalmente.net">Bruno Ferreira</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="gustavo@felisberto.net">Gustavo Felisberto</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="rjlouro@rjlouro.org">Ricardo Jorge Louro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="R.Nogueira@records.usyd.edu.au">Ricardo Nogueira</mail>
</author>
<author title="Russian Translation">
	<mail link="infapx@yandex.ru">Sergey Kuleshov</mail>
</author>
<author title="Russian Translation">
	<mail link="dimsuz@mail.ru">Dmitry Suzdalev</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="lanark@lanark.com.ar">Lanark</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="julio@castillobueno.com">Julio Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="s3r@fibertel.com.ar">Sergio G&#243;mez</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="pablo.leira@pitagoral.com">Pablo Pita Leira</mail>	
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@castillobueno.com">Carlos Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="tirant@menta.net">Tirant</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="jfreire@ya.com">Jaime Freire</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="krusty_ar@yahoo.com">Lucas Sallovitz</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
        <mail link="aycan@core.gen.tr">Aycan Irican</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
        <mail link="bugra@myrealbox.com">Bugra Cakir</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
        <mail link="cagils@biznet.com.tr">Cagil Seker</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
        <mail link="emre@core.gen.tr">Emre Kazdagli</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
        <mail link="evrim@core.gen.tr">Evrim Ulu</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
        <mail link="gurcell@core.gen.tr">Gursel Kaynak</mail>
</author>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Announcing Gentoo Games, Inc.  </uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Gentoo Linux attends E3</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Announcing Gentoo Games, Inc.</title>
		<body>
		<p>
On May 15th, Daniel Robbins and several other Gentoo Linux developers
announced the creation of a new company called Gentoo Games, Inc.
</p><p>
The mission of Gentoo Games is to advance Linux gaming. The
initial efforts of Gentoo Games will be focused around the Gentoo GameCD
technology, which allows anyone with a modern PC to put a CD in their
computer, turn it on, and have the GameCD boot directly into the game. The
game runs from the GameCD, and the GameCD handles the auto-detection and
configuration of all hardware.
</p><p>
By doing this, the Gentoo GameCD transforms any PC with an NVIDIA or ATI
graphics card into a console-like system. And because the GameCD can be used
by anyone -- even Windows users -- it expands the reach of Linux-based
gaming technologies tremendously. The goal of this effort is to cause Linux
gaming to rise to a new level of prominence that will result in wonderful
things for Linux gamers, Linux game developers and publishers, Linux
adoption as a whole, and of course GameCD users who can now have a
console-like experience on any modern PC thanks to the flexibility and power
of free software.
</p><p>
Gentoo Games, Inc. is a separate, independent entity from the Gentoo Linux
free software project. This was done to ensure that the commercial nature of
Gentoo Games will not impact the integrity of the Gentoo Linux social
contract. Funds generated by Gentoo Games, Inc. will be used to fund future
development of Gentoo Linux as well as GNU/Linux in general. In addition,
Gentoo Games hopes to provide exciting opportunities for capable developers
who would like to help us transform Linux gaming.
</p>
<p>
One of the first benefits to be realized from the creation of Gentoo Games,
Inc. (even before Gentoo Games, Inc. officially existed) was last week's
announcement that Gentoo Linux will soon support full 64-bit functionality
on the AMD Opteron platform.
</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Gentoo Linux attends E3</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Gentoo Linux was present at the recent Electronic Entertainment Exposition in Los Angeles to announce the creation of Gentoo Games and the America's Army GameCD.   The show was a huge success, with many companies expressing interest in Gentoo Games' GameCD technology.  In between meetings, the Gentoo Linux folks were able to see at least part of the rest of the show, including some very impressive booths by NVIDIA and the US Army.
		</p>
		<figure link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030519_e3_entrance.jpg" short="The entrance to E3" caption="The entrance to this year's E3" />
		<figure link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030519_e3_nvidia.jpg" short="NVIDIA's booth at E3" caption="NVIDIA attended E3 for the first time this year." />
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Security</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2" >GLSA: kopete</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3" >GLSA: gnupg</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect4" >GLSA: shadow</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect5" >New Security Bug Reports</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>GLSA: kopete</title>
<body>
     <p> 
     The GnuPG plugin in kopete does not properly cleanse the command-line when executing gpg, which could allow
     remote attackers to execute arbitrary commands.
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>Severity: Critical - Cryptographic compromise, remote execution of arbitrary code.</li>
          <li>Packages Affected:  net-im/kopete prior to kopete-0.6.2</li>
          <li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge kopete, emerge clean.</li>
          <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=53909" >GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>GLSA: gnupg</title>
<body>
     <p> 
     There is a bug in GnuPG's validation code that permits keys with
     more than one user to cause all user IDs on that key to be
     treated as though they are as valid as the most valid key.
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>Severity: High - Cryptographic compromise.</li>
          <li>Packages Affected:  app-crypt/gnupg prior to gnupg-1.2.2</li>
          <li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge gnupg, emerge clean.</li>
          <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=54323" >GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=bugtraq&amp;m=105215110111174&amp;w=2" >Advisory</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>GLSA: shadow</title>
<body>
     <p> 
     An upgrade is available for the shadow utility to mitigate a bug in OpenSSH that permits remote attackers to 
     identify the account names for valid users on the system (see last week's GWN).
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>Severity: High - Information exposure.</li>
          <li>Packages Affected:  sys-apps/shadow prior to shadow-4.0.3-r5</li>
          <li>Rectification: Synchronize and emerge shadow, emerge clean.</li>
          <li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=53826" >GLSA Announcement</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="http://lab.mediaservice.net/advisory/2003-01-openssh.txt" >Advisory</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New Security Bug Reports</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The following new security bugs were posted this week:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=20837"></uri>dev-db/firebird</li>
          <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=20992"></uri>sys-apps/xinetd</li>
          <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=20993"></uri>app-games/unreal-tournament</li>
          <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=20997"></uri>app-cdr/cdrtools</li>
          <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=20998"></uri>app-text/lv</li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>User stories</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Kenneth and how he switched his school to Gentoo Linux</p>
<p>Currently a high-school senior, Kenneth does some work on the school's computers during his free time. One day a member of the computer staff asked him to install Linux on six of the lab's 44 computers after being not too happy with what using Office XP would cost the school. So Kenneth decided to make an image containing KDE, GNOME, OpenOffice.org, Mozilla, Samba, CUPS, distcc, gaim (what a nice school! ;), MPlayer, Flash, Java and GNUPlot. And of course he was using Gentoo Linux for his efforts!</p>
<p><b>Some problems</b></p>
<p>As the school uses a Windows network, Kenneth had to assure to make logons work without knowing the administrator password. Furthermore students have to be able to access their server space located on machines running windows. And of course you have to convice people that Linux is not evil...</p>
<p><b>Clever solutions</b></p>
<p>In oder to get logins to work, Kenneth patched the GDM source to run a script which creates a UID if it doesn't already exist. smb_auth is used for PAM and creates home directories according to a template Kenneth made. There were problems with a few programs that recorded the home directory in their configs (e.g. OpenOffice.org), so he made a symlink for it which the template account uses as home directory. To mount Samba shares on login and unmount them on logout he uses smb_authtoken and wrote a C program that manages the mounts by calling smbmount and smbumount.</p>
<p>For easier updates Kenneth gets some stuff from /usr/portage from NFS shares, uses distcc on the boxes and set up a local rsync mirror. When administrating his machines, he uses a special konsole profile which runs ssh to each of them and uses "send input to all".</p>
<p>KDE is used as the standard desktop environment, CUPS handles the network printers and KDE has shortcuts to the various file servers.</p>
<p><b>Conclusion</b></p>
<p>On the first day, Kenneth registered over 57 new users. Some people, including a teacher, really liked it. Kenneth put explanations on each icon, so people didn't have a hard time figuring out what they did, but some people just kept looking for Internet Explorer and didn't quite get why it's not there. Other problems included mounting floppies or just plain refusal to use anything else than Windows. However, Kenneth noticed that some students only use "his" computers, even though they have no clue at all what a kernel is. But his greatest day came when the NT print servers went down and everybody who wanted to print had to use the Gentoo boxes for this task. Even the chemistry teacher (who was previously mad about different software) had to admit that he "played the linux game and it printed fine.".</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Featured Developer of the Week</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Chad Huneycutt</p>
<figure link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030519_chadh.jpg" short="Chad Huneycutt" caption="Chad Huneycutt" />
<p>
<mail link="chadh@gentoo.org">Chad Huneycutt</mail> works on laptop stuff.  Busy in real life, he claims to be relatively inactive as a Gentoo developer, but currently he's working on getting profiles(so that configuration for several different network environments can be stored and chosen from) and automatic network configuration going.  While <uri link="http://pcmcia-cs.sourceforge.net/">pcmcia-cs</uri> already supports 'schemes', Chad is looking for an alternative that will integrate with Gentoo's current configuration system, and thinks that the ultimate solution will require enhancement of Gentoo's init scripts and a little hacking of pcmcia-cs to make it all work together.  And as for automatic network hacking, Chad is working with <mail link="latexer@gentoo.org">Peter Johanson</mail> on adding wireless AP detection to the existing mix of good utilities that are already out there.
</p>
<p>
Chad began using Gentoo about two years ago when he read drobbins' IBM Developerworks articles, and like most developers joined the team by submitting ebuilds, hanging out on IRC (Chad's first time on IRC), and making a nuisance of himself.  While he has a Sourceforge project (<uri link="http://sourceforge.net/projects/hodgepodge/">hodgepodge</uri>), he says that it's a library of some Java code he wrote a long time ago and that he hasn't done much OSS work outside of Gentoo.  Chad says that if he finishes the network profile stuff described above, it'll be his greatest achievement yet.
</p>
<p>
A Ph.D student in Computer Science at the Georgia Institute of technology, Chad studies computer architecture, working in particular on a project called SoftCache, an amalgamation of compiler, cache, and embedded systems concepts.  Chad uses Evolution, Mozilla, Xchat, and Gabber everyday, while his tools of the trade are vim, gcc, and gdb (in that order), all running under GNOME currently, although he also uses KDE regularly.  Chad, 28, lives in Atlanta, Georgia with his wife of almost seven years and his two year-old son.  While he'd love to play tennis and bridge if he had time, what he usually does is spend time with his son and play (mostly German) board games.
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard In The Community</title>
	<section>
	<title>Web Forums</title>
	<body>
	<p><b>Gamers in Seventh Heaven</b></p>

	<p>The only other news so far this year responsible for an equally generous amount of excitement and controversial debate in the Gentoo Forums was the April fool's joke... The strong gamers and players community in Gentoo (complete with a forum of their own) has greeted the creation of Gentoo Games Inc. with the utmost gratitude and exploded in speculation as to what exactly the new company will be doing, aside from the America's Army CD that served as a kickoff to the new legal entity. While some people prefer to discuss whether it's politically wise to move into this direction to begin with, others tried to alleviate the burden on Supercomputing's server bandwidth by hosting the iso image -- only to see their FTP servers crash almost instantly...</p>
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=54265">Good luck to Gentoo Games Inc. !!</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=54311">America's Army: politically sensitive?</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=54133">Gentoo Games !!?!!?</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=54264">YEAH America's Army GameCD is out !!</uri></li>
	</ul>
	<p><b>Ahead of Their Times</b></p>
	<p>Strangely enough, Gentoo's much less controversial announcement of teaming up with Super Computer Inc. for porting Linux to the Opteron platform went without mention in this thread, but it seems as if people are already busy optimizing compiler settings for systems with AMD's new 64-bit CPU:</p>
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=54312">Gentoo on the Opteron (x86-64)</uri></li>
	</ul>
	<p><b>Patch Peeve</b></p>
	<p>John Whitney aka <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=16794">jjw</uri> has developed an application that promises to reduce download times when upgrading software, by fetching only differentials between old and new versions of the respective source code, and applying them as patches to the version already locally available. Here's the discussion thread that greets his ebuild submission:</p>
	<p><ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=53406">Deltup will update packages and reduce download time</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
</body>
</section>
	<section>
	<title>Gentoo Users</title>
	<body>
	<p><b>Learning the Gentoo Ways</b></p>
	<p>Where is xinetd? An innocent question by a Redhat user who went to look for the missing daemon in Gentoo triggered an interesting debate on open ports, enhancing security and the virtues of a minimal default installation: </p>
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://news.gmane.org/onethread.php?group=gmane.linux.gentoo.user&amp;root=%3CNDBBLGIKBJENLAMOLFHGEEPCCBAB.mknecht%40controlnet.com%3E">ports and services</uri></li>
	</ul>
	<p><b>Mostly Harmless</b></p>
	<p>One of those pesky error messages recorded during bootup, the "spurious 8259A interrupt", is <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/32861">sufficiently widespread</uri> to cause uncertainty among Gentoo users. The long and the short of it: If it hurts when you do that, don't do that. Mark Knecht <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/32763">explains</uri> how this error message may sometimes only appear when a system is powered up, but not if it's simply being rebooted. And unless there appears to be something seriously wrong with a system as a result of it, there's no need to worry, says <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/32769">hardware buff</uri> Joe Stone:</p>
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://news.gmane.org/onethread.php?group=gmane.linux.gentoo.user&amp;root=%3C200305121659.43606.Harlekin_666%40gmx.net%3E">spurious 8259A interrupt: IRQ7.</uri></li>
	</ul>
</body>
	</section>
<section>
  <title>gentoo-dev</title>
    <body>
	<p><b>System health and portage diagnostics</b></p>
	<p>Dhruba Bandopadhyay
	   <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8622">thinks</uri> that a lot of the
	   problems user's have when intalling new ebuilds can be solved by issuing <c>ldconfig</c>,
       <c>env-update</c>, <c>source /etc/profile</c> or <c>revdep-rebuild</c> (from the gentoolkit
	   package). So he proposes <e>"that all tools that are scattered around the various
       packages intended for diagnosing and maintaining system health be integrated into one and included
	   in portage"</e>. He has received no feedback so far!
	</p>
    <p><b>ChangeLog change</b></p>
    <p>Weeve timidly
	   <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8603">asked</uri> about the
	   changes to the format of ChangeLogs. Gentoo developer  Dan Armak
	   <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8607">explained</uri> the
	   reasons behind this "change".. and how it was that there was no change at all!
    </p>
	<p><b>Improved JDBC support</b></p>
	<p>Gentoo developer Dylan Carlson
	<uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8602">posted</uri> to gentoo-dev
	to announce the availability of six new packages added to the "dev-java" category that will
	bring JDBC connectivity support to Gentoo.
	</p>
	<p><b>[WIP] GCC 3.3</b></p>
	<p>Gentoo developer Spider
	<uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8624">announced</uri> an initial ebuild
	for GCC 3.3. <e>"Comments and testers are welcome :)"</e>
	</p>
  </body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo International</title>
    <body>
	<p class="secthead">Cologne Meeting Aftermath</p>
<p>About a dozen Gentoo users made it to last week's regional meeting in Germany. Hellers Brauhaus in Cologne was packed with laptops, an unusually high density of electronics for this rather down-to-earth brewery outlet, and everybody of course had a splendid time. In a remarkably swift response to the GWN's mistake in announcing the wrong location two weeks ago, the next meeting is indeed scheduled to take place in Bonn - we know a self-fulfilling prophecy when we see one... And this is what German Gentooists look like after dark:</p>
		<figure link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030519_cologne.jpg" short="Gentoo users meet in Cologne" caption="Gentoo users meet in Cologne, Germany" />
	<p class="secthead">Journee de Gentooiens in France - Yes, But Where?</p>
<p>In spite of at least one semi-serious offer for a shuttle service from the airport to the venue, the issue of a French Gentoo user meeting raised last week is unlikely to resolve with Martinique as its location. Thanks to her colonial past, France has left a prominent linguistic heritage all over the planet, and lots of French-speaking Gentooists live in very nice spots at that. But it's hard to find an equidistant area for a meeting if you have Guadeloupe, New Caledonia and Belgium sitting on the extremes of the map, so people are gradually shifting towards regional meetings here and there. Feel free to post your own suggestions at <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=53860">this thread</uri> in the French forum. </p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Portage Watch</title>
<section>
<title>The following stable packages were updated or added to portage this week</title>
<body>
<p>We are aware that the USE variables section has dissapeared from Portage Watch. It will be back shortly!</p>
<ul>
<li>app-admin/aide: <uri link="http://www.cs.tut.fi/~rammer/aide.html">AIDE (Advanced Intrusion Detection Environment) is a replacement for Tripwire</uri></li>
<li>app-cdr/cdrtools: <uri link="http://www.fokus.gmd.de/research/cc/glone/employees/joerg.schilling/private/cdrecord.html">A set of tools for CDR drives, including cdrecord.</uri></li>
<li>app-crypt/gnupg: <uri link="http://www.gnupg.org/">The GNU Privacy Guard, a GPL pgp replacement</uri></li>
<li>app-emulation/basiliskII: <uri link="http://www.uni-mainz.de/~bauec002/B2Main.html">BasiliskII-0.9.0 Macintosh Emulator (Stable Release)</uri></li>
<li>app-i18n/canna: <uri link="http://canna.sourceforge.jp/">A client-server based Kana-Kanji conversion system</uri></li>
<li>app-office/gnucash: <uri link="http://www.gnucash.org/">A personal finance manager</uri></li>
<li>app-office/gnumeric: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/gnome-office/gnumeric.shtml">Gnumeric, the GNOME Spreadsheet</uri></li>
<li>app-office/lyx: <uri link="http://www.lyx.org/">WYSIWYM frontend for LaTeX</uri></li>
<li>app-sci/gri: <uri link="http://gri.sourceforge.net/">language for scientific graphics programming</uri></li>
<li>app-sci/mupad: <uri link="http://www.mupad.de/index_uni.shtml">MuPAD is an open computer algebra system</uri></li>
<li>app-sci/otter: <uri link="http://www-unix.mcs.anl.gov/AR/otter/">An Automated Deduction System.</uri></li>
<li>app-sci/pari: <uri link="http://www.parigp-home.de/">A software package for computer-aided number theory</uri></li>
<li>app-sci/tbass: <uri link="http://www.cs.man.ac.uk/amulet/projects/balsa/">Balsa is both a framework for synthesising asynchronous hardware systems and the language for describing such systems</uri></li>
<li>dev-db/freetds: <uri link="http://www.freetds.org/">Tabular Datastream Library</uri></li>
<li>dev-db/mysql++: <uri link="http://www.mysql.org/downloads/api-mysql++.html">C++ API interface to the MySQL database</uri></li>
<li>dev-db/mysqltool: <uri link="http://www.dajoba.com/projects/mysqltool/">Web interface for managing one or more mysql server installations</uri></li>
<li>dev-java/bcel: <uri link="http://jakarta.apache.org/bcel/">The Byte Code Engineering Library: analyze, create, manipulate Java class files.</uri></li>
<li>dev-java/bsh: <uri link="http://www.beanshell.org/">BeanShell is a small, free, embeddable, Java source interpreter with object scripting language features.</uri></li>
<li>dev-java/cryptix-jce: <uri link="http://cryptix.org/products/jce/">Cryptix JCE is a complete clean-room implementation of the official JCE 1.2 API as published by Sun.</uri></li>
<li>dev-java/infobus: <uri link="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/infobus/index.html">InfoBus enables dynamic exchange of data between JavaBeans component architecture.</uri></li>
<li>dev-java/jaf: <uri link="http://java.sun.com/products/javabeans/glasgow/jaf.html">Sun's JavaBeans Activation Framework (JAF)</uri></li>
<li>dev-libs/atk: <uri link="http://developer.gnome.org/projects/gap/">Gnome Accessibility Toolkit</uri></li>
<li>dev-lisp/gcl: <uri link="http://www.gnu.org/software/gcl/gcl.html">GNU Common Lisp</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/amrita: <uri link="http://www.brain-tokyo.jp/research/amrita/index.html">A HTML/XHTML template library for Ruby</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/amstd: <uri link="http://www.loveruby.net/en/amstd.html">Ruby utility collection by Minero Aoki</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/devel-logger: <uri link="http://rrr.jin.gr.jp/doc/devel-logger/">Lightweight logging utility</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/eruby: <uri link="http://www.modruby.net">eRuby interprets a Ruby code embedded text file.</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/fxruby: <uri link="http://www.fxruby.org/">FXRuby is the Ruby language binding to the FOX GUI toolkit.</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/mysql-ruby: <uri link="http://www.tmtm.org/en/mysql/ruby/">A Ruby extention library to use MySQL</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/rmagick: <uri link="http://home.nc.rr.com/rmagick/">An interface between Ruby and the ImageMagick(TM) image processing library</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/ruby-postgres: <uri link="http://www.postgresql.jp/interfaces/ruby/">An extension library to access a PostgreSQL database from Ruby</uri></li>
<li>dev-ruby/ruby-tcpwrap: <uri link="http://raa.ruby-lang.org/list.rhtml?name=ruby-tcpwrap">A TCP wrappers library for Ruby</uri></li>
<li>gnome-base/bonobo: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/">A set of language and system independant CORBA interfaces</uri></li>
<li>gnome-base/gail: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/">Part of Gnome Accessibility</uri></li>
<li>gnome-base/gdm: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/">GNOME2 Display Manager</uri></li>
<li>gnome-extra/acme: <uri link="http://www.hadess.net/misc-code.php3">GNOME tool to make use of the multimedia buttons present on most laptops and internet keyboards.</uri></li>
<li>gnome-extra/bug-buddy: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/">Bug Report helper for Gnome</uri></li>
<li>gnome-extra/gal: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/">The Gnome Application Libraries</uri></li>
<li>gnome-extra/gcalctool: <uri link="http://calctool.sourceforge.net/">A scientific calculator for Gnome2</uri></li>
<li>gnome-extra/gnome-pilot: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/gnome-pilot/">Gnome Pilot apps</uri></li>
<li>gnome-extra/gnome-utils: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/">Utilities for the Gnome2 desktop</uri></li>
<li>gnome-extra/gtkhtml: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/">Lightweight HTML rendering/printing/editing engine.</uri></li>
<li>media-gfx/aoi: <uri link="http://aoi.sourceforge.net/index">A free, open-source 3D modelling and rendering studio.</uri></li>
<li>media-plugins/alsa-xmms: <uri link="http://savannah.gnu.org/download/alsa-xmms/">Allows XMMS to output on any ALSA 0.9* device.  Supports surround 4.0 output with conversion</uri></li>
<li>media-video/ati-drivers: <uri link="http://www.ati.com">Ati precompiled drivers for r300, r250 and r200 chipsets</uri></li>
<li>media-video/cinelerra: <uri link="http://heroinewarrior.com/cinelerra.php3">Cinelerra - Professional Video Editor</uri></li>
<li>net-analyzer/cacti: <uri link="http://www.raxnet.net/products/cacti/">Cacti is a complete frondend to rrdtool</uri></li>
<li>net-firewall/firestorm: <uri link="http://www.scaramanga.co.uk/firestorm/">Network IDS</uri></li>
<li>net-fs/autofs: <uri link="http://www.linux-consulting.com/Amd_AutoFS/autofs.html">Kernel based automounter</uri></li>
<li>net-im/bitlbee: <uri link="http://www.lintux.cx/bitlbee.html">Bitlbee is an irc to IM gateway that support mutliple IM protocols</uri></li>
<li>net-irc/lostirc: <uri link="http://lostirc.sourceforge.net/">A simple but functional graphical IRC client</uri></li>
<li>net-irc/ninja: <uri link="http://ninja.qoop.org/">Ninja IRC Client</uri></li>
<li>net-libs/gnet: <uri link="http://www.gnetlibrary.org/">GNet network library.</uri></li>
<li>net-libs/libident: <uri link="ftp://ftp.lysator.liu.se/pub/ident/libs">A small library to interface to the Ident protocol server</uri></li>
<li>net-libs/libwww: <uri link="http://www.w3.org/Library/">A general-purpose client side WEB API</uri></li>
<li>net-libs/soup: <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/">Soup is a SOAP implementation</uri></li>
<li>net-mail/amavis: <uri link="http://www.amavis.org">A perl module which integrates virus scanning software with your MTA</uri></li>
<li>net-mail/balsa: <uri link="http://balsa.gnome.org">Email client for GNOME</uri></li>
<li>net-mail/bogofilter: <uri link="http://bogofilter.sourceforge.net/">Bayesian spam filter designed with fast algorithms, and tuned for speed.</uri></li>
<li>net-mail/checkpassword: <uri link="http://cr.yp.to/checkpwd.html">A uniform password checking interface for root applications</uri></li>
<li>net-mail/courier: <uri link="http://www.courier-mta.org/">An MTA designed specifically for maildirs</uri></li>
<li>net-misc/aria: <uri link="http://aria.rednoah.com">Aria is a download manager with a GTK+ GUI, it downloads files from the Internet via HTTP/HTTPS or FTP.</uri></li>
<li>net-nds/openldap: <uri link="http://www.OpenLDAP.org/">LDAP suite of application and development tools</uri></li>
<li>net-nds/yp-tools: <uri link="http://www.linux-nis.org/nis">NIS Tools</uri></li>
<li>net-nds/ypbind: <uri link="http://www.linux-nis.org/nis/ypbind-mt/index.html">Multithreaded NIS bind service</uri></li>
<li>net-p2p/bittorrent: <uri link="http://bitconjurer.org/BitTorrent">BitTorrent is a tool for distributing files via a distributed network of nodes</uri></li>
<li>net-wireless/hostap: <uri link="http://hostap.epitest.fi/">HostAP wireless drivers</uri></li>
<li>sys-apps/acpid: <uri link="http://acpid.sourceforge.net/">Daemon for Advanced Configuration and Power Interface.</uri></li>
<li>sys-apps/baselayout: <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/">Base layout for Gentoo Linux filesystem (incl. initscripts and sysvinit)</uri></li>
<li>sys-devel/gcc: <uri link="http://www.gnu.org/software/gcc/gcc.html">The GNU Compiler Collection.  Includes C/C++ and java compilers</uri></li>
<li>sys-kernel/compaq-sources: <uri link="http://www.support.compaq.com/alpha-tools/redhat/">Kernel from the Compaq Distribution of Red Hat Linux (ALPHA).</uri></li>
<li>sys-libs/cracklib: <uri link="http://www.crypticide.org/users/alecm/">Password Checking Library</uri></li>
<li>sys-libs/glibc: <uri link="http://www.gnu.org/software/libc/libc.html">GNU libc6 (also called glibc2) C library</uri></li>
<li>sys-libs/libcap: <uri link="http://linux.kernel.org/pub/linux/libs/security/linux-privs/">POSIX 1003.1e capabilities</uri></li>
<li>sys-libs/libchipcard: <uri link="http://www.libchipcard.de/">Libchipcard is a library for easy access to chip cards via chip card readers (terminals).</uri></li>
<li>x11-libs/fltk: <uri link="http://www.fltk.org">C++ user interface toolkit for X and OpenGL.</uri></li>
<li>x11-libs/gtkglext: <uri link="http://gtkglext.sourceforge.net/">GL extentions for Gtk+ 2.0</uri></li>
<li>x11-plugins/asmon: <uri link="http://rio.vg/asmon/">WindowMaker/AfterStep system monitor dockapp</uri></li>
<li>x11-terms/mlterm: <uri link="http://mlterm.sourceforge.net/">A multi-lingual terminal emulator</uri></li>
</ul>
<p>Total categories: 82</p>
<p>Total packages: 4396</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap8_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap8_sect3" >Closed Bug Ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap8_sect4" >New Bug Rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  In the last 7 days, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>277 new bugs this week</li>
	  <li>462 bugs closed or resolved this week</li>
	  <li>3 previously closed bugs were reopened this week.</li>
	  <li>2531 total bugs currently marked 'new'</li>
	  <li>336 total bugs currently assigned to developers</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     There are currently 2910 bugs open in Bugzilla. Of these: 42 are labeled 'blocker', 109 are labeled 'critical',
     and 233 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed Bug Rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs this week are:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li><mail link="swift@gentoo.org" >Sven Vermeulen</mail>, with 20 
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED
                     &amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09&amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15
		     &amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=swift%40gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
         </li>
          <li><mail link="liquidx@gentoo.org" >Alastair Tse</mail>, with 20
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED
                     &amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09&amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15
		     &amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=liquidx%40gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
         </li>
          <li><mail link="mholzer@gentoo.org" >Martin Holzer</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED
                     &amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09&amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15
		     &amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mholzer%40gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
         </li>
          <li><mail link="carpaski@gentoo.org" >Nicholas Jones</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED
                     &amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09&amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15
		     &amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=carpaski%40gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
         </li>
          <li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org" >The KDE Team</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED
                     &amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09&amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15
		     &amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde%40gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
         </li>
     </ul>
     <note>
       <mail link="swift@gentoo.org" >Sven Vermeulen</mail> was overlooked in last week's rankings.
       With 22 closed bugs, he should have been ranked first.
     </note>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New Bug Rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs this week are:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li><mail link="rac@gentoo.org" >Robert Coie</mail>, with 16
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED
                    &amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09
		    &amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=rac%40gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
          </li>
          <li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org" >Martin Schlemmer</mail>, with 12
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED
                    &amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09
		    &amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=azarah%40gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
          </li>
          <li><mail link="xfree@gentoo.org" >The XFree Team</mail>, with 12
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED
                    &amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09
		    &amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=xfree%40gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
          </li>
          <li><mail link="pfeifer@gentoo.org" >Jay Pfeifer</mail>, with 9
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED
                    &amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09
		    &amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=pfeifer%40gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
          </li>
          <li><mail link="x86-kernel@gentoo.org" >The x86-Kernel Team</mail>, with 8
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED
                    &amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-09
		    &amp;chfieldto=2003-05-15&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=x86-kernel%40gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
          </li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Setting the Hardware Clock</p>
<p>
This weeks tip shows you how to set the hardware clock on your Gentoo Linux
box with the command <c>hwclock</c>.
</p>
<p>
Setting the hardware clock is especially useful in case you have clock
problems. If you experience a clock that is losing or gaining a lot of time
each after a reboot, set hardware clock right, then remove /etc/adjtime.
</p>
<p>
<c>hwclock</c> is located in <path>/sbin/hwclock</path> and you'll need
to be root to use it. Without any options, you'll see your current hardware
clock setting.  By using the --systohc option, you can set your hardware
clock to your system clock.
</p>
<pre caption="Using hwclock">
<codenote>Viewing hardware clock</codenote>
# <i>hwclock</i>
<codenote>Setting the hardware clock to system time</codenote>
# <i>hwclock --systohc</i>
</pre>
<note>
There are many other options available for hwclock, see <c>man hwclock</c> for
more information.
</note>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Quote/Signature of the week</title>
<body>
    <p>This week's featured quote actually originated before we started this new section, but still deserves to be mentioned: <e>"I've got this feeling, shared by others I think, that XML is a hammer and everyone's looking for nail-like objects."</e> (Joseph Carter in a <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8422/">discussion</uri> about an init replacement.)</p>
    <p>Nothing against XML though, we happily use it for bringing the GWN to you! It's just that the hype gets a little annoying from time to time...
    </p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, Adds and Changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><e>none this week</e></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo Linux project.</p>
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<body>
	<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Feedback</title>
	<body>
	<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make GWN better.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Subscription Information</title>
	<body>
	<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <email>gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</email>.</p>
	<p>To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <email>gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</email> from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Other Languages</title>
	<body>
	<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
