<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050905-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>September 5th, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="agriffis@gentoo.org">Aron Griffis</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="stuart@gentoo.org">Stuart Herbert</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="curtis119@gentoo.org">Curtis Napier</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 5 September 2005.</abstract>
<summary/>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 35</version>
<date>2005-09-05</date>

<!-- Gentoo News -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo news</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo developer council elected</title>
<body>
<p>
Developer-only polls closed last Wednesday to choose the newly created Gentoo 
Council.  The Council will be made up of seven developers elected from a group 
of <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~slarti/misc/nominees.html">25
candidates</uri> on the ballot. The Council's job will be to support
the cooperation of subprojects within Gentoo. The Council will have
responsibility of making distribution-wide decisions that help the
project to make unified steps forward. This election followed the Gentoo 
Metastructure election, which earlier this year chose <uri 
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~g2boojum/proposal.html">Grant Goodyear's
proposal</uri> for a reform of Gentoo's project management, taking <uri
link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~spb/ciaranm-slacker-boot-proposal.txt">Ciaran 
McCreesh's amendments</uri> into consideration.
</p>
<p>
The voter turnout was "not too shabby", according to the election 
officials, with 148 active Gentoo developers electing the following seven
new council members:</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail></li>
<li><mail link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike Frysinger</mail></li>
<li><mail link="agriffis@gentoo.org">Aron Griffis</mail></li>
<li><mail link="solar@gentoo.org">Ned Ludd</mail></li>
<li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</mail></li>
<li><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></li>
<li><mail link="koon@gentoo.org">Thierry Carrez</mail></li>
</ul>
<p>Congratulations to all those who were elected to the new role (which can be 
collectively addressed as <mail link="council@gentoo.org">"council@gentoo.org"</mail>, 
by the way), and many thanks to all the other nominees and everybody who 
participated in the vote.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Simultaneous PHP4/PHP5 support in Gentoo</title>
<body>
<p>
The PHP Herd is pleased to announce that it has added new packages to
Portage which will allow Gentoo to provide stable PHP4 and PHP5 packages
on the same box at the same time.  These packages have come from the
successful <uri link="http://stu.gnqs.org/diary/gentoo.php">PHP Overlay</uri>.
At the heart of these packages is the new <path>dev-lang/php</path> package (which
will replace the existing <path>dev-php/php</path>, <path>dev-php/php-cgi</path>, and
<path>dev-php/mod_php</path> packages), and the new <path>dev-php4</path>  and <path>dev-php5</path> categories
which allow us to provide, and support, PHP extensions and frameworks
that are specific to each version of PHP.
</p>
<p>
These changes also leave us well-placed for the next major release of
PHP (possibly called PHP-6), which upstream developers are currently brewing.
We hope to move these packages to <path>~arch</path> (on architectures that the PHP
Herd supports) on <b>Thursday 8th September</b>, as part of our <uri 
link="http://svn.gnqs.org/projects/gentoo-php-overlay/">migration plans</uri>.  If 
you find any problems with the packages, please file bugs in Bugzilla as normal.
</p>
<p>
We are aiming to remove the old <path>dev-php/php-4*</path> et al packages on 
<b>8 January 2006</b>; support for non-security issues will cease two months
earlier on <b>8 October 2005</b>.  The older <path>dev-php/php-5*</path> et al packages
have been removed today; anyone still using these packages should move
across to the new <path>dev-lang/php</path> package.
</p>
<p>
Support for other architectures will follow as and when other arch teams
can resource it; you can follow the progress in <uri 
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/102649">a metabug</uri> set up for this purpose, 
and provide feedback to help the arch teams assess the stability of these packages.
The PHP Overlay will continue to be the place where the PHP Herd does
most of its development and testing.  You'll find more packages in the
Overlay than in Portage, and new versions of packages will be tested in
the Overlay first.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Forums TOR rejection policy alleviated</title>
<body>
<p>
As reported <uri link="/news/en/gwn/20050808-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1_sect2">earlier</uri>, 
TOR users were recently blocked from the Gentoo Forums. Thanks to feedback from 
the TOR user community the Forums infrastructure lead, <mail 
link="tomk@gentoo.org">Tom Knight</mail>, has changed the TOR policy to allow 
read-only access to the Forums. All TOR users can now browse the Forums again 
without having to change any settings. TOR users who want to <e>post</e> to 
the forums will have to add the following to their exit policy:
</p>

<pre caption="Reject Forums - TOR exit policy">
ExitPolicy reject 140.211.166.170:80,reject 140.211.166.170:443
</pre>

<p>
If you are receiving a TOR error message while trying to post to the 
Gentoo Forums and you do <b>not</b> use TOR please send an email to the <mail 
link="forum-mods@gentoo.org">Forum administrators</mail> that includes the IP 
address that is being blocked.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Future zone -->
<!-- User Stories -->
<!-- Gentoo Stories -->
<!-- Developer of the week -->
<chapter>
<title>Developer of the week</title>
<section>
<title>"Aight, I put on my robe and wizard hat." -- Mike Doty (KingTaco)</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050905_kingtaco.jpg"
  short="kingtaco" caption="Mike Doty aka KingTaco" />
<p>
Mike Doty, better known as KingTaco to most, is the AMD64 strategic lead, a 
contributor to developer relations/recruitment, and a part-time member of the 
infrastructure team (for torrents and as liaison to two hosting facilities).
His role in Gentoo is, in his own words, "providing long term goals to 
the amd64 team, as well as ensuring that their efforts are directed where 
we need them most." Mike's activities at the developer relation project cover 
new developer account administration, recruitment, and sitting as a judge on 
the devrel panel. He also acts as the contact for the hosting provided by 
<uri link="http://www.cs.luc.edu">Loyola University Chicago</uri> and <uri
link="http://www.tavros.net">Tavros Technology Services</uri>, who both provide 
bandwidth and equipment to gentoo.
</p>
<p>
In terms of PR, Mikes biggest achievement to date is the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/base/amd64/tests/index.xml?part=1&amp;chap=1">ArchTester 
project</uri> which started as an experiment to help power users get more 
involved with Gentoo, quickly received wide public attention, and brought 
in several new devs to the AMD64 team. 
</p>
<p>
"Believe it or not, I was kicked out of Loyola University Chicago for not
attending class," says Mike, who now works for Tavros Technology Services as a
consultant. But he hasn't cut his ties with the university completely, working with
a research group at Loyola doing research on cluster- and grid
computing. Mike is experimenting there with complex topologies using
commodity hardware, mostly ieee1394a ("firewire") interconnects. At the
moment that is mostly done on an 8-node AMD64 cluster with a cube
topology, but this might be expanded to 64 nodes soon - and of course
all these nodes run Gentoo! "Outside of work, research, and Gentoo I 
sometimes find time to play with my cats and watch South Park."
</p>
<p>
Before being submerged into the Gentoo experience, Mike was a coder and 
admin for <uri link="http://strangemud.net">StrangeMUD</uri>, but these days 
his time is shared mostly between work and Gentoo. The hardware he keeps in 
his home demands some attention, too: an AMD Athlon64 3000+ 1280MB RAM with 
dual monitors serves as the main development box, another AMD AthlonXP 1800+ 
768MB RAM as file/web/VoIP server and secondary router. Keeping those two 
company are a sturdy old Intel pII 350 256MB RAM (his primary router), a VIA 
C3/800 ITX 384MB RAM that's destined to become the new web/email server, and 
two Intel pIII 600 laptops, one for traveling, one as a test box for other 
distros. Mikes preferred window manager is <c>xfce4</c>, complemented by 
his choice of applications: Emacs, Firefox, Thunderbird, <c>beep-media-player</c>, 
<c>xchat</c>, <c>xterm</c>, and <c>gxine</c>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Heard in the community: gentoo-dev, gentoo-user, forums -->
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Gentoo events worldwide</b></p>
<p>
The forums have had a special place in "Gentoo Chat" to try and organize
Gentoo events and meetings. It's constantly updated, if you've got an event
the community at large should know about, all you need to do is sending
a personal message to the <mail link="forum-mods@gentoo.org">Forum moderators</mail>.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-250393.html">Gentoo events and meetings</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>x86 arch team</b></p>
<p>
What started as a proposal to put x86 and amd64 under one shared keyword,
causing a long and heated debate which got summarized by <mail
link="chriswhite@gentoo.org">Chris White</mail> in a separate thread,
finally moved on to a different proposal: creating an x86 arch team that
should focus on Quality Assurance and x86-specific problems.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/30952">combining
x86 and amd64 arch keywords </uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/31028">ChrisWhite's
summary </uri></li>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/31060">tentative
x86 arch team GLEP </uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo international -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo international</title>
<section>
<title>Japan: Gentoo booth and conference participation at OSC 2005</title>
<body>
<figure link="/images/gwn/20050905_obs.jpg"
  short="OpenBlockS" caption="Router, firewall, web server: The OpenBlockS, on display at the Gentoo booth" />
<p>
Tokyo's annual <uri link="http://www.ospn.jp:16080/osc2005-fall/">Open Source 
Conference</uri> is scheduled for 17 September this year, and the <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.gr.jp">GentooJP</uri> activists are gearing up for a 
hands-on seminar that will present a complete 2005.1 stage 3 installation, and 
a display of their own: the OSC Gentoo booth is placed under the motto "Actually, 
this runs Gentoo, too..." and will be predominantly showing off pocekt-sized systems
like the <uri link="http://www.plathome.co.jp/products/openblocks/openblocks266/index.html">OpenBlockS</uri>, 
some individually assembled no-name x86 PCs, and other hardware. Books about Gentoo 
will be on sale, and CDs of the 2005.1 release will be distributed to visitors, of 
course. If you're in Tokyo on 17 September, don't miss this event.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- Gentoo in the press -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo in the press</title>
<section>
<title>Linux User &amp; developer (September 2005)</title>
<body>
<p>
In their current issue, the British <uri 
link="http://www.linuxuser.co.uk/">Linux User &amp; Developer</uri> magazine 
published an enthusiastic review of Genesi's Open Desktop Workstation with 
pre-installed Gentoo Linux for PPC (that can be purchased via Gentoo's <uri 
link="http://vendors.gentoo.org/index.cgi?page=1&amp;comGroup=1">vendors 
page</uri>, with ten percent of each sale going to the Gentoo foundation). The 
article gives full marks to the "powerful yet inexpensive PowerPC workstation 
aimed squarely at the Linux market," calls Gentoo and the handful of other 
Linux/PPC  distributions that come pre-installed on the ODW "robust and 
basically identical to their Intel counterparts," although one of the cons 
among a majority of pros in this review is that "PowerPC Linux still lags being 
x86 Linux in terms of popularity," and concludes that - at least for PPC 
developers - "it's hard to see the Open Desktop Workstation as anything other 
than perfect." The magazine is available to subscribers only, but Gentoo sponsor 
Genesi has a reprint permission, and the full article can be downloaded from <uri link="http://genesi.pegasosppc.com/press.php?date=20050901">their website.</uri> 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Tips and Tricks -->
<chapter>
<title>Tips and tricks</title>
<section>
<title>Searching for kernel features</title>
<body>
<p>
If you cannot find what you are looking for in the kernel then there is a
minimal search function provided by the "/" (slash) key. Just 
</p>
<pre caption="make menuconfig">
# <i>make menuconfig</i> <comment>Hit the slash key, then your search term</comment>
</pre> 
<p>
and try it out, perhaps with something easy first, like DMA.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Moves, adds, and changes -->
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>
<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Edgar Hucek (gimli) - Xbox</li>
<li>Stefaan De Roeck (stefaan) - OpenAFS filesystem</li>
<li>Marco Morales (soulse) - netmon herd</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>
<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the
Gentoo Linux project:</p>
<ul>
<li><e>None this week</e></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo security -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Security</title>
<!-- paste from the script -->

<section>
<title>lm_sensors: Insecure temporary file creation</title>
<body>
<p>

lm_sensors is vulnerable to linking attacks, potentially allowing a local
user to overwrite arbitrary files.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200508-19.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>phpGroupWare: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

phpGroupWare is vulnerable to multiple issues ranging from information
disclosure to a potential execution of arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200508-20.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>phpWebSite: Arbitrary command execution through XML-RPC and SQL injection</title>
<body>
<p>

phpWebSite is vulnerable to multiple issues which result in the execution
of arbitrary code and SQL injection.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200508-21.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>pam_ldap: Authentication bypass vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

pam_ldap contains a vulnerability that may allow a remote attacker to gain
system access.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200508-22.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>MPlayer: Heap overflow in ad_pcm.c</title>
<body>
<p>

A heap overflow in MPlayer might lead to the execution of arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200509-01.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gnumeric: Heap overflow in the included PCRE library</title>
<body>
<p>

Gnumeric is vulnerable to a heap overflow, possibly leading to the
execution of arbitrary code.

</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200509-02.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Bugzilla -->
<!-- paste from the script -->
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">New bug rankings</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the
development team.  Between 28 August 2005
and 04 September 2005, activity on the site has resulted in:
</p>
<ul>
<li>753 new bugs during this period</li>
<li>393 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
<li>36 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
</ul>
<p>
Of the 8169 currently open bugs: 97 are labeled 'blocker', 197 are labeled 'critical', and 536 are labeled 'major'.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org">AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 96
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org">Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 22
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">Gentoo Games</mail>, with 16
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org">Gentoo Security</mail>, with 13
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org">media-video herd</mail>, with 13
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 13
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kernel@gentoo.org">Gentoo Kernel Bug Wranglers and Kernel Maintainers</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kernel@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 9
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
</p>
<ul>
<li><mail link="maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for New Packages</mail>, with 35
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org">AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 15
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 12
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org">Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</mail>, with 11
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;assigned_to=maintainer-needed@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="kernel@gentoo.org">Gentoo Kernel Bug Wranglers and Kernel Maintainers</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;assigned_to=kernel@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org">Gentoo Games</mail>, with 10
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org">Java team</mail>, with 8
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-08-28&amp;chfieldto=2005-09-04&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org">new bugs</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- GWN feedback information -->
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and
help make the GWN better.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<!-- GWN subscription information -->
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p> 
<p> To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to
<mail
link="gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>
from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Other Languages -->
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following
languages:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/nl/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt_br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri>
</li>
<li>
<uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri>
</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
