<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>May 12th, 2003</subtitle>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of May 12th, 2003.</abstract>
<summary>Gentoo Linux to make major announcement at E3. Gentoo Technologies to partner with Super Computer, Inc. to bring Gentoo Linux to the Opteron platform.</summary>
<version>Volume 2, Issue 19</version>
<date>12 May 2003</date>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="nesta@iceburg.net">Brice Burgess</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
	<mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="david@phrixus.net">David Narayan</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="mail@psharp.uklinux.net">Peter Sharp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="kim@thinkit.dk">Kim Tingkaer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="matje@lanzone.be">Mathy Vanvoorden</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="tom.vanlaerhoven@luc.ac.be">Tom Van Laerhoven</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="phj.dijkstra@home.nl">Peter Dijkstra</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="bernieke@bernieke.com">Bernard Bernieke</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="zu@pandora.be">Vincent Verleye</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="linux@sejo.be">Jochen Maes</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="yngwin@xs4all.nl">Ben De Groot</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="j.jaarsma@dordrecht.arbounie.nl">Jelmer Jaarsma</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
    <mail link="mat@frheaven.com">Matthieu Montaudouin</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
    <mail link="riverdale@linuxmail.org">Martin Prieto</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="madeagle@gentoo.org">Steffen Lassahn</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="haim@gentoo.org">Matthias F. Brandstetter</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="yanestra@gentoo.org">Klaus-J. Wolf</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="mush@monrif.net">Marco Mascherpa</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="paper@tiscali.it">Claudio Merloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="bsolar@bluewin.ch">Christian Apolloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="kage-chan@gentoo.org">Daniel Ketel</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="hagi@p1d.com">Yoshiaki Hagihara</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="andy@billydpro.com">Andy Hunne</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="yasunori@mail.portland.co.uk">Yasunori Fukudome</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
    <mail link="088@t.email.ne.jp">Takashi Ota</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="venturasbarbeiro@ig.com.br">Ventura Barbeiro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="blueroom@digitalmente.net">Bruno Ferreira</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="gustavo@felisberto.net">Gustavo Felisberto</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="rjlouro@rjlouro.org">Ricardo Jorge Louro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="R.Nogueira@records.usyd.edu.au">Ricardo Nogueira</mail>
</author>
<author title="Russian Translation">
	<mail link="infapx@yandex.ru">Sergey Kuleshov</mail>
</author>
<author title="Russian Translation">
	<mail link="dimsuz@mail.ru">Dmitry Suzdalev</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="lanark@lanark.com.ar">Lanark</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="julio@castillobueno.com">Julio Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="s3r@fibertel.com.ar">Sergio G&#243;mez</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="pablo.leira@pitagoral.com">Pablo Pita Leira</mail>	
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@castillobueno.com">Carlos Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="tirant@menta.net">Tirant</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="jfreire@ya.com">Jaime Freire</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="krusty_ar@yahoo.com">Lucas Sallovitz</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
	<mail link="cagils@biznet.com.tr">Cagil Seker</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
	<mail link="aycan@core.gen.tr">Aycan Irican</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
	<mail link="emre@core.gen.tr">Emre Kazdagli</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
	<mail link="gurcell@gurcell.com">Gursel Kaynak</mail>
</author>
<author title="Turkish Translation">
	<mail link="19913500@mail.baskent.edu.tr">Bugra Cakir</mail>
</author>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Gentoo Linux to make major announcement at E3</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">Gentoo Technologies to partner with Super Computer, Inc. to bring Gentoo Linux to the Opteron platform</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Gentoo Linux to make major announcement at E3</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Gentoo Linux will be present at the upcoming <uri link="http://www.e3expo.com">Electronics Entertainment Exposition</uri> in Los Angeles.  E3, as it is more commonly known as, focuses on items related to electronic entertainment, including game consoles, computer video games, entertainment and edutainment software and other entertainment-related technologies and industries.  Considered as the premier event for its industry, E3 brings all of the major players together under one roof.
		</p>
		<p>
		In addition to building brand awareness and educating people about the benefits of Gentoo Linux, Gentoo Technologies will be making a significant announcement on May 14th that will be covered in detail in next week's GWN.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Gentoo Technologies to partner with Super Computer, Inc. to bring Gentoo Linux to the Opteron and other enterprise platforms</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		We're pleased to announce that <uri link="http://www.supercomputerinc.com">Super Computer, Inc</uri>. (SCI) will be helping
		the Gentoo Linux development team to create a 64-bit version of Gentoo Linux
		for the AMD Opteron processor. SCI will initiate this relationship by
		providing the Gentoo Linux development team with a dual Opteron workstation
		as well as any other assistance required to officially support for the AMD
		Opteron platform.</p>
		<p>
		In cooperation with <uri link="http://www.racksaver.com">RackSaver</uri>, SCI will arrange
		for early access to future enterprise-class hardware. RackSaver has joined
		SCI in its efforts to support the continued development of Gentoo Linux into
		an enterprise-level operating system.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Security</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">GLSAs</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3">New Security Bug Reports</uri></li>
			</ul> 
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GLSAs</title>
		<body>
		<p>
                <e>
				There were no GLSAs issued during the week prior to
                this summary's compilation.
        		</e>
		</p>
                    
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New Security Bug Reports</title>
		<body>
		<p>
        		<e>
				There were no new security bugs reported this week.
				</e>
        </p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>User stories</title>
<body>
<p>Starting with the current issue, the GWN will feature this brand-new section. Here you'll be given the chance to share your story with the Gentoo community!
</p>
<p>So did you just switch an entire serverfarm to Gentoo? Have you convinced your grandma not to make steaks out of Larry the Cow? Or did you build a gigantic space station running Gentoo Linux, to take over the world? Tell us! Anything interesting, funny or plain unbelievable you discovered while installing, using or modifying Gentoo Linux is welcome! Just send your story to <mail link="user-stories@gentoo.org">user-stories@gentoo.org</mail> and enjoy your 15 minutes of fame! ;)</p>

<impo>Due to the sheer volume of responses that we expect, please don't be offended if your submission doesn't make it into the GWN.  There are thousands upon thousands of Gentoo users, but only one issue of the GWN each week.</impo>

<p>Enough talking, let's get the ball rolling and take a look what our first featured user has to tell us:</p>

<p class="secthead">Kai-Uwe Kriewald and rsync7.de.gentoo.org</p>

<figure link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030512_kai.jpg" short="Kai and his servers" caption="Kai and his servers" />

<p>Kai is currently 35 years old and living in Hannover, Germany. There he's working at the <uri link="http://www.fh-hannover.de/english/ueberblick/index.htm">University of Applied Sciences and Arts</uri> where he and his 3 colleagues are trying to keep the University's IT infrastructure up and running. This is not always an easy job when you have to cope with about 6000 students, 100 workstations (Windows) and 15 servers (Novell/Windows/Linux). Despite his job his hobbies include everything regarding computers, as well as movies/going to the cinema, riding his bike and reading (especially dramas and Science Fiction).</p>

<p><b>Why Gentoo Linux?</b></p>
<p>Kai discovered Linux when the Kernel was still at version 0.9x and using it involved a lot of DIY. After a while he switched to SuSE Linux which he effectively run for several years. Like Larry the Cow he became frustrated with all the bloat and graphical wizards featured in most of the latest distros and started to look for an optimzed server OS which gives full control over every detail of the configuration to the admin. At the end of 2002 he finally discovered Gentoo Linux which seemed to fit his needs just perfect.</p> 

<p><b>Running the mirrors</b></p>

<p>Actually Kai found out that he liked Gentoo so much, that he decided to set up a rsync (rsync7.de.gentoo.org) and distfiles mirror. He did this out of two reasons: first he wanted fast access to all the distfiles in the initial phase of trying out and setting up Gento Linux. On the other hand he says he wanted to support Gentoo Linux and give something back to the community which made and still makes this great distribution possible. This is an excellent example of how open source/free software should work!</p>

<p>Currently a  Celeron 1.3GHz, with 256MB of RAM, a 100GB HDD and a 100MBit connections is used for mirroring. This is soon to be replaced by a P4 2.6GHz, with 1GB RAM, a 250GB HDD and a 1GBit connection. But Kai has bigger plans for the future: he wants to set up a High Availability cluster using two of the latter systems.</p>

<p><b>Conclusion and future prospects</b></p>
<p>Thanks to years of experience in running mirrors (in his "Windows days" Kai used to run the primary Tucows mirror for Germany), good advice by <mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail> and the nice people on the mirror-admin mailing list, he dind't run into any major problems yet (except for using compressed rsync which he deactivated). The mirror is offering distfiles to the users in 3 different ways: rsync, WWW (<uri link="http://www.apache.org">Apache</uri>) and FTP (<uri link="http://www.pureftpd.org">PureFTPd</uri>). All these packages are well tested and documented, so running them shouldn't give you too much headaches.</p>

<p>With ongoing hardware upgrades Kai and his team continue to replace SuSE installations with Gentoo Linux and plan to also use it as firewall,proxy, database and CMS server. Sadly they couldn't get Gentoo to run Informix 9.3 (Kai thinks this is due to too new libraries in Gentoo Linux), which is now run on SuSE 8.1.</p>

<p>If you have questions regarding setting up and running mirrors for Gentoo Linux you can contact Kai by <mail link="Kai-Uwe.Kriewald@Verw.FH-Hannover.DE">mail</mail>.</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Featured Developer of the Week</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Jack Morgan</p>
<figure
link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/gwn/20030512_jmorgan.jpg" short="Jack Morgan" caption="Jack Morgan" />
<p>
<mail link="jmorgan@gentoo.org">Jack Morgan</mail> is one of the Gentoo-SPARC project co-leads, and as such makes sure that releases get ready, new developers get recruited, bugs get fixed, ISOs get made, and more.  A Gentoo-SPARC developer since July 2002, just after the SPARC port began, Jack has met about half of Gentoo's developers at Linux World Expo, FOSDEM, and in Oregon, where he lives, and his goal is to meet over 80%.
</p>
<p>
Jack's favorite applications include Mutt and exim, not to mention Tux Racer.  He has a SPARCStation 5 on which to do testing, an Ultra 30, his main development box, as well as two Athlon XP boxen: a fileserver and a workstation; he uses SCSI disks whenever possible.  He usually doesn't run XFree, but uses fluxbox when he does, as well as irssi, mutt, and many other console apps.  Jack recently moved to Eugene, Oregon from Japan, where he lived for eight and a half years and met his wife.  He spends most of his free time with his three kids, but also runs marathons and likes to play Japanese board games like Shogi and Go.
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard In The Community</title>
	<section>
	<title>Web Forums</title>
	<body>
	<p><b>Alleviating the Pressure on rsync Servers</b></p>

	<p>Last week's GWN reminded Gentooists that synching the portage tree should be reigned by sanity, as opposed to abusing the system by issuing an 'emerge rsync' every other hour or so. A few of the usual suspects in the Forums, always true to form, quickly picked this up and started offering their own clever solutions, including checks of the CVS changelogs and only synching if anything of interest to somebody's own configuration has been updated.</p>
	<p><ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=51945">rsync etiquette guideline</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	<p><b>Lotus Domino in Gentoo</b></p>
	<p>Running applications only available in binary form may be tricky in a source-based distribution. In a nice example of help yourself, help others, <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=6806">steveb</uri> has documented his init scripts to get a Lotus Domino server up and running:</p>
	<p><ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=37172">IBM Lotus Domino R6/(R5) gentoo init scripts</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	<p><b>Binary Packages in Gentoo, Portage in Other Distributions?</b></p>
	<p>Source distribution evangelists are hardly ever tempted by pre-compiled applications, and even if they were, serving all USE flag permutations via the Gentoo Reference Platform just doesn't look feasible, does it now... Contrary to popular belief, there are rather nice binary package management systems out there, like Arch's Pacman or Crux' cvsup-based ports system, but would they make sense as tools in Gentoo? Have a look at the latest thread about binary vs. source distro virtues:</p>
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=52224">Superduo?</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=28559">Installing Portage on Other Distros</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</body>
	</section>

  <section>
     <title>gentoo-user</title>
     <body>
       <p><b>gentoo-user as a newsgroup</b></p>
       <p>
	Let's face it, we can all use some extra time during the day. If you're like the many who suffer through several high traffic mailing lists per day, a little time organizing could save you hours! No, we're not going to sell you a pocket organizer or even encourage you to buy a rolodex. What's at hand here is a sound discussion on how to best sort through the gentoo-user list. Apparently, using <uri link="nntp://news.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user">gmane</uri> as a newsgroup reader and/or <uri link="http://www.gnus.org">gnus</uri> to sort through threads is a popular solution. Martin Gramatke <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/32511">pointed out</uri> how to subscribe to the gentoo-user list as post only and use gmane to read the list.
       </p>
       <ul>
         <li><uri link="http://news.gmane.org/onethread.php?group=gmane.linux.gentoo.user&amp;root=%3C200305032047.42330.xmit%40gmx.de%3E">gentoo-user as a newsgroup</uri></li>
       </ul>
       <p><b>why rsync?</b></p>
       <p>
	It appears that some members of the gentoo-user community, namely Rev. Jeffrey Paul, <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/32380">question</uri> the use of rsync in Gentoo's package managment system. His complaint is simple; &quot;rsync requires special server and client software, increases loads on the servers, and significantly limits the number of mirrors (by not being http/ftp compatible).&quot; Others think a change to the system is not necessary at the moment, as Paul de Vrieze best <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/32424">describes</uri>. While others want to see rsync <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/32387">further tweaked</uri> ala Mandrake's Troels bandwith saving system. Whatever the case, this is an enlightening thread covering an interesting issue.
       </p>
       <ul>
         <li><uri link="http://news.gmane.org/onethread.php?group=gmane.linux.gentoo.user&amp;root=%3CPine.LNX.4.44.0305080816370.23093-100000%40datavibe.net%3E">life, the universe, and everything (why rsync?!)</uri></li>
       </ul>
       <p><b>More Portage Sync Etiquette</b></p>
       <p>
	Sticking to the topic of bandwith saving and rsync, Louis Candell began a long <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/31892">discussion</uri> on the proper methods of updating multiple Gentoo machines on a LAN. <uri link="http://nfs.sourceforge.net">NFS</uri> (Network File System) was the agreed upon solution. Rex Young let us know that &quot;It[NFS] just works, and it's just easy.  If you export /usr/portage to all of the machines on the network, syncing from any one of them leaves all of them synced.  It really saves bandwidth, and can be used to ease some of the administration on the machines.&quot; If you plan on implementing NFS to share a common /usr/portage tree, reading Marius Mauch's <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/32013">approach</uri> may help, and be sure all GIDs and UIDs match on all machines and that you read Lee Fickenscher's <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/31991">advice</uri>.
       </p>
       <ul>
         <li><uri link="http://news.gmane.org/onethread.php?group=gmane.linux.gentoo.user&amp;root=%3Cuut7k96t2xz.fsf%40ossh.com%3E">GWN's Portage Sync Etiquette</uri></li>
       </ul>

     </body>
</section>
<section>
  <title>gentoo-dev</title>
  <body>
  <p>This week there is alot of renewed focus on the init system. Suggestions to add functionality or even entirely replace the current system based on shell scripts with one written entirely in Python.</p>
  <p><b>New service dependency</b></p>
  <p>The idea came up to add a means of communicating when a script has started successfully, in between init and the service scripts. So the service can rely on another being up and functional before starting up itself. <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8433">Read about</uri> how this would work.</p>
  <p><b>Init replacement</b></p>
  <p>An interesting proposal was brought up about writing the Gentoo init scripts in Python.  <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8445">Read about</uri> the pros and cons</p>  
  <p><b>GentooBSD</b></p>
  <p>Also, Jeff Jeter has been working on adapting Portage to run on FreeBSD.  <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8436">Here is how far he is with his project.</uri> Interested people should contact Jeff with their feedback and input.</p>
  <p><b>XFree 4.3.0</b></p>
  <p>And finally, we are now well into the second release of XFree 4.3.0. Take a look at the <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/8456">latest</uri> discussion.</p>
  </body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo International</title>
    <body>
	<p class="secthead">Regional German Gentoo User Meeting in Cologne, not Bonn!</p>
<p>Correcting the mistake made in last week's GWN, the meeting of Gentooists in and around K&#246;ln/Bonn will indeed take place this Wednesday, 14 May 2003, but <uri link="http://www.hellers-brauhaus.de">Hellers Brauhaus</uri> is of course located on Roonstrasse in K&#246;ln, not Bonn as previously reported. Be there from 18:00, tell the others you're coming <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=40510">right here</uri>. </p>
	<p class="secthead">German Gentoo User Map</p>
<p>It's merely a fallout from a more ambitious project to get German Gentoo users to register for a future all-German meeting, but it's rather nice in itself: <uri link="http://cybersystem.iq-computing.de/gentoo/"></uri> holds an interactive map where Gentooists in Germany can mark their current whereabouts based on GPS data. </p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Portage Watch</title>
<section>
<title>The following packages were updated since the last issue:</title>
<body>
<p>We have started to use a different method to provide the information we present in this section so, please, report any errors or inconsistencies you may find. Thanks!!</p>
<ul>
<li>app-office/abiword: <uri link="http://www.abisource.com">Fully featured yet light and fast cross platform word processor.</uri></li>
<li>dev-haskell/happy: <uri link="http://haskell.org/happy/">A yacc-like parser generator for Haskell</uri></li>
<li>dev-haskell/hdoc: <uri link="http://www.fmi.uni-passau.de/~groessli/hdoc/">A documentation generator for Haskell</uri></li>
<li>dev-haskell/hmake: <uri link="http://www.haskell.org/hmake/">a make tool for Haskell programs</uri></li>
<li>dev-java/ant: <uri link="http://ant.apache.org">Java-based build tool similar to 'make' that uses XML configuration files.</uri></li>
<li>dev-python/4Suite: <uri link="http://www.4suite.org/">Python tools for XML processing and object-databases.</uri></li>
<li>dev-tcltk/Tk_Theme: <uri link="http://www.xmission.com/~georgeps/Tk_Theme/">Theming library for TCL/TK.</uri></li>
<li>kde-base/arts: <uri link="http://multimedia.kde.org">KDE 3.x Sound Server</uri></li>
<li>kde-base/kde: <uri link="http://www.kde.org/">KDE 3.1 - merge this to pull in all non-developer kde-base/* packages</uri></li>
<li>media-libs/SoGtk: <uri link="http://www.coin3d.org">A Gtk Interface for coin</uri></li>
<li>media-video/DFBSee: <uri link="http://www.directfb.org/dfbsee.xml">DFBSee is image viewer and video player based on DirectFB</uri></li>
<li>net-dialup/capi4k-utils: <uri link="ftp://ftp.in-berlin.de/pub/capi4linux/">Capi4Linux Utils</uri></li>
<li>net-dns/bind: <uri link="http://www.isc.org/products/BIND/bind9.html">BIND - Berkeley Internet Name Domain - Name Server</uri></li>
<li>net-firewall/dynfw: <uri link="http://gentoo.org/projects/dynfw">Dynamic Firewall Tools for netfilter-based firewalls</uri></li>
<li>net-p2p/bittorrent: <uri link="http://bitconjurer.org/BitTorrent">BitTorrent is a tool for distributing files via a distributed network of nodes</uri></li>
<li>sys-kernel/gentoo-sources: <uri link="http://cvs.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/gentoo-x86/sys-kernel/gentoo-sources/ChangeLog?rev=1.24">Full sources for the Gentoo Linux kernel</uri></li>
</ul>
<p>Total number of categories available: 82</p>
<p>Total number of packages available: 4167</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Bugzilla</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<ul>
        <li><uri link="#doc_chap8_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap8_sect3">Closed Bug Ranking</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap8_sect3">New Bug Rankings</uri></li>
        </ul>                           
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Statistics</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
                bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  In the last 7 days, activity
                on the site has resulted in:
                </p>
			<ul>
				<li>229 new bugs this week</li>
				<li>423 bugs closed or resolved this week</li>
                                <li>5 previously closed bugs were reopened this week.</li>
				<li>2523 total bugs currently marked 'new'</li>
				<li>345 total bugs currently assigned to developers</li>
			</ul>
                <p>
                There are currently 2914 bugs open in bugzilla. Of these: 48 are labeled 'blocker', 104 are labeled 'critical',
                and 228 are labeled 'major'.
		</p>
                </body>
        </section>
        <section>
		<title>Closed Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs
                this week are:
                </p>
		<ul>
		<li><mail link="mholzer@gentoo.org">Martin Holzer</mail>, with 20 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-03&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mholzer%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		<li><mail link="x86-kernel@gentoo.org">The x86 Kernel Team</mail>, with 19 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-03&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=x86-kernel%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		<li><mail link="rac@gentoo.org">Robert Coie</mail>, with 18 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-03&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=rac%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		<li><mail link="aliz@gentoo.org">Daniel Ahlberg</mail>, with 15 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-03&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=aliz%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
        <section>
		<title>New Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs this week are:
                </p>
		<ul>		
                <li><mail link="rac@gentoo.org">Robert Coie</mail>, with 19 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-03&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=rac%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>			
                <li><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>, with 12 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-03&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=swift%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>				
                <li><mail link="robbat2@gentoo.org">Robin Johnson</mail>, with 11 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-03&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=robbat2%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>	
                <li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</mail>, with 9 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-05-03&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=azarah%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
                </ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Using Fluxbox Autogrouping</p>
<p>
If you use the Fluxbox window manager, autogrouping and tabs allows you to
view programs as a grouped window instead of separate windows. This week's
tips demonstrates this feature using Eterm as an example.
</p>
<p>
First, you have to edit your <path>~/.fluxbox/init</path> file. Make sure the group file is defined.
</p>
<pre caption="~/.fluxbox/init">
<codenote>Add the following line</codenote>
session.groupFile:    ~/.fluxbox/groups
</pre>
<note>
Make sure there are no tabs or extra spaces at the end of the line or it won't
work correctly.
</note>
<p>
The next file to edit is the <path>~/.fluxbox/groups</path> file. This file
specifies program that automatically open inside a tabbed group. Simply add
one program per line.
</p>
<pre caption="~/.fluxbox/groups">
<codenote>Using our Eterm example, add this line</codenote>
Eterm
</pre>
<note>
To find out the exact name of the command to put in the file, use the command
<c>xprop | grep '^WM_CLASS'</c> and paste the name into the file.
</note>

<p>
Now when you open Eterms, they will open as a group. If you want other programs
to do the same thing, just add them to your <path>~/.fluxbox/groups</path>
file.
</p>

</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Quote/Signature of the week</title>
<body>
<p><e>Starting this week, every issue of the GWN will feature a funny or interesting signature or quote seen in the Gentoo community (forums, IRC, mailing lists).</e></p>
<p>
    Gentoo Developer <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail> uses the following signature for his mails:
    <e>"Thanks to DRM, you know that something has been built in environment of unspecified degree of security, from source you cannot check, written by programmers you don't know, released after passing QA of unknown quality and which is released under a license which disclaims any
        responsibility..."</e>
Something we should all think about...
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, Adds and Changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li>Rodney Rees (manson)</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><e>none this week</e></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo Linux project.</p>
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<body>
	<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Feedback</title>
	<body>
	<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make GWN better.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Subscription Information</title>
	<body>
	<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <email>gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</email>.</p>
	<p>To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <email>gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</email> from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Other Languages</title>
	<body>
	<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
