<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" link="20050110-newsletter.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>January 10, 2005</subtitle>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="bdowney@briandowney.net">Brian Downey</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="dsd@gentoo.org">Daniel Drake</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="ian@gentoo.org">Christian Hartmann</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="patrick@gentoo.org">Patrick Lauer</mail></author>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of 10 January 2005.</abstract>
<summary></summary>
<version>Volume 4, Issue 2</version>
<date>2004-01-10</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>
<section>
<title>Discouraging Forum abuse: visual registration confirmation added</title>
<body>
<p>In the last week of December 2004, an attacker had registered about 8,500 user accounts 
from more than 160 hosts, in less than one hour. While the Forum admins were working 
on a solution to block these registrations, users started reporting the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=271717">mass forum account registrations</uri>.
A few hours later <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=271802">15696 user 
accounts were deleted</uri>, taking along a number of inactive accounts from the past.</p>
<p>
To prevent these mass registration attempts from happening again, a visual registration 
confirmation has now been added to the Forum user account registration process. This function 
was originally implemented in the <uri link="http://www.phpbb.com">phpBB</uri> 2.2 development 
versions, with the changes being backported to version 2.0.11 of phpBB. The same changes 
have now been applied to the customized version of phpBB that is installed at <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">forums.gentoo.org</uri>.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>2.6.10 kernel marked stable</title>
<body>
<p>By the time you are reading this, the Linux 2.6.10 release of 
gentoo-dev-sources will be marked stable, or in the final stages of being 
tested, on supported system architectures. Linux 2.6.10, released late on 
Christmas Eve, is proving to be the best kernel release in a long time, fixing 
almost all of the issues we know about present in 2.6.9 and earlier. 
Relatively few new issues have been reported, and the major ones have already 
been fixed. 2.6 users are recommended to upgrade as soon as possible, as this 
release also fixes some recently discovered security vulnerabilities.</p> 

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Future zone</title>
<section>
<title>Project goals for 2005</title>
<body>
<p>A meta-thread on the <path>gentoo-dev</path> mailing list keeps track
of goals set forth for some Gentoo projects. Here's an overview of
items scheduled to see the light of day shortly: 
</p>
<p><b>Release engineering</b></p>
<p></p>
<ul>
<li>Biannual release schedule:  The first release (2005.0) will be in
January, and the second release (2005.1) will be in July/ August. Each 
release will include install cds, stages, and GRP.</li>
<li>LiveCDs: Plans are to replace the current universal LiveCD with a 
Knoppix-like XLiveCD. Media will be renamed accordingly; the minimal 
LiveCD will remain but will instead be called the minimal installCD.</li>
<li> Gentoo Reference Platform (GRP): Working in a joint effort with 
the installer project, Release Engineering is working on redefining the 
GRP. The current plan, which is subject to change, will use functionality 
similar to <c>quickpkg</c> by packaging the installed packages on the
XLiveCD and copying them to the target system.</li>
</ul>

<p><b>Kernel</b></p>
<ul>
<li>Migrate all existing ebuilds to kernel-2 and linux-* eclasses</li>
<li>Push 2.6 for default where possible for headers and sources.</li>
<li>Consolidate appropriate source packages, e.g. dev-sources ->
vanilla-sources</li>
<li>Further improve our current eclass framework for additional kernels
(BSD, Darwin)</li>
</ul>

<p><b>Gentoo/BSD</b></p>
<ul>
<li>Have a stage or a set of stages that will be used to install
Gentoo/FBSD</li>
<li>Have a working baselayout.</li>
<li>Have an installation CD (a.t.m. FreeSBIE can be used)</li>
<li>Have a fair amount of keyworded ebuilds</li>
<li>Have some of our *BSD specific patches applied to portage</li>
<li>Finish our profile, stabilize our set of tarballs</li>
</ul>

</body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo security</title>
<section>
<title>LinPopUp: Buffer overflow in message reply</title>
<body>
<p>

    LinPopUp contains a buffer overflow potentially allowing execution of
    arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-01.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>a2ps: Multiple vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    The fixps and psmandup scripts in the a2ps package are vulnerable to
    symlink attacks, potentially allowing a local user to overwrite arbitrary
    files. A vulnerability in a2ps filename handling could also result in
    arbitrary command execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-02.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mozilla, Firefox, Thunderbird: Various vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Various vulnerabilities were found and fixed in Mozilla-based products,
    ranging from a potential buffer overflow and temporary files disclosure to
    anti-spoofing issues.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-03.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Shoutcast Server: Remote code execution</title>
<body>
<p>

    Shoutcast Server contains a possible buffer overflow that could lead to the
    execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-04.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>mit-krb5: Heap overflow in libkadm5srv</title>
<body>
<p>

    The MIT Kerberos 5 administration library (libkadm5srv) contains a heap
    overflow that could lead to execution of arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-05.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>tiff: New overflows in image decoding</title>
<body>
<p>

    An integer overflow has been found in the TIFF library image decoding
    routines and the tiffdump utility, potentially allowing arbitrary code
    execution.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-06.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>xine-lib: Multiple overflows</title>
<body>
<p>

    xine-lib contains multiple overflows potentially allowing execution of
    arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-07.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>phpGroupWare: Various vulnerabilities</title>
<body>
<p>

    Multiple vulnerabilities have been discovered in phpGroupWare that could
    lead to information disclosure or remote compromise.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-08.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>xzgv: Multiple overflows</title>
<body>
<p>

    xzgv contains multiple overflows that may lead to the execution of
    arbitrary code.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-09.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Vilistextum: Buffer overflow vulnerability</title>
<body>
<p>

    Vilistextum is vulnerable to a buffer overflow that allows an attacker to
    execute arbitrary code through the use of a malicious webpage.
  
</p>
<p>
For more information, please see the <uri link="/security/en/glsa/glsa-200501-10.xml">GLSA Announcement</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the community</title>
<section>
<title>Web forums</title>
<body>
<p><b>Disappearing X causing slight unrest</b></p>
<p>
The decision by Gentoo developers to gently nudge people to use <path>xorg-x11</path> 
isn't entirely new, but the deletion of XFree86 from Portage on 1 January seems to have come 
as a nasty surprise to some people. One thread out of a handful, to represent them all:</p>

<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=275489">I refuse to use xorg....it sucks! (nevermind....user error)</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>New global moderator Earthwings</b></p>
<p>
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=viewprofile&amp;u=18420">Earthwings</uri> 
has already served in the German subforum for several months before being
promoted to deal with the rest of the lot now:</p>

<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=277091">[forums-announce] New global moderator</uri></li>
</ul></body>
</section>

<section>
<title>gentoo-user</title>
<body>
<p><b>Achieving Hardware Happiness?</b></p>
<p>
Many laptop users experience the same conundrum:  Having a mobile computer results in 
different configurations.  Most of the time these are network-related, for example the 
difference between a corporate LAN and a home network.  But occasionally this includes
hardware as well.  Many laptops have hardware docking stations with additional network cards,
video adapters, and even SCSI.  This presents a unique issue to Linux users since most of the 
time, the various settings are hard-edited into various files in /etc.  Curious how to find your 
own way to portable paradise?  Read on!
</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/113628">gentoo and "rc hell"?</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>Bash Arguments</b></p>
<p>
What could be more Linux-y than a debate on the proper way to delete many files out of a directory?
There's xargs, find, even... for loops?  An informative thread of opinionated answers is what we got this week! 
</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/113591">Bash query? 'Argument list  too long'</uri></li>
</ul>
<p><b>"Monitoring" CPU Usage</b></p>
<p>
On a more humorous note, one list member posted a "helpful" link to a newsforge article on a CPU monitoring 
package called "Hot Babe".  We'll provide GWN readers a link to the gentoo-user thread, and leave it at that.
</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.user/114094">Hot Babe and Debian (GENTOO :-)</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-dev</title>
<body>
<p><b>RFC: Advice on driving compile times down</b></p>
<p>
<mail link="stuart@gentoo.org">Stuart Herbert</mail> asks how to
reduce compile times. Read the thread for the different possibilities
offered to Gentoo users.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/23833">RFC:
Advice on driving compile times down</uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>xfree gone</b></p>
<p>With this short notice Gentoo officially stopped supporting xfree.
All users are asked to migrate to xorg.
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/23744">xfree
gone</uri></li>
</ul>


<p><b>2005.0 2.4 &amp; 2.6 stages</b></p>
<p><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail> asks, on behalf of the
Gentoo Releng subproject, which kernel header and sources 2005.0
stages should be offered. He writes:
"Our options for building include (a) only 2.6 stages, (b) only 2.4
stages, or (c) a combination of 2.4 and 2.6 stages."
From a release point of view only one set would be preferred, but many
users still depend on 2.4 kernels. This rather long thread explores the
many small problems that may arise and shows how difficult it is to make
all people equally happy.

</p>
<ul>
<li><uri
link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/23718">2005.0
2.4 &amp; 2.6 stages</uri></li>
</ul>

</body></section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-server</title>
<body>
<p><b></b></p>
<p>From a mailing list mostly frequented by people using Gentoo
for non-desktop purposes, <path>gentoo-server@gentoo.org</path>, 
here's a noteworthy thread that has spun from the original 
poster asking a simple question:
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://thread.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.server/1629">Who uses Gentoo in production?</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter> 
<title>Gentoo International</title> 
<section>
<title>USA: Gentoo lectures at MIT, 10 and 24 January</title> 
<body>
<p><mail link="rajiv@gentoo.org">Rajiv Manglani</mail>, Gentoo Linux 
Security Team member and PPC developer, will give an introductory 
(10 January) and an advanced lecture (24 January) on Gentoo Linux at 
the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, MIT, in Cambridge, MA. Both
lectures are sponsored by the MIT's Student Information Processing
Board (SIPB) and will be held tonight and Monday 24 starting at 20:00, at
<uri link="http://whereis.mit.edu/map-jpg?selection=4">Building 
4</uri> room 237 (today) and room 231 (24 January) respectively. The
first lecture will focus on giving an overview and demonstrating a 
running Gentoo system, while the "Advanced Gentoo Linux" presentation on 24 
January will have more in-depth discussions of Portage and ebuild script 
creation, system tools such as <c>qpkg</c> and <c>etcat</c>. More details
can be found in Rajiv's <uri link="http://stuff.mit.edu/iap/gentoo/">Independent 
Activities Period Gentoo lecture announcements</uri>. <b>Please make sure to RSVP</b> 
to the <mail link="sipb-iap-gentoo@mit.edu">Student Information Board</mail> if you 
plan on attending.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Canada: Gentoo LTSP project at elementary school</title> 
<body>
<p>The <uri link="http://plug.ca">Prairie Linux User Group</uri> (PLUG) is planning 
to deploy Gentoo Linux at the Holy Cross Elementary School in Winnipeg. The 
project will use reclaimed hardware previously running various shades of Windows 
that are being replaced with Linux due to cost of licensing for upgrades, concerns 
about lax security, growing hardware requirements if Windows was chosen as an 
upgrade path, and the current platform generally not meeting the educational 
requirements at the school any longer. The setup includes an implementation of 
the <uri link="http://www.ltsp.org/">Linux Terminal Server Project</uri> (LTSP) 
across thirty workstations, with Gentoo Linux running <c>openmosix</c> for the 
terminal server system. On Thursday 20 January the PLUG will meet at <uri link="http://www.uwinnipeg.ca">the University of Winnipeg</uri> (starting at 19:00 
in room 2M70) to get a few things straightened out before performing their real world 
test at the school on Sunday, 23 January from 10:00. Thirty elementary students have 
been invited to stress-test the system that they might get to keep if it works as 
advertized: "If the system is successfully able to meet the requirements it would be 
permanently installed," says PLUG member <mail link="ali3n@eliteitminds.com">Mike 
Crawford</mail>, a Gentoo <path>dev-perl</path> developer-to-be and maintainer of one 
of the official Gentoo file mirrors (gentoo.eliteitminds.com). More details can be 
found at the <uri link="http://plug.ca/article.php?story=20050107150627250">PLUG meeting announcement</uri>.
</p>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter> 
<title>Gentoo in the press</title> 
<section>
<title>Linux Journal (5 January 2005)</title> 
<body>

<p>Andrew Cowie with the Linux Journal published a rather flattery piece 
on <uri link="http://www.linuxjournal.com/article/7438">"Gentoo for all 
the unusual reasons,"</uri> providing extensive coverage of Portage as a
tool for professional use: "You might think of Gentoo as a bleeding-edge 
distribution for development workstations, but the simple packaging system 
can make it a good choice for any production system that needs to stay up 
to date," writes the author in his introduction, before explaining in great 
detail the steps for installing and updating software in Gentoo, all nicely 
accompanied by screenshots. The thoroughly researched article was among 
LJ's top reads and most commented-on articles last week - even without the 
GWN boosting its popularity yet again...
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>
<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>
     <ul>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2" >Statistics</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3" >Closed bug ranking</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4" >New bug rankings</uri></li>
     </ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" >bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
     bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  Between 02 January 2005 and 09 January 2005, activity
     on the site has resulted in:
     </p>
     <ul>
          <li>815 new bugs during this period</li>
	  <li>528 bugs closed or resolved during this period</li>
	  <li>23 previously closed bugs were reopened this period</li>
     </ul>
     <p>
     Of the 7862 currently open bugs: 117 are labeled 'blocker', 229 are labeled 'critical', and 568 are labeled 'major'.
     </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 32
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="java@gentoo.org" >Java team</mail>, with 26
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=java@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 26
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 25
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="games@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Games</mail>, with 21
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=games@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="security@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Security</mail>, with 15
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=security@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="plasmaroo@gentoo.org" >Tim Yamin</mail>, with 13
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=plasmaroo@gentoo.org" >closed bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New bug rankings</title>
<body>
     <p>
     The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs during this period are:
     </p>
     <ul>
<li><mail link="sound@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Sound Team</mail>, with 30
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;assigned_to=sound@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="amd64@gentoo.org" >AMD64 Porting Team</mail>, with 21
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;assigned_to=amd64@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-video@gentoo.org" >media-video herd</mail>, with 20
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;assigned_to=media-video@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="media-optical@gentoo.org" >optical media herd</mail>, with 19
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;assigned_to=media-optical@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="x11@gentoo.org" >Gentoo X-windows packagers</mail>, with 17
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;assigned_to=x11@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org" >Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</mail>, with 14
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;assigned_to=gnome@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="base-system@gentoo.org" >Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</mail>, with 11
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;assigned_to=base-system@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
<li><mail link="vmware@gentoo.org" >Gentoo VMWare Bug Squashers</mail>, with 10
              <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2005-01-02&amp;chfieldto=2005-01-09&amp;assigned_to=vmware@gentoo.org" >new bugs</uri>
            </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, adds, and changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li><e>None this week</e></li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo Linux team:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Benedikt Böhm (hollow) - Apache</li>
			<li>Saleem Abdulrasool (compnerd) - Java</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo Linux project:</p>
		<ul>
			<li>Lance Albertson (Ramereth) - New dev for <c>netmon</c> et al. (on top of his regular assignment to the infrastructure team)</li>
			<li>Danny Van Dyk (Kugelfang) and Mike Doty (KingTaco) - AMD64 operational co-leads (taking over from Travis Tilley)</li>
			<li>Jeremy Huddleston (eradicator) - Recruiting co-lead</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and tricks</title>
<section>
<title>Denu - a Portage-savvy menu generator for window managers</title>
<body>
<p>Are you switching from Fluxbox to Gnome to KDE a lot? Would you like to try out 
even more window managers, if it wasn't for the missing application entries in the 
menus to hop along with you? This week's tip brings a nifty solution in reach: <uri link="http://denu.sourceforge.net">Denu</uri> is a brandnew tool to assist in menu 
generation. It can generate similarly structured menus for various window 
managers enabling easy transitions from one to another. Denu synchronizes with an 
online database to allow program definitions to be updated without a software update, and
best of all: Portage itself provides the installed program data!</p>
<pre caption="Emerge Denu">
# cd $PORTDIR_OVERLAY/x11-misc/denu <comment>Create the appropriate overlay as necessary (Denu is not in Portage yet)</comment>
# wget http://dl.sourceforge.net/sourceforge/denu/denu-2.1.2-r1.ebuild
# emerge denu
</pre> 

<p>Before we go any further <b>backup any menu configurations you don't want overwritten</b>.  Now run <c>denu</c> as a normal user, Denu is <e>not</e> meant to be run as <path>root</path>. </p> 

<figure link="/images/gwn/20050110_denu.jpg"
           short="Denu" 
           caption="Screenshot of menu creation with Denu" />
	   
<p>The first step after installing Denu is to run <c>Update</c> (for program definitions) 
and <c>Sysupdate</c> (for the current list of installed programs). Neither of these 
are run at startup, so after installing a new program via Portage, <c>Sysupdate</c> will 
need execution again.
</p>
<p>To create a menu there are two approaches: hand pick entries from the Installed Tree 
and add them, or you can hit <c>Autofill</c>, and Denu will automatically generate a 
menu based on the information it has. Reorganizing a newly created menu is as simple 
as drag and drop, menu systems will respect the order of entries, except for Gnome and KDE 
who sort things alphabetically. Click on <c>generate</c>, and then on one of the boxes 
corresponding to your desired window manager or desktop environment. Some window managers 
like Fluxbox will be able to use your menu immediately, others may need to be reconfigured 
or restarted.
</p>
<p>Denu is still under development, but author <mail link="shux_linux@comcast.net">Shux</mail> 
has scanned half of the Portage tree for items that might be needed in a GUI menu already. For 
the remaining half (or things that might need adding in the future) Denu provides a tool to 
include other applications not in its database yet. Adding programs and their categories, 
descriptions etc. is just as easy as shifting them around. For questions and answers of all 
sorts check the lively <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=268988">Denu 2.0 
thread in the Forums</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN feedback</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make the GWN better.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GWN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>To subscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.</p>
<p>To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter, send a blank email to <mail link="gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-gwn-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail> from the email address you are subscribed under.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="/news/da/gwn/gwn.xml">Danish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/pl/gwn/gwn.xml">Polish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/ru/gwn/gwn.xml">Russian</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
<li><uri link="/news/tr/gwn/gwn.xml">Turkish</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
