<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter">
<title>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>February 17th, 2003</subtitle>
<abstract>This is the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter for the week of February 17th, 2003.</abstract>
<summary>Catch Gentoo Zetagrid fever.  New rsync mirrors.  Gnome 2.2 now in Portage</summary>
<version>Volume 2, Issue 7</version>
<date>17th Feb 2003</date>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="aja@clanarmstrong.com">AJ Armstrong</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="nesta@iceburg.net">Brice Burgess</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="david@phrixus.net">David Narayan</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="plate@gentoo.org">Ulrich Plate</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
    <mail link="mail@psharp.uklinux.net">Peter Sharp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="matje@lanzone.be">Mathy Vanvoorden</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="tom.vanlaerhoven@luc.ac.be">Tom Van Laerhoven</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="roel@roel.ath.cx">Roel Adriaans</mail>
</author>
<author title="Dutch Translation">
	<mail link="phj.dijkstra@home.nl">Peter Dijkstra</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="nicolas.ledez@free.fr">Nicolas Ledez</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="gui@moolfreet.com">Guillaume Plessis</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="thevedge@thevedge.net">Eric St-Georges</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="anfini@free.fr">John Berry</mail>
</author>
<author title="French Translation">
	<mail link="riverdale@linuxmail.org">Martin Prieto</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="madeagle@gentoo.org">Steffen Lassahn</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="haim@gentoo.org">Matthias F. Brandstetter</mail>
</author>
<author title="German Translation">
	<mail link="lordvan@gentoo.org">Thomas Raschbacher</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="mush@monrif.net">Marco Mascherpa</mail>
</author>
<author title="Italian Translation">
	<mail link="paper@tiscali.it">Claudio Merloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="kage-chan@gentoo.org">Daniel Ketel</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="hagi@p1d.com">Yoshiaki Hagihara</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="andy@billydpro.com">Andy Hunne</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@gentoo.org">Yuji Carlos Kosugi</mail>
</author>
<author title="Japanese Translation">
	<mail link="yasunori@mail.portland.co.uk">Yasunori Fukudome</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Brazil) Translation">
	<mail link="venturasbarbeiro@ig.com.br">Ventura Barbeiro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="blueroom@digitalmente.net">Bruno Ferreira</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="gustavo@felisberto.net">Gustavo Felisberto</mail>
</author>
<author title="Portuguese (Portugal) Translation">
	<mail link="rjlouro@rjlouro.org">Ricardo Jorge Louro</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="lanark@lanark.com.ar">Lanark</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="rcm@sasaska.net">Rafael Cordones Marcos</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="julio@castillobueno.com">Julio Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="s3r@fibertel.com.ar">Sergio Gómez</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="pablo.leira@pitagoral.com">Pablo Pita Leira</mail>	
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="carlos@castillobueno.com">Carlos Castillo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="tirant@menta.net">Tirant</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="jfreire@ya.com">Jaime Freire</mail>
</author>
<author title="Spanish Translation">
	<mail link="krusty_ar@yahoo.com">Lucas Sallovitz</mail>
</author>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">Catch Gentoo Zetagrid fever</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">New rsync mirrors</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">Gnome 2.2 now in Portage</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Catch Gentoo Zetagrid Fever</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		We've <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20030106-newsletter.xml#doc_chap4">reported</uri> on the 
		<uri link="http://zetagrid.net">Zetagrid</uri> project before.  Recently, however, the GLUE team broke the
		<uri link="http://www.zetagrid.net/servlet/service/statistic">top 100 producers list</uri> and, as of press time, currently
		ranks <uri link="http://www.zetagrid.net/servlet/service/producers?user=Michael+Imhof">86th</uri> on the list.  Now, thanks to an
		ebuild in Portage, along with a <uri link="http://cvs.gentoo.org/~tantive/zeta.cfg">sample configuration file</uri> from Michael's
		<uri link="http://cvs.gentoo.org/~tantive/">zetagrid site</uri>, it's even easier for Gentoo users to donate their spare CPU cycles 
		to the GLUE team and help increase the chances of winning part of the $1,000,000 prize.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New rsync mirrors.</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		After our recent <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/20030203-newsletter.xml#doc_chap1_sect3">report</uri> on the Gentoo 
		mirror slowdowns, several Gentoo users stepped forward with offers to set up new Gentoo Linux mirrors, both for the Portage tree, as
		well as the source packages.  The result has been a significant increase in the number of 
		<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/mirrors.xml">download mirrors</uri> available to the Gentoo community.</p>
		<p>
		Guidelines are available for users who wish to set up public mirrors to help the Gentoo Linux project, including instructions for setting
		up <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/rsync.xml">rsync</uri> mirrors, which just mirror the Portage tree as well as instructions for
		setting up <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/source_mirrors.xml">source</uri> mirrors, which mirror the actual source tarballs of the
		various packages contained within Portage.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>GNOME 2.2 now in Portage</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		GNOME 2.2 ebuilds were released to the Gentoo community early last week and Gentoo GNOME users everywhere rejoiced at the new features
		like <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.2/notes/rnmultihead.html">multihead support</uri>, 
		<uri link="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.2/notes/rnthemes.html">unified theming</uri> and the official inclusion of the 
		<uri link="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.2/notes/rnwm.html">Metacity window manager</uri>.  A complete list of features and changes 
		can be found in the GNOME 2.2 <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.2/notes/">release notes</uri>.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Security</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect1">GLSA</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">New Security Bug Reports</uri></li>
			</ul> 
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>GLSA</title>
	<body>
	<p>There were no new security alerts issued in the past week.</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>New Security Bug Reports</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The following new security-related bug reports were submitted to the bugzilla database 
		this week:
			<ul>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=15684">net-mail/w3m</uri></li>
                        <li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=15652">syslinux 2.02</uri></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Featured Developer of the Week</title>
<body>
<p class="secthead">Dan Armak</p>
<figure
link="http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/Linux/distributions/gentoo/images/gwn/20030217_danarmak.jpg" short="Dan Armak" caption="Dan Armak" />
<p>
There's been much rejoicing among KDE users lately because of
the release of KDE 3.1, and this week we feature one of the developers
responsible for bringing it to Gentoo: <mail link="danarmak@gentoo.org">
Dan Armak</mail>, KDE team leader.  Dan
began using Gentoo back when you had to scroll halfway down a list of
more than a hundred minor and specialized distros to even see it
mentioned anywhere, and seeing that it was the kind of power-user distro
he was looking for, he started using it and writing ebuilds for some
important apps he needed, like LyX.  It was around this time that Dan
came up with the idea for CVS ebuilds and eclasses in general and,
before he knew it, got invited to become a developer.  Dan wrote the KDE
eclasses(Dan shudders at the thought of the old KDE ebuilds, which
contained most of the code that the KDE eclasses do today) and the 
cvs.eclass, and now maintains both.  Thanks to these eclasses Dan
doesn't have to do too much work with miscellaneous KDE packages (unless
there's a bug in the source that they need to fix) so kde-base (along
with koffice and kdevelop) takes up most of Dan and the other KDE
maintainers' time.
</p>
<p>
Besides KDE, some of Dan's favorite pieces of software include mc, Lyx
(a front-end to LaTeX), bash, and epsxe.  His Toshiba laptop is out for
repairs at the moment, but he's borrowing a nice Athlon with lots of RAM from a
friend, as well as a panoply of ancient boxen for parts and doorstops.
Dan lives in Matan, a smallish town in Israel, and is a student - at
Ami Asaf high school during the day and at the Open University in the
afternoon.  Next
year, he'll be going into the army, but hopes to find a nice job in the
tech/computers unit of the IDF, where he'll be free to preach Gentoo.
His hobbies include Squaresoft RPGs, reading, writing, observing
Interesting People, and OSS evangelism toward his friends.
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Heard In The Community</title>
	<section>
	<title>Web Forums</title>
	<body>
	<p><b>New powerbooks and Gentoo PPC</b></p>
	<p>Apple Computers has whetted the appetite of its fans with the new 12 and 17 inch Powerbooks last month, and now they're finally shipping all over the place. Gentoo PPC users aren't any less excited, they have begun gathering their troops to install Linux as soon as their new gadgets arrive in the mail. After some initial skepticism about kernel support for the new hardware it seems like a quick solution may be available after all:
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=34909">12" Powerbook</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=29173">new 17 inch powerbooks wow</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	<p><b>Bob the Ebuilder</b></p>
	<p>There have been several attempts by Gentoo parents to gather information about Linux software for younger children in the past. A few notoriously addictive games and educational applications for Linux have always been available as ebuilds, but many other alternatives to the huge Windows market for kiddie progs are still out there waiting to be Gentooified. And last week, a collective "Bob the Ebuilder" initiative has come forth that promises to catch up quickly with some of the things missing in Portage. The official thread to post requests, announce ebuilds checked into bugs.gentoo.org, and feedback from beta testers in the age bracket 3-10 is here:
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=13413">Gentoo for children (request for ebuilders)</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>
	<p><b>Gentoo Musicians</b></p>
	<p>Linux user profiles are as varied as in any other random group of people. Just because we happen to use the same operating system doesn't mean necessarily that we have anything else in common. As it turns out, some people do, though: a planetary convention of musicians using Gentoo Linux has built up in the Forums, thrown together by coincidence, united in their effort to come up with something special. One of the possible results of this thread (besides mentions of the most obscure software names ever) may well be a Gentoone on the LiveCD, something to hum along during installation:
	<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=21805">Gentoo Musicians</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</p>

	<p><b>Thirty Minutes...</b></p>
	    <p>...is all it takes to write an ebuild for a missing window manager in Gentoo. What started as an innocent question about Wing's Desktop Manager and why it wasn't available as an ebuild, has become a fine example of how someone with the right skill set and half an hour of spare time on their hands can remedy that on the spot. Have a look at this thread:  
	    <ul>
		<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=35189">why is there no wdm ebuild?</uri></li>
		</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
<section>
     <title>gentoo-user</title>
     <body>
       <p><b>'gcc: command not found'</b></p>
       <p>
        A lot of talk about gcc not being available to the system was happening on gentoo-user this week. 
	<uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104482994004245&amp;w=2">One thread entitled 'distcc'</uri> 
	began with the author's solution to the 'gcc: command not found' problem. The root of the issue is caused by
  attempting to invoke gcc in a shell where /etc/profile isn't being sourced. Three unique solutions were  offered within 
  this thread alone! Nick Jones contributed the simplest one, being 'su -'. A monumental strength and joy of Gentoo is
  the encouragement of customization, thus choose whichever soltuion best fits your needs.
       </p>
       <p><b>All kinds of tars make up the pit</b></p>
       <p>
  Brett Holcomb, a gentoo-user veteran, 
  <uri link="http://marc.theaimsgroup.com/?l=gentoo-user&amp;m=104470482011940&amp;w=2">questioned</uri>
   whether Gentoo's "tar" command was a modified version of the
  one on the GNU site. Tar is the standard *nix utility for compressing all kinds of data into a single file called an archive.
   Interesting enough, the responses made clear that the tar command does vary from distro
  to distro. The switches, especially dealing with bzip2 and gzip, will often vary depending on the distro's compile
  of the tar sources. This shouldn't present itself as a problem as it is easily worked around through the use of
  pipes and standalone utilities.
      </p>
     </body>
</section>
  <section>
    <title>gentoo-dev</title>
    <body>
      <p><b>ProPolice enabled gcc/gentoo.</b></p>
      <p>Matt Rickard has <uri link="http://frogger974.homelinux.org/gentoo_propolice.html">implemented</uri> a <uri link="http://www.trl.ibm.com/projects/security/ssp/">ProPolice</uri> patched GCC ebuild. He <uri link="http://article.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.devel/6984">says</uri>: <e>"This patch will build stack-smashing protection into your code at compile time. This is an excellent security measure -- one that has just recently been implemented in OpenBSD-current.  It can be enabled explicitly through the CFLAG -fstack-protector or turned on by default with a separate patch."</e> Dylan Carlson pointed out that there is a <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=13610">bug</uri> filed regarding this topic.</p>
    </body>
  </section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo International</title>
    <body>

	<p class="secthead">Gentoo Vienna Meeting</p>

<p>Meetings of the Austrian branch of Gentooism have started happening in July last year, but sort of went out of fashion. Last week, the official <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=9161">Viennese Gentoo users</uri> coordination thread has started an attempt to revive the tradition and is making plans for the next gathering. It'll be soon, but a date hasn't been fixed yet, so you can still make your preferences heard.
</p>

	<p class="secthead">Pingüino Papúa</p>

<p><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=35510">tirantloblanc</uri> has traced the official Spanish name for the Gentoo penguin, and discovered that flocks of this fastest swimmer among birds are living in the southernmost parts of Chile. The Pingüino Papúa's largest colonies, however, live on the Falk^H^H^H^HMalvinas islands off the coast of Argentina. Which presumably makes them UK citizens, but as an open source bird rather unlikely to become a sufficient reason for anything more serious than a flame war...
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Portage Watch</title>
<section>
<title>The following stable packages were added to portage this week</title>
<body>
<p>
<note>Because of the pending release of 1.4_final, the Portage tree is currently frozen.  As such, no new stable packages were introduced to Portage this week</note>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Updates to notable packages</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
<li>gnome-base/gnome - gnome-2.2-r1.ebuild; </li>
<li>sys-kernel/* - ac-sources-2.4.21_pre4-r3.ebuild; ac-sources-2.4.21_pre4-r4.ebuild; ck-sources-2.4.20-r3.ebuild; development-sources-2.5.60-r1.ebuild; development-sources-2.5.60.ebuild; hppa-sources-2.4.20_p23.ebuild; hppa-sources-2.4.20_p24.ebuild; hppa-sources-2.4.20_p26.ebuild; mjc-sources-2.5.59-r1.ebuild; ppc-sources-2.4.20-r3.ebuild; rsbac-sources-2.4.20.ebuild; wolk-sources-4.0_pre10.ebuild; </li>
<li>dev-php/php - php-4.3.0-r3.ebuild; php-4.3.0-r4.ebuild; </li>
<li>app-admin/gentoolkit - gentoolkit-0.1.18-r1.ebuild; gentoolkit-0.1.18.ebuild; </li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Bugzilla</title>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			<ul>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect2">Statistics</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect3">Closed Bug Ranking</uri></li>
				<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect4">New Bug Rankings</uri></li>
                        </ul>                           
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Statistics</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla (<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record and track
                bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions with the development team.  In the last 7 days, activity
                on the site has resulted in:
			<ul>
				<li>270 new bugs this week</li>
				<li>191 bugs closed this week</li>
				<li>1680 total bugs currently marked 'new'</li>
				<li>574 total bugs curently assigned to developers</li>
                <li>51 bugs that were previously closed have been reopened.</li>
			</ul>
                There are currently 2305 bugs open in bugzilla. Of these: 45 are labelled 'blocker', 82 are labelled 'critical',
                and 160  are labelled 'major'.
		</p>
                </body>
        </section>
        <section>
		<title>Closed Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs this week are:
			<ul>
				<li><mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>, with 33 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=seemant%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="kde@gentoo.org">The KDE Team</mail>, with 18 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=kde%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="raker@gentoo.org">Nick Hadaway</mail>, with 15 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=raker%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="sethbc@gentoo.org">Seth Chandler</mail>, with 12 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=sethbc%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
				<li><mail link="mholzer@gentoo.org">M. Holzer</mail>, with 11 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=CLOSED&amp;chfield=bug_status&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;resolution=FIXED&amp;assigned_to=mholzer%40gentoo.org">closed bugs</uri></li>
			</ul>
                </p>
		</body>
	</section>
        <section>
		<title>New Bug Rankings</title>
                <body>
                <p>
                The developers and teams who have been assigned the most new bugs this week are:
			<ul>				
                                <li><mail link="azarah@gentoo.org">Martin Schlemmer</mail>, with 17 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=azarah%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>				
                                <li><mail link="gnome@gentoo.org">The Gnome Team</mail>, with 16 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=gnome%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>				
                                <li><mail link="carpaski@gentoo.org">Nicholas Jones</mail>, with 14 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=carpaski%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>				
                                <li><mail link="rphillips@gentoo.org">Ryan Phillips</mail>, with 14 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=rphillips%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>				
                                <li><mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>, with 14 <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;chfield=assigned_to&amp;chfieldfrom=2003-02-08&amp;chfieldto=Now&amp;=&amp;assigned_to=seemant%40gentoo.org">new bugs</uri></li>
			</ul>
                </p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>
  
<body>

	<p class="secthead">Bash Commands and Tricks</p>

<p>
Just about all Gentoo user make use of the command line - this week focuses on some little-known navigation commands that may make your life easier.
</p>

<pre caption="Bash Key Combinations">
Alt+B   <codenote>Go back one word</codenote>
Alt+F   <codenote>Go forth one word</codenote>
Ctrl+K  <codenote>Delete everything from the cursor to the end of the line</codenote>
Ctrl+U  <codenote>Delete everything from the cursor to the beginning of the line</codenote>
Ctrl+Y  <codenote>Paste deleted characters at the current position</codenote>
Ctrl+H  <codenote>Delete one character</codenote>
Ctrl+L  <codenote>Clean screen</codenote>
Ctrl+P  <codenote>Go to the previous history entry</codenote>
Ctrl+N  <codenote>Go to the next history entry</codenote>
</pre>

<p>
Also you can use <c>!word</c> to re-execute the last command beginning with "word".
<pre caption="Using !word">
$ gcc -o test test.c
$ !gcc
gcc -o test test.c
$
</pre>
</p>

<p>
Ever get tired of typing long directory names? Try using the directory stack with the commands <c>pushd</c>, <c>popd</c>, and <c>dirs</c>. THe directory stack allows you to keep a list of directories and navigate between them.
<pre caption="The directory stack">
<codenote>pushd adds a directory</codenote>
~:$ pushd /usr/portage
<codenote>dirs lists all directories on the stack</codenote>
~:$ dirs
/usr/portage ~
<codenote>And popd removes the top entry and cd's to that directory</codenote>
~:$ popd
/usr/portage:$
</pre>
</p>

<p>
	The idea for this weeks tip came from Pavel Tcholakov and was submitted to the GWN feedback list.
</p>
</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Moves, Adds and Changes</title>
	<section>
		<title>Moves</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently left the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Adds</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently joined the Gentoo team:
			<ul>
				<li>Guy Martin (GMSoft) -- Gentoo/HPPA</li>
				<li>Graham Forest (vladimir) -- Gentoo/PPC</li>
				<li>Bartosch Pixa (DarkSpecter) -- Gentoo/PPC</li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Changes</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo project.
			<ul>
				<li><e>none this week</e></li>
			</ul>
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contribute to GWN</title>
	<body>
	<p>Interested in contributing to the Gentoo Weekly Newsletter?  Send us an <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">email</mail>.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GWN Feedback</title>
	<body>
	<p>Please send us your <mail link="gwn-feedback@gentoo.org">feedback</mail> and help make GWN better.</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Other Languages</title>
	<body>
	<p>The Gentoo Weekly Newsletter is also available in the following languages:</p>
	<ul>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/be/gwn/gwn.xml">Dutch</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">English</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/de/gwn/gwn.xml">German</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/fr/gwn/gwn.xml">French</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/ja/gwn/gwn.xml">Japanese</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/it/gwn/gwn.xml">Italian</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/br/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Brazil)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/pt/gwn/gwn.xml">Portuguese (Portugal)</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/es/gwn/gwn.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
	</ul>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
