<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>Bug Wranglers</name>
<longname>The Bug Wranglers Project</longname>
<date>2008-07-23</date>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="jer" />
</author>

<description>
The Gentoo Bug Wranglers project controls, describes the tasks and goals
carried out by everyone who wrangles bugs on Gentoo's bug tracker.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
The Gentoo Bug Wranglers project controls, describes the tasks and
goals carried out by everyone who wrangles bugs on Gentoo's <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/">bug tracker</uri>.
</p>
</longdescription>

<goals>
<p>
The goal of the Bug Wranglers project is to clarify how new bugs on
Gentoo's bug tracker should be handled. This document describes the rules to
bug assignment, CC'ing herd teams, maintainers, the role of metadata.xml and
<uri link="/proj/en/metastructure/herds/herds.xml">herds.xml</uri>,
who are bug wranglers and how one should contact them.
</p>
</goals>

<dev role="Bug wrangler">carlo</dev>
<dev role="Bug wrangler">jakub</dev>
<dev role="Bug wrangler">jer</dev>
<dev role="Bug wrangler">jkt</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Bug Wrangling</title>

<section>
<title>Assessing Bug Reports</title>
<body>
<p>
How and when you assign a bug report depends on the type of bug report and the
correctness and completeness of the bug report.
</p>
<ul>
<li>Bug reports requesting <b>version bumps</b> may be be assigned to
the appropriate maintainers directly. It can be a good idea to check the
Description of the bug for references to security bugs, in which case the bug
report should be assigned to <mail
link="security@gentoo.org">security@gentoo.org</mail> immediately, with the
maintainers CC'd.</li>
<li>Bug reports that say something isn't working or compiling <b>without a
comprehensive analysis of the causes</b>, should contain at least the output of
`emerge --info' as well as a thorough description of the problem, including
error output (or expected versus actual output), the command that led to the
error or faulty output, and concise steps explaining how to reproduce the
issue. It is customary to only assign a bug report once these requirements have
been fulfilled. If the reporter hasn't fulfilled these requirements, the bug
should be ASSIGNED to bug-wranglers, and a full build log should be requested
from the reporter.</li>
<li>Bug reports that <b>include patches</b> or other solutions accompanying the actual bug description can usually be assigned directly to the maintainers.</li>
<li>The <c>Summary</c> uniquely identifies the bug that is being reported. As
there could be several bugs saying that cat/pkg "failed to emerge", it is
important to at least replace such generic descriptions of an emerge failing
with a more exact description, noting the ebuild phase that failed or, better
yet, the first error message that occured.</li>
<li>Bug reports that refer to a single or a few (similar) packages should
detail the package atom as completely as possible in the <c>Summary</c>. Bug reports
about eclasses should list the full eclass filename.</li>
</ul> 
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Assigning Bug Reports</title>
<body>
<p>
To assign a bug report to the right people, you will need to find some more
information, depending on the type of bug report.
</p>
<ul>
<li>If a bug report pertains to a specific <b>package</b>, then you enter the
package's directory in your copy of the <uri
link="http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo-x86/">gentoo-x86 CVS
repository</uri> (or perhaps the online version which should always be more or
less up to date) and read the <c>metadata.xml</c> file you find there. When
<c>metadata.xml</c> lists a single maintainer or herd, then you assign the bug
to that maintainer or herd.  When the file lists multiple entries, then you
assign the bug to the first maintainer, and CC the other maintainer(s) and
herd(s).</li>
<li>In cases where <c>metadata.xml</c> lists a herd which Gentoo Bugzilla
doesn't know about (which it will ask you to correct before it accepts changes
to the bug report), you should consult <uri
link="/proj/en/metastructure/herds/herds.xml">herds.xml</uri> to figure out the
appropriate e-mail alias for that herd.</li>
<li>When a bug report calls attention to <b>multiple packages</b>, then things
become slightly more complicated. When the listed packages do not belong to the
same maintainer or team, for instance when a library upgrade causes several
packages to fail to emerge or run, then you should ask the bug reporter to file
separate bugs assigned to each set of packages' maintainer(s), and make those
bug reports block the original bug report, which then becomes a <b>tracker
bug</b> (denoted by the <c>Tracker</c> keyword. Bug reports with many
maintainers CC'd are known to bog down and never get resolved. Of course, you
should only create a tracker bug when the bug is confirmed and the solution is
clear.</li>
<li>Bug reports that concern <b>eclasses</b> should be assigned to the eclass
maintainer. To figure out who maintains an eclass, browse to the
<uri link="http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo-x86/eclass">gentoo-x86/eclass</uri> directory, open the file and read who maintains the eclass at the top
of the file.</li>
<li>A <b>keyword request</b> should be assigned to the package's maintainer and CC'd
to the appropriate arch team(s).</li>
<li>A <b>stabilisation request</b> should be handled by the package's maintainer, so
you should not CC arches in your role as bug wrangler.</li>
<li>Bug reports that relate to issues other than the portage tree, like
problems with Gentoo's bugzilla, Gentoo infrastructure, mirrors or staffing
matters (devrel, userrel and so on) are usually easier to assign. The <c>Product</c>
and <c>Component</c> fields of each bug should help you (re)assign these reports
appropriately.</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Participating</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Any Gentoo developers who can change the <c>Assignee</c> fields of new bugs are
welcome to help assign bugs to the right developers. Most developers will
appreciate it if, while doing so, you follow the rules layed out above.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>How to contact us</title>
<section>
<title>Via e-mail</title>
<body>
<p>
There is currently no single contact. Please refer to the developer list above. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
