<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>Bug Wranglers</name>
<longname>The Bug Wranglers Project</longname>
<date>2008-05-21</date>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="jer" />
</author>

<description>
The Gentoo Bug Wranglers project controls, describes the tasks and goals
carried out by everyone who wrangles bugs on Gentoo's bug tracker.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
The Gentoo Bug Wranglers project controls, describes the tasks and goals
carried out by everyone who wrangles bugs on Gentoo's bug tracker.
</p>
</longdescription>

<goals>
<p>
The goal of the Bug Wranglers project is to clarify how new bugs on
Gentoo's bug tracker should be handled. This document describes the rules to
bug assignment, CC'ing herd teams, maintainers, the role of metadata.xml and
herds.xml, who are bug wranglers and how one should contact them.
</p>
</goals>

<dev role="Bug wrangler">carlo</dev>
<dev role="Bug wrangler">jakub</dev>
<dev role="Bug wrangler">jer</dev>
<dev role="Bug wrangler">jkt</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Bug Wrangling</title>

<section>
<title>Checking Bug Reports</title>
<body>
<p>
How and when you assign a bug report depends on the type of bug report and the
correctness and completeness of the bug report.
</p>
<ul>
<li>Bug reports requesting <b>version bumps</b> may be be assigned to
the appropriate maintainers directly. It can be a good idea to check the
Description of the bug for references to security bugs, in which case the bug
report should be assigned to <mail
link="security@gentoo.org">security@gentoo.org</mail> immediately, with the
maintainers CC'd.</li>
<li>Bug reports that say something isn't working or compiling <b>without a
comprehensive analysis of the causes</b>, should contain at least the output of
`emerge --info' as well as a thorough description of the problem, including
error output (or expected versus actual output), the command that led to the
error or faulty output, and concise steps explaining how to reproduce the
issue. It is customary to only assign a bug report once these requirements have
been fulfilled.</li>
<li>Bug reports that <b>include patches</b> or other solutions accompanying the actual bug description can usually be assigned directly to the maintainers.</li>
</ul> 
</body>
</section>

<!--
<section>
<title>Assigning Bug Reports</title>
<body>
</body>
</section>
-->

</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Participating</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>All Gentoo developers who can change the Assignee fields of new bugs, are
welcome to help assign bugs to the right developers. Most developers will
appreciate it if, while doing so, you follow the rules layed out above.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>How to contact us</title>
<section>
<title>Via e-mail</title>
<body>
<p>
There is currently no single contact. Please refer to the developer list above. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
