<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/docs/Attic/release_policy.xml,v 1.1 2004/02/26 03:26:39 zhen Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="release_policy.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Official Release Policy</title>

<author title = "Author">
<mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide outlines the entire Gentoo Linux release process. It is intended
to answer and address all aspects of the release process.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>DRAFT</version>
<date>25 February 2004</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Release Overview</title>
	<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
		<body>
		<p>A common misconception is that a major software release is stressful. In the past,
		this was surely the case with Gentoo.  The fluid nature of Gentoo makes it very
		hard to organize a release because Gentoo redefines the software paradigm.
		We all know that there is never a need to install a service pack in Gentoo, or
		reinstall to use the latest and the greatest piece of software.  So what do we release
		then, and how? </p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>What is an Official Release?</title>
		<body>
		<p>In some ways we conform to the release paradigm, but in most cases, we do not.
		Usually, a software vendor will release a new version of their product that the
		users have not had mainstream access to yet.  With Gentoo, users <i>always</i> have
		access to the newest and the greatest software.  So where does that leave releases?  
		Why do we even have them at all? </p>

		<p>Gentoo releases give Gentoo an opportunity to showcase the best of what we have to
		offer.  Sure, we have the new KDE or GNOME in Portage, but what isn't in Portage is
		a GameCD with the killer game of the year on it.  What isn't in Portage is a new
		distribution method, like the Gentoo Store, that allows users to buy an easy installation
		method that does not require a fast Internet connection.  I think that you get my point.
		Releases are Gentoo's way of getting our name out there, our chance to really show
		what we can do with our product.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Release Structure</title>
		<body>
		<p>So how does Gentoo release? The current scheme for release is a quarterly one.
		Our releases are designated 2004.0, 2004.1, 2004.2, and 2004.3, for example.  Doing
		quarterly releases allows us to maintain our fluid nature, as well as get our technology
		out to the world in a timely fashion. </p>

		<p>What is included in an Official Release? An official Gentoo release must include the
		following: </p>

		<table>
		<tr>
			<th>Requirement</th>
			<th>Description</th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>Installation stages</ti>
			<ti>Stage tarballs used to install the Gentoo distribution</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>Bootable LiveCD</ti>
			<ti>A Bootable LiveCD that follows the given specs</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>GRP (Gentoo Reference Platform)</ti>
			<ti>Binaries versions of critical system packages</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>Installation documentation</ti>
			<ti>In the form of the Gentoo Handbook</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti>Release notes</ti>
			<ti>Detailed notes on the release</ti>
		</tr>
		</table>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Release Process</title>

	<section>
		<title>Specifications</title>
		<body>
		<p>The following release components must adhere to the following specifications:</p>

		<p><b>Installation stages</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>Must be built by Catalyst</li>
			<li>Must be built for all supported subarches of the given main arch</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p><b>Bootable LiveCDs</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>Must be built by Catalyst</li>
			<li>Must adhere to the official LiveCD filesystem structure</li>
		</ul>
		
		<p>The official LiveCD filesystem structure is as follows: </p>
		
		<p><b>Disc One</b></p>
		<table>
		<tr>
			<th>Directory</th>
			<th>Contents</th>
		</tr>
		</table>

		<p><b>Disc Two</b></p>
		<table>
		<tr>
			<th>Directory</th>
			<th>Contents</th>
		</tr>
		</table>

		<p><b>GRP (Gentoo Reference Platform) sets</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>Must be built by Catalyst</li>
			<li>If the GRP is installation specific GRP, the spec file used for building
			must be approved by releng. </li>
		</ul>

		<p><b>Installation documentation</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>The main docmentation must be the Gentoo Handbook</li>
			<li>Supplemental documentation may be used, but it is strongly
			recommended that the supplmental documentation is merged into
			the Handbook. </li>
		</ul>

		<p><b>Release notes</b></p>
		<ul>
			<li>They must follow the template laid down by releng</li>
			<li>They must be included on the LiveCD as well as the Internet</li>
			<li>They have to reside in some form, whether linked to or otherwise,
			in a common location specified by releng for easy user access. </li>
		</ul>
		</body>	
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Timeline</title>
		<body>
		<p>The aim of this document is not to define concrete timelines that have to
		be met.  Doing so would be counterproductive and unrealistic.  Release timelines
		are found through a compromise of the releng leads and the arch leads.  Releng
		guides the direction and schedule of the release, but it is up to the arch leads
		when they want to release. </p>

		<p>There is one certainty that can be expected.  Releng expects that at least
		fifty percent of the entire release process is spent on QA of the release components.
		<b>Release will be delayed until proper QA measures are taken</b>. </p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Preliminaries</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Initial Building</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>The Next Step - QA</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Pre-Release</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>More QA</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>One more Pre-Release</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Final Release</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>What to do in Between Major Releases</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>FAQ</title>
	<section>
		<title>FAQ</title>
		<body>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
