<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Video">
  <name>video</name>
  <longname>Gentoo Video project</longname>
  <date>2007-05-03</date>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="chriswhite@gentoo.org">Chris White</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="flameeyes@gentoo.org">Diego Pettenò</mail>
  </author>

  <description>
    The Video team strives to provide users with the best multimedia experience
    through providing encoding tools and media players.
  </description>

  <longdescription><p>
    The Video team strives to provide users with the best multimedia experience
    through providing encoding tools and media players.  We do so by maintaining
    various video based applications including MPlayer, Xine, and Transcode.
  </p></longdescription>

  <subproject ref="/proj/en/desktop/video/vdr/index.xml" inheritmembers="yes"/>

  <dev role="lead" description="Gentoo/PPC work, mplayer, ffmpeg">lu_zero</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="Webcam">phosphan</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="DVB">lordvan</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="MythTV and misc TV apps">cardoe</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="DVB, VDR">zzam</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="VDR">hd_brummy</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="XdTV, gpac, other">aballier</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="misc">spatz</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="misc">ssuominen</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="DVB, VDR, misc">idl0r</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="SMPlayer and dependencies">yngwin</dev>

  <herd name="video" />
  <herd name="media-tv" />

  <resource link="/proj/en/desktop/video/xine.xml">
    Notes about media-libs/xine-lib package and relative frontends
  </resource>
  <resource link="/proj/en/desktop/video/vlc.xml">
    Notes about media-video/vlc package
  </resource>

  <extrachapter>
  <title>Notes about removed packages</title>

  <section>
  <body>

  <p>
  In autumn 2005 many packages which were present on portage for a long time
  were removed, for a series of different causes. Most of them are not going to
  re-enter portage until upstream decides to clean up their own dirt, as they
  were a high weight to maintain.
  </p>

  <p>
  Packages that were depending on <c>divx4linux</c> should all be able to read
  and write DivX files using <c>ffmpeg</c>'s MPEG4 codec, and that package was
  so bugged that it was segfaulting on newer Pentium4 processors. It was also
  closed source and it was then impossible to maintain.
  </p>

  <p>
  <c>helixplayer</c> was removed because it had a bad history of serious
  security-related problems, and it was difficult to maintain because of its
  complex build system. Looking forward for the new 2.0 version, the old 1.x ebuilds
  got removed from the tree, people using it can consider using
  <c>realplayer</c> instead, or a more complete video player such as <c>xine</c>
  or <c>mplayer</c>.
  </p>

  <p>
  <c>quicktime4linux</c> was another hard-maintenance package because of its
  custom build scripts that were not working well for Gentoo's standards. It
  also used <c>nasm</c> heavily, making it impossible to use it on non-x86 based
  systems (amd64 systems seemed to work, too). Instead of this, it's possible
  to use <c>libquicktime</c> that forked from the old 1.x series of the package
  and still works fine on non-x86 arches and non-Linux systems.
  </p>

  <p>
  <c>avifile</c> is mostly a dead project, needing CVS snapshots to be updated,
  its maintainership was made harder by being incompatible with newer versions
  of <c>ffmpeg</c>. Packages depending on it are being modified not to use it
  or pending removal with <c>avifile</c> itself.
  </p>

  </body>
  </section>

  </extrachapter>
</project>

<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; -->
