<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/video/vlc.xml,v 1.28 2015/01/20 22:27:48 dilfridge Exp $ -->

<guide lang="en" disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Video/VLC">
<title>vlc and related</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="flameeyes@gentoo.org">Diego Pettenò</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="aballier@gentoo.org">Alexis Ballier</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Maintainer notes about vlc and its relatives
</abstract>


<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.24</version>
<date>2009-11-12</date>

<chapter> <!-- vlc -->
<title>vlc</title>

<section> <!-- Introduction -->
<title>Introduction</title>

<body>

<note>
This guide was last updated for <c>vlc</c> version 1.0.3.
</note>

<p>
<c>media-video/vlc</c> is
<uri link="http://www.videolan.org/">VLC media player</uri>, a multimedia player
with different interface modules, though primarily as a streaming client.
There are no frontends a part the core <c>vlc</c> binary, but the different
interfaces are loaded as modules.
</p>

<p>
Because of its structure, a crash into the decoding routines means a complete
crash of the interface, too. A careful maintenance is needed, similarly to
<c><uri link="xine.xml">xine-lib</uri></c>.
</p>

<p>
Its maintenance is usually simple, as it's one of the most portable solutions
(it runs natively on Linux, Windows, OSX and FreeBSD). Related to <c>vlc</c>
there are, though, different libraries that might be a problem to maintain,
as they are handled differently in Portage from what the other distributions do.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section> <!-- Patches -->
<title>Patches</title>

<body>

<p>
Patches for <c>vlc</c> are a bit different respect <c>xine-lib</c>, as they are
sometimes exclusive to Gentoo Linux and simply can't be upstreamed at all. This
is the case of the patches that change some libraries from builtin to plugins
(with the assumption that Gentoo always have them as PIC libraries).
</p>

<p>
In general there might be necessity to patch vlc when something in its
dependencies changes, as it's usually quite good-written the internal code and
also the <path>configure.ac</path>. In the past it needed patching to get
wxGTK or Samba dependencies fixed.
</p>

<p>
The bootstrap script provided with the sources should not be used to rebuild
autotools support. While it's usually better to use the upstream-provide file,
that bootstrap script contains also instructions to update gettext support, that
might create confusion with the shipped version, and requires also the cvs
command to get autopoint right. A simple <path>eautoreconf</path> call should
be enough.
</p>

<p>
There are two ways to send patches upstream: either via their <path>vlc-devel</path>
<uri link="http://developers.videolan.org/lists.html">mailing list</uri> or by
<uri link="http://wiki.videolan.org/Report_bugs">reporting a bug</uri> in the
<uri link="https://trac.videolan.org/vlc/">Trac system</uri>.
</p>

<p>
The patches are hosted in CVS inside <path>gentoo/src/patchsets/vlc</path>
and are organized by version. Released patchsets are tagged with the name of the
tarball minus the <path>.tar.bz2</path>. The directories contains also a series
file, as they are used by quilt: just symlink the checked out directory inside
an extracted source tree of vlc (for that version) and use <c>quilt</c> to
manage the patches.
</p>

<note>
Also if usually this point was never stressed out, now that patches are hosted
on the CVS it's important that they bring a description in the header, with also
a link to relevant bugs, both in Gentoo and upstream.
</note>

</body>
</section>

<section> <!-- External libraries and plugins -->
<title>External libraries and plugins</title>

<body>

<p>
<c>vlc</c> uses a mixed architecture for linking decoding libraries: some of
them are linked as <e>builtin</e>, statically into the vlc binary, while others
are built as <e>plugins</e> that gets loaded at runtime.
</p>

<p>
As the plugins are by all means shared objects, they must be built with PIC
enabled and can't link against static non-PIC libraries. As some libraries used
to decode or demux (such as libmatroska and libdts) used to be static libraries
only, the configure sometimes checks for two names for libraries, one for the
PIC version (<path>_pic</path> or <path>_p</path>) and one for the non-PIC,
enabling the plugin or the builtin depending on the case.
</p>

<p>
As in Gentoo most of the libraries are patched to build the PIC shared version
with the same name of the original one, the configure script sometimes gets
false negatives, and builds as builtin something that could have been built as
plugin. In those cases, it's needed to edit the <path>configure.ac</path> file
to get the right name for the library to build as plugin.
</p>

<p>
The use of plugins instead of builtins allows VLC to continue working also if
one of the libraries gets broken by a changed ABI, as the plugins fails to load
on demand, while builtins breaks the main executable file.
</p>

<p>
Like newer versions of <c><uri link="xine.xml">xine-lib</uri></c>, <c>vlc</c>
always uses an external copy of <c>ffmpeg</c>. This means that when a new
version of that package is stabilized, <c>vlc</c> has to be checked against it.
It also means that it does not suffer from problems related directly to
<c>ffmpeg</c> code, such as security vulnerabilities.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section> <!-- Testing versions -->
<title>Testing versions</title>

<body>

<p>
As many other projects, also <c>vlc</c> releases beta versions of the code
before the actual final release. These beta versions are usually useful to test
the changes to the dependencies and the code in package.mask so that problems
can be found before unleashing the final version to users.
</p>

<p>
Test versions are usually announced on <path>vlc-devel</path> mailing list and
can be found at
<uri link="http://download.videolan.org/pub/videolan/testing/">http://download.videolan.org/pub/videolan/testing/</uri>.
The naming scheme used is X.Y.Z-testT.
</p>

<p>
Since version 0.8.4, the ebuild carries the transformation between _beta to
-beta versions and uses the right URL for betas without having to edit it by
hand.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section> <!-- useflags -->
<title>useflags</title>

<body>

<p>
As many other multimedia programs, also <c>vlc</c> have quite a lot of useflags
to disable and enable dependencies and extra features. There are a few missing
dependencies that are not enabled, and a few useflags that were removed for
many reasons in the past.
</p>

<p>
The <b>nsplugin</b> useflag is used to build the Netscape-compatible plugins
(used by Mozilla, Firefox and Konqueror); this plugin is quite fragile, and the
useflag (that was added after 0.8.2 release) was removed till the latter 0.8.5
revisions, with patches to build against Firefox or Seamonkey rather than the
old Gecko-SDK (no more supported) or XULRunner (experimental). The plugin itself
is unsatble anyway, and if bugs are confirmed is probably simpler to remove it
or declare it experimental.
</p>

<p>
Most of the nsplugin's problems were fixed in 0.8.6, although the way
to select against which package to build changed drastically (as the
patch applied to 0.8.5 was rejected for a different approach). Since
this version, you need to pass the XPIDL variable with the path to the
IDL libraries for the package to link against (firefox or seamonkey)
and the MOZILLA_CONFIG variable with the path to the
<path>*-config</path> script, again depending on which one you want to
link against.
</p>

<p>
The <b>live</b> useflag enable support of live555 for RTSP support,
provided by <c>media-plugins/live</c>. Starting from version
2006.12.08 of this latter package, the way it is installed in the
system is drastically changed; while previously it installed in a
"build tree", and was linked statically, the newer versions installs
as a normal package using lib and include directories. For this
reason, the <path>--with-live555-tree</path> option is not passed
anymore, in vlc 0.8.6 and later, if the newer version of live is
present.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Useflag</th>
    <th>Local description</th>
    <th>Dependency</th>
    <th>Reason for removing</th>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <ti>portaudio</ti>
    <ti>PortAudio output plugin</ti>
    <ti>&gt;=media-sound/portaudio-19</ti>
    <ti>
      The required version of <c>portaudio</c> is the currently experimental
      version (19), not present in Portage and too unstable.
    </ti>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <ti>tremor</ti>
    <ti>Enables Tremor decoder support</ti>
    <ti></ti>
    <ti>Missing dependency</ti>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <ti>tarkin</ti>
    <ti>Enables experimental tarkin codec</ti>
    <ti></ti>
    <ti>Missing dependency</ti>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <ti>cyberlink</ti>
    <ti>Enable CyberLink UPnP stack</ti>
    <ti></ti>
    <ti>Missing dependency</ti>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <ti>libtar</ti>
    <ti>Enables libtar support for skins2 module</ti>
    <ti>dev-libs/libtar</ti>
    <ti>libtar doesn't build a PIC shared library thus we disable it</ti>
  </tr>

</table>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>

<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; -->
