<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/user-relations/summerofcode/Attic/Announcement.xml,v 1.4 2006/04/28 21:31:11 antarus Exp $ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/user-relations/summerofcode/Announcement.xml" disclaimer="draft" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo and Google's Summer of Code</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
We are proud to announce Gentoo's participation in the Google Summer of Code initiative.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-04-28</date>
<chapter>
<title>What Is Google Summer of Code?</title>

<section>
<body>
<p>
As many of you know by now, Gentoo has been chosen to fill one of the
last spaces in this year's Google Summer of Code.  This is a great
opportunity for developers and users to interact and help out Gentoo as
well as the OSS community.
</p>

<p>
Google's SoC is an initiative whereby Google funds the development of 
a selected number of OSS projects.  This year, only students are allowed
to do actual development for Google's SoC.  But anyone can mentor a 
Student on one of the projects for which Gentoo is the Mentoring
Organization.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>How do I participate with Gentoo in Google's Summer of Code</title>
<section>
<title>Mentor Role</title>
<body>
<p>
The role of a Mentor is as someone who has knowledge in the project
domain and can assist the student in a strategic development role, as
opposed to actually writing code.  Mentors are involved in evaluating
the work of the student and monitoring the project's progress, and is
also instrumental in enabling the student to complete the project by
providing the student with the tools needed to complete the project
(think about someone who needs read-only cvs access to the tree, for
example).
</p>

<p>
All Gentoo developers should have received the mail sent to -core about
Gentoo's acceptance into Google SoC.  The information and links to sign
up as a Mentor for Gentoo are enclosed in that mail.  If you are interested
please see the -core e-mail for details, as well as the 
<uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/mentorfaq.html">Mentor FAQ</uri>.
You cannot be both a Mentor and a Student in SoC.  Please choose carefully
which role you will play.  Those who are not Gentoo developers may stll
apply for the role of Mentor on behalf of Gentoo.  If you are
not a Gentoo developer but are interested in applying, please stop by
#gentoo-soc @ irc.freenode.net or send mail to 
<mail link="user-relations@gentoo.org">Gentoo User Relations</mail>.
Please have a few projects in mind when applying for Mentorship.  The Gentoo
SoC team is hoping to have more Mentors than projects; backup Mentors
are encouraged by Google.
</p>
<note>You do not have to be a Gentoo developer to be a Mentor on behalf
of Gentoo.  If you are interested in mentoring for any of the projects
that Gentoo may select, we encourage you to apply.</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Student Role</title>
<body>
<p>
If you are interested in participating as a student with Gentoo for the
SoC, please take a look at our current 
<uri link="/proj/en/devrel/user-relations/summerofcode/">
project list</uri>.  Note that it is undergoing continuous improvement as 
we add proposals, Mentors, etc.
</p>
<p>
All interested students should refer to Google's <uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/studentfaq.html">
Student FAQ</uri> to check whether they are eligible to participate in
the SoC with Gentoo.  For Gentoo developers who are also Students, you 
are probably eligible to work on SoC for Gentoo provided you work on a 
proposal that is in a different area than your normal Gentoo developer 
work.  Once again please check the <uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/studentfaq.html">
Student FAQ</uri> for more details.  Student applications are open May 
1st through the 8th.  The URL for the student application is not yet 
known.  The project page will be updated with the link as soon as we 
receive it from Google.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Project Ideas</title>
<body>
<p>
Project Ideas/Discussion:
Anyone can submit project ideas and contribute to the discussion of
existing project ideas.  Those who have new ideas or comments on
existing ideas for Gentoo's SoC, please submit them via E-mail to the
<mail link="gentoo-soc@gentoo.org">Gentoo SoC mailing list</mail> 
or on #gentoo-soc @ irc.freenode.net.  If you are unsure of your idea
or wish to ask questions you may do so via the same means.  As always,
feel free to ask any questions using those two avenues of communication
to ensure that the correct people receive your thoughts.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
