<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>soc</name>
<longname>Gentoo Summer of Code</longname>
<date>2006-04-18</date>
<author title="Author"><mail link="nattfodd@gentoo.org">Alexandre Buisse</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="gerrynjr@gentoo.org">Gerald J. Normandin Jr.</mail></author>
<description>
The Gentoo Summer of Code subproject oversees Gentoo's participation in the
2006 Google Summer of Code.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>For the second year running, Google is organising a <e>Summer of Code</e>,
funding students to work on open-source projects over the summer. For more
details, see <uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/">the official SoC
website</uri>.</p>
<p>This year, Gentoo is participating as a mentor organisation. As a result,
we hope to see several students working on specific projects with Gentoo over
the summer, and hopefully becoming more involved long-term in Gentoo 
development.</p>
</longdescription>

<dev role="Lead">gerrynjr</dev>
<dev role="Lead">christel</dev>
<dev role="Member">patrick</dev>
<dev role="Member">nattfodd</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Project Ideas</title>
<section>
<body>
    <p>Here is a list of some of the project ideas:</p>

    
        <table>
	    <tr>
		<th>Idea</th>
		<th>Details</th>
	    </tr>

            <tr>
	    <ti>Rewrite of repoman</ti>
            <ti>Repoman is a tool used by gentoo
                    developers for Quality Assurance and commits to the tree.
                    As it is now, additional checks are hard to implement into
                    the application. Seeking a modular rewrite preferably in
                    python but other languages are possible</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
	    	<ti>WYSIWYG editor for guidexml</ti>
            	<ti>Entails writing a graphical front-end so that people who
                    do not necessarily know GuideXML can create compliant XML.
                    Might consist of either a web based frontend or a client
                    application based frontend.</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>gentoolkit rewrite</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Port "sandbox" to other platforms</ti>
            	<ti>Perhaps get sandbox functioning on Alpha, ARM, MIPS, or
                    PowerPC</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Write a configuration file manager (etc-update
                    replacement)</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>GLEP 42 implementation</ti>
            	<ti>This GLEP would entail modifying portage to allow for critical news reports.
		For more information please read the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0042.html">GLEP</uri></ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Graphical frontend to baselayout</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Modify Java Packages to build with an open source
                        JVM</ti>
                <ti>Patch packages that use proprietary classes while
                        working with upstream. Over three hundred packages
                        would need to be modified. This would allow platforms
                        that are not necessarily supported by a proprietary
                        JVM to run Java applications such as Eclipse and
                        Azureus.</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Rewrite backend for NetworkManager</ti>
                <ti>Would possibly include adding Avahi support, Dialup/Modem support, or
                        Reading settings from baselayout</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Work on "Gentoo-Stats"</ti>
		<ti>This project would allow arch teams to know how much testing 
		each package gets and it would let developers know about what types 
		of CFLAGS/USE flags our users are utilising</ti>
	    </tr>
        </table>


</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Gentoo Developers willing to mentor</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Here is a list of developers willing to mentor:</p>
<ul>
<li>g2boojum</li>
<li>metalgod</li>
<li>chriswhite</li>
<li>nichoj</li>
<li>tigger</li>
<li>lu_zero</li>
<li>steev</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Getting Involved</title>
<section>
<body>

<p><b>As a student:</b> If you want to work on any of the suggested projects,
or have a project idea of your own, you should apply through the Google page --
see the <uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/studentfaq.html">Student 
FAQ</uri> for information. The team is happy to discuss any ideas you may have
before you apply to Google; see below for how to find us. </p>

<p><b>As a developer:</b> If you have an idea for a project, or would like to
become a mentor or join the gentoo-soc team, please get in touch by emailing any
member of the team, or find us in #gentoo-soc on Freenode.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>


</project>
