<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>soc</name>
<longname>Gentoo Summer of Code</longname>
<date>2006-04-18</date>
<author title="Author"><mail link="nattfodd@gentoo.org">Alexandre Buisse</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="gerrynjr@gentoo.org">Gerald J. Normandin Jr.</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail></author>

<description>
The Gentoo Summer of Code subproject oversees Gentoo's participation in the
2006 Google Summer of Code.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>For the second year running, Google is organising a <e>Summer of Code</e>,
funding students to work on open-source projects over the summer. For more
details, see <uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/">the official SoC
website</uri>.</p>
<p>This year, Gentoo is participating as a mentor organisation. As a result,
we hope to see several students working on specific projects with Gentoo over
the summer, and hopefully becoming more involved long-term in Gentoo 
development.</p>
</longdescription>

<dev role="Lead">gerrynjr</dev>
<dev role="Lead">christel</dev>
<dev role="Member">patrick</dev>
<dev role="Member">nattfodd</dev>
<dev role="Member">antarus</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Deadlines</title>
<section>
<body>
<p> Students and Developers (Mentors) may signup for the program between May 1st and May 8th. Ideas from developers are also due by the same date. There also also a limited number of slots available for both Mentors as well as Students, so please to respond quickly if you are interested. </p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Project Ideas</title>
<section>
<body>
    <p>Here is a list of some of the project ideas:</p>    
        <table>
	    <tr>
		<th>Idea</th>
		<th>Details</th>
	    </tr>

            <tr>
	    <ti>Rewrite of repoman</ti>
            <ti>Repoman is a tool used by gentoo
                    developers for Quality Assurance and commits to the tree.
                    As it is now, additional checks are hard to implement into
                    the application. Seeking a modular rewrite preferably in
                    python but other languages are possible</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
	    	<ti>WYSIWYG editor for guidexml</ti>
            	<ti>Entails writing a graphical front-end so that people who
                    do not necessarily know GuideXML can create compliant XML.
                    Might consist of either a web based frontend or a client
                    application based frontend.</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>gentoolkit rewrite</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Port "sandbox" to other platforms</ti>
            	<ti>Perhaps get sandbox functioning on Alpha, ARM, MIPS, or
                    PowerPC</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Write a configuration file manager (etc-update
                    replacement)</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>GLEP 42 implementation</ti>
            	<ti>This GLEP would entail modifying portage to allow for critical news reports.
		For more information please read the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0042.html">GLEP</uri></ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Graphical frontend to baselayout</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Modify Java Packages to build with an open source
                        JVM</ti>
                <ti>Patch packages that use proprietary classes while
                        working with upstream. Over three hundred packages
                        would need to be modified. This would allow platforms
                        that are not necessarily supported by a proprietary
                        JVM to run Java applications such as Eclipse and
                        Azureus.</ti>
	    </tr>
            <tr>
		<ti>Rewrite backend for NetworkManager</ti>
                <ti>Would possibly include adding Avahi support, Dialup/Modem support, or
                        Reading settings from baselayout</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Work on "Gentoo-Stats"</ti>
		<ti>This project would allow arch teams to know how much testing 
		each package gets and it would let developers know about what types 
		of CFLAGS/USE flags our users are utilising</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
	    	<ti>Gentoo/*BSD projects</ti>
		<ti>The Gentoo/*BSD project, while maturing quickly, still needs a lot of work
		in several areas. Useful project ideas include: catalyst support for building
		*BSD stages and livecds, porting Sandbox to work on BSD systems, better support
		for BSD file flags in Portage, Gnome porting (running GNOME on FreeBSD requires 
		a large collection of patches from the Ports collection; this project would clean
		these up, make them more generic, and attempt to send them upstream so that others
		can benefit), and potentially modifying alsa-lib to use FreeBSD's OSS system as
		a sound backend, so that applications written to use ALSA can work unmodified on
		FreeBSD. Also useful would be to port Gentoo/FreeBSD to AMD64, and potentially
		other, hardware, sorting out any architecture issues that may crop up, such as
		building a proper multilib toolchain.</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>GLEP 27 Implementation</ti>
		<ti>Provide an implementation of <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0027.html">
		GLEP 27</uri> in which ebuilds may add and remove necessary accounts in a variety
		of environments.  At present only <path>/etc/passwd</path> is support.  Adding support
		for LDAP and NIS/NIS+ environments would increase the usefulness of the Portage system.
		</ti>
	    </tr>
        </table>


</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Gentoo Developers willing to mentor</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Here is a table of Mentors and their interests.  We have attempted to list their interests so that
prospective students have an idea of who to talk to regarding their idea.  No mentor's have been assigned,
this table servers only as an aid to applicants.</p>

	<table>
	    <tr>
		<th>Mentor</th>
		<th>E-mail</th>
		<th>Interests</th>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Grant Goodyear</ti>
		<ti>g2boojum@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Gentoo/*BSD related projects, GLEP 27 implementation, 
		"ambitious student proposals"</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Luis Medinas</ti>
		<ti>metalgod@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Baselayout front-end, portage front-end</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Chris White</ti>
		<ti>chriswhite@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>GuideXML Editor</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Joshua Nichols</ti>
		<ti>nichoj@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Anything Java related</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Rob Holland</ti>
		<ti>tigger@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Security and Auditing related projects, Project to create customized 
		portage tree, others.</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Luca Barbato</ti>
		<ti>lu_zero@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Must speak with him</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Stephen Klimaszewski</ti>
		<ti>steev@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Willing to work on most anything</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Stephen Bennett</ti>
		<ti>spb@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Gentoo/*BSD related projects</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Diego Pettenò</ti>
		<ti>flameeyes@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Backup Mentor for Stephen Bennett (spb), Gentoo/*BSD related projects</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Patrick Lauer</ti>
		<ti>patrick@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Portage modifications, Pkgcore modifications, Repoman modifications, 
		Collecting stats on Gentoo's usage</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Alexandre Buisse</ti>
		<ti>nattfodd@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Must speak with him</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Gerald J. Normandin Jr.</ti>
		<ti>gerrynjr@gentoo.org</ti>
		<ti>Must speak with him</ti>
	    </tr>
	    <tr>
		<ti>Brian Harring</ti>
		<ti>ferrinb@gmail.com</ti>
		<ti>Portage related projects, Anything with regards to Python</ti>
	    </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Getting Involved</title>
<section>
<body>

<p><b>As a student:</b> If you want to work on any of the suggested projects,
or have a project idea of your own, you should apply through the Google page --
see the <uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/studentfaq.html">Student 
FAQ</uri> for information. The team is happy to discuss any ideas you may have
before you apply to Google; see below for how to find us. </p>

<p><b>As a developer:</b> If you have an idea for a project, or would like to
become a mentor or join the gentoo-soc team, please get in touch by emailing any
member of the team, or find us in #gentoo-soc on Freenode.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>


</project>
