<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/x/x11/herd-testers.xml,v 1.2 2012/10/28 15:21:02 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide lang="en">
<title>X11 Herd Testers Project Team</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="scarabeus@gentoo.org">Tomáš Chvátal</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The X11 HT Project is devoted to help the developers with testing packages,
identifying issues and finding fixes.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2009-08-26</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As defined by <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0041.html">GLEP 41</uri>, an HT is
a trustworthy user who is able to help with testing packages, identifying issues
and finding fixes.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>What you get</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
All HTs receive a <c>/gentoo/contributor/${NAME}</c> IRC cloak, are added to
the "Arch/Herd Tester" group on the <uri link="https://forums.gentoo.org/">
Gentoo forums</uri>, are added to the <c>x11@gentoo.org</c> mail alias.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>What persons like Herd Testers have to do?</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
HTs usually test packages (stabilisation preparations, live packages, new
versions testing, ...),
provide guidance on bug reports (verifying issues, providing patches),
communicate with the X11 team through the team's IRC channel
(<c>#gentoo-desktop</c>) and mail to the <c>x11@gentoo.org</c> mail alias.
HTs are also invited to help users on forums, mailing lists and IRC channels.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Requirements</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
We expect people to do good testing, show good knowledge about Gentoo in general
and to be active (taking into account RL constraints). Also we require people
have willingness to learn new stuff about freedesktop.org bug sumbission and
patch tracking, or actualy willingness to learn anything interesting about x11
:].
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Participating</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
If you think your comments and patches submitted to Bugzilla and willingness to
help other users on IRC, mailinglists and/or forums justifies HT status you can
talk to the X11 team. Users will also be invited to become HTs by members of the
X11 team that notice their work, abilities and desire to help the X11 team.
</p>

<p>
To become an HT, the user will have to complete the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz/ebuild-quiz.txt">ebuild
quiz</uri> and have a review session with the AT lead (<mail
link="hparker@gentoo.org">hparker</mail>).
</p>

<p>
Interested users should read the <uri link="http://devmanual.gentoo.org/">Gentoo
Development Guide/DevManual</uri> and the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo
Developer Handbook</uri> and should work with the other members of the herd to
address the questions on the quiz. The KDE HT lead will work closely with all
HTs, helping them prepare for the quiz and the interview, and will coordinate
their work on the herd.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
