<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/x/x11/xorg-server-1.5-upgrade-guide.xml,v 1.7 2012/10/28 15:21:02 swift Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Xorg 1.5 Upgrade Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="remi"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide shows you how to upgrade X.org to version 1.5.
</abstract>

<!-- The  content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1</version>
<date>2009-03-30</date>

<chapter>
<title>Ebuild changes</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <c>x11-misc/xkbdata</c> is now completely deprecated. If you were not using
    its replacement (<c>x11-misc/xkeyboard-config</c>), Portage may ask you to
    remove it before proceeding with the update.
  </li>
  <li>
    X now no longer forces a double hidden build of <c>media-libs/mesa</c>.
    Mesa now builds the software renderer (swrast) and whatever hardware driver
    you've chosen with the <c>VIDEO_CARDS</c> variable.
  </li>
  <li>
    Due to the above change, the <c>dri</c> USE flag was dropped. Xorg will now
    always have OpenGL support unless <c>USE=minimal</c> is set.
  </li>
  <li>
    XPrint has been removed in Xorg 1.6 and newer, but we've decided to drop it
    as well from 1.5. XPrint support has been removed from all X libraries.
  </li>
  <li>
    Xorg now supports HAL to automatically hot-plug input devices, see the
    section below to properly configure it.
  </li>
  <li>
    The "synaptics" driver is now provided by
    <c>x11-drivers/xf86-input-synaptics</c>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring Input</title>
<section>
<title>With HAL (with xf86-input-evdev)</title>
<body>

<p>
In a nutshell, HAL allows to set the exact same properties as
<path>xorg.conf</path> does but with a lot more flexibility: you can now have
per-device layouts for instance. All of this is provided by the
<c>xf86-input-evdev</c> driver.
</p>

<p>
First, make sure you've built xorg-server
with <c>INPUT_DEVICES="evdev"</c> and enabled evdev in your kernel.
</p>
<pre caption="Configuration for 2.6 kernels">
Device Drivers ---&gt;

Input device support ---&gt;

--- Input device support
[*]     Event interface
</pre>

<p>
Then, we can configure HAL to correctly report the keyboard's layout. HAL ships
with device rules that are kept in <path>/usr/share/hal</path>. 
</p>

<impo>
Do <e>not</e> edit those, they will be overwritten during the next HAL update.
You can instead add your own rules into <path>/etc/hal/fdi/policy</path>.
</impo>

<p>
Sample configuration FDI files are available
<path>/usr/share/doc/hal-*/*.fdi*</path>. Pick the one that best fits your
current configuration and copy it to <path>/etc/hal/fdi/policy</path>.
</p>

<p>
For example, if you just want a basic configuration for a non-US keyboard
layout, copy the content of
<path>/usr/share/doc/hal-*/use-estonian-layout.fdi.bz2</path> into
<path>/etc/hal/fdi/policy/10-xinput-configuration.fdi</path> (using
<c>bzcat</c>) and edit it to match the keyboard layout you wish to use.
</p>

<p>
Don't forget to read <c>man evdev</c> to see the driver's capabilities and
options (especially mouse wheel emulation, middle mouse button emulation, ...).
</p>

<note>
Current HAL versions are not (yet) able to pick up FDI file changes on their
own. You'll have to restart HAL's init script to see your changes. To make sure
everything is correct, use the <c>lshal</c> utility to display HAL's device tree
and search for "input". The content of your HAL rules should show up in lshal's
output.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>With HAL and other drivers (xf86-input-synaptics, linuxwacom, ...)</title>
<body>

<p>
By default, HAL will tell the X server to use the <c>evdev</c> driver to access
all input devices. However this can be changed to any input driver you wish.
</p>

<p>
You can therefore put all your input device configuration into HAL even if you
use other input drivers such as <c>synaptics</c> or <c>linuxwacom</c>.
</p>

<p>
More information on how to configure those drivers can be found here:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri>http://cgit.freedesktop.org/xorg/xserver/tree/config/x11-input.fdi</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri>http://cgit.freedesktop.org/xorg/driver/xf86-input-synaptics/tree/fdi/11-x11-synaptics.fdi</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
     <uri>http://cvs.fedoraproject.org/viewvc/rpms/linuxwacom/F-10/10-linuxwacom.fdi?view=markup</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Without HAL</title>
<body>

<p>
If you don't want to use HAL, you can either build <c>xorg-server</c> with
<c>USE="-hal"</c> or you can turn AutoAddDevices option off in the
ServerFlags section of your <path>xorg.conf</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="Turning AutoAddDevices off">
Option      "AutoAddDevices"    "false"
</pre>

<p>
Both options will allow the X server to use the legacy <c>mouse</c> and
<c>kbd</c> drivers.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring the graphics card</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The "Device" section in your xorg.conf should mostly work unchanged.
</p>

<p>
However, if you have any issues, here's a few steps you can try:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Try commenting out all "Options" in the "Device", "Screen" and "Monitor"
    sections in your xorg.conf
  </li>
  <li>
    Even better, try running Xorg without <e>any</e> <path>xorg.conf</path> (you
    can rename it to <path>xorg.conf.old</path>)
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Xorg drivers are now much better at actually detecting what kind of hardware you
have and (except for a <e>few</e> special cases) the default settings should be
kept.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Miscellaneous Options</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The old font handling was shaken quite a bit in our version of 1.5.3. The
<c>freetype</c> module is now useless since the server uses <c>libXfont</c> to
load whatever fonts you might have for legacy applications.
</p>

<p>
As for legacy fonts themselves, they are now nearly useless as we provide a
built-in "fixed" font which all legacy applications and toolkits should be able
to use. Beware though that this font is extremely ugly.
</p>

<p>
Xdmx is broken. Don't use it unless you know what you're doing.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
If you have strange mouse behaviour in all SDL-based applications
(many games), you need to set the following in your <path>xorg.conf</path>:
</p>
<pre caption="Turning DGA off">
Section "Module"
       ...
       SubSection  "extmod"
         Option    "omit xfree86-dga"
       EndSubSection
       ...
EndSection
</pre>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
