<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/releng/installer/release-0.2.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Installer 0.2 Release Announcement</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="agaffney@gentoo.org">Andrew Gaffney</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="blackace@gentoo.org">Blackace</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Information regarding the 0.2 release of the Gentoo Linux Installer.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>21 Nov 2005</date>

<chapter>
<title>Version 0.2</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The installer team is proud to announce the release of version 0.2 of the Gentoo
Linux Installer.  There have been many improvements over the 0.1 ("alpha")
release including many new features and many annoying bugs squished.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Improvements</title>
<section>
<title>New features</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>Sub-progress bar (shows the progress of the individual install step).</li>
  <li>
    Tarball extraction progress (shows how far along it is extracting a
    tarball).
  </li>
  <li>
    New code for dynamic-stage3 that cuts the time in half along with not
    cluttering up your new install with binary packages.
  </li>
  <li>Optional verbose logging for debug purposes.</li>
  <li>
    Notification of which packages are available in GRP form (gli-dialog only).
  </li>
  <li>
    More graceful failure cleanup (now unmounts mounted partitions) (gtkfe
    only).
  </li>
  <li>
    Pre-configured xorg.conf is now copied to the new system when xorg-x11 is
    installed.
  </li>
  <li>
    If selecting a graphical desktop xdm is set to boot automatically in
    standard mode (prompt in advanced) (gli-dialog only).
  </li>
  <li>
    Automatic snapshot/make.conf screens for dynamic stage3 installs (this is
    necessary to prevent b0rkage).
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bugs fixed since 0.1</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>NTFS/FAT32 code problem that left you with an empty partition table.</li>
  <li>Attempting to mount unallocated space.</li>
  <li>Various bootloader bugs.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Issues not resolved in 0.2 but fixed in CVS</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    Mounting windows partitions can cause filesystem format issues (fat16/32
    instead of vfat).
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Issues not yet resolved</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>gli-dialog error cleanup (should be an option).</li>
  <li>
    Bootloader customizability.  Currently the boot device is determined by
    <path>/boot</path> (or <path>/</path> if no <path>/boot</path>) and the MBR
    of that device is written to instead of whatever device boots first.  This
    is currently being fixed.
  </li>
  <li>
    Internationalization support in gli-dialog is still only at "ready to go"
    status.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>New LiveCD</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Along with the new version of the installer, there is also a new LiveCD (extra
thanks to wolf31o2 for that).  Some of the changes include:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Gimp and bittorrent have been added.</li>
  <li>Fixes to allow Gnome to install properly via GRP.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Coming soon to a LiveCD near you! (i.e. what to expect from 0.3)</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    Dynamic/virtual hard-drives!  You can define partitions with percentages.
  </li>
  <li>
    A brand new FE!  Webgli, a web-browser-based FE, combines aspects from the
    previous two FEs into a new and simple interface for creating install
    profiles.
  </li>
  <li>
    Mastergli (TEMPORARY NAME), a mass-installation utility, which will be
    combined with webgli to help create profiles.  This finally addresses the
    second half of the Gentoo Installer's project goals.  It will allow users to
    PXE boot client machines that will be detected by the mastergli server
    (these can also be defined manually) and specify which install profile to
    use for that machine.  This lets you create template machines such as
    "image-server" or "mail-server" or "normal-workstation" for example and pick
    and choose boxes and profiles.  It then will spawn off the selected installs
    and provide status updates via the same web interface.  The mastergli
    settings will of course be able to be saved/loaded with a master profile XML
    file.  Since this interface will work remotely (if allowed) and in links2,
    it is not likely that there will be a command-line version of mastergli
    anytime soon.  Mastergli utilizes SecureXMLRPC code from samyron as well as
    backend code from chotchki and of course agaffney.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
