<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/releng/installer/release-0.1.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Installer 0.1 Release Announcement</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="agaffney@gentoo.org">Andrew Gaffney</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="blackace@gentoo.org">Blackace</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Information regarding the 0.1 release of the Gentoo Linux Installer.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>08 Aug 2005</date>

<chapter>
<title>Version 0.1 (a.k.a. "the alpha")</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
We are happy to announce GLI 0.1 (a.k.a. "the alpha") along with a <e>real</e>
LiveCD (usable X environment with goodies) as opposed to the normal minimal or
universal "LiveCD".  It is currently available from the
<uri link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri> under <path>/experimental</path>.
</p>

<p>
The LiveCD contains most of the standard GRP set as usable packages.  This
includes (but isn't limited to):
</p>

<ul>
  <li>GNOME</li>
  <li>Firefox</li>
  <li>Thunderbird</li>
  <li>OpenOffice.org (Ximian goodness)</li>
  <li>sylpheed</li>
  <li>xmms</li>
  <li>gaim</li>
  <li>xchat</li>
  <li>mplayer</li>
</ul>

<p>
Obviously, the installer will also be included.  In GNOME, there is even a handy
desktop launcher for the GTK frontend!  We have strived to allow you to do
anything with the installer that you could do if installing with the current
method.  Keep in mind that this is only a first release, and there is a lot of
room for improvement.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Known Limitations &amp; New Features</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Here are some known limitations:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>No <path>/etc/portage</path> customization support in the frontends.</li>
  <li>No way to modify runlevels for services in the frontends.</li>
  <li>Only supports x86 and probably amd64 (other arches are in the works).</li>
  <li>
    The GTK frontend's <path>make.conf</path> screen only offers a few options.
  </li>
  <li>
    No way to custom configure a kernel without a premade <path>.config</path>.
  </li>
  <li>No lvm or software raid support.</li>
</ul>

<p>
Of course, to offset these bad things, we have a few features that are available
with the installer that were not available previously:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <e>livecd-kernel</e> - the installer will install the kernel from the LiveCD
    into the new install so that you don't have to wait for genkernel to do its
    thing.  It is installed as a package with emerge so that certain
    dependencies are satisfied (virtual/alsa for example).
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>GRP w/o an extra CD</e> - the installer will <c>quickpkg</c> and
    <c>emerge -K</c> packages from the LiveCD instead of using prebuilt binary
    packages.  This obsoletes the GRP CD, which will probably disappear in the
    next release.
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>dynamic stage3</e> - the installer can build a stage3 equivalent in the
    chroot directory from the packages on the CD.  This will be useful down the
    road for networkless installs.  Currently, there is no snapshot on the
    LiveCD for space reasons, but play with it anyway.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Dialog Frontend</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Along with the GTK frontend, there is also a dialog-based frontend.  This is
useful for doing remote installs via SSH.  <c>gli-dialog</c> also supports some
things that the GTK frontend doesn't and vice versa.  If not using gnome, the
installer can be started by running '<c>installer</c>' from a terminal.  This
will try to launch the GTK frontend first with the '<c>installer-gtk</c>'
script.  If this fails, it will fall back to the dialog installer with the
'<c>installer-dialog</c>' script.  If you wish to use the dialog frontend, you
can run '<c>installer-dialog</c>' directly.
</p>

<p>
Other features of the dialog frontend include "standard" and "advanced"
installation modes, where in the "standard" mode the default input for common
steps will be automatically given.  The dialog frontend also includes a detailed
explanation of all steps for those not as experienced with installing Gentoo.
It also supports custom kernel uri's and will load a list of mirrors for the
stage tarball selection.  Internationalization support is almost complete for
this frontend.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Reporting Bugs</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Now, for the <e>most</e> important part...reporting
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/">bugs</uri>.  Gentoo's bugzilla has a special
sub-section for the installer.  When you click the link to enter a new bug
report, select "Gentoo Linux" and then "GLI" from the "Component" list.  Please
search for the bug you're reporting <e>before</e> creating a new bug.  We would
much rather see "me too" comments, or even the much more silent act of adding
yourself to the bug's CC, than having to deal with tons of duplicate bugs.  When
you do encounter an error in the installer, try to grab
<path>/tmp/installprofile.xml</path> and <path>/var/log/install.log</path> from
the LiveCD environment.  We may request them when you file a bug.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
