<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/hardened/docs/index.xml,v 1.2 2004/08/08 02:33:48 tseng Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE mainpage SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<mainpage id="docs">
  <title>Hardened Gentoo Documentation Resources</title>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="tseng@gentoo.org">Brandon Hale</mail>
  </author>
<version>1.0</version>
<date>August 7, 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Hardened Gentoo Documentation Resources</title>

<section>
<body>
<p>
The <b><uri link="glossary.xml">Hardened Gentoo Glossary</uri></b> breifly
explains the several technologies that make up Hardened Gentoo.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SELinux</title>
<body>

<p>
SELinux is a system of mandatory access controls. SELinux can enforce the security 
policy over all processes and objects in the system. The following documents will
help you to build a new SELinux-enabled system, or to convert an existing system,
and get up to speed with the basics of SELinux policies.
</p>

<p>
The <b><uri link="../selinux/selinux-x86-install.xml">SELinux x86 Install Guide
</uri></b> provides a step-by-step explanation on how to install and configure
a new system using SELinux.
</p>

<p>
The <b><uri link="../selinux/selinux-quickstart.xml">SELinux QuickStart Guide
</uri></b> includes instructions on converting your existing Gentoo install to
SELinux.
</p>

<p>
The <b><uri link="../selinux/selinux-policy.xml">SELinux Policy Overview</uri></b> 
covers the basics of working with SELinux policies.
</p>

<p>
The <b><uri link="../selinux/selinux-faq.xml">SELinux FAQ</uri></b> answers many
frequently asked questions and has solutions for common pitfalls.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>RSBAC</title>
<body>

<p>
RSBAC is Mandatory Access Control security system based on the Role Compatibility 
model. It can enforce access rules on your operating system.
</p>

<p>
The <b><uri link="../rsbac/overview.xml">RSBAC Overview</uri></b> is a glossary
that establishes a basic understanding of RSBAC-related concepts.
</p>

<p>
The <b><uri link="../rsbac/quickstart.xml">RSBAC Quickstart</uri></b> 
covers converting an existing system to RSBAC.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>PaX</title>
<body>
    
<p>
PaX is a combination of technologies that enable comprehensive memory protection
in Linux. The following docs cover both the PaX kernel and complementary userland
technologies.
</p>

<p>
The <b><uri link="pax-howto.xml">PaX Howto</uri></b> helps to get a system
up and running with a PaX kernel and PIE/SSP userland.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
