<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="todo.xml">
<title>TODO list</title>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="calchan@gentoo.org">Denis Dupeyron</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="tomjbe@gentoo.org">Thomas Beierlein</mail>
</author>

<abstract>TODO list of the Electronics subproject</abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2010-10-26</date>

<chapter>
<title>Test benches</title>

<section>
    <title>General comments</title>
<body>
<p>We need to collate, and create when necessary, test benches for each package. The goal is to provide arch testers and users with a way
of checking that an application is properly working.</p>
<p>These test benches can be anything from a set of written instructions to an automated script. They should be as simple as possible.
A non-specialist must be able to use them.</p>
<p>Let's not forget they must be maintained to work with the new versions of the packages.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Package maintenance</title>

<section>
<title>All packages</title><body>
<p>
Stabilize latest versions whenever possible, and get rid of the others. Portage should be kept as lean as possible.
</p>
</body></section>

<section>
<title>electric</title><body>
<ul>
<li>Stabilize version 8.11.</li>
<li>See if building versions 8 and later from sources is a good idea (it's java). Current decision is no, but that may change.</li>
</ul>
</body></section>

<section>
<title>geda</title><body>
<ul>
<li>Complete stabilization of version 1.6.1 (see <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=285470">bug #285470</uri>).</li>
<li>Get rid of version 1.4.0-r1 after stabilisation of 1.6.1</li>
</ul>
</body></section>

<section>
<title>geda-suite</title><body>
<ul>
<li>Write a newer ebuild (than version 20050820) with updated dependencies.</li>
<li>Include gspiceui (see <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=74201">bug #74201</uri>)</li>
</ul>
</body></section>

<section>
<title>gerbv</title><body>
<ul>
<li>Finish stabilization version 2.4.0. (see <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=342811">bug #342811</uri></li>
<li>Get rid of older versions.</li>
</ul>
</body></section>

<section>
<title>gnucap</title><body>
<p>Quite some mess to fix, here. Version 20060708 was stabilized due to version 0.34 not playing nice with gcc 4.1
(if I remember correctly). Recently, version 0.35 was released by upstream, but in portage it appears older than
20060708 although it is more recent. Thus, users not masking versions 2006mmdd, as indicated in the ChangeLog, will
not see the new release.</p>
<ul>
<li>Later development versions will need to be called 0.35_p2006mmdd in order to avoid this mess again.</li>
</ul>
</body></section>

<section>
<title>kicad</title><body>
<p>Denis should provide and document the ugly script he uses to generate the custom tarballs.</p>
</body></section>

<section>
<title>ng-spice-rework</title><body>
<ul>
<li>Change the package name to ngspice. This is confusing for some users.</li>
<li>Investigate the use boehm-gc. Heavy simulations can make use of better memory management.</li>
</ul>
</body></section>

</chapter>

</guide>
