<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE book SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/Attic/desktop.xml,v 1.3 2004/04/25 16:29:07 swift Exp $ -->

<book link="desktop.xml">
<title>Gentoo Handbook - Desktop Part</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor"><!-- OpenBox section -->
  <mail link="dimiduk.1@osu.edu">Nick Dimiduk</mail>
</author>


<abstract>
This is the Gentoo Handbook, an effort to centralise Gentoo/Linux
information. This one only contains the desktop-specific part.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->
<license/>

<version>0.2</version>
<date>April 18, 2004</date>

<part>
<title>Configuring a Gentoo Desktop</title>
<abstract>
Gentoo is able to turn your system into an extremely powerful desktop. This part
lets you discover the power of the Linux desktop and how Gentoo enables you to
deal with this immense plethora of choices.
</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>The X Server</title>
<abstract>
Xorg is the X Window server which allows users to have a graphical
environment at their fingertips. We explain what Xorg is, how to install it
and what the various configuration options are.
</abstract>
  <include href="hb-desktop-xorg.xml"/>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The K Desktop Environment</title>
<abstract>
One of the most used desktop environments is KDE. This chapter tries to describe
all aspects of KDE, including installation, configuration, usage, ...
</abstract>
  <include href="hb-desktop-kde.xml"/>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The GNOME Environment</title>
<abstract>
Another frequently used environment is GNOME. As like with the previous chapter
we describe all aspects of GNOME, including installation, configuration, usage,
...
</abstract>
  <include href="hb-desktop-gnome.xml"/>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The various Window Managers</title>
<abstract>
Right next to the desktop environments, which tend to cover all aspects of
desktop usage, we have the window managers which only provide an interface to
manage the various graphical tools. Here we try to give a sum up on the
available window managers.
</abstract>
  <include href="hb-desktop-wm.xml"/>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Getting Sound to Work</title>
<abstract>
A desktop without sound is hardly a desktop. This chapter explains how to setup
ALSA (the Advanced Linux Sound Architecture) on your system and have it work
flawlesly with your installed DE/WM.
</abstract>
  <include href="hb-desktop-sound.xml"/>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>What about 3D Acceleration?</title>
<abstract>
It is a frequently heard myth that Linux doesn't support 3D. This is hardly true
as you will find out when you read this chapter.
</abstract>
  <include href="hb-desktop-3d.xml"/>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Integrating in a Network</title>
<abstract>
A desktop by itself is a desktop. But many users have a LAN at their disposal
and really like to have their Gentoo desktop integrated in the existing network.
This chapter explains how to setup Samba for file- and printer sharing.
</abstract>
  <include href="hb-desktop-network.xml"/>
</chapter>

</part>

</book>
