<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/Attic/hb-desktop-wm.xml,v 1.2 2004/04/11 01:50:15 swift Exp $ -->

<sections>
<section>
<title>What Window Managers does Gentoo support?</title>
<subsection>
<title>What is a Window Manager Anyway?</title>
<body>

<p>
Our previous chapters spoke about <e>Desktop Environments</e>. The difference
between a Desktop Environment and a <e>Window Manager</e> is that a Desktop
Environment contains a Window Manager together with various applications and
X clients which create a common graphical user interface. A Window Manager is an
X client application which controls how windows are positioned and such.
</p>

<p>
To that respect, Window Managers are slim and quick but don't contain all the
features of a desktop environment. But because they are slim and quick they are
also very popular.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>What Window Managers does Gentoo Provide?</title>
<body>

<p>
There are several Window Managers out there. Just take a look inside
<path>/usr/portage/x11-wm</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Checking the available Window Managers">
# <i>ls /usr/portage/x11-wm/</i>
</pre>

<p>
As you can imagine, it's quite difficult to go document every possibility. We
will explain some window managers and their specifics - if your favorite window
manager is missing, you're free to write up a small section. Just create a <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugreport</uri> for it and we'll make sure it gets
added to this document.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>How Do I Proceed?</title>
<body>

<p>
First of all, choose the Window Manager you want and simply <c>emerge</c> it.
For instance, to install the FluxBox Window Manager:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing FluxBox">
# <i>emerge fluxbox</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once this is finished, you need to make sure that your Window Manager is started
when you run <c>startx</c>. For instance:
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring your Session to run FluxBox">
$ <i>echo "exec fluxbox" &gt; ~/.xinitrc</i>
</pre>

<p>
When you run <c>startx</c>, you'll be greeted by your Window Manager.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>What about xdm/kdm/gdm?</title>
<body>

<p>
In case you want to log on graphically, you have to add <c>xdm</c> to your
default runlevel. Unlike other distributions, Gentoo has opted to not alter the
initlevel for this task:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding XDM to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add xdm default</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now edit <path>/etc/rc.conf</path> and select the logon manager of your choice.
If you have installed GNOME or KDE, then you can use <c>gdm</c> or <c>kdm</c>
respectively. Otherwise you'll need to stick with <c>xdm</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/rc.conf to select the logon manager">
DISPLAYMANAGER="xdm"
</pre>

<p>
Then take a look inside <path>/etc/X11/Sessions</path> and see if you find the
session name for your Window Manager. For instance, FluxBox has <c>fluxbox</c>
as its session name. Alter the XSESSION variable inside
<path>/etc/rc.conf</path> to have your logon manager start your Window Manager
by default:
</p>

<pre caption="Editing /etc/rc.conf to select the default window manager">
XSESSION="fluxbox"
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Fluxbox</title>
</section>
</sections>
