<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/draft/Attic/index.xml,v 1.4 2004/10/29 22:42:06 swift Exp $ -->

<guide link="index.xml">
<title>Gentoo Handbook</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The Gentoo Handbook is an effort to centralise documentation into a coherent
handbook. Information that cannot be inserted coherently is not taken into
account.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>0.21</version>
<date>October 30, 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>The Gentoo Handbook Effort</title>
<section>
<title>Available languages</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Handbook is available in the following languages:
</p>

<p>
<uri link="/doc/da/handbook">Danish</uri> |
<uri link="/doc/de/handbook">German</uri> |
<!-- <uri link="/doc/nl/handbook">Dutch</uri> | -->
<uri link="/doc/en/handbook">English</uri> |
<uri link="/doc/fr/handbook">French</uri> |
<uri link="/doc/id/handbook">Indonesian</uri> |
<uri link="/doc/it/handbook">Italian</uri> |
<uri link="/doc/es/handbook">Spanish</uri> | 
<uri link="/doc/zh_tw/handbook">Traditional Chinese</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Welcome to the Gentoo Handbook page. This page will give you some explanation
about the Gentoo Handbook and should answer most
of your questions regarding the handbook. We will talk about the ideas behind
the handbook, its current status, the future plans, how bug reports are handled,
etc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>View the Handbook</title>
<section>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Format</th>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>Links</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>HTML</ti>
  <ti>Latest version, one page per chapter, perfect for online viewing</ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="handbook-x86.xml">x86</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-alpha.xml">alpha</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-amd64.xml">amd64</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-hppa.xml">hppa</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-mips.xml">mips</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-ppc.xml">ppc</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-sparc.xml">sparc</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>HTML</ti>
  <ti>Latest version, All in one page</ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="handbook-x86.xml?full=1">x86</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-alpha.xml?full=1">alpha</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-amd64.xml?full=1">amd64</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-hppa.xml?full=1">hppa</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-mips.xml?full=1">mips</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-ppc.xml?full=1">ppc</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-sparc.xml?full=1">sparc</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>HTML</ti>
  <ti>Latest version, all in one page, printable version</ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="handbook-x86.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">x86</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-alpha.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">alpha</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-amd64.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">amd64</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-hppa.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">hppa</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-mips.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">mips</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-ppc.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">ppc</uri>,
    <uri link="handbook-sparc.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">sparc</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>HTML</ti>
  <ti>2004.2 version, one page per chapter, perfect for online viewing</ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-x86.xml">x86</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-alpha.xml">alpha</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-amd64.xml">amd64</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-hppa.xml">hppa</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-mips.xml">mips</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-ppc.xml">ppc</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-sparc.xml">sparc</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>HTML</ti>
  <ti>2004.2 version, All in one page</ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-x86.xml?full=1">x86</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-alpha.xml?full=1">alpha</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-amd64.xml?full=1">amd64</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-hppa.xml?full=1">hppa</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-mips.xml?full=1">mips</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-ppc.xml?full=1">ppc</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-sparc.xml?full=1">sparc</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>HTML</ti>
  <ti>2004.2 version, all in one page, printable version</ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-x86.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">x86</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-alpha.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">alpha</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-amd64.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">amd64</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-hppa.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">hppa</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-mips.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">mips</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-ppc.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">ppc</uri>,
    <uri link="2004.2/handbook-sparc.xml?style=printable&amp;full=1">sparc</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Information about the handbook</title>
<section>
<title>Goal</title>
<body>

<p>
The goal of the Gentoo Handbook is to create a coherent document that describes
every possible aspect of Gentoo Linux. It combines already existing guides in
one consistent book so that the same document is used for every possible
architecture, every install, every user. This not only makes it easier for us to
maintain, but also for the user to see that the differences are slim, and that
other architectures are not seen as a separate entities.
</p>

<p>
It also allows us to elaborate about difficult points and give more examples. We
aren't forced to write all documentation into a single displayed page anymore
making the documentation read more fluently.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Status</title>
<body>

<p>
At this time, the third part on <uri link="handbook-x86.xml?part=3">Working
with Portage</uri> is finished and officially available. This part contains
an in-depth coverage of Portage aspects.
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in the development of the Handbook, please use <mail
link="gentoo-doc@gentoo.org">the gentoo-doc mailinglist</mail> for all feedback,
or mail <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail> directly.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reporting bugs and enhancement requests</title>
<body>

<p>
If you find a bug in the handbook, please visit our <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Bugzilla</uri> and create a bug for
<e>Docs-user</e>, Component <e>Handbook</e>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter id="faq">
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<section>
<title>Can't you magically have the handbook dynamically created for each choice?</title>
<body>

<p>
Everything is possible, but we have opted not to do this for several reasons.
</p>

<p>
<b>Maintaining</b> the guide would be a lot more difficult. Not only will we
have to map bug reports to certain decisions (far from all bug reports would 
tell us what choices they made before) but it would be more difficult to write
the guide fluently: we would have to pay more attention to the line in the 
handbook, the consistencies, etc.
</p>

<p>
Although we currently only have an online version, <b>other formats</b> are
being developed, such as PDF versions. If we created PDFs for every
architecture and option, we would have to provide numerous PDFs of which only
a few sections differ. Talk about a waste of resources :).
</p>

<p>
The choices that the user makes are made <b>in different places</b>. This would
make it more difficult for the user to just print out the handbook -- we would
first have to inform the user of all possible options before they can begin,
probably scaring them away.
</p>

<p>
The part on "Installing Gentoo" <b>is not the only part</b> of the Gentoo
Handbook. It is the first, but all following parts are independent of the
choices the user made. Dynamically creating the handbook just for the
installation instructions would be overkill.
</p>

<p>
By not separating the instructions for each possible option, the user can view
the results of the other choices easily. This provides a <b>better view on the
installation instructions</b> for the user: even though they chose - for 
instance - stage3, they are easily informed about what stage2 or stage1 does. 
Not hiding these instructions is a good thing.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>You have a current version and one for Gentoo's latest release? What's
the deal?</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo is a moving target. When the official installation instructions are
considerably different from our latest installation instructions, we fork the
documentation into a release-specific one and a current one. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I disagree with ...</title>
<body>

<p>
Please <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">report</uri> your idea; disagreeing 
without providing us with constructive feedback doesn't help the situation.
Documentation is made for the community, so community feedback is well
appreciated.
</p>

<p>
However, you must know that most decisions made while developing documentation
are based on a consensus-model. It is <e>impossible</e> to write/structure
documentation in such a way that everybody is happy with it. You must be able to
accept a "No" with the reason that we believe the current implementation
benefits most people.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
