<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>elections</name>
<longname>Gentoo Elections</longname>

<description>
Gentoo Elections Project gathers all the information necessary to conduct
elections in Gentoo.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
The goal of Gentoo Elections project is to gather all the people participating
in the organization of elections in Gentoo together as well as providing the
project with procedures, documentation and scripts to run those elections.
</p>
</longdescription>

<dev role="Member">jmbsvicetto</dev>
<dev role="Member">neddyseagoon</dev>
<dev role="Member">rane</dev>
<dev role="Member">robbat2</dev>
<dev role="Member">dabbott</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Election archives</title>
<section>
<title>Elections Results</title>
<body>

<ul>
<li><uri link="trustees/">Trustees archives</uri> with the results of past Trustees elections.</li>
<li><uri link="council/">Council archives</uri> with the results of past Council elections.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Elections organization</title>
<section>
<title>Election Officials</title>
<body>

<p>
To ease the process of finding officials to run each election, we decided to
create a list of people volunteering to serve as officials in the upcoming
elections as well as their credentials and basic information about them.
Officials for each election may (but don't necessarily have to) be chosen from
among those people.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>nickname</th>
  <th>projects</th>
  <th>organized elections</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>rane</ti>
  <ti>Documentation and Developer Relations</ti>
  <ti>Trustees 2008, Council 2008, Trustees 2009, Council 2009</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>jmbsvicetto</ti>
  <ti>Forums, User Relations, Developer Relations, KDE, Release Engineering</ti>
  <ti>Trustees 2008, Council 2008, Council 2008b, Trustees 2009, Council 200906, Council 200912</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>neddyseagoon</ti>
  <ti>Forums, Foundation President, #gentoo-ops</ti>
  <ti>Council 200906</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Foundation Board of Trustees Elections</title>
<body>

<p>
Election rules, based on <uri link="/foundation/en/">Gentoo Foundation
Bylaws</uri>:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Gentoo Board of Trustees is composed of five elected members</li>
  <li>Elections happen every year starting in February</li>
  <li>
    There should be at least three election officials plus at least one person
    assigned from Gentoo Infrastructure project to handle their side of the
    election. Officials are allowed to vote in the election but they aren't
    allowed to run in it. They are selected by the current Board of Trustees.
  </li>
  <li>
    There's one month for nominations and one month for voting. In special cases
    current Board of Trustees may decide to shorten that period. Anyone can
    nominate.
  </li>
  <li>
    All Gentoo Foundation members may vote but only members of age above 18 are
    allowed to run (legal requirement). To run in the election, a person has to
    be nominated on the <c>gentoo-nfp</c> mailing list and personally accept
    that nomination on the same list.
  </li>
  <li>
    Members who are active Gentoo developers vote using <c>votify</c> script on
    <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Members who aren't active Gentoo developers should mail their GPG-signed
    ballot files to election officials who will verify authenticity of those and
    pass them to infra so they are taken into account while counting votes.
    Special care should be taken to ensure the ballot is signed by the gpg key
    in the Foundation records.
  </li>
  <li>
    After voting period is over, all election officials verify results provided
    by Infrastructure project member assigned to the election and then post them
    to the <c>gentoo-nfp</c> mailing list.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Council Elections</title>
<body>

<p>
Election rules (based on <uri link="/proj/en/glep/glep-0039.html">GLEP 39</uri>):
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Council elections generally happen once a year</li>
  <li>The council is composed of seven elected members</li>
  <li>Nominations are allowed for 15 days.</li>
  <li>Only Gentoo developers may be nominated</li>
  <li>Anyone can nominate (nominating yourself is OK)</li>
  <li>Nominees must accept their nomination before voting begins</li>
  <li>Voting is opened for 15 days.</li>
  <li>Only Gentoo developers that have joined the project before nomination starts may vote</li>
  <li>Condorcet method of voting is used</li>
</ul>

<p>
There should be at least three officials for this election plus one Gentoo
Infrastructure project member assigned to it to handle their side of the
process. Officials are allowed to vote in the election but aren't allowed to run
in it. Nominating and accepting nominations should happen on the
<c>gentoo-project</c> mailing list.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Condorcet method of voting</title>
<body>

<p>
For both Foundation and Council elections, <uri
link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Condorcet_method">Condorcet method of
voting</uri> is used to count votes.
</p>

<p>
To cast votes we use program names <c>votify</c> which is by default installed
on <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>.
</p>

<p>
Instruction on how to use <c>votify</c> to cast a vote:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>If you're eligible to vote in that election, log in to <c>dev.gentoo.org</c></li>
  <li>Type <c>votify --new election-name</c> to create a new ballot file</li>
  <li>
    Edit <path>.ballot-election-name</path> file in your home directory and rank
    the candidates
  </li>
  <li>
    Once you're finished, use <c>votify --verify election-name</c> command to
    verify validity of your ballot file
  </li>
  <li>
    If everything is okay, use <c>votify --submit election</c> your vote.
  </li>
  <li>
    If you run into problems, you can either work them out yourself using
    <c>votify --help</c> or contact election officials and ask them for help
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Verification and publication of results</title>
<body>

<p>
Verification and publication of results (ID sending, master ballot verification
by officials, so on). Also all scripts should be posted and explained here.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
