<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/scire/index.xml,v 1.12 2014/07/17 13:50:35 creffett Exp $ -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project disclaimer="obsolete">
<name>Scire</name>
<longname>Systems Configuration, Installation, and Replication Environment</longname>

<date>2008-08-01</date>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="codeman@gentoo.org">Preston Cody</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="blackace@gentoo.org">Blackace</mail>
</author>

<description>
	The Scire project aims to create a simple interface for installing, 
	configuring, updating, and managing mass numbers of client machines.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
	The Scire project aims to create a widely extensible common portal for
	administrative tasks for multiple Linux client machines.  Common tasks will
	include updating software, installing software, customizing configuration
	files, and running scripts.
	The goal of Scire is to make administration of massive networks of Linux 
	machines easy on administrators.  It will be extremely modular so as to
	allow users to create modules that extend its functionality.  This project
	is closely tied to the Gentoo Linux Installer project since it shares many
	developers.
</p>
<p>
	The Scire project is actively seeking developers for help on this project!
</p>
</longdescription>

<dev role="lead" description="Project co-lead">agaffney</dev>
<dev role="member">blackace</dev>

<extrachapter position="top">
	<title>News</title>
	<section>
		<title>2008-01-02: New Year, New Plan</title>
		<body>
		  <p>
		  	After doing very little for many months, a new attempt has been made to revive
			this project.  The original python XMLRPC client/server model is being replaced
			with a perl SSH-based cleint/server.  This resolves some of the drawbacks of the
			previous model that we didn't like, mainly that it was a pain and not fun to work
			with.  More info will be posted later when this project gets closer to an alpha
			release.
		  </p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>2007-05-21: Making some progress</title>
		<body>
		  <p>
		  	Now that the 2007.0 release has occurred, Andrew and I are finally able to
			devote some more time to SCIRE.  Some progress has been made in recent weeks.
			The permissions system is being fleshed out and new permissions are being thrown
			in all over the UI.  This will allow finely-grained control over which users
			can do which things in the UI.  Also, the database class has been modified to
			use ADOdb's library, allowing SCIRE to work with a multitude of databases
			instead of being locked into mysql.  This was always the plan, but coding for
			mysql was a nice way to get the project rolling early on.  Many thanks to blackace
			for the original mysql DB class.
		  </p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>2007-02-18: Project in temporary hibernation</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				Seeing how it has been ages since the last real update, I bet many
				are wondering what is going on with this project.  The answer is that
				both leads are also the only developers of the Gentoo Linux Installer.
				This is a long-existing project that has recently undergone a large
				overhaul to improve stability.  GLI also requires us to make release
				deadlines.  As such, we have been unable to work on SCIRE for the last
				few months because of a rush to get a new branch of the installer
				stable.
		  </p>
			<p>
				Rest assured that this project is not "dead" and that we will get
				back to work on it as soon as possible.  Andrew Gaffney has made
				great progress on Quickstart, an automated gentoo installer written
				to run in a netboot image.  This will be used by SCIRE instead
				of the existing plan of using the netfe/be of GLI.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>2006-12-10: Jobs being run!</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				Thought I'd over a status report of the progress over the past couple weeks.
				I have been picking away slowly but surely at the script and job pages.
				I have gotten the script library functional enough to add scripts.
				I have gotten the job addition page functional enough to use those
				scripts and create simple non-recurring jobs.
			</p>
			<p>
				I set up a vmware machine and launched the scire server and then
				client on that vmware machine, pointing the server's DB at my main
				desktop.
				The client registered itself and put itself as Pending.
				I used the UI to accept the client and assign permissions to it and
				then create a job for it.
				I then ran  the scire client program again and the jobs were retrieved
				and ran successfully, reporting their results into the job_history
				table.
			</p>
			<p>
				Things are still quite rough and many aspects are not implemented or
				tested yet on either the UI or the backend.  Also the permissions
				structure is not yet being enforced in the UI (makes it easier to
				develop stuff).  Overall, however, I am happy with the recent
				progress.  Hopefully we can get most of the core operational by the
				new year.
				Cheers,
				-Codeman
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>2006-11-13: Scire development status</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				It has been quite some time since there was any progress made on
				Scire.  This is due to many factors, but mainly because the developers
				working on it are busy with other projects or real life work.
				We lost our SoC dev mdisney to school, but he will hopefully resurface
				soon.  Andrew is working with me on a much-needed overhaul of GLI.  He
				is also the x86 release lead, so we will lose some of his upcoming
				time to that.
				All that being said, the project is not dead!!  It just isn't coming
				along as quickly as we had hoped.
			</p>
			<p>
				Areas currently needing work are job creation/management/reporting and
				the scrpt library.  Parts of these components are still really in the
				design phase, so any/all help is appreciated.
				-Codeman
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>2006-10-16: Announcing Quickstart!</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				Today Andrew Gaffney (agaffney) has announced to the world a new
				project called Quickstart.  This is an entire rewrite of the Gentoo
				Linux Installer in POSIX-compliant sh.  This allows Quickstart to
				fit in netboot images and run in busybox.  The goal was to create 
				something more like what the installer was *supposed* to be. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Quickstart is meant to be closer to	Kickstart or Jumpstart (do you 
				see a pattern with the name? :P) than GLI or other single user 
				installers.  Quickstart uses an installation profile (which is
				documented 
				<uri link="http://agaffney.org/repos/quickstart/trunk/doc/config.txt">here</uri>.
				It has been designed to be extremely flexible in that every step of
				the installation has pre/post hooks and can even be overwritten
				entirely in the profile!
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>2006-07-05: A Long-overdue update</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				The Scire project is moving along quite nicely despite some setbacks
				from disagreements on the implementation of various componenets of
				the system.  The UI is progressing slowly but surely, and the backend
				is able to connect and authenticate from client to server.  There is
				still TONS left to do but at least it's a start.
			</p>
			<p>
				We have been blessed this summer with the addition of Matt Disney, a
				Google Summer of Code student, who will be working on the project and
				hopefully getting the backend operational by the end of the summer.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
  <section>
    <title>2006-04-30: Project page created</title>
    <body>
      <p>
				The Scire project has been in the design phase for the last few months
				so it's time we made our project page.
        A working requirements document is in progress and viewable 
				<uri link="requirements.xml">here</uri>.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Other resources or documentation in progress</title>
<section>
<body>
	<p>These links are likely very old.  See the wiki (top link) for what is likely to be the more current version</p>
<ul>
	<li><uri link="http://agaffney.org/mediawiki/index.php">Scire Project Wiki</uri></li>	
  <li><uri link="requirements.xml">Initial design specifications.</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~codeman/GIMLI/scire.dia">Pretty (old) diagram of interconnections.</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="scire.png">Same as above in PNG form.</uri></li>
	<li><uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~codeman/GIMLI/user_interface.dia">Old Diagram showing parts of user interface.</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>How to find us</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
  In the usual spirt of Gentoo, our development is very open and we invite you
  to watch/idle/lurk or even participate. You can join our mailing list by
  sending an email to gentoo-scire-subscribe@gentoo.org, or find us on
  irc.freenode.net at #gentoo-scire.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Meeting logs and summaries</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
  Summaries of each meeting called will be available here, along with raw logs
  for public viewing.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>13 Mar 2006</th>
    <ti><uri link="/proj/en/scire/meetings/meeting_20060318.txt">Log</uri></ti>
  </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
