<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>php</name>
<longname>Gentoo PHP Herd</longname>
<date>2005-06-04</date>

<description>
The Gentoo PHP Herd is responsible for delivering high-quality support for
the PHP programming language for Gentoo Linux.
</description>

<longdescription>

<p><b>What we do, and who we are</b></p>
<p> The Gentoo PHP team look after the packages for the PHP programming language.  PHP is by far the most important and popular programming language for web-based applications, and is the 'P' in the LAMP stack.</p>
<p>We're also onhand to provide information and support on PHP to other
Gentoo developers.</p>
</longdescription>

<goals>
Our goal is to ensure that Gentoo provides the best environment possible
for developing and running software written in PHP.
</goals>

<!-- Developer Roles -->
<dev role="Lead" description="Core PHP packages">CHTEKK</dev>
<dev role="Lead" description="PEAR">Sebastian</dev>
<dev role="Member">jakub</dev>
<dev role="Member">Stuart</dev>
<dev role="Member">tomk</dev>
<dev role="Member">voxus</dev>

<!-- Project Specific Pages/Documentation -->
<resource link="http://svn.gnqs.org/projects/gentoo-php-overlay/">The Gentoo PHP Overlay &amp; Wiki</resource>
<resource link="php-upgrading.xml">Upgrading from dev-php/php to dev-lang/php</resource>
<resource link="php4-php5-configuration.xml">Configure Apache To Work With PHP4 and PHP5</resource>

<!-- Subprojects -->
<!--subproject ref="/proj/en/gdp/international.xml"/-->

<!-- Status updates -->
<extrachapter>
<title>Status Updates</title>
<section>
<title>What are Status Updates?</title>
<body>
<p>We provide regular status updates covering what the PHP team has
accomplished since the previous status update.  It is written by one of
the team leaders and contains a quick overview of recent progress.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Listing</title>
<body>
<p>The following status updates are available:</p>
<p>The PHP team has not published any status updates at this time.</p>
<!--
<ul>
<li><uri link="status/status_2006Q1.xml>Jan-March, 2006</uri></li>
</ul>
-->
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<!-- Chapter regarding mailing list & participation -->
<extrachapter>
<title>Participating</title>
<section>
<title>#gentoo-php on irc.freenode.net</title>
<body>
<p>The best way to reach us is on IRC in the <uri link="irc://freenode/gentoo-php">#gentoo-php</uri> channel on irc.freenode.net.  Please feel free to stop by to talk about PHP on Gentoo.  We welcome any suggestions for improvement.</p>
<p>We hold our monthly meetings in the <uri link="irc://freenode/gentoo-php">#gentoo-php</uri> channel too.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Participating</title>
<body>
<p>The best way to get involved with what we do is to hang out in #gentoo-php.  There are always things to be done (and exciting new ideas to turn into reality), and we're always looking for new ways to make Gentoo the first choice for developers programming in PHP, and for system administrators running webservers with PHP.</p>
<p>Once we get to know you, we'll give you commit access to our overlay and wiki.  We use this as our master repository for the PHP packages and docs.  From there, we'll then look to recruit you as a full-blow Gentoo developer.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
