<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/pr/gmn/gmn-howto.xml,v 1.7 2013/10/13 09:49:08 hwoarang Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Monthly Newsletter Howto</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="hwoarang"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide details the process for creating the Gentoo Monthly Newsletter.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>4</version>
<date>2013-10-13</date>

<chapter>
<title>Overview</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
So, you want to be a GMN editor, eh? This guide will show you how to write a
Gentoo Monthly Newsletter from start to finish. It's more or less structured
like the newsletter itself.
</p>

<p>
It's very important to familiarize yourself with <uri
link="/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">GuideXML</uri>, the language the GMN's written in.
Pay careful attention to coding style; you want the code to be nice and easy to
read, both for yourself, and for your teammates. So take the time to read <uri
link="/news/en/gmn/">past issues</uri>, and especially view the source code! You
can view the source online by appending <path>?passthru=1</path> to the
<path>.xml</path> URL of any newsletter. Or just open up a copy from your local
CVS checkout in your editor of choice.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Files</title>
<body>

<p>
Putting together a newsletter requires several scripts and files. These can be
found in our <uri
link="http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo/src/gwn/">code
repository</uri>. Be sure to save the following files to your GMN working
directory:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><c>gmn_bugzie.py</c></li>
  <li><c>gmn_bugzie_aggregate.py</c></li>
  <li><c>get_portage_stats.py</c></li>
  <li><c>print-dev-stats.py</c></li>
  <li><c>gmn2text.xsl</c></li>
  <li><c>pygooglechart.py</c></li>
  <li><c>gwn_adds_removes.py</c></li>
</ul>

<p>
There's also a <uri link="skel-newsletter.xml">skeleton newsletter</uri>
available. This template will let you get a quick start on each monthly
newsletter. Adjust the dates, times, locations, links, and numbers for each new
edition. It's pretty straightforward.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Articles</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Feature articles are arguably the heart of the newsletter. However, articles
don't usually just fall from the sky: you may have to actively scour the
internet looking for articles, news releases, blogs, etc. pertaining to Gentoo.
However, rather than do all this work yourself, you can make better use of your
time by actively soliciting help from the user community and your fellow
developers. Get <e>them</e> to send in articles and links of interest. The more
they write up ahead of time, the better, as you'll need to do less editing. When
someone sends interesting material your way, be sure to give them an author or
contributor credit in the GMN. Participation should be fun <e>and</e> rewarding.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo news</title>
<body>

<p>
Lead off the GMN (after the usual introduction) with general distribution news.
The GMN is the first place people look for things like Gentoo release
announcements, <uri link="/proj/en/council">Council</uri> and <uri
link="/foundation/en/">Trustees</uri> meetings, and other important news.
Oftentimes critical systemwide changes or security notes may be found here, such
as the mask &amp; removal of PHP4, stabilization of the latest Portage version,
baselayout changes, and similar. Or mention projects that Gentoo is
participating in, such as Google Summer of Code; see the <uri
link="/news/en/gmn/20080424-newsletter.xml">April 2008</uri> newsletter for a
nice example.
</p>

<p>
The Council and Trustees post meeting summaries, minutes, and agenda both to the
mailing lists and to their individual project pages. Use the summaries (with
links to the full documents) here; this way you don't waste time duplicating
their efforts. Occasionally there will be an important project meeting for
security, desktop, Portage, etc.  Make sure to include such meeting notes.
Pester the project secretaries/leads for minutes and summaries if you have to.
Remember, you don't have much time to play investigative journalist. Try to get
the other projects to cooperate with you. Publicity should good for them, after
all.
</p>

<p>
Next: the mini-calendar with the next month or three's events. Upcoming events
might include monthly <uri link="/proj/en/bugday/">bugdays</uri>, Gentoo IRC
meetings, and Linux/FOSS trade shows.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo international</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo International chapter reports the
happenings at events around the world in which Gentoo and its developers have a
presence. Pictures are always good!
</p>

<p>
In the past, the GMN has extensively covered events such as FOSDEM, SCALE,
FliSol, LinuxTag, and various development summits in which Gentoo has a
presence.
</p>

<p>
There won't always be a Gentoo International chapter to include, as events
happen just a few times a year. But when they do, make sure to cover them! Talk
to the developers and teams who went; check their blogs, etc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Community news</title>
<body>

<p>
The community news chapter can consist of:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Interviews with individuals, companies, and other folks who use Gentoo for
    work, play, school, etc. This is one of the best ways to highlighting the
    things Gentoo is capable of, and how it's being used. Google Summer of Code
    interviews are another favorite for this chapter.
  </li>
  <li>
    Articles focusing on a particular bit of community-produced Gentoo-related
    software, like <uri link="http://www.haskell.org/himerge/">Himerge</uri>.
    Interest pieces on things that affect the community of developers and users
    alike, such as <uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org">Sunrise</uri> or
    Bugzilla, may be found here.  However, the GMN doesn't really cover things
    like individual non-Gentoo-specific applications, or applications that are
    not in the tree. "Community news" shouldn't be a general advertising space.
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org">Planet Gentoo</uri>, an aggregator of
    Gentoo developer blogs. Pick the best of the Gentoo-related posts from the
    past month and include one or two sentence summaries.
  </li>
  <li>
    "Gentoo in the News" is a good place to share sightings of Gentoo. Reviews,
    enterprise Gentoo usage, magazine appearances, new distributions based on
    Gentoo, and other Gentoo links &amp; references go here. The more the
    merrier, even if they're just short tidbits.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Tips and tricks</title>
<body>

<p>
This chapter contains useful information for administering your system, keeping
things up-to-date, tweaking applications, monitoring boxes, and so on. If you're
lucky, you can get users and other developers to email some collected tips or
"best practices" each month. You may want to cull the forums for useful
material.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Statistics collection</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The first half of the newsletter features articles, and those vary quite a bit
month-to-month. The second half contains general statistics on Bugzilla,
the Portage tree, developer changes, and so on. It's very formulaic,
straightforward, but also can be the most time consuming part of the newsletter
to write. This is where you'll use all the scripts we have to round out the GMN.
</p>

<p>
The statistical chapters are assembled as follows:
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bugzilla statistics</title>
<body>

<p>
To generate the nice table of <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Bugzilla</uri>
statistics (new bugs, closed bugs, distribution, etc.), do the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Generating Bugzilla statistics">
$ <i>touch breport</i>
$ <i>python gmn_bugzie.py > breport</i>
$ <i>python gmn_bugzie_aggregate.py > gmn-bugzilla.txt</i> <comment>(For safekeeping)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
The first script, <c>gmn_bugzie.py</c>, generates a statistics file called
<path>breport</path> after querying Bugzilla.
</p>

<p>
The second script, <c>gmn_bugzie_aggregate.py</c>, creates and fills in the
statistics table that you copy into the GMN. It also generates three graphs:
<path>activity.png</path>, <path>opened.png</path>, and <path>closed.png</path>.
These three files come courtesy <uri
link="http://code.google.com/apis/chart/">Google Chart</uri> (via
<c>pygooglechart.py</c>). Save the graphs to your working directory; you'll be
adding them to CVS later on.
</p>

<p>
Once you've got your statistics output saved to <path>gmn-bugzilla.txt</path>
(or whatever you named it), you can paste it into the appropriate GMN section.
Make sure to properly link in the generated graphs. Take a look at the code for
the <uri link="/news/en/gmn">past issues</uri> to see how it goes.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Portage statistics</title>
<body>

<p>
To create the Portage statistics (number of packages by keyword, distribution,
etc.), you'll need an unmodified Portage installation. This means you shouldn't
be using PORTDIR_OVERLAY or anything else that affects the number of categories
and packages reported. Also, you'll have to use the downloaded metadata cache
obtained from syncing, so you can't set various fun things like
<c>portdbapi.auxdbmodule = cache.metadata_overlay.database</c> in
<path>/etc/portage/modules</path>.
</p>

<p>
First, you'll need to <c>emerge portage-utils</c>, and run one of its utilities
as shown.
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining Portage statistics">
$ <i>./get_portage_stats.py</i>
</pre>

<p>
This script creates the table suitable for direct inclusion in the GMN post
and a URL to a Google chart. Download the chart and save it to
your working directory as <path>keywords.png</path>. You'll be committing this file
with the rest of the charts soon. Again, make sure to add the proper link to
this file within the GMN.
</p>

<p>
The package adds/removes are generated by saving the logs emailed by
infrastructure, and running <c>gwn_adds_removes.py</c> on them:
</p>

<pre caption="Generating package adds/removes">
$ <i>python gwn_adds_removes.py add-removals.1220227200.log > foo.txt</i>
</pre>

<p>
In this example, the output of the command is saved to a file, rather than
printed straight to the terminal. <c>gwn_adds_removes.py</c> will create the
GuideXML; all you have to do is paste it into the newsletter.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Developer statistics</title>
<body>

<p>
You can get the developer statistics (total recruited, away, etc.) by first
downloading the devaway XML file, and then by hand-editing the
<c>print-dev-stats.py</c> script to point at your own CVS checkout directory.
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining developer statistics">
$ <i>python print-dev-stats.py</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once you've done this, paste the numbers into the developers summary section
(number recruited, active, and away).
</p>

<p>
For developer changes (joining/leaving projects or teams), run a diff of the
changes to <path>herds.xml</path> since the last issue. This information is
available <uri
link="http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/metastructure/herds/herds.xml">in
CVS</uri>.
</p>

<p>
You should also keep a close eye on new developer emails sent to the
gentoo-dev-announce and/or gentoo-dev mailing lists. You should receive
automated retirement notices generated by Infra sent directly to the GMN email
alias.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Finishing up</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As a courtesy to your fellow Gentoo developers, solicit feedback on the latest
issue by writing to the gentoo-core mailing list at least one day in advance of
publication. Be sure to provide them with a working URL to the issue.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Final touches</title>
<body>

<p>
Once you've applied the final fixes from gentoo-core, you'll need to add a few
more bits to the issue <e>immediately</e> before committing. Time is important
here, as the webnodes take awhile to update.
</p>

<p>
Finally, make sure the dates inside the GMN issue are set to the correct date of
publication. You'll also need to adjust the submission deadline date for the
next issue; this information is found at the very end of the newsletter. You
should also verify that the volume and issue numbers are correct; these are
scattered through the first part of the GMN.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Committing</title>
<body>

<p>
Write up the front page announcement for www.gentoo.org and add
it to <path>gentoo/xml/htdocs/news/</path>. See the <uri
link="/news/20080831-gmn.xml">August 2008 news item</uri> for how it's done. Add
it to CVS (<c>cvs add</c>).
</p>

<p>
Now that the online edition of the GMN is published, you can send out the
plain-text email version. Log in to dev.gentoo.org and upload the text version
of the GMN so you can email it. Once logged in, run:
</p>

<p>
There . . . the front page and forum announcements are in place, the newsletter
is online, the email edition is sent . . . now you can take a break! At least
until the emails for the next issue arrive. And it all starts over again . . .
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="skel-newsletter.xml">GMN skeleton newsletter</uri>: use this
    template for each monthly issue. You'll find that pretty much all possible
    sections have been added; if you don't have a certain section, just delete
    it. Be sure to fill in appropriate dates, issue numbers, and links where
    marked.
  </li>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/pr/gmn/">GMN project page</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="/news/en/gmn">Index of GMN issues</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">GuideXML Guide</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri>: the Gentoo Chat
    subforum contains discussion and feedback threads for the GMN; you may want
    to search the archives.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
