<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/project.dtd">
<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:ARM">
  <name>Gentoo ARM</name>

  <longname>Gentoo Linux ARM Development</longname>

  <description>
    The ARM Development Project is devoted to keeping Gentoo in good shape
    on the ARM architecture.
  </description>

  <longdescription>

    <p>The Gentoo/ARM Project works to keep Gentoo the most up to date and
    fastest ARM distribution available. We are responsible for the
    maintainance of all ARM specific meta-data and the testing of all other
    non ARM specific meta-data on the ARM architecture to ensure
    portability. Portability implies reuseable meta-data.</p>

    <p>Bugs are tracked and resolved from the <uri
    link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo bug tracker</uri> and correspondence is
    maintained on the various ARM related mailinglists.  (gentoo-arm and those belonging to the sub-projects).</p>

  </longdescription>

  <goals>

    <p>The goal of the Gentoo ARM development project is to guarantee that
    the ARM packages build using Gentoo meta-data are up to date.  By
    continuously enhancing the meta-data, we provide the ARM user with the
    Gentoo community feeling, performance, freedom and up to dateness.  The
    meta-distribution notion allows for a user to to be as bleeding edge as
    he/she wants:</p>

    <p>Gentoo is unique because of its interpretation of the Meta-Distribution
    notion: all architectures share the same 'generic' meta-data (information
    about how to build packages - how to build a distribution). The ARM
    developers are responsible for building and testing packages using this
    meta-data.  The meta-data gets marked 'tested' or 'stable' afterwards,
    depending on the building and testing expierience. Our users can use (but
    don't have to use) this information to build a system that suits their
    needs.</p>

  </goals>

  <dev role="Lead" description="Gentoo/ARM">steev</dev>
  <dev role="Lead" description="Gentoo/ARM">zerochaos</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">vapier</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">armin76</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">maekke</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">xmw</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">dilfridge</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">blueness</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">pinkbyte</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">dlan</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">zlogene</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Security bugs primarily">ago</dev>
  <dev role="Member" description="Gentoo/ARM">mrueg</dev>

  <extrachapter position="bottom">
    <title>How to Participate</title>
    <section>
      <body>

        <p>Can you make computers do amazing things? Are you excited about
        exploring areas of computing never explored before? We are continuously
        looking for volunteers willing to spend some of their free time on this
        project. In return for your work, you get the respect of the ARM
        community.</p>

        <p>If you are interested in helping, but don't have a niche that you are
        interested in filling, you can always look through <uri
        link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>. There are many many
        bugs waiting to be found and fixed and many enhancements looking to find
        someone to code them. Figure out a fix, implement it, test it, and then
        keep trying to make the patch smaller. Post it for review on <uri
        link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>, and keep working on
        it. If it seems ignored, make a new comment in the bug and/or mention it
        in #gentoo-ARM.</p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

<herd name="arm"/>

</project>
