<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/foundation/en/legal/copyrightpolicy.xml,v 1.2 2013/04/24 13:45:18 dabbott Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="draft">
<title>Gentoo Copyright Policy</title>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="rich0"/>
</author>

<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="dabbott"/>
</author>


<abstract>
Gentoo Copyright Policy
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1</version>
<date>2013-04-23</date>

<chapter>
<title>Purpose / Scope</title>
<section>
<body>

 <warn>
   THIS IS A DRAFT POLICY POSTED ONLY FOR COLLABORATION/REVIEW/COMMENT/ETC. THIS
   POLICY DRAFT HAS NO EFFECT.
 </warn>

<p>
This policy documents how Gentoo contributors comply and document copyright for
any contributions made to Gentoo.  Anyone committing documentation or sources to
any repository hosted on Gentoo infrastructure must comply with this policy.
OPEN QUESTION - DOES THIS APPLY TO DOCS?
</p>

<p>
Questions regarding this policy should be directed to the trustees or the
-project list.  Any concerns over possible copyright violations should be
directed to the Trustees if they cannot be worked out to anyone's satisfaction
with the appropriate maintainer.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Licensing of Gentoo Projects</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
All Gentoo projects must abide by the <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/contract.xml">Gentoo Social
  Contract</uri>, being published under an open source license.  The license for
each project is documented below.
</p>
 
 <table>
   <tr><th>Project</th><th>License</th></tr>
   <tr><ti>Portage</ti><ti>TODO</ti></tr>
   <tr><ti>Portage Tree</ti><ti>TODO</ti></tr>
   <tr><ti>Docs</ti><ti>TODO</ti></tr>
   <tr><ti>eudev</ti><ti>TODO</ti></tr>
 
 
 </table>
 
 <p>
 Any project hosted on Gentoo infrastructure not listed above must be licensed GPL-2+.
 </p>
 
 <p>
 If you wish to add a new Gentoo project to this page, contact the trustees.
 </p>
 
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Certificate of Origin</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
All commits to Gentoo-hosted repositories must be accompanied by a certificate
of origin.  The purpose of the certificate is to declare that the content of the
commit may be used in accordance with the project license.
</p>

<p>
For commits made using CVS, the commiter will certify agreement to the DCO by
adding "Signed-off-by: Name/email" to the commit message as a separate line.
Repoman will add this automatically if DCO_SIGNED_OFF_BY is set to Name/email in make.conf.
</p>

<p>
The following is the current Gentoo DCO 1.0:
</p>

<note>TODO - OFFSET THIS SOMEHOW</note>

<pre caption="Gentoo DCO 1.0">
        By making a contribution to this project, I certify that:

        The contribution was created in whole or in part by me and I have the
        right to submit it under the open source license indicated in the file;
        or

        The contribution is based upon previous work that, to the best of my
        knowledge, is covered under an appropriate open source license and I
        have the right under that license to submit that work with
        modifications, whether created in whole or in part by me, under the same
        open source license (unless I am permitted to submit under a different
        license), as indicated in the file; or

        The contribution was provided directly to me by some other person who
        certified (a), (b) or (c) and I have not modified it.

        I understand and agree that this project and the contribution are public
        and that a record of the contribution (including all personal
        information I submit with it, including my sign-off) is maintained
        indefinitely and may be redistributed consistent with this project or
        the open source license(s) involved.
</pre>

<note>The DCO is based on the <uri
    link="http://git.kernel.org/cgit/linux/kernel/git/torvalds/linux.git/tree/Documentation/SubmittingPatches">
    Linux Kernel DCO</uri>.</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Copyright Attribution</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
All files hosted by Gentoo must contain an appropriate copyright notice, as
defined by this policy.
</p>

<p>
A proper copyright notice appears near the top of the file, and reads,
"Copyright YEAR LARGEST-CONTRIBUTOR <e>and others (see below)</e>."  The largest
contributor is whatever entity owns copyright to some portion of the largest
number of lines in the file.  The "and others (see below)" text may be ommitted
if the largest contributor holds copyright to the entire file.
</p>

<p>
If there are other copyright holders, then somewhere in the file the full list
of copyright holders must be listed, or a reference to a list in another file
stored in a Gentoo repository.
</p>

<p>
No file may be committed to a Gentoo repository unless at least 60% of the lines
in the file are accounted for in the list of copyright holders.  Any content
already in a Gentoo repository as of DATE shall count towards the 60% rule even
if not attributed.  Note that 60% is the minimum required for compliance with
this policy - all contributors are strongly encouraged to strive for 100%
attribution.
</p>

<p>
It is the responsibility of anyone making a commit to update the contributor
list for any additions made to the repository.  Committers are not required to
double-check content already in the repository.
</p>

<p>
Anyone finding a file out of compliance should log a bug against the associated
project/package providing as much information as possible.  Files that are not
brought into compliance within 60 days or upon a request for removal by a
aggrieved copyright holder will be removed. Any concerns not addressed by a
maintainer can be appealed to the Trustees.
</p>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Copyright Assignment</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
All are welcome and encouraged (but NOT required) to assign copyright for their
contributions to the Gentoo Foundation. Doing so makes compliance with this
policy easier (fewer copyright holders to list), and allows the Foundation to
enforce copyrights and re-license content if appropriate (this will only be done
in accordance with the social contract and the FLA).
</p>

<p>
Copyright is assigned to the Foundation by electronically signing the <uri
  link="fla.pdf">Gentoo Fiduciary License Agreement (FLA)</uri>.  The agreement
may be signed BY <e>TODO...</e>  If the scope of the signed agreeement included
future contributions, the contributor may document their wish to stop assigning
copyright by <e>TODO...</e>
</p>

<p>
A list of those who have signed this agreement and the scope of their
assignments may be found at LINK.  This list may be useful when attributing
copyright.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
