<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd"> 
<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Ada">
	<name>Ada</name>
	<longname>Gentoo Resources for Ada</longname>

	<date>28 Sep 2007</date>

	<author title="Developer">
		<mail link="george@gentoo.org">George Shapovalov</mail>
	</author>


	<description>
		Gentoo Specific Support for Programming in Ada.
	</description>

	<longdescription>
		<p>
			This project provides support for Ada compilers and libraries in portage. 
			At present two gnat compilers are provided, gnat-gcc by FSF and gnat-gpl by 
			AdaCore. Both are SLOTted and made to coexist, with the selection of the active
			compiler performed via the eselect gnat module. Various Ada libraries and related 
			packages are available under dev-ada. The libs support the multi-compiler 
			situation by being built for every gnat profile that is installed. Selection 
			of the active lib variant is done simultaneously with the selection of the 
			active compiler via the same eselect gnat command. More details on the 
			setup can be found in the 
			resource section below and the lengthy discussion that lead to this organization in 
			<uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=111340">bug #111340</uri>.
			The implementation of the structure is nearing completion. Its progress can be
			tracked via:
			<uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=137268">bug #137268</uri>. 
			"Old-style" dev-lang/gnat and dev-ada/asis packages have been masked and recently removed. 
		</p>
	</longdescription>

	
<!--  <herd name="ada" />  -->

<dev role="lead">george</dev>

<resource link="dev_reference.xml">
	Developer reference: internal structure and organization of Ada packages.
</resource>

<resource link="notes.xml">
	Misc notes: something that should be recorded but does not fit in primary guides.
</resource>

</project>
