<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/release/2005.1/ppc64-release-notes.xml,v 1.2 2012/10/28 15:21:15 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>ppc64 Release Notes for Gentoo Linux 2005.1</title>

<author title="Author">
 <mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>

<author title="PPC64 Release Co-Coordinator">
  <mail link="dostrow@gentoo.org">Daniel Ostrow</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo 2005.1 Release Notes.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2005-08-03</date>

<chapter>
  <title>The Gentoo Linux Project</title>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <body>
      <p>Gentoo Linux is a community driven project committed to producing high
        quality opensource software. These release notes for Gentoo Linux 2005.1
        summarize important package updates, security updates, and many other
        changes that have happened since Gentoo Linux 2005.0</p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Table of Contents</title>
    <body>
    <ul>
      <li>1. Overview</li>
      <li>2. Important Changes</li>
      <li>  2.1 Security Updates</li>
      <li>  2.2 Profile Update</li>
      <li>  2.3 Errata</li>
      <li>  2.4 Critical Package Updates</li>
      <li>  2.5 Portage Updates</li>
      <li>  2.6 Userland Updates</li>
      <li>  2.7 Documentation Updates</li>
      <li>3. Upgrading from previous versions of Gentoo Linux</li>
    </ul>

    </body>
  </section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Important Changes for 2005.1</title>
  <section>
    <title>Security Updates</title>
    <body>
      <p>Gentoo Linux 2005.1 contains security updates to address GLSAs (Gentoo
        Linux Security Advisories) numbered 200503-18 to 200507-27.  </p>

      <p>Individual GLSAs can be referenced by going to
        <c>http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-$x.xml</c>, and
        substituting <c>$x</c> with the desired GLSA number. </p>

      <p>For more information, please consult the the <uri
          link="http://security.gentoo.org/">Gentoo Linux Security Project home
          page</uri>.</p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Profile Update</title>
    <body>
      <p>With Gentoo Linux 2005.1 the PowerPC teams completed the first steps 
        to merge the PowerPC 32-bit and PowerPC 64-bit development teams.  
	This merge results in the use of a common profile. The ppc64 profiles 
	can be found in
        <path>/usr/portage/profiles/default-linux/ppc/2005.1/ppc64</path>. You
	must choose a bit level for your userland. At the moment 32-bit and
	64-bit are supported, a multilib userland will be supported in the 
	near future. For each bit level we also support further sub-profiles 
	for <path>970</path> (the JS20), <path>970/pmac</path> (the G5),
        <path>power3</path>, <path>power4</path> and <path>power5</path>.  
	Please update your profile as described in <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml" />.</p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Errata</title>
    <body>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Errata</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>32-bit userland and external kerenl modules.</ti>
          <ti>Due to complications that arose from creating a 32-bit userland
	    external kernel modules will not yet compile and function. The
	    team is working on rectifying this issue.</ti>
        </tr>
      </table>

    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Critical Package Updates</title>
    <body>
      <p>Important package-versions in this release:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>gcc-3.4.4</li>
        <li>glibc-2.3.4.20041102-r1</li>
        <li>gentoo-sources-2.6.12-r6</li>
        <li>vanilla-sources-2.6.12.2</li>
        <li>portage-2.0.51.22-r2</li>
        <li>xorg-x11-6.8.2-r2</li>
        <li>kde-meta-3.4.1</li>
        <li>xfce4-4.2.2</li>
      </ul>

      <p>There are several kernels on the LiveCD:</p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Kernel filename</th>
          <th>Capabilites</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>G5</ti>
          <ti>Supports Apple Powermac G5 and iMac G5 machines.</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>xserv</ti>
          <ti>Supports Apple xServ G5 machines.</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>pseries</ti>
          <ti>Supports IBM pSeries hardware.</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>ibm-power5</ti>
          <ti>Supports IBM POWER5 based hardware.
	    This includes the IBM i5.</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>js20</ti>
          <ti>Supports IBM JS20 Blades.</ti>
        </tr>
      </table>

      <p>For information about how to change your profile please read <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml" />.</p>

      <warn>Cascading profiles will only work with Portage >=2.0.51. Make sure
        to first upgrade to an appropriate version of Portage and <b>then</b>
        upgrade your profile!</warn>


    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Portage Updates</title>
    <body>
      <p>The Portage version included in this release is 2.0.51.22-r2 and the <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/portage/ChangeLog?root=gentoo-src">ChangeLog</uri>
        can be found via our online CVS repository.</p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Userland Updates</title>
    <body>
      <ul>
        <li>Catalyst, the Gentoo Release Metatool, is stable in Portage as
          version 1.1.10.10. To use Catalyst, simply <c>emerge catalyst</c>.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Documentation Updates</title>
    <body>
      <p>Much consideration and time has been spent on the <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-ppc64.xml">Gentoo
          Installation Handbook</uri> in order to get it more in sync with
        Gentoo 2005.1. Please note that it is a constant work in progress, and
        if any bugs are encountered, please refer them to the Gentoo Linux
        bugtracking system at <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" />.  </p>
    </body>
  </section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Upgrading and Installation of Gentoo Linux 2005.1</title>
  <section>
    <title>Installing Gentoo Linux 2005.1</title>
    <body>
      <p>The entire Gentoo Linux installation process is documented in the <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo
          Handbook</uri>.</p>

      <p>Each architecture offers three LiveCDs. The first one being a universal
        bootable LiveCD which can be used to install with or without an Internet
        connection.  The second LiveCD is a non-bootable subarch-optimized
        Gentoo Reference Platform (GRP) LiveCD which contains precompiled
        binaries of popular programs such as X.org-x11 and KDE. The third LiveCD 
	is a bootable minimal LiveCD that is smaller in size and includes only 
	the basics needed to simply boot a machine.</p>

      <p>At a minimum, the universal or minimal LiveCD is required to boot the
        machine and install Gentoo.  The universal LiveCD requires an Internet
        connection to install from a stage1 installation tarball, but does not
        require an Internet connection to install from a stage3 installation
        tarball. The minimal LiveCD requires an Internet connection to install
        Gentoo Linux.</p>

      <p>There is one kernel available on both bootable cds. It will run on
        both, uniprocessor and multiprocessor systems.  The kernel is based on
        linux-2.6.12 (vanilla-sources-2.6.12.2).</p>

      <p>The LiveCDs are located on the mirrors as follows: </p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>LiveCD Description</th>
          <th>Location on Mirrors</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>Universal bootable LiveCD</ti>
          <ti>/releases/ppc/2005.1/ppc64/installcd/install-ppc64-universal-2005.1.iso</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>Minimal bootable LiveCD</ti>
          <ti>/releases/ppc/2005.1/ppc64/installcd/install-ppc64-minimal-2005.1.iso</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>Non-bootable GRP-/Packages CD</ti>
          <ti>/releases/ppc/2005.1/ppc64/packagecd/packages-ppc64-64ul-2005.1.iso</ti>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Upgrading to Gentoo Linux 2005.1</title>
    <body>
      <p> If you already have a working installation of Gentoo Linux (Version
        1.4, 2004.0 through 2005.0) there is no need to reinstall. You will
        automatically get Gentoo 2005.1 if you sync your Portage tree and run
        <c>emerge --update world</c>. If you still have an installation with a
        Gentoo 1.2 profile it might make sense -- in some cases -- that you do a
        new installation.</p>

      <p> There is also the possibility to update your system to a 1.4 profile
        from which you -- as already stated -- can easily get to Gentoo 2005.1.
        This update includes recompiling of glibc and some essential system
        packages; it will take a very long time (possibly longer as a complete
        re-installation) and it might also fail. So if you still have an
        installation with a Gentoo 1.2 profile, it's your decision whether you
        update or reinstall.</p>
    </body>
  </section>
</chapter>

</guide>
