<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/extreme-security/threatmodels/Attic/index.xml,v 1.2 2007/11/16 18:17:03 pappy Exp $ -->

<!--
threatmodels: describe three threat models relative to company size:$
- small company (no internet infrastructure, NAT, no remote sites, 1-2 servers, 5-20 desktops)$
- medium company (one mail server in-house, DMZ, NAT, one or two remote sites, max. 5-10 servers, 20-100 desktops)$
- big company (router backbones, NAT, DMZ, VPN, internet servers (www,smtp,ssh, business2business connections),$
100-1000 desktops, 10-100 servers)$
-->

<guide link="/proj/en/extreme-security/threatmodels/index.xml">
    <title>Threat Models</title>
    <author title="Author">
        <mail link="pappy@gentoo.org">Alexander Gabert</mail>
    </author>

    <abstract>
        The threat model is the starting point of a security improvement process.
    </abstract>
    <version>0.1</version>
    <date>2007-10-27</date>
    
    <chapter>
        <title>
            Introduction to threat models
        </title>
        <section>
            <body>
                <p>
                    An attacker-centric threat model is the starting point of a security improvement process over existing infrastructure:
                    It contains the possible attack vectors to the technology encountered in any business.
                </p>
                <p>
                    In our threat model we will impersonate the role of a security principal doing in-house consulting and providing
                    guidelines and a security architecture for responding to attacks based on fictional examples taking place in an idealized,
                    non-existing, example company with almost no constraints on time, money,
                    receiving the full support from upper management in their decisions.
                </p>

                <p>
                  Of course, in reality one never happens to work this way.
                  And this is also why there is people making money from doing security assessment and consulting in this business:
                  The value of a decision cannot be learned from a document in the internet, it comes from positive and negative experience in protecting companies from cyber threats.
                </p>
            </body>
        </section>
    </chapter>
    
    <chapter>
        <title>
          Example threat model for a small-sized company business
        </title>
        <section>
            <title>
              Physical Security
            </title>
            <body>
                <p>
                  TODO
                </p>
            </body>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>
            Network security
          </title>
          <body>
            <p>
              TODO
            </p>
          </body>
        </section>
        <section>
          <title>
            Software security
          </title>
          <body>
            <p>
              TODO
            </p>
          </body>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>
          Example threat model for a medium-sized company business
        </title>
        <section>
          <title>
            Physical Security
          </title>
            <body>
                <p>
                  TODO
                </p>
            </body>
        </section>
    </chapter>

    <chapter>
        <title>
          Example threat model for a large company business
        </title>
        <section>
            <body>
                <p>
                  The IT security people in large companies usually perform the job as a professional career and have a wise and experienced understanding about the protection of their infrastructure, hence it won't be necessary to go into too much details about threat models affecting them.
                  Physical site security is often not a problem, though special attention can be given to industrial espionage via dumpster diving for technical papers, social engineering attacks via telephone, for example people claiming to be from the recently outsourced helpdesk and needing your email password for resetting an important server.
                </p>

                <p>
                  A typical threat model for a big insurance company or a financial institute would for example cover things like preventing any negative impact from the insider knowlegde of a disgruntled employee getting into the hands of the competition or people with a broader interest in industrial sabotage.
                  In this example, a long-term senior administrator of the server staff (around 10 to 20 people) has been forced to leave the company because a fraud has been discovered in which he was involved and now the bosses want to know how vulnerable they are if he might be interested in selling his passwords and knowledge to an unknown party.
                </p>

                <p>
                  As an overview, a threat model for such a case could cover the following areas of interest, which is not an exhaustive list:
                </p>

                <p>
                  Physical security: magnetic id cards, keys for (emergency) doors and machine racks could have been duplicated or forged before returning them upon leaving.
                </p>

                <p>
                  Network security: the employee could still have access to password-protected publicly accessible network hardware like firewalls, routers and switches, especially in cases where it is not easily possible to regularily change the passwords of network hardware located in offshore locations or dialup stations.
                </p>

                <p>
                  Software security: the employee would have detailed internal knowledge about infrastructure and software used on the server farms, the update cycles, the response time to security issues and the machine-specific security policy.
                  With this knowledge getting sold to him, an attacker could specifically identify and address the weakest part of a protection pattern and could have very fast and very easy success in whatever he or she is planning, may it be information retrieval or inflicting damage.
                </p>
                
            </body>
        </section>
    </chapter>


</guide>
