<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>user-relations</name>
<longname>Gentoo User Relations</longname>
<date>2006-03-28</date>
<author title="Author"><mail link="christel@gentoo.org">Christel Dahlskjær</mail></author>
<description>
The Gentoo User Relations Subproject offers a point of contact between the 
development and user communities.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>The Gentoo User Relations project's main function is to act as a facilitator
for the various user focused projects within Gentoo. The project takes the
initiative in soliciting feedback from users and developers, creating surveys
on relevant issues, promoting the distribution to individuals and groups, and
fostering cross-project interaction.</p>

<p>The project also offers a point of contact between the development and user
communities. It looks at ways of keeping advanced users and prospective
developers informed about the development community, and encourages relations
between the two communities.</p>

<p>It is important to note that user-relations' activities are intended to be
proactive rather than reactive -- any specific conflicts or other incidents
are dealt with by other groups; our part is to help reduce their workload by
making such incidents less likely.</p>

<p><b>What we do</b></p>
<p>The user-relations project's intended activities and responsibilities include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Resolve conflicts where possible, and find creative solutions to them. Help to
work through ongoing conflicts, miscommunication, and other such issues that
affect our relationship with the user community.</li>
<li>Help to turn 'more communication' into 'better communication'.</li>
<li>Understand and appreciate different project types and management styles.</li>
<li>Collaborate with, and where possible learn from, the user community.</li>
</ul>

<p><b>What we offer</b></p>
<p>User-relations acts as a form of umbrella project, providing resources and input
to the projects in its area of responsibility. Some of the things we can do for
projects include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Arrange cross-project meetings for discussion of issues that affect more than
one participating project.</li>
<li>Develop and carry out user surveys, and other methods for gathering input from
the user community.</li>
<li>Provide a central source of information and resources to make user-focused
projects' jobs easier and more productive.</li>
<li>Encourage and facilitate sharing of experience and expertise amongst
participating projects.</li>
</ul>

<p>Overall, we intend to encourage relevant projects to co-operate with each other
and with us. Our main goal is to help projects to do their own jobs by providing
information and support as outlined above, and to represent the needs of the user
community within Gentoo. As such, in our dealings with projects we focus more on
how to achieve their goals, leaving the goals themselves for the projects to
decide on. To this end, we hope to stay objective, and be seen as a facilitator
helping the projects to do what they want to do, rather than an authority
dictating policy to others. We can also act as a single entity to represent all the
participating projects should any of them wish to implement anything that would
need discussion with other parts of Gentoo.</p>

</longdescription>

<dev role="Lead">christel</dev>
<dev role="Member">dsd</dev>
<dev role="Member">antarus</dev>
<dev role="Member">marienz</dev>
<dev role="Member">nattfodd</dev>
<dev role="Member">jokey</dev>
<dev role="Member">gerrynjr</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="Arch Tester liaison">hparker</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="GWN liaison">patrick</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="Bugday liaison">tannewt</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="Forums liaison">mark_alec</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="#gentoo liaison">chriswhite</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="Infra/WWW liaison">curtis119</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="User Representative">Fieldy</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="Infra/Overlays liaison">Stuart</dev>

<subproject ref="/proj/en/devrel/user-relations/summerofcode/index.xml"></subproject>

<extrachapter>
<title>Participating Projects</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Some of the projects and groups with which User Relations will be working closely
include:</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/pr/">Gentoo Public Relations</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://bugday.gentoo.org">Gentoo Bugdays</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/">Gentoo Infrastructure</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/base/amd64/tests/index.xml">
    AMD64 (and other) Arch Testers</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo Bugzilla</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/pr/gwn.xml">The Gentoo Weekly 
    Newsletter</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/irc-gentoo-policy.xml">#gentoo ops</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org">Planet Gentoo</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Getting Involved</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>There are a number of areas in which interested users can contribute to Gentoo:</p>

<p><b>Gentoo Linux Development team:</b> Prospective developers are encouraged to 
become active on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugzilla</uri>. The bug 
reports are monitored by development recruiters, so start squashing bugs and 
you will become noticed. </p>

<p><b>Gentoo Bugdays:</b> On the first Saturday of each month both developers and
users gather in #gentoo-bugs on irc.freenode.net where bugs are tested, 
discussed and resolved. Bugdays offer a great way for developers and users to
work together and get to know each other. It also provides an opportunity for
potential developers to be scouted. For further information the
<mail link="bugday@gentoo.org">Bugday team</mail> can be contacted. </p>

<p><b>Gentoo Linux Documentation team:</b> The team provides users with clear and
concise documentation. It is comprised of Technical Writers, Editors/Proofreaders,
and Translators. For more information on joining take a look at the 
<uri link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-policy.xml">Gentoo Linux Documentation Policy</uri>. </p>

<p><b>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter:</b> If you would like to offer your help to the GWN team 
as a contributor or translator then contact information can be found in the 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">Gentoo Weekly Newsletter 
Overview</uri>. </p>

<p><b>#gentoo IRC Channel:</b> Knowledgeable users are encouraged to come and help
out in #gentoo on irc.freenode.net. </p>

<p><b>#gentoo-dev-help IRC Channel:</b> Anyone wanting to know more about ebuild
writing and/or Gentoo development is welcome to come and ask in #gentoo-dev-help on
Freenode, where developers and other users are waiting to help. </p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Contact User Relations</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Do you have questions about the Gentoo development community? Do you have a 
suggestion to improve Gentoo? Then we'd love to hear them. Send an email to
<mail link="user-relations@gentoo.org">user-relations@gentoo.org</mail> or the
<mail link="gentoo-userrel@gentoo.org">gentoo-userrel mailing list</mail>, or find
us in #gentoo-userrel on irc.freenode.net.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
