<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
	<name>user-relations</name>
	<longname>Gentoo User Relations</longname>
	<date>2005-10-28</date>
	<author title="Author"><mail link="brandy@gentoo.org">Brandy Westcott</mail></author>
	<author title="Editor"><mail link="cybersystem@gentoo.org">Sascha Schwabbauer</mail></author>
	<description>
		The Gentoo User Relations Subproject offers a point of contact between the development community and the user community.
	</description>

	<longdescription>
	The Gentoo User Relations Subproject offers a point of contact between the development community and the user community. It looks at ways of keeping advanced users and prospective developers informed about the development community and it encourages fostering relations between the development community and the user community.
	</longdescription>

	<dev role="lead">christel</dev>
	<dev>cybersystem</dev>
	<dev>dsd</dev>
	<dev>antarus</dev>
	<dev>marienz</dev>
	<dev description="User representative">FieldySnuts</dev>
	<dev>cokehabit</dev>

	<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml">Gentoo Developer Mailing List</resource>
	<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">Gentoo Weekly Newsletter</resource>
	<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/index.xml">Gentoo Linux Documentation</resource>
	<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/about.xml">About Gentoo Linux</resource>

	<extrachapter>
	<title>Getting Involved</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>
	There are a number of areas in which interested users can contribute to Gentoo:
	</p>
	<p>
	<b>Gentoo Linux Development team:</b> Prospective developers are encouraged to become active on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugzilla</uri>. The bug reports are monitored by Development Recruiters, so start squashing bugs and you will become noticed.
	</p>
	<p>
	<b>Gentoo BugDays:</b> On the first Saturday of each month both developers and users gather in #gentoo-bugs on irc.freenode.net where bugs are tested, discussed and resolved. BugDays offer a great way for developers and users to work together and get to know each other. It also provides an opportunity for potential developers to be scouted. For further information <mail link="kloeri@gentoo.org">Bryan Ostergaard</mail> can be contacted.
	</p>
	<p>
	<b>Gentoo Linux Documentation team:</b> The team provides users with clear and concise documentation. It is comprised of Technical Writers, Editors/Proofreaders, and Translators. For more information on joining take a look at the <uri link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-policy.xml">Gentoo Linux Documentation Policy</uri>.
	</p>
	<p>
	<b>Gentoo Weekly Newsletter:</b> If you like to offer your help to the GWN team as a contributor or translator then contact information can be found in the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml">Gentoo Weekly Newsletter Overview</uri>.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>

	<extrachapter>
	<title>Contact User Relations</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>
	Do you have questions about the Gentoo development community? Do you have a suggestion to improve Gentoo? Then we'd love to here them. Send an email to <mail link="user-relations@gentoo.org">user-relations@gentoo.org</mail>.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>

</project>
