<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/council/coc.xml,v 1.5 2012/10/28 15:21:00 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Code of Conduct</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="christel@gentoo.org">Christel Dahlskjaer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Joshua Saddler</mail>
</author>
<author title="Reviewer">
  <mail link="marienz@gentoo.org">Marien Zwart</mail>
</author>
<author title="Reviewer">
  <mail link="kloeri@gentoo.org">Bryan Østergaard</mail>
</author>
<author title="Reviewer">
  <mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>
<author title="Reviewer">
  <mail link="uberlord@gentoo.org">Roy Marples</mail>
</author>
<author title="Reviewer">
  <mail link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike Frysinger</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="spb@gentoo.org">Stephen Bennett</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="kingtaco@gentoo.org">Mike Doty</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="robbat2@gentoo.org">Robin H. Johnson</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="kugelfang@gentoo.org">Danny van Dyk</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="lack@gentoo.org">Jim Ramsay</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="musikc@charter.net">Christina Fullam</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document describes Gentoo's Code of Conduct for public communication fora,
as well as the action taken should it be broken.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>2.0</version>
<date>2007-03-15</date>

<chapter>
<title>Draft disclaimer</title>
<section>
<body>
<impo>
This document is an ongoing work, subject to growth and revision as Gentoo grows and changes.
</impo>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Scope</title>
<section>
<title>Joining and participation agreement</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo prides itself on being a community driven distribution that acts with the best interest of the community at heart. Rules and regulations that keep us all moving in a forward direction are a reality for a community of this size. 
</p>

<p>
This document describes Gentoo's Code of Conduct for public communication mediums, who shall enforce said Code of Conduct, the action taken should the Code of Conduct be broken, as well as the method for appeals. Questions about this document and its contents can be directed to the council at council@gentoo.org.
</p>

<impo>
By joining and/or participating in the Gentoo community, you are stating that
you accept and agree to adhere to the rules listed below, even if you do not
explicitly state so.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Behaviour and Consequences</title>

<section>
<title>Acceptable behaviour</title>
<body>

<p>
Things that should be seen:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <b>Be courteous.</b> Though respect is earned, it must start somewhere. Respect someones right for their own opinion and acknowledge that they do deserve a measure of politeness in your response.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Give accurate information in the spirit of being helpful.</b>
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Respectfully disagree with or challenge other members.</b> The
    operative word here is respectfully.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Using the correct forum for your post.</b> Bug reports and idle chatter
    do not belong on the gentoo-dev mailing list; discussion about a
    wide-ranging change to the tree probably does not belong on Bugzilla.
    Different fora will also have different standards of behaviour -- a joke
    that is perfectly acceptable on IRC will be taken differently when made on a
    mailing list.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Admit the possibility of fault and respect different point of views.</b>
    Noone is perfect -- you will get things wrong occasionally. Don't be afraid
    to admit this. Similarly, while something may seem perfectly obvious to you,
    others may see it differently. 
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>If you screw up, take responsibility for your actions.</b>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Unacceptable behaviour</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo developers have come together with a common purpose, to further the project. Conflicts will undoubtedly arise, and though you are encouraged to work through issues on your own, assistance is available as requested and as needed.
</p>
<p>
Deciding to suspend or ban someone isn't a decision to be taken lightly, but
sometimes it has to happen. Below is a list of things that could result in disciplinary action.
</p>

<ul>
 <li>
   <b>Flaming and trolling.</b> What is trolling? You are deemed to be trolling if you make comments intended to provoke an angry response from others. What is flaming? Flaming is the act of sending or posting messages that are deliberately hostile and insulting.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Posting/participating only to incite drama or negativity</b> rather than
    to tactfully share information.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Being judgmental, mean-spirited or insulting.</b> It is possible to
    respectfully challenge someone in a way that empowers without being judgemental.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Constantly purveying misinformation</b> despite repeated warnings.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Consequences</title>
<body>

<p>
Disciplinary action will be up to the descretion of the proctors. What is a proctor? A proctor is an official charged with the duty of maintaining good order. Currently this responsibility falls to two existing Gentoo projects: <uri link="/proj/en/devrel">DevRel</uri> and <uri link="/proj/en/userrel">UserRel</uri>.
</p>

<p>
If you perceive a breach of the Code of Conduct guidelines, let the appropriate proctors know. Though they will also be watching many of the public mediums for any problems, they can not be expected to catch everything. If the offender is a Gentoo developer, contact <mail link="devrel@g.o">devrel@g.o</mail>, otherwise contact <mail link="userrel@g.o">userrel@g.o</mail>.
</p>

<p>
The proctors will attempt to resolve the problem by talking to involved parties, potentially issuing warnings if appropriate. If the problem repeats itself, there are various options open to the proctors, including temporary or permanent suspension of a person's ability to post to mailing lists, removal of Bugzilla access, or in more severe cases suspension of developer privileges.
</p>

<p>
If discplinary measures are taken and the affected person wishes to appeal, appeals should be addressed to the Gentoo Council via email at <mail link="council@g.o">council@g.o</mail>. To prevent conflicts of interest, Council members may not perform the duties of a proctor.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Summary</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
If you are unsure whether or not something is OK to post/comment/etc,
assume it isn't, and reconsider whether you need to post it. Remember that posts
made to mailing lists are archived for perpetuity, and read by far more people
than will be actively involved in any one thread. A comment made in anger can
have far-reaching consequences that you might not have thought about at the time.
</p>

<p>
Remember, the moment you participate in a public discussion on Gentoo medium,
you have made yourself a representative of the Gentoo community. We hope that
you will not take this responsibility lightly, and will prove to be a positive
force in it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
