<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/base/x86/arch-testers-faq.xml,v 1.33 2015/03/14 18:30:16 dilfridge Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:X86/Arch_Testers_FAQ">
<title>Gentoo x86 Arch Tester's FAQ</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="halcy0n@gentoo.org">Mark Loeser</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="fox2mike@gentoo.org">Shyam Mani</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="fauli@gentoo.org">Christian Faulhammer</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="tomka@gentoo.org">Thomas Kahle</mail>
</author>


<abstract>
This document is the x86 Arch Tester's bible.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>30</version>
<date>2012-01-17</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This FAQ attempts to answer the most commonly asked questions about being an
Arch Tester with the x86 team. Questions can be asked on irc at #gentoo-x86 or
mailed to the Author.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Questions</title>
<section>
<title>The Basics</title>
<body>

<p>
General queries regarding Arch Testing.
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#whoat">Who is an Arch Tester?</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#whyat">Why does Gentoo need Arch Testers?</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#basicsk">What are the basic skills I need to be an AT?</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#basicsys">What are the basic system requirements if
    any?</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#x86at">What does it mean to be part of the x86 AT
    Team?</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#atwhat">What do I have to do as an AT? What are my
    roles/responsibilities?</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#athow">How do I get involved with the team and start
    helping out?</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Getting Ready</title>
<body>

<p>
How to get your system setup and ready to test packages.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="#stchroot">I don't run stable x86, my box is ~x86. How can I setup
    an x86 chroot?</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#kernelv">I run an unstable kernel. Would that be an issue when
    I'm testing packages?</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Work Work Work!!!</title>
<body>

<p>
Stuff that you do on a day to day basis.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="#steptest">What are the steps I need to follow	when I'm
    testing a package?</uri>
  </li>
  <li><uri link="#powers">What godly powers do I have as an AT?</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#whomct">Whom do I contact in case of breakages?</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#methct">What are the best ways of contacting
    maintainers/devs?</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The Basics</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This section aims to be quite generic and questions answered here hold true
across most archs in Gentoo.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="whoat">
<title>Who is an Arch Tester?</title>
<body>

<p>
An Arch Tester (commonly referred to as "AT") is a trustworthy user capable of
testing an application to determine its stability.  To be an AT you must be able
to test a wide array of packages, and be able to understand and modify ebuilds.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="whyat">
<title>Why does Gentoo need Arch Testers?</title>
<body>

<p>
We need ATs to help improve Quality Assurance (QA), and to help Arch Devs ensure
packages are actually stable by having it tested by others whom report their
findings. As the tree gets larger and larger we will need more people to
actively watch for things that break, and help get them fixed.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="basicsk">
<title>What are the basic skills I need to be an AT?</title>
<body>

<p>
You should be able to modify ebuilds and recognize mistakes that should be
corrected before we mark the package stable. It is also expected that you can
test packages and give good bug reports if there are problems with anything.
This means you should be comfortable with bash scripting as well as Gentoo
specific areas such as Portage overlays.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="basicsys">
<title>What are the basic system requirements if any?</title>
<body>

<p>
You'll need a system or chroot, which only uses packages marked
"x86". This is so we actually use stable libraries to test packages
against, and can find bugs in packages marked stable.  Alternatively
you can run Gentoo on a dedicated machine for testing only or in a
virtual machine.  Suitable programs for the latter are VirtualBox,
VMWare or QEmu/KVM, although its use for architecture work is
discouraged because it does not run on actual hardware.
</p>
<p>
Additionally you should set <c>FEATURES="test collision-protect"</c>
to catch test failures and file collisions between packages.  Some
packages do not respect the values of LDFLAGS and CFLAGS/CXXFLAGS when
building, which can lead to breakage.  So you should at least set
<c>LDFLAGS="${LDFLAGS} -Wl,--hash-style=gnu"</c>, which makes Portage
output a warning about it.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section id="x86at">
<title>What does it mean to be a part of the x86 AT Team?</title>
<body>

<p>
Being part of the x86 AT Team means you are prepared to dedicate some amount
of time to help Gentoo/x86. It also means that you are interested in helping
test any applications we are asked to mark stable.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="atwhat">
<title>What do I have to do as an AT? What are my
roles/responsibilities?</title>
<body>

<p>
You need to help arch devs test packages. Testing a package requires more
than just ensuring it compiles. It is expected that you will ensure that
atleast major functionality works in the application. When testing a package,
ensure you have <c>FEATURES="test collision-protect"</c> on. If any package fails to
emerge with this feature set, it is a major QA issue and we can't proceed 
until it's resolved.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="athow">
<title>How do I get involved with the team and start helping out?</title>
<body>

<p>
First you should read this entire FAQ so you are familiar with what being an
AT actually means.  After completing that, you should come on irc.freenode.net
and hang out in #gentoo-x86.  Developers often ask for help with testing a
package, and you can try helping out wherever you can.
</p>

<p>
The main way for you to start helping out is to look at our bugs.  Here are a
few links for you bookmark or save as searchs on bugzilla:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/4y97e9e">All x86 bugs</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/6xog3y8">Security related x86 bugs</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Finally, after you have shown some level of commitment and we believe you
will be a good addition to the team, we will give you the
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz/ebuild-quiz.txt">ebuild
quiz</uri> and then there will be a 30 day mentoring period.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Getting Ready</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This section deals with commonly asked "how to setup" style questions to guide
you through getting your system ready to do some AT work :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="stchroot">
<title>I don't run stable x86, my box is ~x86. How can I setup an x86
chroot?</title>
<body>

<p>
Please take a look at the <uri link="chroot.xml">Chroot Guide</uri> for more
information regarding setting up a chroot environment.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="kernelv">
<title>I run an unstable kernel. Would that be an issue when I'm testing
packages?</title>
<body>

<p>
It is preferred that you use a stable kernel outside of the chroot but it is
not a firm requirement.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Work Work Work!!!</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Questions on how exactly to go about doing your work on a daily basis are
answered here.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="steptest">
<title>What are the steps I need to follow when I'm testing a package?</title>
<body>

<ol>
  <li>Ensure that all packages in the system/chroot are stable.</li>
  <li>
    Set <c>FEATURES="test collision-protect"</c> in
    <path>/etc/make.conf</path> and use a "sane" set of <c>CFLAGS</c>,
    as described in the <uri
    link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gcc-optimization.xml">Compilation
    Optimization Guide</uri>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Choose a request from the above-mentioned bug lists, where
    security bugs and keywording requests have absolute priority.
  </li>
  <li>
     Normally, all needed packages are listed in the request, but
     sometimes, dependencies are forgotten.  This is usually no
     problem for most things, but you should include it in your report
     nonetheless.  To automatically add all needed packages to the
     <c>package.keywords</c> file, you may use <uri
     link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/app-portage/tatt">app-portage/tatt</uri>.
  </li>
  <li>
    After merging the package with various USE flag combinations, run
    it and ensure that basic functionality works.  If the package is a
    library, emerge a couple of packages that use the library to
    ensure they still work with the new version (best option: all that
    depend on it and have a stable version).  The so-called
    reverse-dependencies are found in the <uri
    link="http://tinderbox.dev.gentoo.org/misc/dindex/">dindex</uri>.
   </li>
   <li>
     Inform the team about the successful test or the occured failures
     on the corresponding bug report including what you did and on
     what platform.  If there were problems, add your <c>emerge
     --info</c> output, too.
   </li>
   <li>
     Problems that occur in the currently stable version, too, will
     not always be an obstactle to stabilisations, but need to be
     reported nonetheless.
   </li>
</ol>

<p>Additional hints you may find useful:</p>

<ul>
   <li>
     Architecture testers not only test packages but also seek
     actively for solutions were problems occured.  Important sources
     of information are version control systems and bug trackers of
     other distributions and also upstream.  Reporting bugs to the
     authors is as important as testing packages!
   </li>
   <li>
     Set a user watch for Bugzilla in your <uri
     link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/userprefs.cgi?tab=email">preferences</uri>
     on the x86@gentoo.org alias.  Thus you will receive all mails
     from Bugzilla directed towards the x86 team.
   </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section id="powers">
<title>What godly powers do I have as an AT?</title>
<body>

<p>
Hah. You were joking when you asked that right? AT's are minions who do all the
work and have no powers or play......okay, I was kidding :)
</p>

<p>
Things you have access to/can do as an AT:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Elevated priviledges on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo
    Bugzilla</uri> so that you can modify all aspects of a bug. This is mainly
    given so that you can re-assign bugs correctly in case needed and
    co-ordinate with package maintainers/other arch teams etc.
  </li>
  <li>Read-only cvs access to the gentoo-x86 repository, which is not
  a privilege, but may come in handy for ATs.  See <uri
  link="http://sources.gentoo.org/">ViewCVS</uri> for a checkout URL
  for anonymous access.</li>
</ul>

<p>
Things you don't have access to/can't do as an AT:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
     Commit fixes for ebuilds. You'll have to find the maintainer or another
     developer with access to do that for you.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section id="whomct">
<title>Whom do I contact in case of breakages?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you notice some major breakage in the tree, first try to contact the person
that caused the breakage. This can be found in the <path>ChangeLog</path>
normally, but if not, use <uri link="http://sources.gentoo.org/">ViewCVS</uri>
to see who committed the change. If you can't get in touch with this person, try
the maintainer or herd of the package (if the maintainer is not the same person
that caused the breakage). If all else fails, make an x86 dev aware of the
situation so we can address it as best as we can until someone is available to
address it properly.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="methct">
<title>What are the best ways of contacting maintainers/devs?</title>
<body>

<p>
Normally the easiest way to contact a dev is to "ping" them on IRC. If they
aren't around on IRC, send them an email. If you are unable to get in touch
with them, try contacting someone else in the herd (if applicable). If there
is no herd to get in touch with then tell someone in the x86 team what the
issue is and we'll figure out how to proceed. Also, unless the problem is
severe, give them enough time to respond back through email. Do check the
<uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/devaway/">devaway</uri> to make sure the
person you're trying to reach isn't away.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>

