<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/project.dtd">
<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:X86">
  <name>Gentoo Linux/x86</name>
  <longname>Gentoo Linux x86 Architecture Development</longname>
  <date>2011-08-07</date>

  <description>
    The Gentoo Linux x86 Development Project is devoted to keeping Gentoo
    Linux in good shape on the x86 architecture, which represents all
    32-bit Intel-compatible processors
  </description>
  <longdescription>
    <p>
      The Gentoo Linux/x86 Project works to keep Gentoo the most up to
      date and secure x86 distribution available. We are responsible
      for the maintainance of all x86 specific meta-data and the
      testing of all other non-x86 specific meta-data on the x86
      architecture to ensure portability. Portability implies
      reuseable meta-data.
    </p>

    <p>
      Bugs are tracked and resolved from the <uri
      link="http://bugs.gentoo.org"> Gentoo bug tracker</uri> and
      correspondence is maintained over the x86 mail alias.
    </p>
  </longdescription>

  <goals>
    <p>
      The goal of the Gentoo Linux x86 Arhitecture Development project
      is to guarantee that the x86 packages build using Gentoo
      meta-data are up to date.  By continuously enhancing the
      meta-data, we provide the x86 user with the Gentoo community
      feeling, performance, freedom and up-to-dateness that they
      expect and deserve.  The meta-distribution notion allows for a
      user to to be as bleeding edge as he/she wants:
    </p>

    <p>
      Gentoo is unique because of its interpretation of the
      Meta-Distribution notion: all architectures share the same
      'generic' meta-data (information about how to build
      packages&mdash;how to build a distribution). The x86 developers
      are responsible for building and testing packages using this
      meta-data.  The meta-data gets marked 'tested' or 'stable'
      afterwards, depending on the building and testing
      experience. Our users can use (but don't have to use) this
      information to build a system that suits their needs.
    </p>
  </goals>

  <recruitment>
    <job>
      <summary>Arch Tester</summary>
      <details>
        Gentoo/x86 needs more people testing packages. See
        <uri link="/proj/en/base/x86/arch-testers-faq.xml">Arch Tester's FAQ
        </uri> for more information.
      </details>
      <requirements>
        Being able to test packages and give good bug reports if there are
        problems with anything. Running a stable x86 Gentoo system or chroot.
        No quiz is required to start.
      </requirements>
      <contact>x86@gentoo.org</contact>
    </job>
    <job>
      <summary>Team member</summary>
      <details>
        Gentoo/x86 needs more people testing packages and updating x86 keywords
        (marking packages as tested or stable on x86).
      </details>
      <requirements>
        Good understanding of ebuilds and Gentoo policies, experience with
        testing packages and most common QA issues. Becoming an Arch Tester
        is a great start. Team members are Gentoo developers, so they are
        required to take ebuild quizzes.
      </requirements>
      <contact>x86@gentoo.org</contact>
    </job>
  </recruitment>

  <subproject ref="/proj/en/base/x86/at.xml"/>

  <extrachapter position="bottom">
    <title>How to Participate</title>
    <section>
      <body>
	<p>
	  Can you make computers do amazing things? Are you excited
	  about exploring areas of computing never explored before? We
	  are continuously looking for volunteers willing to spend
	  some of their free time on this project. In return for your
	  work, you get the respect of the x86 community.
	</p>

	<p>
	  If you are interested in helping, but don't have a niche
	  that you are interested in filling, you can always look
	  through <uri
	  link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>. There
	  are many, many bugs waiting to be found and fixed and many
	  enhancements looking to find someone to code them. Figure
	  out a fix, implement it, test it, and then keep trying to
	  make the patch smaller. Post it for review on <uri
	  link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>, and
	  keep working on it. If it seems ignored, make a new comment
	  in the bug and/or mention it in #gentoo-x86.
	</p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

  <extrachapter position="bottom">
    <title>Documentation</title>
    <section>
      <body>
	<ul>
	  <li><uri link="arch-testers-faq.xml">Arch Tester's FAQ</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="chroot.xml">Chroot Guide</uri></li>
	  <li><uri link="exceptions.xml">List of packages</uri> that can be marked stable by their maintainers</li>
	</ul>
      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

  <dev role="Lead/Security Liaison/Arch Tester lead" description="Gentoo/x86">jdhore</dev>
  <dev role="Developer" description="Security bugs primarily">ago</dev>
  <dev role="Developer" description="Gentoo/x86">armin76</dev>
  <dev role="Developer" description="Gentoo/x86">phajdan.jr</dev>
  <dev role="Developer" description="Gentoo/x86">vincent</dev>
  <dev role="Developer" description="Gentoo/x86">zlogene</dev>
  <dev role="Developer" description="">nativemad</dev>
  <herd name="x86"/>
</project>
