<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">


<guide link="./gentoo-stats.xml" >
  <title>Gentoo-Stats.org - Gentoo Buildtime and Statistics</title>
 
  <author title="Author" >
    <mail link="pvdabeel@gentoo.org" >Pieter Van den Abeele</mail>
  </author> 
  <author title="Author" >
    <mail link="dma147@gentoo-stats.org" >Alexander Mieland</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Translator" >
    <mail link="expose@gentoo-stats.org" >Daniel Herzog</mail>
  </author>

  <abstract>
    This document describes the Gentoo Stats project, a subproject of 
    the Gentoo Tools top level project. The goal of the Gentoo Stats project 
    is to build a client server application that collects data about
    the Gentoo software distribution and its users.
    
    Currently our biggest contributor and developer in training is the author of
    www.gentoo-stats.org, which is currently not considered an official Gentoo project. 
    Nevertheless every developer or user is invited to contribute code and to 
    help improve and audit all contributed code, thereby ensuring the engineering process 
    for this Gentoo project is transparent and leads to 
    software that has been verified to meet Gentoo's high engineering standards.
    
    Since www.gentoo-stats.org serves as the semi-official experimental
    statistics database in the meantime, a short description
    of the project is included on this page. This page will also be updated 
    in the near future with a roadmap for the currently unofficial project.
  </abstract>

  <!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
  <!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
  <license/>
  <version>1.0</version>
  <date>December the 21th, 2004</date>
  
  <chapter>
    <title>BAS/c - Buildtime And Statistics /client - gentoo-stats.org</title>
    <section>
      <title>What we wanted to do</title>
      <body>
        
        <p>
	  The goal of this non-Gentoo project was to create an advanced version of 
	  the (currently unmaintained) stats.gentoo.org. This project 
          has been written from scratch, feature enhancements to the old 
	  stats.gentoo.org include the ability to estimate the time needed for 
	  a package to be build on any given system. This tool also allows 
          users to submit screenshot, xorg.conf and kernel configs to a moderated 
          central repository. 
        </p>
        
        <p>
	  The first unofficial version of this project was available in July 2004.
          The privacy policy for the project can be found on its webpage.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>The Team</title>
      <body>

	<p>
	  Pieter Van den Abeele &lt;<mail link="pvdabeel@gentoo.org">pvdabeel@gentoo.org</mail>&gt;
	</p>        
        <p>
          Alexander Mieland &lt;<mail link="dma147@gentoo-stats.org">dma147@gentoo-stats.org</mail>&gt;
        </p>
        <p>
          Daniel Herzog &lt;<mail link="expose@gentoo-stats.org">expose@gentoo-stats.org</mail>&gt;
        </p>

      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Project specifics?</title>
      <body>
	
	<p>
	  Gentoo ebuild: emerge basc
	</p>     
   
        <p>
          URI to the project: <uri>http://www.gentoo-stats.org</uri>
        </p>
      
     </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

</guide>
