<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
  <name>chromium</name>
  <longname>Chromium in Gentoo Project</longname>

  <description>
    The Chromium in Gentoo project manages the Chromium-related ebuilds
    within Gentoo.
  </description>

  <longdescription>
    <p>
      The Chromium in Gentoo project manages the Chromium-related ebuilds
      within Gentoo.
    </p>
  </longdescription>

  <goals>
    <ul>
      <li>
        ensure that Chromium-related ebuilds are kept up to date and well
        integrated with the rest of the Gentoo system
      </li>
      <li>
        build a community of Gentoo users interested in Chromium development
        and packaging efforts (testing, bug fixing, feedback)
      </li>
      <li>
        make Gentoo the best and most friendly platform for Chromium
        development
      </li>
    </ul>
  </goals>
  
  <recruitment>
    <job>
      <summary>Herd Tester</summary>
      <details>
        Chromium in Gentoo project needs more people testing packages.
        We are not always able to reproduce reported issues, and having
        more people respond to testing requests would be useful.
        No quiz is necessary to start.
      </details>
      <requirements>
        If you are running www-client/chromium or chromium-bin,
        and are willing to spend some time helping Gentoo,
        feel free to apply.
      </requirements>
      <contact>chromium@gentoo.org</contact>
    </job>
    <job>
      <summary>Developer</summary>
      <details>
        We have ambitious plans to start maintaining more chromium-related
        packages like v8. We could also create some Gentoo-specific
        documentation for people who would like to contribute to or hack on
        the upstream project. To complete those tasks, we may need more
        manpower.
      </details>
      <requirements>
        Being a Gentoo developer who wants to join the project. Moderate
        knowledge of upstream project. Being a committer of the upstream
        project would be a huge plus.
      </requirements>
      <contact>chromium@gentoo.org</contact>
    </job>
  </recruitment>

  <extrachapter position="bottom">
    <title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

    <section>
      <title>What is the difference between Google Chrome and Chromium?</title>
      <body>
        <p>See <uri link="http://code.google.com/p/chromium/wiki/ChromiumBrowserVsGoogleChrome">
        differences between Google Chrome and Linux distro Chromium</uri>.</p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Why are dev channel releases hard masked?</title>
      <body>
        <p>Dev channel releases are for developers and people who want more
        experimental features and accept more unstable software. It also allows
        you to choose the channel you want to be on (dev = hard masked,
        beta = ~arch, stable = arch).</p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Aren't dev channel releases just weekly snapshots?</title>
      <body>
        <p>No, each release goes through QA first. It's not uncommon to delay
        a release because of increased crashiness or other instability.</p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Where can I find more info about the releases?</title>
      <body>
        <p>You can also follow <uri link="http://googlechromereleases.blogspot.com/">
        Google Chrome releases blog</uri>.</p>
      </body>
    </section>
    
    <section>
      <title>Why my gecko-mediaplayer plugin doesn't get recognized?</title>
      <body>
        <p>It'd hang the browser, and is blacklisted upstream. See
        <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/309231">Gentoo bug #309231</uri> and
        <uri link="http://code.google.com/p/chromium/issues/detail?id=24507">upstream bug</uri>.
        You may want to "star" the upstream bug to give it more attention.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>
        Where can I find more info about the upstream package, system
        integration issues, etc?
      </title>
      <body>
        <p>See <uri link="http://dev.chromium.org/developers/linux-technical-faq">
        Linux technical FAQ</uri>.</p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

  <extrachapter position="bottom">
    <title>Useful bug queries</title>

    <section>
      <body>
        <ul>
          <li><uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;emailassigned_to2=1&amp;emailreporter2=1&amp;emailcc2=1&amp;emailtype2=exact&amp;email2=security%40gentoo.org&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;emailreporter1=1&amp;emailcc1=1&amp;emailtype1=exact&amp;email1=chromium%40gentoo.org&amp;order=Bug+Number">chromium security bugs</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;emailreporter1=1&amp;emailcc1=1&amp;emailtype1=exact&amp;email1=chromium%40gentoo.org&amp;order=Bug+Number">chromium bugs</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=NEW&amp;bug_status=ASSIGNED&amp;bug_status=REOPENED&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;emailreporter1=1&amp;emailcc1=1&amp;emailtype1=exact&amp;email1=chromium%40gentoo.org&amp;order=Bug+Number&amp;status_whiteboard_type=allwordssubstr&amp;status_whiteboard=ht-wanted">chromium bugs (Herd Testers' help wanted)</uri></li>
          <li><uri link="http://code.google.com/p/chromium/issues/list?q=gentoo&amp;sort=-opened">chromium upstream bugs mentioning Gentoo</uri></li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>
  
  <extrachapter position="bottom">
    <title>Herd Testers' corner</title>

    <section>
      <title>How to become a Herd Tester?</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          You can just start contributing, see bug queries above, especially
          the one for Herd Testers. Frequently project members ask for help
          with reproducing issues, or testing fixes, or just
          any helpful comments. Feel free to ask for more details
          on the project mail alias, see <uri link="#JOBS">recruitment</uri>.
        </p>
        <p>
          To formally become a Herd Tester you will be required to take
          ebuild quizzes. Please note that you can still contribute a lot
          without becoming a Herd Tester.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>What benefits do I get as a Herd Tester?</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          First, you are helping your favorite distribution, which in itself
          is quite an achievement. Second, you can get a special badge on the
          Gentoo Forums, and more privileges on Gentoo Bugzilla.
        </p>
        <p>
          Please note that Chromium in Gentoo project appreciates all
          contributions and gives credit where credit is due. That means
          if you have submitted a good bug report, a helpful comment,
          or a patch, you can expect an entry in the package's ChangeLog.
          If you contribute more, you can be listed as one of the contributors
          on the project page. Becoming a Herd Tester is not necessary
          to get recognized. However, if you are interested in becoming
          a Gentoo Developer, Herd Testing is a good first step.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

  <dev role="lead">phajdan.jr</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="arm arch liaison">armin76</dev>
  <dev role="member">voyageur</dev>
  <dev role="member">wired</dev>

  <extrachapter position="devs">
    <title>Developer notes</title>
    <section>
      <body>
      	<note>Not all developers listed here are included in the
        <c>chromium@g.o</c> e-mail alias.</note>
      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

  <herd name="chromium" />
</project>
