<?xml version='1.0'?>
<news category="linux">
	<poster>drobbins</poster>
	<date>23 Jan 2002</date>
	<title>AMD's official position: this is not a CPU bug</title>

	<summary><p>Yesterday, Rik van Riel, William Lee Irwin and myself were able
	to discuss this issue of Athlon/AGP instability with AMD.  This converation
	was very enlightening, to say the least.  <b>Let's start with some facts.
	The issue that is being discussed here is not related to the so-called
	"INVPLG bug".</b>  So, what is the issue, and who's at fault?
	<b>Yesterday, AMD offered us an explanation of what <i>may</i> be happening
	to cause AGP instability on Linux systems.</b></p></summary>
	
	<body> <p>Yesterday, Rik van Riel, William Lee Irwin and myself were able
	to discuss this issue of Athlon/AGP instability with AMD.  This converation
	was very enlightening, to say the least.</p>

	<p><b>Let's start with some facts.  The issue that is being discussed here
	is not related to the so-called "INVPLG bug".</b>  So, what is the issue,
	and who's at fault?  <b>Yesterday, AMD offered us an explanation of what
	<i>may</i> be happening to cause AGP instability on Linux systems.</b>
	This explanation appears to be the exact scenario that bit Windows 2000 in
	September 2000.  AMD characterizes this issue as a cache coherency problem
	resulting from how other components on the motherboard (the GART in
	particular) interact with a particular performance-enhancing feature of the
	Athlon Processor called speculative writes.  The GART and the CPU have two
	different views of memory -- the GART's view does not "see" the contents of
	the Athlon's internal caches, and herein lies the problem.  <b>In certain
	situations the CPU and the GART can step on each other's toes, resulting in
	memory corruption.</b>   For more information, see my <uri
	link="http://www.geocrawler.com/lists/3/Linux/35/175/7626960/">Linux kernel
	mailing list post</uri> that  contains an explanation of this particular
	problem in AMD's own words.</p>

	<p><b>So, is the Linux kernel affected by this problem?  It appears so.</b>
	The GART and the CPU see two different views of memory, and it's the
	kernel's responsibility to map memory in such a way as to prevent bad
	interactions.  Currently, that isn't happening. Third-party drivers such as
	the NVIDIA driver for Linux may also have some problems in this area.  Now
	that the Linux kernel development community is aware of the issue, they
	have started the process of devising a good approach to avoid this memory
	corruption problem.  Disabling extended paging via the <c>mem=nopentium</c>
	boot option is really not a good long-term solution since it can impact
	performance, so a better solution is needed.</p>

	<p>I guess the big question on everyone's mind is this -- who's to blame
	for this very real problem?  Strangely enough, no one party appears to be
	at fault here.  But now that the problem is out in the open, the solution
	is clear.  <b>The Linux kernel's approach to memory management must become
	more sophisticated in order to address potential conflicts between the
	highly-speculative nature of Athlon processors and the non-cache-coherent
	AGP GART.</b></p> 

	<p>I'll be following the resolution of this issue closely and post
	information here as I get it.</p>
		

	</body>
</news>
