<?xml version='1.0'?>
<news gentoo="yes" category="nvidia">
	<poster>drobbins</poster>
	<date>07 Feb 2002</date>
	<title>New Gentoo Linux NVIDIA driver layout</title>
	<summary>
	<p>
	<b>Thanks to Arcady Genkin, we now have some nice newly-designed NVIDIA driver/GLX ebuilds for Gentoo Linux.</b>
	The old ebuild was easy to install but didn't isolate various NVIDIA files from those in <path>/usr/X11R6</path>.  These
	new ebuilds correct this as well as several other problems.  To learn how to use these new ebuilds, read Arcady's instructions by clicking on the 	  "full story" below.
	</p>
	</summary>
	<section>
	<title>New Gentoo Linux NVIDIA ebuild install instructions</title>
	<body>
	<p> The NVIDIA kernel driver and GLX ebuild has been upgraded and split
	into two new, more mature ebuilds.  This announcement covers the ebuild
	changes to and explains the installation and upgrade procedures.  </p>

	<p><b>Summary of Changes</b></p>
	<ul>
	<li>The <c>media-gfx/nvidia</c> ebuild was split into two components: <c>media-video/nvidia-kernel</c>
and <c>media-video/nvidia-glx</c>.  This was done to map to the organisation of the drivers
as released by NVIDIA and to ease the kernel upgrade procedure.</li>

<li>The new NVIDIA ebuilds have been moved to a different category, <c>media-video</c>.</li>
<li>The new NVIDIA ebuilds no longer overwrite any of the files installed by xfree86 (<c>x11-base/xfree</c>.)
Instead, everything from the <c>media-video/nvidia-glx</c> package now goes into <c>/opt/nvidia</c>.</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing the new NVIDIA ebuilds</title>
<body>
<ol>
<li>Merge the <c>media-video/nvidia-kernel</c> and <c>media-video/nvidia-glx</c> packages.</li>
<li>Add the following to the <c>Files</c> section of your <path>XF86Config</path> file:
<pre>
      ModulePath  "/opt/nvidia/modules"
      ModulePath  "/usr/X11R6/lib/modules"
</pre>
</li>
<li>If you want the <path>NVdriver</path> kernel module to be loaded automatically
at boot up, add <c>NVdriver</c> to your <path>/etc/modules.autoload</path> file.
</li>
<li>If you had the old <c>media-gfx/nvidia</c> package installed, optionally follow the
instructions to unmerge it and restore any files that it clobbered.</li>
</ol>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Easy post-upgrade cleanup</title>
<body>
<p>If you're just interested in upgrading to the new packages, you can keep your existing installation
as-is.  It should be fine as long as you continue to use the NVIDIA drivers.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Pristine post-upgrade cleanup</title>
<body>
<p>
If you want to restore your <path>/usr/X11R6</path> directory to its original pristine state, follow these instructions:
</p>
<ol>
<li>Unmerge the <c>media-gfx/nvidia</c> port.</li>
<li>Restore the files overwritten by it.  The easiest way to do this
is to remerge <c>x11-base/xfree</c>.</li>
</ol>
</body>
</section>
</news>
