<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<!--$Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/hardened/selinux/index.xml,v 1.36 2006/04/28 03:56:24 pebenito Exp $-->
<project>

<name>SELinux</name>
<longname>SELinux</longname>

<description>
  SELinux is a system of mandatory access controls.  SELinux can enforce
  the security policy over all processes and objects in the system.
</description>

<longdescription>
	This project manages SELinux support in Gentoo.  This includes providing
	kernels with SELinux support, providing patches to userland utilities, writing
	strong Gentoo-specific default profiles, and deploying policies from Portage.
</longdescription>

<goals>
  The intention of the project is to make SELinux available to more users, and
  improving its integration.
  Policy should be available for common daemons, and files merged in from Portage
  should have the correct file context.  Currently we only work on servers, but
  desktops will be supported in the future.
</goals>

<extrachapter position="goals">
<title>What is SELinux?</title>
<section><body>
<p>
  <uri link="http://www.nsa.gov/selinux">Security-Enhanced Linux</uri> (SELinux)
  is a system of mandatory access control using type enforcement and role-based
  access control. It is implemented as a
  <uri link="http://lsm.immunix.org/">Linux Security Module</uri> (LSM).
  In addition to the kernel portion, SELinux consists of a library (libselinux)
  and userland utilities for compiling policy (checkpolicy), and loading policy
  (policycoreutils), in addition to other user programs.
</p>
<p>
  One common misconception is that SELinux is a complete security solution,
  however, it is not.  SELinux only provides one piece of a security
  solution.  It can work well with other Hardened projects, such as PaX,
  for a more complete solution.
</p>
</body></section>
</extrachapter>

<dev role="lead" description="Base policy, x86, PPC, AMD64">pebenito</dev>
<dev description="Portage support, x86, SPARC">method</dev>
<dev description="Daemon policy, x86">kaiowas</dev>

<extraproject name="Base Policy" lead="pebenito">
  SELinux policy for the core system, including users, administrators, and
  daemons in the system profile.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Daemon Policy" lead="kaiowas">
  SELinux policies for common daemons.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="x86" lead="pebenito">
  Support for the x86 architecture.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="PPC" lead="pebenito">
  Support for the PowerPC architecture.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="SPARC" lead="method">
  Support for the SPARC64 architecture.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="AMD64" lead="pebenito">
  Support for the AMD64 (x86-64) architecture.
</extraproject>

<plannedproject name="non-x86 Support">
  Profiles, installation guides, and support for non-x86 architectures.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Desktop">
  SELinux support on destktops.  This involves enhancements to XFree&#39;s
  security, and accompanying policy.
</plannedproject>

<!--
<resource link="http://selinux.dev.gentoo.org">SELinux Demonstration Machine</resource>
-->
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/selinux/selinux-handbook.xml">Gentoo SELinux Handbook</resource>

<extrachapter position="resources">
<title>How Do I Use This?</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
  SELinux can be installed on a new system by following the above install guide.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
  To participate in the SELinux project first join the mailing list at
  <i>gentoo-hardened@gentoo.org</i>. Then ask if there are plans to support
  something that you are interested in, propose a new subproject that you are
  interested in or choose one of the planned subprojects to work on. You may talk
  to the developers and users in the IRC channel <i>#gentoo-hardened</i> on
  <i>irc.freenode.net</i> for more information or just to chat about the project
  or any subprojects. If you don&#39;t have the ability to actively help by
  contributing work we will always need testers to use and audit the SELinux
  policies. All development, testing, feedback, and productive comments will
  be greatly appreciated.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section><title>Policy Submissions</title>
<body>
<p>
  The critical component of a SELinux system is having a strong policy.  The
  team does its best to support as many daemons as possible.  However, we cannot
  create policies for daemons with which we are unfamiliar.  But we are happy
  to receive policy submissions for consideration.  There are a few requirements:
</p>
<ul>
<li>
  Make comments (in the policy and/or bug), so we can understand changes
  from the NSA example policy.
</li>
<li>
  The policy should cover common installations.  Please do not submit policies
  for odd or nonstandard daemon configurations.
</li>
<li>
  We need to know if the policy is dependent on another policy (for example
  rpcd is dependent on portmap) other than base-policy.
</li>
<li>
  An ebuild for the policy can also be submitted to help the developers
  integrate the policy into Portage more quickly, if it is accepted.  
  See current daemon policies in Portage for example uses of the
  selinux-policy eclass.
</li>
</ul>
<p>
  The policy should be submitted on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/">bugzilla</uri>.
  Please attach the .te and .fc files separately to the bug, not as a tarball.
  The bug should be assigned to <c>selinux@gentoo.org</c>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
