<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/sound/alsa.xml,v 1.1 2005/11/21 00:12:34 flameeyes Exp $ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/desktop/sound/alsa.xml" lang="en">
<title>ALSA package maintenance</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="flameeyes@gentoo.org">Diego Pettenò</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Guide to maintenance of ALSA drivers and ALSA packages, to help new maintainers
to know the catch ups in its packages.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2005-11-21</date>

<chapter> <!-- Advanced Linux Sound Architecture -->
<title>Advanced Linux Sound Architecture</title>

<section> <!-- Introduction -->
<title>Introduction</title>

<body>

<p>
ALSA is the "next generation" sound drivers suite for Linux, that supersedes the
old OSS (Open Sound System) drivers. The ALSA drivers are provided by kernels
2.6 inside the kernel's sources and are available as external package for those
who are still running 2.4 series kernels. The external package can be used with
2.6 kernels, too, and allows to run a different version of ALSA drivers than the
one shipped with the current kernel.
</p>

<p>
This guide is being wrote to help developers interested in maintenance of ALSA
related packages, as they might be tricky, and it's always useful to know a few
things that are not in the official documentation. It also shows the reasons why
the external ALSA drivers package can't be dropped for 2.6 kernels.
</p>

<p>
Expansion of this guide is really welcome as it might be a bit tricky sometimes
as details are often forgotten until you really need to remember them.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section> <!-- Resources -->
<title>Resources</title>

<body>

<p>
It's important to know the resources that might be needed to get ALSA right, as
there can be lot of problems that might require one to dig through many
different sites and mailing lists.
</p>

<p>
The first important resource is, obviously, the main
<uri link="http://www.alsa-project.org">ALSA Project homepage</uri>. You can
find there a list of latest news with changelog for different version and a
simple box with latest releases for stable and development packages. As you'll
see later, sometimes development releases are needed to go in ~arch or even on
stable trees, depending on the kernel version used in those trees.
</p>

<p>
As many other projects, ALSA project has a <uri link="https://bugtrack.alsa-project.org/alsa-bug/main_page.php">bugtracker</uri>,
but that might be a bit difficult to get a hold of, as it's a Mantis tracker
instead of the more common Bugzilla. It's important to note the selector on
top right of the screen: if you select something there you mask all the other
projects' bug and looking for or reporting bugs becomes an hell.
</p>

<p>
Other important resources are the mailing list. ALSA project have different
mailing lists, but the main ones you need to subscribe if you're interested in
maintaining ALSA related packages are <c>alsa-announce</c> and
<c>alsa-devel</c>. You might also want to take a look to
<uri link="http://lkml.org">lkml</uri>, as ALSA drivers are also developed as
part of 2.6 series kernel.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section> <!-- The packages -->
<title>The packages</title>

<body>

<p>
ALSA support in Linux is provided by a list of different packages; most of them
are just ebuilds for upstream's packages, while <c>alsa-headers</c> is a simple
ebuild that installs the headers for <c>alsa-driver</c> upstream package, this
way the actual drivers are installed by themselves and can be installed within
the kernel without having problems with <c>alsa-lib</c> not finding the right
headers.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>

<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; -->
