<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/sound/decibel.xml,v 1.12 2014/09/05 18:18:25 creffett Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Sound/Decibel_Audio_Player_Mini-installation_Guide">
<title>Decibel Audio Player</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This page contains the installation instructions for Decibel, a gtk+ audio
player.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>11</version>
<date>2011-09-22</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>What's Decibel?</title>
<body>

<p>
From the <uri link="http://decibel.silent-blade.org/">homepage</uri>: Decibel
Audio Player is a GTK+ open-source (GPL license) audio player designed for
GNU/Linux, which aims at being very straightforward to use by means of a very
clean and user friendly interface. It is especially targeted at Gnome and will
follow as closely as possible the Gnome HIG.
</p>

<p>
Decibel is a nifty, simple little app. It has as much playback functionality as
you want it to have. It's not an audio Swiss Army knife; for that, take a look
at Banshee, Exaile, or Amarok. It's intended for easy browsing and playing of
your music collection. It supports several audio formats and CD playback, and
can keep track of several different music library locations. (A nice improvement
over other audio applications that track only one library).
</p>

<p>
Decibel mostly uses Python, gtk+, and gstreamer. It also needs a few Gnome
libraries to handle the Gnome keyring for Last.fm integration. It should still
be lightweight even if you don't use Gnome. If you <e>do</e> use Gnome, it will
be fully integrated into your desktop.
</p>

<p>
Decibel has optional additional runtime integration with various Gnome libraries
such as gnome-applets, gnome-media, and a few others. More on this later.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Installation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
First, let's take a look at the available USE flags. Since Decibel uses the
modular gstreamer framework, you can choose the kinds of audio formats you want
to be able to play. Decibel currently supports WMA (via ffmpeg), mp4 (aac), mp3,
mp2, ac3, APE, FLAC, Musepack, WavPack, and Ogg Vorbis.
</p>

<p>
Here are the USE flags available for the Decibel ebuild:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>USE flag</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>aac</ti>
  <ti>Enables support for MPEG-4 AAC audio (mp4)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>cdda</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for CD audio playback and lookups via CDDB</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>gnome</ti>
  <ti>
    Adds Gnome media keys support, so you can control Decibel using hotkeys
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>gnome-keyring</ti>
  <ti>Uses <c>gnome-keyring</c> to store your Last.fm and Twitter passwords</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>libnotify</ti>
  <ti>
    Enables desktop notification on track change. You'll get a customizable
    popup window.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>musepack</ti>
  <ti>Enables support for the Musepack audio (mpc)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>wavpack</ti>
  <ti>Enables support for WavPack audio (wv)</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Decibel's ebuild depends on <c>gst-plugins-meta</c>, a metapackage that provides
most of the audio codecs. You can add support for the desired codec by
activating the appropriate USE flag for <c>gst-plugins-meta</c>:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>USE flag</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>a52</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for ac3 playback, a common DVD audio format</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ffmpeg</ti>
  <ti>
    Adds support for audio formats that use the ASF container, such as
    Windows Media Audio (WMA)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>flac</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for FLAC: Free Lossless Audio Codec</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>mp3</ti>
  <ti>
    Adds support for mp3 playback via MAD, a high quality decoder library
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>mpeg</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for mp2 playback</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>vorbis</ti>
  <ti>Adds support for Ogg Vorbis audio (ogg)</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
You can set your desired USE flags globally in <path>/etc/make.conf</path>, or
locally in <path>/etc/portage/package.use</path>. For example, to enable support
for everything but Musepack, you could do the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Setting USE flags in package.use">
# <i>echo "media-plugins/gst-plugins-meta ffmpeg flac mp3 vorbis" >> /etc/portage/package.use</i>
# <i>echo "media-sound/decibel-audio-player -musepack aac cdda gnome-keyring libnotify" >> /etc/portage/package.use"</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once your flags are set, install Decibel:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing Decibel">
# <i>emerge -avt decibel-audio-player</i>
</pre>

<p>
One thing Decibel <e>doesn't</e> do is edit tags. Its creators believe such
functionality is best provided by dedicated tag editing applications. Remember,
Decibel focuses on being a <e>real</e> audio player focused on playback. There
are <uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org">plenty of other tagging apps</uri>
available, such as <uri
link="http://pwp.netcabo.pt/paol/tagtool">TagTool</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Decibel has a couple of commandline switches you may want to use.
<c>decibel-audio-player --no-glossy-cover</c> removes the shiny effect overlayed
on album covers, which can make them hard to see. The <c>-p</c> switch uses the
playbin2 GStreamer component to play files. This adds support for ReplayGain and
gapless playback. You can view the other commandline switches by running
<c>decibel-audio-player --help</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Decibel is new, exciting, and going places, so stay on top of it! Here are a few
links to get you started:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The <uri link="http://decibel.silent-blade.org/">Decibel Audio Player</uri>
    homepage. Screenshots, instructions, downloads, and more.
  </li>
  <li>
    Decibel's <uri link="https://launchpad.net/decibel-audio-player">bug
    tracker</uri>. If you find bugs <e>in the program itself</e>, report them
    here. The bug tracker is also the best way to make feature requests and stay
    on top of development.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
