<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/sound/xmms.xml,v 1.5 2014/09/05 18:18:25 creffett Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide lang="en" disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Sound/The_How_and_Why_of_XMMS_Removal">

<title>The How and Why of XMMS removal</title>

<author title="Author">
    <mail link="kopp@gentoo-userreps.org">Bertrand Coppa</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
    <mail link="amne@gentoo.org">Wernfried Haas</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
    <mail link="nattfodd@gentoo.org">Alexandre Buisse</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
    This webpage explains the removal of XMMS from the Portage tree and gives
    some hints on how to deal with it.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-10-29</date>

<chapter>
  <title>Why remove XMMS?</title>
  <section>
    <body>
      <p> There has been a lot of fuss last week following the hardmasking of
          XMMS and the packages depending on it for a future removal from the tree. A lot
          of flames went on Gentoo's bugzilla and forums, with conspiracy theories,
          shameful insults etc. The truth is the decision of removing it from the tree
          was taken after a lot of debate between Gentoo developers and users and it is
          for the better, despite the fact that a lot of us liked XMMS.</p> 

      <p>XMMS has been around for a very long time and was used by a lot of people.
          Unfortunately, upstream developement stopped a long time ago and it became
          broken over time. Gentoo developers had to maintain it and deal with the bad
          design. As of late, nobody took care of it and bugs began to accumulate,
          topping over 30 unresolved bugs. Furthermore, it depended on GTK+ version 1
          which is old, broken with no support of UTF-8 and isn't supported anymore by
          upstream either.</p>

      <p>Metalgod, the current maintainer, decided to step down as XMMS was beyond
          repair down and since nobody wanted to undertake the massive work, it was
          decided that support will be dropped in the main Portage tree since Gentoo
          obviously can't afford to offer unmaintained packages.</p>
  </body>
  </section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Alternatives</title>
  <section>
      <body>
<ul>
<li><b>Audacious</b> is a XMMS look-alike written in GTK 2. It supports XMMS
skins but does not behave exactly like XMMS. Several plugins are available like
audacious-docklet that displays an icon in the systemtray, audtty that allows
you to control audacious in the command line, audacious-crossfade that allows
continuous output and crossfading and a lot more to come or already available.
There is a <uri
link="https://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-510532.html">thread</uri> on the
forums where you can request plugin ports.</li>

<li><b>MPD</b>: Music Player Deamon is another good player which uses a
client/server architecture. You can even launch it at start-up and have music
playing before you get on your desktop. It has a lot of clients and obviously,
there are some that don't require X, like ncmpc which is ncurses-based.</li>

<li><b>Amarok</b>: the well-known full-featured player, considered by many as
the best player available. Amarok was initially designed for KDE and does
almost everything, except dishes.</li>

<li><b>Rhythmbox</b>: Rhythmbox plays in the same category as Amarok but is
designed for Gnome. Both are comparable to iTunes.</li>

<li><b>Banshee</b>: Banshee is also in the category of heavyweight audio
players. There are lots of plugins available and under development. It uses
Mono.</li>

<li><b>Muine</b>: A simple music player for Gnome that runs upon mono
framework. It has a simple interface and supports plugins.</li>

<li><b>Listen</b>: Listen is promising audio player, also heavyweight. It is
also designed for Gnome. It doesn't do dishes either.</li>

<li><b>mpg123</b>: Another category here. mpg123 is a CLI player for those of
you that do not like graphical interfaces or do not have access to it at the
moment.</li>

<li><b>Quod Libet</b>: A GTK+2 based music player written in python. It is full
featured and even has built-in tag editing. There are a number of plugins
available to add additional functionality.</li>

</ul> 

<p>If you really can't part from XMMS, you can still keep the ebuilds in an
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-x86.xml?part=3&amp;chap=5">overlay</uri>.</p>

</body> 
</section> 
</chapter>

<chapter>
    <title>Removing XMMS</title>
    <section>
        <body>
            <p>
                To cleanly remove XMMS from your system, follow this procedure:
            </p>

<ul><li>Check in <c>/etc/make.conf</c> and <c>/etc/portage/package.use</c> that
the xmms USE isn't enabled. If it is, remove it. The command <c>grep xmms
/etc/make.conf /etc/portage/package.use</c> shouldn't return anything.</li>

<li>Sync your portage tree with <c>emerge --sync</c></li>

<li>Unmerge xmms and all plugins. To get a list, you can for instance use <c>equery -qc list xmms -i</c>. You can then check this list against what <c>grep xmms /usr/portage/profiles/package.mask</c> says.</li>

<li>Rebuild your tree without the xmms USE flag : <c>emerge -auvDN world</c></li></ul>

        </body>
    </section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Developers views</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Here are links to some developers' blogs which are relevant:
</p>
<ul><li><uri link="http://farragut.flameeyes.is-a-geek.org/articles/2006/10/23/my-personal-birthday-present">Flameeyes</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/seemant/2006/10/27/on_masking_popular_packages_xmms">Seemant</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/metalgod/2006/10/29/xmms_final_thoughts">Metalgod</uri></li></ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Farewell</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>After years of using xmms, now it is time to return the goodbye issued on
the <uri link="http://xmms.org">xmms homepage</uri> - thanks to the xmms team
for bringing a nice piece of software, and goodbye old sailor. :-)</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>

