<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/forums/translations.xml,v 1.1 2006/04/08 12:06:27 tomk Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/forums/translations.xml">
<title>Gentoo Forums Translator Guidelines</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tomk@gentoo.org">Tom Knight</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
This guide is for people helping out with forums translations
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-04-07</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>Targeted Audience</title>
<body>

<p>
The aim of this guide is to provide the basic guidelines to anyone working
on translations for the forums. This includes those with direct CVS access
as well as people who don't. Detailed instructions are provided for both
groups.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reasons for Translations</title>
<body>

<p>
When new features are released to the Gentoo Forums, either by Gentoo or by
phpBB, new phrases and words are added. Typically they are added to the
English language pack only, this means that anyone using a different
language pack will see these phrases in English. The supported languages are
listed below.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Chinese (simplified)</li>
  <li>Chinese (traditional)</li>
  <li>Danish</li>
  <li>Dutch</li>
  <li>Esperanto</li>
  <li>Finnish</li>
  <li>French</li>
  <li>German</li>
  <li>Greek</li>
  <li>Italian</li>
  <li>Norwegian</li>
  <li>Polish</li>
  <li>Portuguese</li>
  <li>Russian</li>
  <li>Spanish</li>
  <li>Swedish</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Translator Guidelines</title>
<section>
<title>File Structure</title>
<body>

<p>
The files to be translated reside within the
<path>gentoo-projects/forums/translations</path> CVS directory, in this
directory you will find subdirectories for each supported language. In each
language directory there is a <path>README</path> containing instructions as
well as the files that need translating, the main one being
<path>lang_extra.php</path>. This file is where most of the new phrases will
be added.
</p>

<p>
The files will usually be php files where it's important to keep the
syntactical structure in place. Only the textual strings should be
translated. Any other code structures should be kept in place, including code
within those strings. Comments (anything after a # or //) can optionally be
translated. The line-wrapping used in these files should also be preserved.
</p>

<p>
So in the following example only the string '%sThis%s is an example' should be
translated, ensuring that the %s are kept in place.
</p>

<pre caption="Translation example">
<var>$lang['Example']</var> = <const>'%sThis%s is an example'</const>; <comment>// this is a comment</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CVS</title>
<body>

<p> 
If you are a Gentoo Developer/Staff/Translator then you can be added to the
cvsforumtrans group on cvs.gentoo.org so that you have write access to
the <path>translations</path> directory. This will give you full
access to commit translations. Instructions for getting started with CVS can
be found in the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/cvs-tutorial.xml">Gentoo Linux CVS
Tutorial</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Use the following instructions for working with the translations CVS.
</p>

<pre caption="CVS instructions">
<i>cvs co gentoo-projects/forums/translations</i>
<comment>(Edit the relevant files)</comment>
<i>cd gentoo-projects/forums/translations/$LANGUAGE</i>
<i>$EDITOR lang_extra.php</i>
<comment>(Always make sure you update before committing)</comment>
<i>cvs up</i>
<i>cvs ci -m "Added translations for $LANGUAGE"</i>
</pre>

<impo>
Always make sure you use the right character encoding for the files, the
encoding is shown in the README.
</impo>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Working Without CVS Access</title>
<body>

<p> 
If you don't have CVS access you can still help out with the translations. 
You will need to add your diffs to <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo's 
Bugzilla</uri> then someone with CVS access will check them in. You can 
download the files to be translated using
<uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/forums/translations/?root=gentoo-projects">Gentoo's
ViewCVS</uri>. Make sure you make a note of the revision number of the
file downloaded. Once you've made your translations you need to
create a diff.
</p>

<pre caption="Create a diff">
<i>diff -u original_file.php translated_file.php &gt; file_name.php.diff</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once you've created the diff you need to create a bug report. Make sure
you use the Gentoo Infrastructure product and the Forums component. The summary
should be in the format &quot;[language] Translation for file_name.php&quot;.
In the report you should specify which CVS revision number this is a diff
against. Once you've created the bug report you should add your diff as an
attachment.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Testing &amp; Deployment</title>
<section>
<title>Testing Translations</title>
<body>

<p>
The translations are kept separate from the code that is deployed onto the
forums. When you've added a translation you can request that someone with
the right access adds the files to our <uri
link="https://forumstest.gentoo.org">test server</uri>. You will be able to
find someone to do this in the #gentoo-forums channel on irc.freenode.net. You
will also be given the username and password needed to access the test server.
The test server is used to test new features and bug fixes so sometimes things
may not always work correctly.
</p>

<note>
All translations must be tested before they can be deployed onto the forums.
</note>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Deployment</title>
<body>

<p>
Once the translations have been tested they will be ready for deployment
onto the forums. This will happen during the normal release cycle and they
will go live the next time the forums are upgraded, which is usually when we
have new features to be released.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-forum-translations@gentoo.org</title>
<body>

<p>
This mailing list has been set up to help coordinate the translation
efforts. If you have any questions about the translations or the processes
used please use this list. To subscribe send an empty email to:
</p>

<p>
<c>gentoo-forum-translations+subscribe@gentoo.org</c>
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>IRC - #gentoo-forums</title>
<body>

<p>
If you need any help with testing and deployment of the translations you can
get hold of a <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/forums/index.xml#doc_chap3">Forums
Administrator</uri> in the #gentoo-forums channel on irc.freenode.net.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Forums Test Server</title>
<body>

<p>
A <uri link="https://forumstest.gentoo.org/">test server</uri> is available for
you to test your translations. This server is password protected, the 
username/password will be supplied to you when you need it. This server's
database is a snapshot of the live Forum and is not always up to date.
If you do not have an account on this server please contact a <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/forums/index.xml#doc_chap3">Forums
Administrator</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
