<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Summer of Code application guide</title>
<author>antarus</author>
<abstract>This guide is intended to be read by anyone who is interested
in applying to Gentoo in the Google Summer of Code.  Interested students
need not be Gentoo developers; anyone who meets the eligibility requirements of
Google is encouraged to apply.
</abstract>
<version>1.5</version>
<date>2012-04-08</date>
<chapter>
<title>Applying as a student</title>
<section>
<title>Communication</title>
<body>
<p>Students interested in applying to do a project for Gentoo should join
#gentoo-soc on irc.freenode.net and the gentoo-soc mailing list.
Announcements related to Gentoo's Summer of Code effort will be relayed to both
places</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>What interested students need to do</title>
<section>
<title>Get feedback on your idea</title>
<body>
<p>
Students interested in applying to do a project for Gentoo should review 
the <uri 
link="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Google_Summer_of_Code/2013/Ideas">projects</uri>. 
Each project should have a potential mentor listed, who you should 
contact to discuss your idea before applying. You are free to apply for 
a project that is not on our list.  In either case, once you have an 
idea of what you want to work on, find a potential mentor to discuss it 
with. The gentoo-soc mailing list, #gentoo-soc on irc.freenode.net or 
any of the listed mentors on the <uri 
link="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Google_Summer_of_Code/2013/Ideas">ideas 
page</uri> should be able to provide feedback.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Write a proposal</title>
<body>
<p>Students should author a proposal that attempts to convince Gentoo why
their project should be chosen over other competing proposals.  A few sentences
is not sufficient in most cases to sway anyone.
</p>
<ol>
  <li><b>Abstract</b> - What does the project do; try to keep this section to one
  paragraph.  It should not be an in depth analysis but is helpful when
  someone desires an overview of the project.</li>
  <li><b>Objective</b> - What problem does the project solve.  This does not need to
  be a long section.  Generally software tries to help make people more
  efficient, or foster communication, or entertain folks.  Any proposed
  software should have a purpose and applicants should define that purpose
  here.</li>
  <li><b>Deliverables</b> - What will the project consist of when it is finished?
  Source code, documentation, a build system, libraries, binaries; these should
  all be enumerated in your proposal.  Without a concrete set of deliverables
  it is difficult to judge if a student finished their proposal.  If it is
  difficult to judge if the proposal was finished, it is difficult to pay for
  the work as well.</li>
  <li><b>Timeline</b> - When will the deliverables be done?  This is <b>very</b>
  important for the mid-term evaluation as the mentor has to determine if a
  given student has made enough progress to award them money.  A student should
  strive to make this as easy for the mentor as possible by providing a bar
  to be measured by and then meeting that bar.  A student should be careful to
  make good judgements in time costs and if the student slips behind he/she
  should alert their mentor to this fact and explain why the estimates were
  wrong. Your timeline should be at a level of detail of one work item 
  every 1-2 weeks</li>
  <li><b>Biography</b> - The student should talk about themselves: where they are from
  what they like to study, what they do in their free time, etc.  Part of this
  contest is to make new friends and learn about each other and this is an
  important part of that goal.  This section should include things like previous
  jobs, internships, and any educational experience an applicant may have.  This
  section is also intended to promote oneself and convince Gentoo that we should
  chose a given student over other applicants.</li>
</ol>
<p>
For Gentoo, the coding period should not explicitly include time to 
learn, research, investigate, etc. Your initial research should be done 
before writing the proposal, to convince us that you know enough about 
your project to understand it and complete it successfully. If further 
dedicated time for research/learning is required, it should happen 
during the community-bonding period, which comes before the coding 
period.
</p>
<p>
We understand that sometimes implementations cannot match the proposal, 
and further experimentation and research may be necessary while 
implementing any given week's work, but this falls under the time for 
the implementation itself rather than devoting a week to research.
</p>
<p>We highly recommend having some initial discussion with one of the mentors about
your proposal before you submit it.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Submitting your proposal</title>
<body>
<p>Next, you must submit the proposal to the Google program site. Google provides
<uri
link="http://en.flossmanuals.net/melange/students-students-application-phase/">documentation
for this process</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
