<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Summer of Code ideas</title>
<author>dberkholz</author>
<abstract>This guide is intended to be read by anyone who is interested
in applying to Gentoo in the Google Summer of Code.  Interested students
need not be Gentoo developers; anyone who meets the eligibility requirements of
Google is encouraged to apply.
</abstract>
<version>1.0</version>
<date>2011-03-19</date>
<chapter>
<title>Read this first</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
<b>Most ideas listed here have a contact person associated with them. Please
get in touch with them earlier rather than later to develop your idea into a
complete application.</b> You can find many of them on Freenode's IRC network
under the same username. If there is no contact information, please join the
gentoo-soc mailing list or #gentoo-soc on the Freenode IRC network, and we
will work with you to find a mentor and discuss your idea.
</p>

<p>
You don't have to apply for one of these ideas! You can come up with your own,
and as long as it fits into Gentoo, we'll be happy to work with you to develop
it. Remember, your project needs to have deliverables in less than 3 months of
<b>full-time</b> work. Be ambitious but not too ambitious ;)
</p>

<p>
<b>Applications are not yet open</b> — the earlier the better, but don't rush
through it! We have a custom application template that we will ask you to fill
out. Here it is:
</p>

<p>
<b>Congratulations on applying for a project with Gentoo!</b> To improve your
chances of succeeding with this project, we want to make sure you're
sufficiently prepared to invest a full summer's worth of time on it. <b>In
addition to the usual application, there are 2 specific actions and 1 piece of
info we would like to see from you:</b>
</p>

<ul>
<li>
<b>Use the tools that you will use in your project to make changes to code</b>
(e.g., source code management [SCM] software such as CVS, Subversion, or
git). Please use the same SCM as you will use for your project to check out
one of our repositories (more repositories), make a change to it, and post
that change as a patch on a mailing list or bug. Please fix a real bug
reported in Bugzilla to show that you can use the tools to make a meaningful
change; your mentor can help you identify a good one. Your contact in Gentoo
can help you determine which SCM and repository you should use for this. If
your idea doesn't have a contact, please get in touch with us on the
gentoo-soc mailing list or in real-time on IRC at Freenode/#gentoo-soc. Once
you've made your change, link to it from your application.
</li>
<li>
<b>Participate in our development community.</b> Please make a post to one of
our mailing lists and link to it from your application (archives.gentoo.org
holds past postings). The gentoo-soc list would be a good starting point, if
you aren't subscribed to any others already. The best posts would be an
introduction of the project you're applying for and a little background about
you, to introduce yourself to the community and get some broader input about
your project.
</li>
<li>
<b>Give us your contact info and working hours.</b> Please provide your email
address, home mailing address, and phone number. This is a requirement and
provides for accountability on both your side and ours. Also, please tell us
what hours you will be working and responsive to contact via email and IRC;
these should sum to at least 35 hours a week.
</li>
</ul>

<p>
These actions are things you will do extremely commonly as an open-source developer, and they really aren't that hard, so don't let them hold you back! The remainder of the application is free-form. Please read our application guidelines and Google's FAQ to complete it. Good luck!
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Ideas</title>
<section>
<title>libbash runtime</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Ebuild QA checks based on libbash AST</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Kernel Security issue handling/notifications</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Package statistics reporting tool</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Porthole plug-ins and extensions</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Support for Fortran modules/libraries with multiple compilers</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Virtual Machine Builder (website or desktop client)</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Porthole backend re-structure</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>gentoo-x86 QA website</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Add "tags" support to Portage</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Add "mnemonic names" to Packages in metadata.xml</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Fastboot on Gentoo</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Systemd/Upstart on Gentoo</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Cache sync</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Improved binary package support</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>User Generated Content for Portage packages</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Automated numerical libraries benchmark suite</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>SCM snapshot management infrastructure</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>EBuild generator</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Maven integration</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo/Java IDE integration</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Rewrite java-config in C++ or python</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Web interface for submitting Documentation changes</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Package Manager Specification (PMS) compliance test suite</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Repository of self-contained ebuild source packages</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Make the clustering LiveCD from a previous GSoC bootable from USB</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>OpenBSD port of Gentoo</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Glendix: Create a lean distro based on Gentoo and Plan 9 (Glentoo?)</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Provide Gentoo 11 LiveDVDs with Anaconda installer</title>
<body>
<p>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
