<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>soc</name>
<longname>Gentoo Summer of Code</longname>
<date>2007-03-16</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="nattfodd@gentoo.org">Alexandre Buisse</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="gerrynjr@gentoo.org">Gerald J. Normandin Jr.</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="beandog@gentoo.org">Steve Dibb</mail>
</author>
<author title="Reviewer">
  <mail link="dberkholz@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholz</mail>
</author>

<description>
The Gentoo Summer of Code subproject oversees Gentoo's participation in the
annual Google Summer of Code program.</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
For the third year running, Google is organising a 
<uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/">Summer of Code</uri>, funding students
to work on open-source projects over the summer. This year, Gentoo is participating
as a mentoring organisation.
</p>

</longdescription>

<dev role="Lead">christel</dev>
<dev role="Member">antarus</dev>
<dev role="Member">eroyf</dev>
<dev role="Member">pioto</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Project Ideas</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As of yet Gentoo is unaware of how many slots have been allocated.
Some project ideas are below:
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Project</th>
    <th>Details</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>equizApp</ti>
    <ti>Create a system that allows Gentoo recruiters and developers
        to submit questions into a database.  The questions should be
        categorized by subject.  This system should also allow a user
        to create a quiz from the set of questions and the user should
        be able to specify how many questions per category.  The system
        should also store the answers to each question and hide them when
        generating a quiz.  The system may optionally support a voting or
        reporting mechanism such that people can report bad questions.</ti>
	</tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/scire">SCIRE</uri></ti>
    <ti>The Scire project aims to create a widely extensible common 
        portal for administrative tasks for multiple Linux client machines.
        Common tasks will include updating software, installing software,
        customizing configuration files, and running scripts. The goal 
        of Scire is to make administration of massive networks of Linux 
        machines easy on administrators.  The project has large goals so
        applicants would be advised to focus on a specific subsystem to
        develop for the SoC.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>CVS Code Review</ti>
    <ti>This project involves implemented a code review system for cvs.
        The workflow would be: User tries to make a commit, a cvs pre-commit
        script examines the commit and must uniquely identify it (difficult).
        Once uniquely identified; the commit must be checked in a data store
        to see if it is already approved.  If it has been approved previously
        then the commit succeeds.  Otherwise the commit fails and mail is sent
        to zero or more 'interested parties'.  The project should include some
        sort of script or application to approve commits.  The project may also
        need to include a webGUI to track commits and approvals and whatnot;
        depending on how difficult the rest of the project becomes.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Improved Bugs Reporting Form</ti>
    <ti>Improve upon Gentoo's Bugzilla (either within bugzilla or externally)
        to get better metrics per CP(V).  Have some sort of AJAX lookup for 
        real CPV's.  Store the CPV per bug (how to do bugs w/multiple CPVs?).
        This lets us harvest bug information better because we can bind CPV's
        to bugs.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Integration of LVM/EVMS into the Gentoo Linux Installer</ti>
    <ti>Make it possible to use LVM or EVMS while installing Gentoo with
        the GLI.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Expand Python Eclasses to build for multiple python versions.</ti>
    <ti>Build python applications against multiple (installed) versions of
        python.  Assume the user has python2.4 and python2.5 and they install
        a python app; the app should build against both versions, not just
        the highest one.</ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<!--
<extrachapter>
<title>Mentors for Summer of Code 2006</title>
<section>
<body>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Developer</th>
    <th>E-mail</th>
    <th>Projects</th>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Students for Summer of Code 2006</title>
<section>
<body>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Student</th>
    <th>E-mail</th>
    <th>Project</th>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
-->

<!--
<extrachapter>
<title>Planet Gentoo</title>
<section>
<body>
  
<p>
Planet Gentoo has setup an RSS feed and website for the Summer of Code
bloggers. The website is available at <uri>http://planet.gentoo.org/soc</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
-->

</project>

