<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>soc</name>
<longname>Gentoo Summer of Code</longname>
<date>2007-03-16</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="christel@gentoo.org">Christel Dahlskjaer</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="codeman@gentoo.org">Preston Cody</mail>
</author>

<description>
The Gentoo Summer of Code subproject oversees Gentoo's participation in the
annual Google Summer of Code program.</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
For the third year running, Google is organising a 
<uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/">Summer of Code</uri>, funding students
to work on open-source projects over the summer. This year, Gentoo is participating
as a mentoring organisation.
</p>

</longdescription>

<dev role="Lead">christel</dev>
<dev role="Member">antarus</dev>
<dev role="Member">eroyf</dev>
<dev role="Member">pioto</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Project Ideas</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As of yet Gentoo is unaware of how many slots have been allocated.
Some project ideas are below:
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Project</th>
    <th>Details</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>equizApp</ti>
    <ti>Create a system that allows Gentoo recruiters and developers
        to submit questions into a database.  The questions should be
        categorized by subject.  This system should also allow a user
        to create a quiz from the set of questions and the user should
        be able to specify how many questions per category.  The system
        should also store the answers to each question and hide them when
        generating a quiz.  The system may optionally support a voting or
        reporting mechanism such that people can report bad questions.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
	<ti><uri link="/proj/en/java">Java Configuration tool</uri></ti>
	<ti>Create an application that is a GUI for what java-config and eselect
		java-nsplugin currently offer. If this is written in Java it can 
		for example use jython to interface with java-config that is written
		in python. Besides offering a GUI for current configuration options
		the application should be able to configure used JDK and options on
		a per application launcher basis.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
	<ti><uri link="/proj/en/java">Unify FOSS Java VM handling in Gentoo</uri></ti>
	<ti>This project involves creating eclass functions for setupping a JDK
        around packages like dev-java/cacao and dev-java/jamvm. As there are
        multiple choices for for example javadoc implementations the student
		should also come up with configuration tools by for example extending
		java-config. As part of this project the FOSS Java stack should be
		tested to compile everything Java that Gentoo has to offer.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
	<ti><uri link="/proj/en/java">Integrate Maven into Gentoo</uri></ti>
	<ti>Currently maven can't be used in ebuilds because it downloads dependencies
		from the network. JPackage has patches to make maven integrate into
		rpm based distributions. As part of this project you will port these
		patches into Gentoo and develop eclass functions needed to easily write
		ebuilds that use maven as the build system and follow Gentoo Java policies.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
	<ti><uri link="/proj/en/java">Java binary package repository</uri></ti>
	<ti>Due to the nature of Java it should be possible to setup a Gentoo binary
		Java package repository. This project involves developing the necessary tools
		to automatically keep this repository up2date and initially setting it up.
    </ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/scire">SCIRE</uri></ti>
    <ti>The Scire project aims to create a widely extensible common 
        portal for administrative tasks for multiple Linux client machines.
        Common tasks will include updating software, installing software,
        customizing configuration files, and running scripts. The goal 
        of Scire is to make administration of massive networks of Linux 
        machines easy on administrators.  The project has large goals so
        applicants would be advised to focus on a specific subsystem to
        develop for the SoC.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>CVS Code Review</ti>
    <ti>This project involves implemented a code review system for cvs.
        The workflow would be: User tries to make a commit, a cvs pre-commit
        script examines the commit and must uniquely identify it (difficult).
        Once uniquely identified; the commit must be checked in a data store
        to see if it is already approved.  If it has been approved previously
        then the commit succeeds.  Otherwise the commit fails and mail is sent
        to zero or more 'interested parties'.  The project should include some
        sort of script or application to approve commits.  The project may also
        need to include a webGUI to track commits and approvals and whatnot;
        depending on how difficult the rest of the project becomes.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Improved Bugs Reporting Form</ti>
    <ti>Improve upon Gentoo's Bugzilla (either within bugzilla or externally)
        to get better metrics per CP(V).  Have some sort of AJAX lookup for 
        real CPV's.  Store the CPV per bug (how to do bugs w/multiple CPVs?).
        This lets us harvest bug information better because we can bind CPV's
        to bugs.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Integration of LVM/EVMS into the Gentoo Linux Installer</ti>
    <ti>Make it possible to use LVM or EVMS while installing Gentoo with
        the GLI.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Paludis Ebuild Development Tool</ti>
    <ti>Paludis needs a tool to aid in ebuild development.  It could
        be similar in scope to the portage 'ebuild' tool or the pkgcore
        'pebuild' tool.  However it doesn't have to conform to either
        tool and could very well be something different (yet equally
        or more useful).</ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>


<extrachapter>
<title>Mentors for Summer of Code 2007</title>
<section>
<body>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Developer</th>
    <th>E-mail</th>
    <th>Projects</th>
  </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Alec Warner</ti>
    <ti>antarus@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Alexander Faeroy</ti>
    <ti>eroyf@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Christel Dahlskjaer</ti>
    <ti>christel@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Denny Van Dyk</ti>
    <ti>kugelfang@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Dimity Bradt</ti>
    <ti>diox@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Grant Goodyear</ti>
    <ti>g2boojum@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Markus Ullman</ti>
    <ti>jokey@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Matt Disney</ti>
    <ti>mdisney@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Mike Kelly</ti>
    <ti>pioto@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Patrick McLean</ti>
    <ti>chutzpah@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Preston Cody</ti>
    <ti>codeman@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Stephen Bennett</ti>
    <ti>spb@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Steve Dibb</ti>
    <ti>beandog@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

   <tr>
    <ti>Xavier M.G Neys</ti>
    <ti>neysx@gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti></ti>
   </tr>

</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<!--
<extrachapter>
<title>Students for Summer of Code 2006</title>
<section>
<body>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Student</th>
    <th>E-mail</th>
    <th>Project</th>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
-->

<!--
<extrachapter>
<title>Planet Gentoo</title>
<section>
<body>
  
<p>
Planet Gentoo has setup an RSS feed and website for the Summer of Code
bloggers. The website is available at <uri>http://planet.gentoo.org/soc</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
-->

</project>

