<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>soc</name>
<longname>Gentoo Summer of Code</longname>
<date>2008-02-27</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="christel@gentoo.org">Christel Dahlskjaer</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="codeman@gentoo.org">Preston Cody</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tsunam@gentoo.org">Joshua Jackson</mail>
</author>

<description>
The Gentoo Summer of Code subproject oversees Gentoo's participation in the
annual Google Summer of Code program.</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
For the fourth year running, Google is organising a 
<uri link="http://code.google.com/soc/">Summer of Code</uri>, funding students
to work on open-source projects over the summer. Applications for mentoring organizations start soon and Gentoo is hoping to be accepted once again.
</p>

</longdescription>

<dev role="Lead">tsunam</dev>
<dev role="Member">g2boojum</dev>
<dev role="Member">antarus</dev>
<dev role="Member">jmbsvicetto</dev>
<dev role="Member">mark_alec</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Project Ideas</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As of yet Gentoo is unaware of how many slots have been allocated.
Some project ideas are below:
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Project</th>
    <th>Details</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Sandbox improvements</ti>
    <ti>Since Martin (azarah) has been busy and then was retired, there was nobody working full-time on sandbox, yet it's one of the core utilities that Gentoo uses; Martin left an experimental branch of sandbox, which has code used for Gentoo/FreeBSD support in it. At the moment that sandbox fails badly with Linux modules, and is non trivial to fix. Having someone cleanup sandbox code and ensure that building continues to occur in a safe environment from the running system is of critical importance. It would also be useful to port sandbox to other operating systems such as: Darwin, Solaris, *BSD and more.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
	  <ti>Autoepatch</ti>
  	<ti>Autoepatch was a project to replace gnuconfig.eclass and elibtoolize that you find used in quite a few ebuilds to help ensure packages build correctly. Its goal is to apply common patches and fixes to source code after the unpacking but before you get to the compile phase. Ensuring that common mistakes made in source code, such as a broken autotools issue, is resovled before you have to fix it on an ebuild by ebuild basis.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Eselect GCC</ti>
    <ti>Eselect is Gentoo's configuration tool for selecting versions or linguas of applications that have multiple instances that can fulfill a need. A previous attempt at making a selector for gcc, caused far more problems then what it was attempting to resolve.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Eselect modules</ti>
    <ti>Eselect is Gentoo's configuration tool for selecting versions or linguas of applications that have multiple instances that can fulfill a need. There are many applications such as tar, whois, cpio, sendmail, and countless others that are different versions/implementations of the same application. Eselect is ideal for allowing you to have multiple versions of these applications installed but having the default system version be selected via the Eselect framework. Adding more modules will allow users to have better control over their various packages.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>packages.gentoo.org</ti>
   <ti>The current version of packages.gentoo.org does not allow searching. This is a feature needed to make the website as useful as the old version was. Another possible feature is to integrate tinderbox (binary package repository) with the web interface of packages.g.o</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>baselayout on Prefix</ti>
   <ti>Users of prefixed Portage cannot currently use runscripts as baselayout does not work in their environment</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>scanmacho</ti>
   <ti>The equivalent of scanelf but for Darwin, will be used to replace otool</ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>


<extrachapter>
<title>Mentors for Summer of Code 2008</title>
<section>
<body>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Developer</th>
    <th>E-mail</th>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <ti>Diego Petteno</ti>
    <ti>flameeyes@gentoo.org</ti>
  </tr>

  <tr>
    <ti>Saleem Abdulrasool</ti>
    <ti>compnerd@gentoo.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Alec Warner</ti>
    <ti>antarus@gentoo.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Fabian Groffen</ti>
   <ti>grobian@gentoo.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Damian Florczyk</ti>
   <ti>thunder@gentoo.org</ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<!--
<extrachapter>
<title>Students for Summer of Code 2006</title>
<section>
<body>
<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Student</th>
    <th>E-mail</th>
    <th>Project</th>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
-->

<!--
<extrachapter>
<title>Planet Gentoo</title>
<section>
<body>
  
<p>
Planet Gentoo has setup an RSS feed and website for the Summer of Code
bloggers. The website is available at <uri>http://planet.gentoo.org/soc</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
-->

</project>

