<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Summer of Code mentoring guide</title>
<author>antarus</author>
<abstract>This guide is intended to be read by anyone who is interested
in mentoring students for Gentoo in the Google Summer of Code.
Interested mentors need not be Gentoo developers; anyone interested in
mentoring should be able to make a case as to why they want to mentor should
the SOC team have questions.
</abstract>
<version>1.1</version>
<date>March 9, 2009</date>
<chapter>
<title>What it is to be a Mentor</title>
<section>
<title>Attributes</title>
<body>
<ul>
  <li><b>Willing</b> - A mentor should be willing to mentor.  Mentoring is not a
  forced activity and it is not required.  A mentor should not mentor
  half-heartedly.  The Summer of Code experience is a great experience for
  students and part of that experience is having some help along the way.  It
  is also a great opportunity to recruit new people into a project and this
  opportunity should not be squandered.  Of course mentoring also offers a
  great opportunity for friendship.</li>
  <li><b>Informed</b> - A mentor should know what they are signing up for; generally
  by reading this document.  A mentor should be aware of the time requirements
  and any mentor who knows they cannot devote the time required should probably
  take a back-seat role; perhaps as a secondary or backup mentor.</li>
  <li><b>Capable</b> - A mentor should be capable of mentoring for the given task.
  Knowledge of the language the student is using is important as is knowledge
  of the problem domain.  The student will (hopefully) be asking questions
  about the project and their implementation (and as a mentor you should
  arguably be questioning their implementation as you review it.)</li>
  <li><b>Sociable</b> - A mentor should try to foster a relationship with the student.
  It is important to critique the students work in a professional manner.
  Complaints about rudeness and abuse should be filed to the GSoc team lead
  and/or the Google Summer of Code staff.</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Process</title>
<body>
<p>Being a mentor is about getting to know the student, helping the student,
critiquing the student and insuring the student is making progress.  These are
roles generally performed by a 'Tech Lead' or 'Project Manager'.  A person
interested in mentoring should be prepared to do these tasks.</p>
<p><b>Helping the Student</b>:
The mentor should assist the student with common questions about the domain
area, implementation and language specifics.  As a mentor you should not write
the code for the student; however using unrelated examples that can communicate
your point to the student are a good tool.</p>
<p><b>Critiquing the student</b>:
As a mentor you should review the student's work on a regular basis.  A
recommendation that has worked in the past is every week; however you and the
student should discuss meeting times, number of meetings, and meeting duration.
It is important that you as a mentor ensure the student is staying on track and
and is meeting the deadlines set forth in their application.  If there are road
blocks that are hindering the student's progress you should aid the student in
overcoming them.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Applying to be a Mentor for GSOC 2010</title>
<body>
<p>
Applications for mentorship are now open. You can apply on the <uri 
link="http://socghop.appspot.com/">gsoc webapp</uri>. Once you apply, you 
will be contacted by the program administrators (dberkholz or antarus) 
to answer some questions about mentoring and why you have elected to be 
a Mentor.  Mentor selection is currently decided at the sole descretion 
of the program administrators.  All mentors should have sufficient 
involvement within the Gentoo community to support their application.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
