<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE mainpage SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/main/en/about.xml,v 1.35 2006/05/07 23:20:48 neysx Exp $ -->

<mainpage id="about">
<title>About Gentoo</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="curtis119@gentoo.org">Curtis Napier</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="peesh@gentoo.org">Jorge Paulo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="fox2mike@gmail.com">Shyam Mani</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
About Gentoo, an overview.
</abstract>

<version>1.5</version>
<date>2006-05-07</date>

<chapter>
<title>About Gentoo</title>
<section>
<body>

<fig link="/images/poster.jpg"/>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What is Gentoo?</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo is a free operating system based on either Linux or FreeBSD that can be 
automatically optimized and customized for just about any application or need.
Extreme configurability, performance and a top-notch user and developer community
are all hallmarks of the Gentoo experience.
</p>

<p>
Thanks to a technology called Portage, Gentoo can become an ideal
secure server, development workstation, professional desktop, gaming system,
embedded solution or something else -- whatever you need it to be. Because of
its near-unlimited adaptability, we call Gentoo a <b>meta</b>distribution.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What is Portage?</title>
<body>

<p>
<b>Portage</b> is the heart of Gentoo, and performs many key functions.
For one, Portage is the <e>software distribution</e> system for Gentoo.
To get the latest software for Gentoo, you type one command: <c>emerge
--sync</c>. This command tells Portage to update your local "Portage tree" over 
the Internet. Your local Portage tree contains a complete collection of scripts
that can be used by Portage to create and install the latest Gentoo packages.
Currently, we have <uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org/categories">more than 
10000 packages</uri> in our Portage tree, with updates and new ones being 
<uri link="http://packages.gentoo.org">added all the time</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Portage is also a <e>package building and installation</e> system.  When you
want to install a package, you type <c>emerge packagename</c>, at which point
Portage automatically builds a custom version of the package to your exact
specifications, optimizing it for your hardware and ensuring that the optional
features in the package that you want are enabled -- and those you don't
want aren't.
</p>

<p>
Portage also keeps your system <e>up-to-date</e>. Typing <c>emerge -uD
world</c> -- one command -- will ensure that all the packages that <e>you</e>
want on your system are updated automatically.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
