<?xml version='1.0'?>

<mainpage id="contract">
<title>Gentoo Linux Social Contract</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>

<abstract></abstract>

<version>1.2</version>
<date>19 July 2003</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Linux Social Contract</title>
	<section>
		<title>About the Gentoo Linux Social Contract</title>
	<body>	
		<p>This social contract
		is intended to clearly describe the overall development policies and standards of the Gentoo Linux
		development team.  Parts of this document have been derived from the <uri link="http://www.debian.org/social_contract">Debian Social Contract</uri>, and is generally very similar to it except that certain parts have been clarified and
		augmented while other parts deemed redundant have been removed.  Comments are welcome.  Please send
		them to our <mail link="gentoo-dev@gentoo.org">gentoo-dev@gentoo.org</mail> mailing list.</p>
	</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Gentoo Linux is and will remain Free Software</title>
	<body>

<p>
We will release our contributions to Gentoo Linux as free software, under the
GNU General Public License version 2 (or later, at our discretion.) Any external
contributions to Gentoo Linux (in the form of freely-distributable sources or
binaries) may be incorporated into Gentoo Linux provided that we are legally
entitled to do so.  However, Gentoo Linux will never <i>depend</i> upon a piece of
software unless it conforms to the GNU General Public License, GNU Lesser 
General Public License or some other license approved by the Open Source 
Initiative 
(<uri link="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/index.html">OSI</uri>.)
</p>

<note>We are considering extending the above clause to require that all core
Gentoo Linux components must conform to a license approved by the OSI <e>and</e> Free
Software Foundation (<uri link="http://www.gnu.org/">FSF</uri>.)</note>

	</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>We will give back to the Free Software Community</title>
	<body>
<p>
We will establish relationships with Free Software authors and collaborate when
possible.  We will submit bug-fixes, improvements, user requests, etc. to the
"upstream" authors of software included in our system.  We will also clearly
document <e>our</e> contributions to Gentoo Linux as well any improvements or
changes we make to external sources used by Gentoo Linux (whether in the form
of patches, "sed tweaks" or some other form.)  We acknowledge that our
improvements and patches are much more meaningful to the larger Free Software
community if they are clearly documented and explained, since not everyone has
the time or ability to understand the literal changes contained in the patches,
tweaks, etc. themselves.
</p>
	</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>We will not hide problems</title>
	<body>
<p>We will keep our <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/">bug report database</uri> open for public view at all times.
Reports that users file on-line will immediately become visible to others.</p>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
