<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-15"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<mainpage id="lists">
  <title>Gentoo Linux Mailing Lists</title>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>
  </author>
  <version>1.0</version>
  <date>05 Nov 2002</date>
  <chapter>
    <title>Gentoo Linux Mailing List Overview</title>
	<section>
      <body>
	  	
		<p>The Gentoo Linux free software project has a number of public mailing lists, covering a variety of Gentoo Linux-related
		subjects. Our mailing lists are powered by a customized version of <uri link="http://www.ezmlm.org">ezmlm/idx</uri> that provides
		<c>List-Id:</c> mail headers and <c>[listname]</c> subject prefixes to comply with modern mailing list manager standards
		and conventions.</p>

		<p>One interacts with <c>ezmlm/idx</c> via email. To subscribe to a list, send an empty email to:</p>
		<p><c>listname-subscribe@gentoo.org</c></p>
		<p>Once subscribed to the list, you can post to it by sending an email to:</p>
		<p><c>listname@gentoo.org</c></p>
		<p>To unsubscribe from a list, send an empty email to:</p>
		<p><c>listname-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</c></p>
		<p>All of our lists also have a corresponding digest list. Digest lists will mail a single email to you every couple of days, 
		rather than individual emails for each post. Send an empty email to the following addresses to subscribe and unsubscribe from
		mailing lists respectively:</p>
		<p><c>listname-digest-subscribe@gentoo.org</c><br/>
		<c>listname-digest-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</c></p>
		<p>You can learn more about the capabilities of ezmlm/idx by reading the <uri link="http://www.ezmlm.org/ezman-0.32/ezman1.html">Ezmlm/idx User's Manual</uri>. You can also learn more about the Gentoo Linux mailing list system by reading the short Gentoo Linux mailing
		list FAQ that appears later in this document.</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Linux Mailing Lists</title>
	<section>
	<title>Primary Gentoo Linux Mailing Lists</title>
	<body>
		<table>
			<tr>
				<th>List name</th>
				<th>Description</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-user</c></ti>
				<ti>General Gentoo Linux user support and discussion mailing list</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-announce</c></ti>
				<ti>General Gentoo Linux announcements list (new releases, security fixes)</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-dev</c></ti>
				<ti>General Gentoo developer discussion mailing list</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-security</c></ti>
				<ti>For the discussion of security issues and fixes</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-desktop</c></ti>
				<ti>Mailing list devoted to Gentoo Linux on the desktop</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-admin</c></ti>
				<ti>Mailing list devoted to Gentoo Linux administration issues</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-doc</c></ti>
				<ti>For documentation contributions, suggestions, improvements and translations</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-ppc-user</c></ti>
				<ti>For Gentoo Linux/PowerPC user support and discussion</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-ppc-dev</c></ti>
				<ti>For Gentoo Linux/PowerPC developer discussion</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-sparc</c></ti>
				<ti>For Gentoo Linux/Sparc user support and discussion</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-sparc-dev</c></ti>
				<ti>For Gentoo Linux/Sparc developer discussion</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-cvs</c></ti>
				<ti>Subscribe to this list if you would like to receive a daily CVS Portage ChangeLog</ti>
			</tr>
                        <tr>
                                <ti><c>gentoo-alpha</c></ti>
                                <ti>For Gentoo Linux/Alpha user support and discussion</ti>
                        </tr>
		</table>
</body>
    </section>
  	<section>
	<title>Non-English Gentoo Linux Mailing Lists</title>
	<body>
		<table>
			<tr>
				<th>List name</th>
				<th>Description</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-user-de</c></ti>
				<ti>deutschsprachige Gentoo User Diskussionsliste</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-user-es</c></ti>
				<ti>Lista para la ayuda y discusión de usuarios hispano-hablantes de Gentoo</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>gentoo-doc-es</c></ti>
				<ti>Lista de correo dedicada a la traducción y creación de documentación en Español de Gentoo</ti>
			</tr>
                        <tr>   
                                <ti><c>gentoo-user-kr</c></ti>
                                <ti>Korean Gentoo User Mailinglist</ti>
                        </tr>
		</table>
	</body>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Other Gentoo Linux Mailing Lists</title>
	<body>
		<table>
			<tr>
				<th>List name</th>
				<th>Description</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>libconf</c></ti>
				<ti>For the discussion of libconf development</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti><c>bug-wranglers</c></ti>
				<ti>Special-purpose list for the Gentoo Linux Bug Wranglers</ti>
			</tr>
		</table>
	</body>
	</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Linux Mailing List Mini-FAQ</title>
		<section>
		<title>I subscribed to a list using my home email address, but I can't post to the list from work. What do I do to fix this?</title>
		
		<body><p>To reduce spam, all of our lists are configured to only allow posts from official subscriber email addresses. Fortunately,
		<c>ezmlm/idx</c> supports a concept known as "aliases," allowing you to register alternate email addresses that can also be used to
		post to the list. Here's an example of how this works. Let's say you subscribed to the <c>gentoo-dev</c> list as <c>jim@home.com</c>,
		but you'd also like to post to the list using your <c>james@work.com</c> email address. To do this, send a message (as <c>jim@home.com</c>)
		to <c>gentoo-dev-allow-subscribe-james=work.com@gentoo.org</c> (note the <c>@</c> becoming an <c>=</c>,) and then reply to the confirmation email you receive. You should then
		be allowed to post to <c>gentoo-dev</c> using both your home and work email addresses.
		</p></body>
		</section>
		
		<section>
		<title>Where to I set/store my mailing list password?</title>
		<body><p><c>ezmlm/idx</c> does not use passwords; instead, it uses auto-generated cryptographic cookies for security. 
		</p></body>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>I want to switch from regular delivery to digest delivery. How do I do this?</title>
		<body><p>Unsubscribe from the normal list and then subscribe to the digest list. For list <c>listname</c>, this would be done by
		sending empty emails to the following two addresses:</p>
		<p><c>listname-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</c><br/>
		<c>listname-digest-subscribe@gentoo.org</c>
		</p></body>
		</section>


		<section>
		<title>How do I use procmail to filter Gentoo Linux mailing list messages?</title>
		<body><p>To filter incoming mail arriving from list <c>listname</c>, use the following <c>procmail</c> recipe:</p>
		<pre>
:0
* ^List-Id:.*listname\.gentoo\.org
Mail/listname
		</pre>
		<p>This identical to how you'd filter incoming <e>Mailman</e> mailing list manager emails.</p>
		</body>
		</section>

</chapter>
</mainpage>
