<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/main/en/name-logo.xml,v 1.11 2015/01/13 15:55:28 dabbott Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Name and Logo Usage Guidelines</title>

<author>
  The Gentoo Foundation
</author>

<abstract>
This document covers the guidelines on the Gentoo Name and Logo usage.
</abstract>

<!-- The works of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>11</version>
<date>2015-01-13</date>

<chapter>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This document describes proper use of the Gentoo name, the "g" logo and any 
other associated marks for software and computer-related efforts that are not 
under the direction of the Gentoo Foundation, Inc. If you
have any questions about these guidelines, please contact <mail
link="trustees@gentoo.org">Gentoo Foundation, Inc.</mail>
</p>

<p>
Gentoo Foundation, Inc. reserve the right to change these terms from time to 
time at their sole discretion. For that reason, we encourage you to review this 
statement periodically.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Definitions</title>
<section>
<title>The Gentoo project</title>
<body>

<p>
The volunteer development efforts currently directed by Gentoo Foundation, Inc.,
a not-for-profit corporation.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content produced by the Gentoo project</title>
<body>

<p>
Any works that is copyright Gentoo Foundation, Inc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The "g" logo</title>
<body>

<fig link="/images/glogo-small.png" linkto="/images/gblend.png"/>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo artwork</title>
<body>

<p>
All artwork produced by <e>the Gentoo project</e> (see above definition).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo community site</title>
<body>

<p>
A non-profit website whose primary objective is to provide any Gentoo 
user with additional information on Gentoo and Gentoo-related topics.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Ownership of marks</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The name "Gentoo" and the "g" logo are currently trademarks of Gentoo
Foundation, Inc. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Use of Gentoo name</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
You are permitted to use the Gentoo name in computer-related works, provided
that:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    You acknowledge that the name "Gentoo" is a trademark of Gentoo
    Foundation, Inc., and
  </li>
  <li>
    you do not entitle any software project or computer-related product "Gentoo"
    or have "Gentoo" appear within its name, and 
  </li>
  <li>
    the fully-qualified domain name for your software project or
    computer-related products does not contain "Gentoo", and
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>
      you clearly state that the works, project, site, product or any other
      type of item with which the "Gentoo" name is associated is not part of the
      Gentoo project and is not directed or managed by Gentoo Foundation, Inc.
    </e>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
We do not consider these restrictions to apply to the <uri 
link="http://www.obsession.se/gentoo/">Gentoo file manager</uri> project, 
developed by Emil Bink, as it is not an operating system project.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Use of Gentoo Logo and artwork</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
You are permitted to use the Gentoo "g" logo and artwork copyright Gentoo
Foundation, Inc. (hereafter called "Gentoo
artwork") under the following conditions:
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Commercial Use</title>
<body>

<p>
Commercial use of the Gentoo "g" logo and Gentoo artwork is allowed for <e>any
software or computer hardware product</e> that <e>contains</e> or is <e>based
upon</e> works produced by the Gentoo project, or any project or service 
referencing Gentoo or the Gentoo Project, provided that the following 
conditions are met:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    You acknowledge that the "g" logo is a trademark of Gentoo Foundation,
    Inc. and that any Gentoo artwork is copyright Gentoo Foundation, Inc., and
  </li>
  <li>
    the artwork used is <e>not</e> the primary (largest) mark displayed on the
    product, and is thus intended to convey that the product contains "works
    produced by the Gentoo project", but is <e>not itself a product being sold
    or supported</e> by Gentoo Foundation, Inc.
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
<e>
Commercial use of the Gentoo "g" logo and Gentoo artwork for any other
purpose is expressly denied. 
</e>
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Non-Commercial Use</title>
<body>

<p>
Non-commercial use of the "g" logo and Gentoo artwork is permitted provided that
the following conditions are met:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    You acknowledge that the "g" logo is a trademark of Gentoo Foundation,
    Inc., and that any Gentoo artwork is copyright Gentoo Foundation, Inc, and,
  </li>
  <li>
    the "g" logo and Gentoo artwork are used in works that pertain to "the
    Gentoo project", as directed by the Gentoo Foundation, Inc., and not any
    effort outside or beyond the authority of the Gentoo Foundation, Inc., and
  </li>
  <li>
    <e>
      you clearly state that the works, project, site, product or any other
      type of item with which the "g" logo or Gentoo artwork is associated is
      not part of the Gentoo project and is not directed or managed by Gentoo
      Foundation, Inc.
    </e>
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Community Projects</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo Foundation, Inc. grant Gentoo community sites, as
defined above, the right to use the Gentoo name in their project name and
fully qualified domain name provided that:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    the website clearly states, on each page, that the project is no official
    Gentoo project by labelling itself as a "news site", "fan site", "unofficial
    site" or "community site", and
  </li>
  <li>
    the website does not closely mimic the name or layout of one of our 
    official websites, and
  </li>
  <li>
    you acknowledge that the name "Gentoo" is a trademark of Gentoo
    Foundation, Inc.
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
Any other use of the Gentoo name, logo and artwork remains bound by the
beforementioned guidelines.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
