<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<mainpage id="performance">
<title>Gentoo Linux Performance Metrics</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>
<version>1.0</version>
<date>4 Oct 2003</date>

<chapter>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux... performance?</title>
<body>
<p>People have often wondered what kind of performance improvement Gentoo Linux provides over
other Linux distributions. This section is intended to help answer that question in a tangible way.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>HispaLinux 2003: Gentoo Linux 1.4 vs. Mandrake 9.1 load-times</title>
<body>
<p>On 23 Sep 2003, <b>Jose Alberto Suarez Lopez</b> gave a presentation at <uri
link="http://congreso.hispalinux.es/edicion/2003/presentacion/">HispaLinux
2003</uri> where he demonstrated the load-time performance of the official
<i>Gentoo Linux 1.4</i> release.  To compare load-time performance, he used <i>Mandrake
9.1</i>. Mandrake 9.1 ships with its binaries "pre-linked," which allows for faster
load-times. In contrast, Gentoo Linux ships without pre-linked binaries by
default.</p>

<p>These benchmarks compare Mandrake 9.1 against Gentoo Linux 1.4 in both a
un-prelinked (default) and pre-linked state. For the "Gentoo with prelink" test, prelinking was performed as per
the steps of the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/prelink-howto.xml">Gentoo Prelinking
Guide</uri> and only the applications being tested were pre-linked, not the
entire system (as is Mandrake 9.1.)</b></p>

<p>Here is an overview of the operating systems benchmarked for the load-time test:
<ul>
<li><b>Mandrake 9.1</b> (with prelink enabled by default, default kernel)</li>
<li><b>Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III</b> (official prebuilt "GRP" packages from CD, <b>no prelink</b>, gaming-sources-2.4.20-r3)</li>
<li><b>Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III</b> (official prebuilt "GRP" packages from CD, <b>with prelink</b>, gaming-sources-2.4.20-r3)</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>Here is an overview of the system used for the load-time test:
<ul>
<li>Pentium III Coppermine 733Mhz</li>
<li>128MB RAM</li>
<li>1461 BogoMIPS (not an authoritative performance measure but people seem to like to know this :)</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>To perform the test, three applications (<b>Mozilla</b>, <b>NetBeans</b> and
<b>Kmail</b>) were repeatedly loaded. Initial load speed as well as subsequent
load speed was recorded.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>HispaLinux 2003: Load time results</title>
<body>
<note>In these tests, the first column lists initial load time. The second and third columns
list the time required to load the application the second and third time respectively.</note>

<p><b>Test 1: Mandrake 9.1 with prelink enabled by default</b>

<table>
<tr><th></th><th>1st run</th><th>2nd run</th><th>3rd run</th></tr>
<tr><th>Mozilla</th><ti>5.34s</ti><ti>5.45s</ti><ti>5.32s</ti></tr>
<tr><th>NetBeans</th><ti>38.37s</ti><ti>14.58s</ti><ti>20.43s</ti></tr>
<tr><th>Kmail</th><ti>0.42s</ti><ti>0.42s</ti><ti>0.46s</ti></tr>
</table>
</p>

<p><b>Test 2: Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III without prelink</b>

<table>
<tr><th></th><th>1st run</th><th>2nd run</th><th>3rd run</th></tr>
<tr><th>Mozilla</th><ti>2.88s</ti><ti>2.82s</ti><ti>2.88s</ti></tr>
<tr><th>NetBeans</th><ti>18.98s</ti><ti>18.35s</ti><ti>18.51s</ti></tr>
<tr><th>Kmail</th><ti>0.39s</ti><ti>0.97s</ti><ti>0.33s</ti></tr>
</table>
</p>

<p><b>Test 3: Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III with prelink</b>

<table>
<tr><th></th><th>1st run</th><th>2nd run</th><th>3rd run</th></tr>
<tr><th>Mozilla</th><ti><b>2.8s</b></ti><ti><b>2.78s</b></ti><ti><b>2.82s</b></ti></tr>
<tr><th>NetBeans</th><ti>n/a</ti><ti>n/a</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><th>Kmail</th><ti><b>0.03s</b></ti><ti><b>0.02s</b></ti><ti><b>0.01s</b></ti></tr>
</table>

<note>The NetBeans test was not performed for Test 3 since NetBeans itself is
not prelinkable. Also, <i>only the tested applications (rather than the entire
system) were prelinked.</i> Prelinking the entire system shouldn't negatively
impact these performance numbers, and could theoretically improve them.</note>

</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>HispaLinux 2003: Load-time conclusion</title>
<body>
<p>Here are the conclusions of the load-time test:</p>
<ul>
<li><b>Mozilla loads nearly twice as fast under Gentoo Linux 1.4</b> for Pentium III (both initial and subsequent loads)</li>
<li>Initial load time for NetBeans under Gentoo is over twice as fast as on Mandrake 9.1</li>
<li>Subsequent load time for NetBeans seems about even for both Gentoo and Mandrake</li>
<li><b>Gentoo Linux 1.4 with prelink loads Kmail over 10 times faster than Gentoo Linux without prelink or Mandrake 9.1 with prelink</b></li>
</ul>
<p><b>What can be gleaned from these results?</b> For one, the default
optimizations of Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III appear to make <i>a very
significant difference</i> in "real world" application load-time performance.
Binary applications like NetBeans do not benefit as much from this performance
improvement, although initial load-time for binary applications does seem to be
a lot better under Gentoo Linux.</p>

<p>In addition, KDE C++ applications like Kmail seem to show a huge load-time
peformance improvement -- <i>over 10 times faster than Mandrake 9.1</i> and
Gentoo 1.4 without prelink -- when prelinked. Prelinking seems to be very
beneficial for improving load-time performance for KDE apps, although Mozilla
shows negligible improvement. Could this be due to Mozilla's internal
architecture which prevents it from being able to benefit significantly from
being pre-linked?  Or did our tester mistakenly try to prelink
<path>/usr/bin/mozilla</path> instead of of
<path>/usr/lib/mozilla/mozilla-bin</path>?  Only time (and another load-time
performance test) will tell! :)</p>

<p><b>Gentoo Linux is able to generally deliver better overall performance than
other Linux distributions for a couple of reasons.</b> First and most important, we
try our best to offer the latest and best free software technologies to our
users, including the latest compiler toolchains. Newer compilers produce faster
code, so by getting these tools into your hands sooner, Gentoo is able to give
you better performance.  It's important to understand that there is no magic
involved except getting the latest free software improvements to you in a
timely manner.</p>

<p><b>Here's the second way we improve the performance of Gentoo.</b> <i>The official
Gentoo Linux 1.4 release ships with pre-built binary packages</i> that have been
optimized for specific CPU models. We've chosen optimizations that perform well
and are very stable.</p>

<p>
For example, <uri link="http://store.gentoo.org/index.php?item=16&amp;action=viewitem">Gentoo Linux for
Pentium III</uri> was used in this test, which runs very fast on Pentium III and higher
processors, but will not run on Pentium II or "lower" processors. It takes full advantage
of the Pentium III's instruction set, including MMX and SSE instructions.</p>

<p>
By providing
tailored builds for each CPU model, we are able to use the full instruction set
of your CPU and deliver the best possible system performance to you. For x86
systems, we currently offer 1.4 builds for <uri link="http://store.gentoo.org/index.php?item=13&amp;action=viewitem">x86</uri> (generic PC), <uri link="http://store.gentoo.org/index.php?item=14&amp;action=viewitem">i686</uri> (Pentium
Pro and higher), <uri link="http://store.gentoo.org/index.php?item=16&amp;action=viewitem">Pentium III</uri>, <uri link="http://store.gentoo.org/index.php?item=17&amp;action=viewitem">Pentium 4</uri> and <uri link="http://store.gentoo.org/index.php?item=18&amp;action=viewitem">Athlon XP</uri> systems. In addition,
we provide an easy way for users who wish to "build Gentoo from scratch" so that they can optimize and configure Gentoo Linux
as needed.
</p>

<p>If you'd like to purchase Gentoo Linux, please visit <uri
link="http://store.gentoo.org">The Gentoo Store</uri>. The official x86 1.4
release contains a number of official builds and pre-built packages, all
optimized to provide the best possible performance and stability.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
