<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<mainpage id="performance">
<title>Gentoo Linux Performance Metrics</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>
<version>1.0</version>
<date>4 Oct 2003</date>

<chapter>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux... performance?</title>
<body>
<p>People have often wondered what kind of performance improvement Gentoo Linux provides over
other Linux distributions. This section is intended to help answer that question in a tangible way.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>HispaLinux 2003: Gentoo Linux 1.4 vs. Mandrake 9.1 load-times</title>
<body>
<p>On 23 Sep 2003, Jose Alberto Suarez Lopez gave a presentation at <uri
link="http://congreso.hispalinux.es/edicion/2003/presentacion/">HispaLinux
2003</uri> where he demonstrated the load-time performance of the official
Gentoo Linux 1.4 release.  To compare load-time performance, he used Mandrake
9.1. Mandrake 9.1 ships with its binaries "pre-linked," which allows for faster
load-times. In contrast, Gentoo Linux ships without pre-linked binaries by
default.</p>

<p>These benchmarks compare Mandrake 9.1 against Gentoo Linux 1.4 in both a
un-prelinked (default) and pre-linked state. Prelinking was performed as per
the steps of the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/prelink-howto.xml">Gentoo Prelinking
Guide</uri>.  </p>

<p>Here is an overview of the operating systems benchmarked for the load-time test:
<ul>
<li>Mandrake 9.1 (with prelink enabled by default, default kernel)</li>
<li>Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III (official prebuilt "GRP" packages from CD, no prelink, gaming-sources-2.4.20-r3)</li>
<li>Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III (official prebuilt "GRP" packages from CD, with prelink, gaming-sources-2.4.20-r3)</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>Here is an overview of the system used for the load-time test:
<ul>
<li>Pentium III Coppermine 733Mhz</li>
<li>128MB RAM</li>
<li>1461 BogoMIPS (not an authoritative performance measure but people seem to like to know this :)</li>
</ul>
</p>

<p>To perform the test, three applications (<b>Mozilla</b>, <b>NetBeans</b> and
<b>Kmail</b>) were repeatedly loaded. Initial load speed as well as subsequent
load speed was recorded. Note that NetBeans is not prelinkable, so the results
for the Gentoo prelink and non-prelink test are identical for NetBeans.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>HispaLinux 2003: Load time results</title>
<body>
<note>In these tests, the first column lists initial load time. The second and third columns
list the time required to load the application the second and third time respectively.</note>

<p><b>Test 1: Mandrake 9.1 with prelink enabled by default</b>

<table>
<tr><th></th><th>1st run</th><th>2nd run</th><th>3rd run</th></tr>
<tr><th>Mozilla</th><ti>5.34s</ti><ti>5.45s</ti><ti>5.32s</ti></tr>
<tr><th>NetBeans</th><ti>38.37s</ti><ti>14.58s</ti><ti>20.43s</ti></tr>
<tr><th>Kmail</th><ti>0.42s</ti><ti>0.42s</ti><ti>0.46s</ti></tr>
</table>
</p>

<p><b>Test 2: Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III without prelink</b>

<table>
<tr><th></th><th>1st run</th><th>2nd run</th><th>3rd run</th></tr>
<tr><th>Mozilla</th><ti>2.88s</ti><ti>2.82s</ti><ti>2.88s</ti></tr>
<tr><th>NetBeans</th><ti>18.98s</ti><ti>18.35s</ti><ti>18.51s</ti></tr>
<tr><th>Kmail</th><ti>0.39s</ti><ti>0.97s</ti><ti>0.33s</ti></tr>
</table>
</p>

<p><b>Test 3: Gentoo Linux 1.4 for Pentium III with prelink</b>

<table>
<tr><th></th><th>1st run</th><th>2nd run</th><th>3rd run</th></tr>
<tr><th>Mozilla</th><ti><b>2.8s</b></ti><ti><b>2.78s</b></ti><ti><b>2.82s</b></ti></tr>
<tr><th>NetBeans</th><ti>n/a</ti><ti>n/a</ti><ti>n/a</ti></tr>
<tr><th>Kmail</th><ti><b>0.03s</b></ti><ti><b>0.02s</b></ti><ti><b>0.01s</b></ti></tr>
</table>

<note>The NetBeans test was not performed for Test 3 since NetBeans itself is not
prelinkable.</note>

</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
