<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/shots.html">
<title>Gentoo Linux ScreenShots!</title>
<author title="Chief Architect">
	<mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="svyatogor@gentoo.org">Sergey Kuleshov</mail>
</author>


<abstract>Screenshots of Gentoo Linux in action.  Whee!</abstract>

<version>1.0.3</version>
<date>28 July 2003</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Here they are... click for larger PNG versions!</title>

	<section>
		<title>Jason A. Mobarak aka aether</title>
		<body><p>
		Here is the Jason's desktop showing Openbox with 'Twice' style. He is running vim to interface java-config, XMMS, root tail of /var/log/message /var/log/kern.log and gkrellm with a bunch of pluggins (xmms, weather, screen shooter and mixer).
		</p>
		<fig link="/images/shots/aether-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/aether.png"/>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Stewart Honsberger aka blkdeath</title>
		<body><p>
		Below we are featuring Stewart's KDE desktop with Mozilla Firebird and Thunderbird, Licq and XChat. Also he is running VMWare to meet any needs he might have in Win32 platform and is monitoring his home server with log tails in transparent Eterms.
		</p>
		<fig link="/images/shots/blkdeath-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/blkdeath.png"/>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Brad Laue aka brad</title>
		<body><p>
		Here is Brad's desktop with Bluecurve for KDE as well as GTK. You can see that he's playing music with noatun and also running knotes - "the ultimate personal organiser".
		</p>
		<fig link="/images/shots/brad-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/brad.png"/>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Grant Goodyear aka g2boojum</title>
		<body><p>
		According to Grant this is a 'fairly generic xfce4 desktop'. There is a couple of gnome terminals and irssi inside screen. knotes and licq are docked in the system tray.
		</p>
		<fig link="/images/shots/g2boojum-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/g2boojum.png"/>
		</body>
	</section>
		<section>
		<title>Peter Johanson aka latexer</title>
		<body><p>
		Peter is showing us another xfce4 desktop with 'Tabs' theme (xfce4-3.99.2) with xfce4-mixer and xfce4-iconbox. He is running mutt from cvs inside antyaliased xterm along with mozilla-firebird-cvs, gkrellm2 with xfce4 theme and gaim.
		</p>
		<fig link="/images/shots/latexer-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/latexer.png"/>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
	<title>Luke-jr</title>
	<body><p>
	Luke-jr is giving an example of what KDE desktop could look like. Here is what he has running: Gaim 0.64, X-Chat 2.0.3 (on #gentoo-dev), Konsole, Konqueror (Gentoo website). Also on the kicker, which is KDE's taskbar there is KMenu, a bunch of Quicklaunch buttons, MediaControl Applet, controling XMMS. In the systray there is keyboard layout applet, KOrganizer, Klipper, Volume Control, KHexClock (this is his own applet, diplsaying time/date in hex) and Clock.
	</p>
	<fig link="/images/shots/luke-jr-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/luke-jr.png"/>
	</body>
	</section>
<section>
	<title>Donnie Berholz aka spyderous</title>
	<body><p>
	Here's what Donnie's screen looks like with XChat on #gentoo-cluster channel, two Eterms in which he tries to port an old patch to a newer verion xfree-drm, Gaim, KMail and Mozilla Firebird. All these windows are controled by Fluxbox.
	</p>
	<fig link="/images/shots/spyderous-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/spyderous.png"/>
	</body>
	</section>
<section>
	<title>Mike Frysinger aka vapier</title>
	<body><p>
	 Mike (who is out current Games Team lead) runs 
enlightenment while listening to http://di.fm/ via xmms all the time.  Here 
you find him working on the quake2 qmax ebuild (background Eterms) while 
testing it out to make sure it doesn't have any bugs.  Games Q.A. is such 
hard work :(.
	</p>
	<fig link="/images/shots/vapier-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/vapier.png"/>
	</body>
	</section>
<section>
	<title>Gerrynjr</title>
	<body><p>
	Here is how he describes his screen: 
	"Well, this is my desktop screenshot. I have easy access to my various
loki/independent games. Games like Uplink, descent3, quake3, RTCW, enemy
territory, jediKnight2, ut2003, Sof, Mindrover, Alpha Centauri, Sim
City, and RailRoad Tycoon. Who said there were no games for linux :D.
Standard GTk theme with liteamp running, as well as a mozilla compile,
and xchat."
	</p>
	<fig link="/images/shots/gerrynjr-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/gerrynjr.png"/>
	</body>
	</section>
<section>
	<title>John Mylchreest aka johnm</title>
	<body><p>
	Johnm is giving us an example of a Gnome-based desktop. He is running Galeon (on Gentoo home page), irssi in screen, xmms, Nautilus File Manager, terminal, Evolution and Gaim.
	</p>
	<fig link="/images/shots/johnm-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/johnm.png"/>
	</body>
	</section>
<section>
	<title>Okrain Genady aka Mafteah</title>
	<body><p>
	Genady, who is Gentoo user was very kind to provide us screenshot of his desktop. He is running KDE along with Mozilla web browser, Open Office (demonastrating the right-to-left wrighting in hebrew) and xmms.
	</p>
	<fig link="/images/shots/mafteah-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/mafteah.png"/>
	</body>
	</section>
<section>
	<title>edon-tux</title>
	<body><p>
	Edon-tux is another Gentoo users, who provided us his screenshot, showing Gnome desktop.
	</p>
	<fig link="/images/shots/edon-tux-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/edon-tux.png"/>
	</body>
	</section>
<section>
	<title>Daniel Goller</title>
	<body><p>
	Dnaiel decided to show us what an IceWM desktop would look like if you put
	an icequa theme on it and run idesk with AquaFusion icons as well as
	gkrellm and xmms with their own aqua themes.
	</p>
	<fig link="/images/shots/daniel-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/daniel.png"/>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
