<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/main/en/shots.xml,v 1.40 2010/06/20 20:59:01 dabbott Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Linux Screenshots</title>

<author title="Previous Chief Architect">
  <mail link="drobbins"/>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift"/>
</author>

<author title="Author">Sergey Kuleshov</author>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="dabbott"/>
</author>

<!--
  Method for publishing screenshots:
  - Remove the bottom screenshot from the page; don't forget removing the images
    from CVS afterwards as well
  - Add the new screenshot on top of the page

  We keep the 10 most recent screenshots so that we don't provide outdated
  screenshots to our users.
-->

<abstract>Screenshots of Gentoo Linux in action.</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.39</version>
<date>2010-06-19</date>

<chapter>
<title>Here they are... click for larger PNG versions!</title>

  <section>
  <title>Disclaimer</title>
  <body>

	<impo>We are currently in the process of running the <uri
			link="/proj/en/pr/2010-screenshot-contest.xml">Gentoo Screenshot Contest
			2010.</uri> The top three finishers will have their screenshots posted on
		the page. If you don't enter you can not win, so trick up that desktop and
		enter!.</impo>
	
	<p>
  The screenshots on this page are contributed by various Gentoo users.
  Information about the used themes, background images, etc. is not available
  through Gentoo. You will need to contact the author of the screenshot (if
  you can find this person) for more information.
  </p>

  <p>
  You can always try locating the authors on our #gentoo chat channel on
  irc.freenode.net or through the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">gentoo
  forums</uri>.
  </p>

  </body>
  </section>

<section>
<title>(Almost) default GNOME</title>
<body>

<p>
Bartek's shot is one of Gentoo Screenshot Contest winners. Bartek got this
decent look by illusion of 3d wallpaper connected with arrangement of pretty
icons. This is good example of how a default theme can be used to create a
beautiful screenshot.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/gnome-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/gnome.png" />

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Elegant black WM</title>
<body>

<p>
The second winner of Gentoo Screenshot Contest is Mikołaj aka mklimek, who is a
KDE user so far, and he doesn't look to change that. On his exclusive screenshot
you can see some KDE's utilities and  icons which looks kinda gnome-like.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/rash-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/rash.png" />

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Space trip</title>
<body>

<p>
Robert's screenshot demonstrates an appealing use of blue hues. Excluding
cairo-clock, his KDE runs (as we can notice) qt-based only applications, as
Kopete, Konsole and amaroK. Robert also cares about his irssi theme, which is
distinguished by green colors.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/sshotpw4-small.png" linkto="/images/shots/sshotpw4.png"/>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Even more gentooish</title>
<body>

<p>
That is probably the most "Gentooish" screenshot here ever and personally for
me it is the most beautyful. Alexander runs  GNOME, which not only looks pretty
but also befits a Gentoo workstation.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/Bildschirmfoto-small.png"
linkto="/images/shots/Bildschirmfoto.png" />

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Emerge that!</title>
<body>

<p>
As you will notice, Massimiliano is going to build media-video/dvdauthor on his
KDE box.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/darkgentoo2sf2-small.png"
linkto="/images/shots/darkgentoo2sf2.png" />

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Minimal beauty</title>
<body>

<p>
The second pretty screenshot of Bartek's desktop. This time he runs fluxbox with
his "dark theme" whatever that means. But the hidden beauty of the screenshot
is sane connection of audacious theme, fluxbox's theme and wallpaper.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/fluxbox-small.jpg" linkto="/images/shots/fluxbox.jpg"
/>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Default things can be pretty too</title>
<body>

<p>
A fellow who goes by Purple (whether that is his nickname or real name we don't
know) submitted his nice-looking screenshot of KDE displaying yakuake during sync
process, and conky. All composed with decent wallpaper makes it unusual.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/snapshotzi4-small.png"
linkto="/images/shots/snapshotzi4.png" />

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Darkclown Coronado</title>
<body>

<p>
Darkclown (don't ask) submitted his nice-looking screenshot, displaying the
vista-Inspirate icons by saki and the gears desktop by ChristianNickel. His
desktop is a KDE environment with Plastik window decorations and keramik style.
You'll also notice karamba plugins like liquid weather and cynapses aero.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/desktop-rehcmx-small.jpg"
linkto="/images/shots/desktop-rehcmx.jpg" />

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Scott S Short</title>
<body>

<p>
Scott's box uses the 2.6.14-gentoo-r2 kernel with Gnome 2.12, showing off the
Milk 2.0 theme. All icons originated from the Gentoo web site.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/desktop-scottsshort-small.png"
linkto="/images/shots/desktop-scottsshort.png" />

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Richard Head</title>
<body>

<p>
Richard is one of our many Gentoo users who is impressed with Gentoo's
flexibility. He describes his screenshot as "pretty cool", showing mp3 player,
system status information, transparent terminals and menu and a root tail of a
port scan.
</p>

<fig link="/images/shots/desktop-cadaver138-small.png"
linkto="/images/shots/desktop-cadaver138.png" />

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
