<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE mainpage SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/main/en/sponsors.xml,v 1.120 2014/11/25 13:35:31 ultrabug Exp $ -->

<mainpage>
<title>Gentoo Sponsors</title>

<author title="Present author">
  <mail link="robbat2"/>
</author>
<author title="Past author">
  <mail link="klieber"/>
</author>
<author title="Past author">
  <mail link="swift"/>
</author>
<author title="Past editor">
  <mail link="curtis119"/>
</author>

<abstract>
Sponsors of Gentoo
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>5.0</version>
<date>2014-02-01</date>

<chapter>
<title>Hosting Sponsors</title>

<section>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo would like to thank the following companies and organizations who 
donate various services and equipment to further the development of Gentoo.
Without these organizations, Gentoo would not be where it is today.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.1, Sun Mar 16 17:18:50 2003 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Oregon State University: Open Source Lab (OSUOSL)</title>
<body>
<!-- We want the two images to be adjacent, not stacked, but I can't get the
     docs to do that! Help welcome. -->
<fig link="/images/sponsors/osu-logo.png" linkto="http://oregonstate.edu" 
     short="Oregon State University"/>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/osuosl-logo.png" linkto="http://osuosl.org" 
     short="OSU Open Source Lab"/>
<p>
Located at <uri link="http://oregonstate.edu">Oregon State University</uri>
in beautiful Corvallis, Oregon, the <uri link="http://osuosl.org">Open Source 
Lab</uri> is a focal point of development, hosting and other assorted services
for the Open Source community.
</p>
<p>
OSU provides several services to the Gentoo project.  In addition to 
serving as the primary source mirror for Gentoo, they also provide 
colocation space for several Gentoo servers.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.49, Wed Jun 18 18:50:39 2008 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Bytemark Hosting</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/bytemark_logo.png" linkto="http://www.bytemark.co.uk/r/gentoo-sponsors"
     short="Bytemark Hosting"/>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.bytemark.co.uk/r/gentoo-sponsors">Bytemark Hosting</uri>
provide Gentoo Linux with servers and services which drive our
network of global mirrors.  They are a leading Internet Service Provider (ISP)
in the United Kingdom and provide scalable, powerful and affordable hosting
with lots of "geek friendly" extras as standard. They've deployed Gentoo Linux
within their network to provide a flexible solution to difficult problems, such
as providing a network rescue environment for all dedicated hosts.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.57, Tue Mar 10 23:37:34 2009 UTC -->
<section>
<title>7L Networks</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/sevenl_logo.png" linkto="http://www.7L.com/"
     short="7L.com" />
 <p>
<uri link="http://www.7L.com/">7L</uri> Networks is a leader in <uri
link="http://www.7L.com/">Cloud Hosting</uri> services, dedicated servers, and
is a leading <uri
link="http://www.7L.com/business-hosting-solutions/Toronto-Colocation-Hosting-Provider.html">Toronto
server colocation provider</uri>. 
7L has been proudly donating server hosting services to Gentoo Linux since
2004. In addition, they donate dedicated servers to CentOS, Linux Mint, Arch
Linux and a number of other open source communities that rely on sponsorship to
succeed.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.115, Sun, 25 May 2014 13:00:36 +0000 -->
<section>
<title>DigiCert</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/digicert.jpg" linkto="http://www.digicert.com/"
     short="digicert.com" />
 <p>
DigiCert is a premier online trust provider of enterprise security solutions
with an emphasis on authentication and encryption via its PKI and
high-assurance digital certificates. Headquartered in Lehi, Utah, DigiCert
is trusted by a continually growing clientele of more than 80,000 of the
world's leading government, finance, healthcare, education and Fortune 500
organizations. The company also leads the market in enabling the Direct,
secure exchange of healthcare information via its DirectAssuredT
certificates. DigiCert has been recognized with dozens of awards for
providing enhanced customer value, premium customer support and market
growth leadership. For the latest DigiCert news and updates, visit
<uri link="https://digicert.com">digicert.com</uri>, like <uri
link="https://www.facebook.com/digicert">DigiCert on Facebook</uri> or follow
Twitter handle <uri link="https://twitter.com/digicert">@digicert</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.89, .... -->
<section>
    <title>TOP-IX &amp; Fastbull</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/topix-fastbull-400x125.png" linkto="http://www.top-ix.org/topix-e-fastbull-insieme-a-supporto-del-software-open-source-e-della-open-culture"
     short="TOP-IX &amp; Fastbull" />
<p><uri link="http://www.top-ix.org">TOP-IX</uri> (TOrino
Piemonte Internet eXchange) is a non-profit consortium set up in 2002 with the 
aim of creating and managing a NAP (Neutral Access Point) for the exchange of
Internet traffic in North West Italy. Starting from 2006 TOP-IX directly
supports start-ups and entrepreneurial environment with the <uri
link="http://www.top-ix.org/development-program">Development Program</uri>.</p>

<p><uri link="http://www.fastbull.org/">Fastbull</uri> association
aims at supporting and promoting opensource
software and free contents by means of mirroring services.</p>

<p>TOP-IX and Fastbull together foster broadband and 
open source culture.</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.91, 2010/11/18 23:46:57 -->
<section>
<title>DedicatedNOW</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/dedicatednow_logo.png" linkto="http://www.dedicatednow.com/"
     short="dedicatednow.com" />
<p>
<uri link="http://www.dedicatednow.com/">DedicatedNOW is an award winning
managed dedicated server</uri> provider located on the East Coast (US).
Established in 1997, DedicatedNOW provides managed dedicated servers,
colocation, server security, CDN and a wide range of complex hosting services.
</p>

<p>DedicatedNOW provides Gentoo with a dedicated server within its NY-Metro
datacenter.</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.92, .... -->
<section>
<title>hotelkatalog24/thinex</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/thinex-hotelkatalog24_logo.png" linkto="http://www.hotelkatalog24.de"
     short="hotelkatalog24.de" />
<p>
hotelkatalog24.de is a <uri link='http://www.hotelkatalog24.de'>hotel
catalogue</uri> and online travel agency founded in 2003. Today serving 90,000+
hotels with hotel descriptions from 150+ travel businesses, 450,000
hotelreviews and many thousand pictures from the most beautiful <uri
link='http://www.hotelkatalog24.de/urlaubsziele'>travel destinations</uri>.
</p>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.thinex.eu/">thinex</uri> provides IT services for
hotelkatalog24, and run Gentoo on their servers. Together, they support the
ongoing great work of the Gentoo developers and contributors by sponsoring a
server for the community.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.83, 2010/08/26 00:37:48 robbat2 Exp -->
<section>
    <title>Tek Alchemy</title>
<body>
<p>
<uri link="http://tek.net/">Tek Alchemy, Inc.</uri>, located in Austin, Texas
provides dedicated servers, VPS, managed servers and colocation in the US. They
host many Open Source Projects on dedicated servers including Gentoo. They
cater the the "geek" customer, providing stock or custom hardware, custom
operating system installations or "do it yourself" installations.  They offer
dedicated servers with the operating system of your choice, including Gentoo,
Debian, CentOS, Ubuntu, Fedora and more.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- Added by antarus on 20120606. -->
<section>
  <title>Indoor Cycling</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/indoorcycling-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.indoorcycling.org/"
     short="IndoorCycling" />
<p>
Indoorcycling.org is the leading expert in Europe for
<uri link="http://www.indoorcycling.org/">indoor cycling</uri> and
<uri link="http://www.indoorcycling.org/Nach-Marke/Spinning/">spinning</uri>.
They feature all the major labels and Brands such as Tomahawk, Star Trac and
<uri link="http://www.indoorcycling.org/Nach-Marke/Schwinn/">Schwinn</uri>, as
well as many house-brands. Because they want to focus on our business, they very
much depend on a reliable IT-Infrastructure for our servers, which is provided
by Linux and brought to a very high standard by Gentoo Linux. They welcome the
idea of OpenSource software and are very happy to contribute our small part by
sponsoring the project as a sign of their gratitude to the entire Gentoo
community.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added by antarus on 20120606 -->
<section>
  <title>Kartenzia</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/kartenzia-logo.jpg"
     linkto="http://www.kartenzia.de/"
     short="Kartenzia"/>
<p>
Kartenzia is a young start-up based in germany, providing their
customers with personalized invitations for various occasions like <uri
link="http://www.kartenzia.de/hochzeitskarten/">Hochzeitskarten</uri>
as well as <uri
link="http://www.kartenzia.de/weihnachtskarten/">Weihnachtskarten</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.50, Thu Jul 3 01:44:53 2008 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Buchhorn GmbH: Gutscheinexperte, Online Kredit Index, Fern Studiengang</title>
<body>
<p>
Buchhorn GmbH is a small development shop with diverse interests.  They follow
their hearts and personal credos in working to continuously secure the freedom
of Open Source Projects for all users. They greatly appreciate the value of
Gentoo and understand the necessity of supporting both developers and
infrastructure.
</p>
<p>
Find the best providers in Germany in distance learning at <uri
link="http://www.fern-studiengang.de/">Fern Studiengang</uri>.
</p>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.gutscheinexperte.de/">gutscheinexperte</uri> is a German online coupon portal.
</p>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/online-kredit-index.jpg" linkto="http://www.online-kredit-index.de/"
     short="Online Kredit Index" />
<p>
<uri link="http://www.online-kredit-index.de/">Online Kredit Index</uri>
is a German finance service provider. 
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added by antarus on 20140201 -->
<section>
  <title>Rackspace</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/rackspace-logo-sized.png"
     linkto="http://www.rackspace.com"
     short="Rackspace"/>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.rackspace.com">Rackspace®</uri> (NYSE: RAX) is the global leader in hybrid cloud and founder of OpenStack®, the open-source operating system for the cloud. Hundreds of thousands of customers look to Rackspace to deliver the best-fit infrastructure for their IT needs, leveraging a product portfolio that allows workloads to run where they perform best—whether on the public cloud, private cloud, dedicated servers, or a combination of platforms. The company's award-winning Fanatical Support® helps customers successfully architect, deploy, and run their most critical applications. Headquartered in San Antonio, TX, Rackspace operates data centers on four continents. Rackspace is featured on Fortune's list of 100 Best Companies to Work For.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added by ultrabug on 20141124 -->
<section>
  <title>Numberly</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/numberly-logo-sized.jpg"
     linkto="http://www.numberly.com"
     short="Numberly"/>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.numberly.com">Numberly</uri> is a 1000mercis Group brand, a pioneer in interactive advertising and marketing, providing innovative solutions for companies willing to optimise their customer acquisition and retention through interactive media (Internet, mobile phones and tablets). Numberly helps its clients to design, develop, implement, and maximise the ROI of their interactive marketing and advertising campaigns.
</p>
<p>Numberly proudly provides 3 powerful physical server dedicated to the Gentoo Infra with ipv6 support.</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added by a3li on 20130915 -->
<section>
  <title>LeaseWeb</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/leaseweb.png"
     linkto="http://www.leaseweb.com/"
     short="LeaseWeb"/>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.leaseweb.com/">LeaseWeb</uri> is a leading Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) provider serving a worldwide portfolio of over 15,000 
customers ranging from SMBs to Enterprises. Services include Public Cloud, Private Cloud, Hybrid Hosting, 
Colocation, CDN, and Dedicated Hosting supported by exceptional customer service and technical support. 
With more than 60,000 servers under management, LeaseWeb provides infrastructure since 1997. The 
company operates 6 data centers in the U.S. and Europe, all of which are backed by a superior worldwide 
network with a total capacity of more than 3.5 Tbps.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.64 2009/11/05 23:41:45 robbat2 Exp -->
<section>
<title>Hetzner Online AG</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/hetzner-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.hetzner.com/"
     short="Hetzner Online AG" />
<p>
<uri link="http://www.hetzner.com/">Hetzner Online</uri> is one of the leading
web hosting companies and data center operators in Germany.  They offer powerful
dedicated hosting solutions, managed servers, vServers, colocation, web space,
domains and SSL certificates.  Coupled with best prices and outstanding
support, Hetzner Online surpasses customers' expectations around the world.
Hetzner Online supports the Gentoo project with a powerful dedicated
server. 
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added by a3li on 20121116 -->
<section>
  <title>tintenalarm.de</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/tintenalarm-logo.jpg"
     linkto="http://www.tintenalarm.de/"
     short="tintenalarm.de"/>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.tintenalarm.de/Guenstige-Druckerpatronen.php">Tintenalarm.de</uri>
is a German family business specialized in offering rebuilt toner cartridges and
refilled ink cartridges with a two-year warranty. Their focus is on providing
goods from high-quality recyclers whose work is legally compliant.
<uri link="http://www.tintenalarm.de/Druckerzubehoer.php">www.tintenalarm.de</uri>
also sells original products for all types of printers, multifunction devices
and copiers.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.52, Thu Jul 10 18:19:46 2008 UTC -->
<section>
<title>WebHosting.UK.com</title>
<body>
	<fig link="/images/sponsors/web-hosting-uk-591x97.gif"
		 linkto="https://www.webhosting.uk.com/?utm_source=gentoo&amp;utm_medium=banner&amp;utm_campaign=gentoo.org"
		 short="WebHosting.UK.com" />
<p>
Founded in 2001, WebHosting UK offers cheap and affordable Gentoo Linux
Dedicated Servers in UK. Webhosting UK also provides fully managed Shared
hosting, Reseller Hosting, Semi Dedicated Hosting and Virtual Private Servers
with all important features such as 24x7x365 technical support, 99.95% Uptime
Guarantee included as standard.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.33, Fri Jun 10 14:44:58 2005 UTC -->
<section>
<title>HP</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/hp-logo.jpg" linkto="http://opensource.hp.com"
     short="HP OpenSource Logo"/>
<p>
HP is a technology solutions provider to consumers, businesses and
institutions globally.  HP has over 200 products that ship with open
source software.  From client to server to data center, HP is
contributing to hundreds of open source projects every day.  For
more information about HP's open source involvement, check out
<uri link="http://opensource.hp.com/">http://opensource.hp.com/</uri>
</p>
<p>
HP provides R&amp;D resources and has loaned and hosted Alpha and IA64 hardware
for the Gentoo project.
</p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<chapter>
<title>Specific donations</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo would like to thank the following companies and organizations who have
made specific donations to further the development of Gentoo.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.xx 2013/08/16 ..:..:.. robbat2 Exp -->
<section>
<title>Imagination Technologies</title>
<body>
	<fig link="/images/sponsors/imagination-tech.png" linkto="http://www.imgtec.com/News/Release/index.asp?NewsID=783"
     short="Imagination Technologies" />
<p>
<uri link="http://www.imgtec.com/News/Release/index.asp?NewsID=783">Imagination Technologies</uri>
is a global leader in multimedia, processor and communication technologies.
The company creates and licenses market-leading IP solutions for graphics,
video and vision, CPU/general purpose processing, multi-standard communications
and connectivity, and cross-platform voice and video communications.
Imagination's MIPS CPU cores and architectures range from solutions for ultra
low-power 32-bit microcontrollers to high-performance 32/64-bit advanced
applications and network processing.  MIPS is supported by a broad ecosystem of
tools and software including open source Linux distributions like Gentoo.
Imagination has donated two MIPS64-based Ubiquiti ERLite-3 routers, plus
resources to aid Gentoo in providing up-to-date root file system builds for
MIPS.
</p>
</body>
</section>


<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.67 2010/02/02 20:09:35 robbat2 Exp -->
<section>
<title>Opengear</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/opengear-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.opengear.com/"
     short="Opengear" />
<p>
<uri link="http://www.opengear.com/">Opengear</uri> designs and manufactures
next generation console server solutions for secure remote access and control
of network devices such as routers, switches, servers, firewalls,
uninterruptable power supplies, power distribution units and environmental
monitoring devices. The mission of Opengear is to be a leading supplier and
thought leader in open source technologies for infrastructure management and an
innovative developer of next generation console server and power management
solutions.  Opengear have donated a number of console servers to Gentoo.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: 1.18, Sat Mar 13 14:47:01 2004 UTC -->
<section>
<title>NVIDIA</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/nvidia-logo.gif" linkto="http://www.nvidia.com" 
     short="NVIDIA"/>
<p>
NVIDIA Corporation (Nasdaq: NVDA) is a market leader in visual
computing technology dedicated to creating products that enhance the
digital media experience on consumer and professional computing
platforms, from desktops and workstations to notebooks and handhelds.
The company's graphics and communications processors have broad market
reach and are incorporated into a wide variety of computing platforms,
including consumer PCs, enterprise PCs, professional workstations,
digital content creation systems, military navigation systems and video
game consoles.
</p>

<p>
NVIDIA has provided the Gentoo project with numerous AMD
development machines and video cards to further development of Gentoo on the
Athlon XP and Athlon64 platforms.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.43, Tue Sep 5 12:53:24 2006 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Cloanto</title>
<body>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.amigaforever.com/">Cloanto</uri> has donated the <uri
link="http://www.amigaforever.com/">Amiga Forever CD</uri> to support
development and maintenance of Amiga emulation software in Gentoo.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.63 2009/09/30 19:20:06 robbat2 Exp -->
<section>
<title>OSTC</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/ostc-ad.png" linkto="http://www.ostc.com/" short="OSTC" />
<p><uri link="http://www.ostc.com/">OSTC</uri> is the first and largest proprietary
derivatives trading company in Poland. They push the boundaries of global
market electronic trading using Gentoo and Open Source software as a
integral components.</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.24, Sat Nov 13 12:49:04 2004 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Genesi</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/genesi_logo.gif" linkto="http://www.genesi.lu/" 
     short="Genesi"/>
<p>
Genesi is a leading provider of Freescale and IBM PowerPC based
computing products. Genesi's <uri
link="http://www.pegasosppc.com">PegasosPPC MicroATX computer</uri> is
designed to bring PowerPC technology flexibility and efficiency to the
desktop, low-end server and pervasive market segments at an affordable
price.  Beginning with the 2004.3 release, the Open Desktop Workstation
will ship with Gentoo pre-installed.
</p>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.genesi.lu">Genesi</uri>  has provided many PowerPC based
<uri link="http://www.pegasosppc.com/odw.php">Open Desktop
Workstations</uri> to Gentoo. For information about Genesi's
involvement in the Linux Open Source community, please see
<uri link="http://www.ppczone.org">www.PPCZone.org</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.29, Tue Jun 7 08:09:05 2005 UTC -->
<section>
<title>DataRescue</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/datarescue-logo.gif"
     linkto="http://www.datarescue.com" short="DataRescue logo"/>
<p>
DataRescue is the developer of the IDA Pro Disassembler &amp; Debugger,
an essential tool for vulnerability research and hostile binary
analysis. DataRescue runs several of its public servers and its main
internal server on Gentoo Linux.
</p>

<p>
DataRescue has donated software to the Gentoo Audit Team.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>


<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<chapter>
<title>Past sponsors</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>Gentoo would like to extend a special thanks to all of our past sponsors.</p>

<p>If your organization previously has sponsored Gentoo, and was accidently
omitted from the following list, please don't hesitate to contact our
infrastructure team, so that we may recognize you. We've tried to track down
all past sponsors, but a few have been non-responsive to requests, or we simply
didn't know about them from the very early years of the project.</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.49, Wed Jun 18 18:50:39 2008 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Hyves.net</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/hyves-logo.png" linkto="http://www.hyves.net/"
     short="Hyves.net" />
<p>
Hyves provides Gentoo Linux with servers and hosting for the Bugzilla cluster.
They are a cutting-edge European social network, and run <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gmn/20080424-newsletter.xml#doc_chap3">
Gentoo on 1800+ servers</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v 1.71 2010/08/06 16:59:25 robbat2 Exp -->
<section>
<title>Hegerys</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/hegerys-logo.png" linkto="http://hegerys.com"
     short="gentoo dedicated servers provided by hegerys.com" />
<p>
Founded in 2003, Hegerys (formerly Euro-WEB &amp; SD-France) provides advanced
outsourcing solutions; leasing and hosting of dedicated servers; development
and customized services for SME to large corporate clients. Coupled with best
prices and outstanding customers support, Hegerys have over 5,000 customers and
850 managed servers. Hegerys supports the Gentoo project by providing them a
number of powerful dedicated servers coupled with strong IPv6 connectivity.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.21, Wed Oct 20 12:37:03 2004 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Global Netoptex, Inc.</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/gni_logo.png" linkto="http://www.netoptex.com" 
     short="Global Netoptex, Inc."/>
<p>
GNi is a leading provider of customer-centric managed services that extend 
their customer's infrastructure and dramatically reduce their customer's total 
cost of ownership. They provide the experts, resources and solutions to meet 
and exceed their customer's unique on-site and off-site requirements.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.4, 2003/04/29 -->
<!-- Formerly known as UltraDNS -->
<section>
<title>Neustar UltraDNS</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/neustar-logo.gif" linkto="http://ultradns.com/"
     short="NeuStar UltraDNS"/>
<p>
Neustar's UltraDNS provides advanced, highly intelligent, and globally scalable
directory service solutions that significantly enhance the performance and
reliability of networks and mission critical information-exchange applications.
</p>
<p>
Neustar previously provided DNS hosting services to the Gentoo project,
including advanced features including <uri 
link="http://www.ultradns.com/solutions/directionaldns.html">Directional 
DNS</uri> to provide load-balanced DNS services for our rsync.gentoo.org pool 
of rsync servers, and <uri 
link="http://www.ultradns.com/solutions/sitebacker.html">SiteBacker</uri> for
server health monitoring and failover capabilities to our core infrastructure
servers.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.11, Wed Oct 8 12:50:59 2003 UTC  -->
<section>
<title>Indiana University (IU)</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/iu-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.iu.edu" 
     short="Indiana University"/>
<p>
Indiana University was founded in Bloomington, Indiana in 1820.  The
University has since then grown to eight campuses across Indiana, with a
total enrollment reaching 100,000 graduate and undergraduate students.  IU
offers 116 academic programs that are ranked in the nation's top 20.
There are over 460,000 IU alumni worldwide.
</p>
<p>
Indiana University has provided colocation for Gentoo infrastructure servers, as 
well as a high volume source and portage mirror.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.35, Wed Jan 4 21:49:00 2006 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Department of Physics - University of Trieste</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/units_logo.png" linkto="http://physics.units.it"
     short="Department of Physics - University of Trieste"/>
<p>
The Physics department at the University of Trieste has provided infrastructure services to the 
Gentoo project and hosts all of our mailing lists for several years.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.35, Wed Jan 4 21:49:00 2006 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Inverse Path</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/inversepath_logo.png" linkto="http://www.inversepath.com"
     short="Inverse Path Ltd."/>
<p>
Inverse Path Ltd. is an international consultancy providing design and
implementation of secure network and infrastructures with particular expertise
in open source software. Among its services it offers Gentoo commercial
support for deployment in production environments as well as professional
training.
</p>
<p>
Inverse Path previously provided a VOIP server for use by Gentoo developers.
</p>
</body>
</section>


<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.1, Sun Mar 16 17:18:50 2003 UTC -->
<!-- removed: sponsors.xml, v1.13, Tue Dec 9 02:25:17 2003 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Pilosoft</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/pilosoft-logo.gif" linkto="http://www.pilosoft.com/" short="Pilosoft"/>
<p>
Pilosoft provides a multitude of Internet-related services, including DSL connectivity, shared and dedicated web hosting, colocation facilities and customized IP services.
</p>
<p>
Pilosoft provided bandwidth and colocation services for the Gentoo Linux project.
</p>
</body>
</section>


<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.1, Sun Mar 16 17:18:50 2003 UTC -->
<!-- removed: sponsors.xml, v1.20, Mon Oct 11 14:02:32 2004 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Southern Nazarene University (SNU)</title>
<body>
<p>
Founded in 1899, Southern Nazarene University is a private, Christian, liberal
arts university-a service of the Church of the Nazarene. Located on a 40-acre
campus just west of Oklahoma City, SNU grew out of several small colleges
committed to training people for service to God and their fellow man. More than
25,000 alumni work and serve throughout the United States and the world.
</p>
<p>
SNU provided use of a dedicated server and bandwidth to the Gentoo Linux project.
</p>
</body>
</section>


<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.1, Sun Mar 16 17:18:50 2003 UTC -->
<!-- removed: sponsors.xml, ???? -->
<section>
<title>University of Florida: Open Systems Group</title>
<body>
<p>
The <uri link="http://open-systems.ufl.edu/">Open Systems Group</uri> at the
<uri link="http://www.ufl.edu/">University of Florida</uri> previously hosted a
small cluster powering the rsync1.us.gentoo.org master mirror service for all
community mirrors.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.9, Sun Aug 17 23:26:25 2003 UTC -->
<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.17, Thu Feb 19 14:59:06 2004 UTC -->
<!-- removed: sponsors.xml, v1.20, Mon Oct 11 14:02:32 2004 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Melior, Inc.</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/melior-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.meliorinc.com" short="Melior"/>
<!-- <fig link="/images/sponsors/isecure-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.ddos.com"/> -->
<p>
Melior, Inc. provides proven distributed Denial of Service (dDoS) protection
and the industry's only Infrastructure Cloaking technology: the iSecure True
Intrusion Prevention System (TIPSTM)
</p>
<p>
Melior, Inc. provided the server, bandwidth and colocation facilities for a old
developer account box, main web node, and a dedicated rsync server.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.13, Tue Dec 9 02:25:17 2003 UTC -->
<!-- removed: sponsors.xml, v1.16, Sat Jan 31 13:30:52 2004 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Ethernetworks.de</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/ethernetworks-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.ethernetworks.de" short="Ethernetworks Germany"/>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.ethernetworks.de">Ethernetworks Germany</uri> is specialized on professional networking, internet security solutions as well as shared and dedicated web hosting. Server integration into multi platform business networks is Ethernetworks Deutschland main scope of duties, just as Crossplatform network design including Linux, MacOS X and Windows.
</p>
<p>
Ethernetworks Germany provided use of a PowerPC G4 along with colocation and bandwidth space for it.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.17, Thu Feb 19 14:59:06 2004 UTC -->
<!-- removed: sponsors.xml, v1.20, Mon Oct 11 14:02:32 2004 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Lumen Software</title>
<body>
<fig link="/images/sponsors/lumen.png" linkto="http://www.lumensoftware.com/" short="Lumen Software"/>
<p>
Lumen Software utilizes Gentoo as the base Linux distribution in all our
pre-configured server products. Lumen Software's EzThin Server products
are pre-configured Linux server solutions that provide a complete
solution for the small office to a large scale enterprise organization.
EzThin features pre-installed applications (productivity software,
graphics, etc.), virtual desktops (maintenance free and require no base
OS), remote access, centralized user and user desktop management,
automated server updates and more. Lumen Softwares development has
focused on creating an environment that allows organizations to take
advantage of the full benefits of Linux without the need of any Linux
experience or training. This focus has culminated into the EzThin Server
solutions we have today, with EzThin Server certified partnerships with
Dell and Gateway.</p>
<p>
Lumen Software provided funding in 2004 to further development of our Portage
package management solution.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.20, Mon Oct 11 14:02:32 2004 UTC -->
<!-- removed: sponsors.xml, v1.22, Thu Oct 21 17:05:03 2004 UTC -->
<section>
<title>Tera-Byte.com Inc</title>
<body>
<p>Tera-Byte.com is Canada's largest webhost, offering services ranging from
shared web hosting to virtual servers to co-location and dedicated servers.</p>
<p>Tera-Byte.com provided a dedicated rsync server which was part of the
rsync.gentoo.org rotation.</p>
</body>
</section>

<!-- added: sponsors.xml, v1.29, Tue Jun 7 08:09:05 2005 UTC -->
<!-- removed: sponsors.xml, v1.94 Tue Jun 3 04:31:17 UTC -->
<section>
<title>University of Virginia</title>
<body>

<fig link="/images/sponsors/virginia-logo.gif" linkto="http://www.virginia.edu"
short="University of Virginia Logo"/>

<p>
University of Virginia hosted quite a few Alpha boxes used by the Gentoo/Alpha
developers for building new Gentoo releases as well as daily work such as
keyword testing and security bumps.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<chapter>
<title>Source and rsync mirrors</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo relies heavily upon a global network of rsync and source mirrors.
Without these mirrors, access to new packages, updates to the Portage tree and 
new releases of Gentoo Linux would be impossible.  Some mirrors are provided by
individuals, others by companies. You can find a complete listing on our <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">Gentoo mirrors page</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- ====================================================================== -->
<chapter>
<title>Anonymous Sponsors</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Several other companies and organizations provide services and assistance to 
the Gentoo project, but have expressed a desire to remain anonymous.  We 
would like to thank those sponsors for their support of Gentoo.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- 
	TODO:

	Present:
	========
	Org: VR.org
	Contact: ...
	Boxes: loon.g.o, wren.g.o, magpie.g.o, motmot.g.o, cockatoo.g.o, sparrow.g.o

	Org: TopIX
	Contact: ...
	Boxes: kea.g.o

	Org: Gossamer
	Contact: ...
	Boxes: gannet.g.o, godwit.g.o, grebe.g.o, grouse.g.o
	
	Past:
    =====
	Org: Tavros Technology Services, Inc.
	Contact: kingtaco
	Boxes: waxwing.g.o

	Org: 36m
	Contact: kengland
	Boxes: heron.g.o, roadrunner.g.o

-->

</mainpage>
