<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE mainpage SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<mainpage id="sponsors">
<title>Gentoo Linux Sponsors</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail></author>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>16 March 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Linux Sponsors</title>
<section>
<title>Sponsors of Gentoo Linux</title>
<body>
		<p>
		Gentoo Linux would like to thank the following companies and organizations who donate various services and equipment to further the development of Gentoo Linux.  Without these organizations, Gentoo Linux would not be where it is today.
		</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Oregon State University</title>
<body>
	<fig link="/images/sponsors/osuosl-logo.jpg" linkto="http://osuosl.org" short="OSU Open Source Lab"/>
	<p>
	Located at <uri link="http://oregonstate.edu">Oregon State University</uri>
	in beautiful Corvallis, Oregon, the <uri link="http://osuosl.org">Open Source Lab</uri> is a focal point of
	development, hosting and other assorted services for the Open Source
	community.
	</p>
	<p>
	OSU provides several services to the Gentoo Linux project.  In addition to serving as the primary source mirror for Gentoo Linux, they also provide colocation space for several Gentoo Linux servers.
	</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Indiana University</title>
<body>
	<fig link="/images/sponsors/iu-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.iu.edu" short="Indiana University"/>
	<p>
	Indiana University was founded in Bloomington, Indiana in 1820.  The
	University has since then grown to eight campuses across Indiana, with a
	total enrollment reaching 100,000 graduate and undergraduate students.  IU
	offers 116 academic programs that are ranked in the nation's top 20.
	There are over 460,000 IU alumni worldwide.
	</p>
	<p>
	Indiana University provides colocation for Gentoo infrastructure servers, as well as a high volume source and portage mirror.
	</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>NVIDIA</title>
<body>
	<fig link="/images/sponsors/nvidia-logo.gif" linkto="http://www.nvidia.com" short="NVIDIA"/>
	<p>
	NVIDIA Corporation (Nasdaq: NVDA) is a market leader in visual
	computing technology dedicated to creating products that enhance the
	digital media experience on consumer and professional computing
	platforms, from desktops and workstations to notebooks and handhelds.
	The company's graphics and communications processors have broad market
	reach and are incorporated into a wide variety of computing platforms,
	including consumer PCs, enterprise PCs, professional workstations,
	digital content creation systems, military navigation systems and video
	game consoles.
	</p>
	<p>
	NVIDIA has provided the Gentoo Linux project with numerous AMD
	development machines and video cards to further development of Gentoo
	Linux on the Athlon XP and Athlon64 platforms.
	</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>UltraDNS</title>
<body>
	<fig link="/images/sponsors/ultradns-logo.jpg" linkto="http://www.ultradns.com" short="UltraDNS"/>
	<p>
	UltraDNS provides advanced, highly intelligent, and globally scalable directory service solutions that significantly enhance the performance and reliability of networks and mission critical information-exchange applications.
	</p>
	<p>
	UltraDNS provides DNS services to the Gentoo Linux project, including advanced features like <uri link="http://www.ultradns.com/services/ddns.html">Directional DNS</uri> to provide load-balanced DNS services for our rsync.gentoo.org pool of rsync servers, and <uri link="http://www.ultradns.com/services/sitebacker.html">SiteBacker</uri> to provide server health monitoring and failover capabilities to our core infrastructure servers.
	</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Global Netoptex, Inc.</title>
<body>
	<fig link="/images/sponsors/gni_logo.png" linkto="http://www.netoptex.com" short="Global Netoptex, Inc."/>
	<p>
	GNi is a leading provider of customer-centric managed services that extend their customer's infrastructure and dramatically reduce their customer's total cost of ownership. They provide the experts, resources and solutions to meet and exceed their customer's unique on-site and off-site requirements.
	</p>
	<p>
	GNi provides a dedicated server that is used to provide BitTorrent seeds to our users.
	</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Source and rsync mirrors</title>
<body>
	<p>
	Gentoo Linux relies heavily upon a global network of rsync and source mirrors.  Without these mirrors, access to new packages, updates to the Portage tree and new releases of Gentoo Linux would be impossible.  Some mirrors are provided by individuals, others by companies.  Below is a sampling of some of our mirror providers:</p>
	<table>
		<tr>
			<th>Name</th><th>Mirror Type</th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti><uri link="http://www.pair.com">pair Networks</uri></ti><ti>Source</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti><uri link="http://www.ibiblio.org">ibiblio</uri></ti><ti>Source</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti><uri link="http://www.ufl.edu">University of Florida</uri></ti><ti>rsync</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti><uri link="http://www.netoptex.com">GNI</uri></ti><ti>rsync</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti><uri link="http://www.zentek-international.com">Zentek</uri></ti><ti>Source</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<ti><uri link="http://www.munich.net">Munich.net</uri></ti><ti>rsync</ti>
		</tr>
	</table>
	<note>Since some sponsors wish to remain anonymous, we only list mirrors here upon request.  If you would like to see your mirror added to this list, please contact <mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail></note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Other Sponsors</title>
<body>
	<p>
	Several other companies and organizations provide services and assistance to the Gentoo Linux project, but have expressed a desire to remain anonymous.  We would like to thank those sponsors for their support of Gentoo Linux.
	</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
