<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>Releng Status Report</title>
<author><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail></author>
<abstract>Status report of the Releng project</abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>June 07, 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>This is the status report of the Gentoo Release Engineering project,
commonly abbreviated as "releng". Status reports will be posted by the
releng strategic manager, <mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail>, on
a regular basis. Questions regarding releng can be directed to the
releng <mail link="gentoo-releng@gentoo.org">mailing list</mail>. </p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content</title>
<body>

<p>The following subjects will be covered in this status update:</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap2">News</uri></li>
<li><uri link="#doc_chap3">Catalyst News/ Updates</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>News</title>
<section>
<body>

<p><mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail> has been named the releng
QA Manager. His jobs include maintenance of the livecd herd,
x86 LiveCD QA and testing, and general testing of release materials. Congratulations!</p>

<p><mail link="roger55@gentoo.org">Roger Miliker</mail> is now an official part of releng
and will be working with beejay on x86 releases. Welcome!</p>

<p>2004.2 testing has been officially underway for quite some time. The PPC team has
been busy building 2004.2 test releases, which are available for
<uri link="http://metadistribution.org/gentoo/experimental/2004.2-rc/">download</uri>.</p>

<p>The x86 team is working hard on improving LiveCDs and is actively tracking the
<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=51396">progress</uri>. Test LiveCDs
can be found on wolf31o2's <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~wolf31o2">devspace</uri>.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Catalyst News/ Updates</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>Catalyst will shortly be bumped to version 1.0.8.1 in Portage to reflect
the changes explained below. The update is dependent on the stabilization of Genkernel
3.0.2b, so as soon as it is stable, Catalyst 1.0.8.1 will be stable as well. </p>

<p>The Catalyst <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/*checkout*/src/catalyst/ChangeLog?rev=1.59&amp;root=gentoo&amp;content-type=text/plain">ChangeLog</uri>
contains details regarding all commits made to the Catalyst codebase, but the following
highlights are of special interest: </p>

<p>A new option for snapshots, portdir_overlay, has been added. As you may have guessed,
portdir_overlay allows for the use of a Portage Overlay directory in the Portage Snapshot.
It can be invoked as so: <c>catalyst target=snapshot version_stamp=foo portdir_overlay=/foo</c>. </p>

<p>DistCC support in Catalyst has been much improved. There had been issues with bind mounts,
but tweaks to the distcc process handling code in Portage should remedy those problems. </p>

<p>Portage snapshot creation time has been improved dramatically thanks to some rsync tweaks.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
