<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
  <name>Gentoo PPC</name>
  <longname>Gentoo Linux PowerPC Development</longname>
  <date>May 20, 2004</date>

  <description>
    The PowerPC Development Project is devoted to keeping Gentoo in good shape
    on the PowerPC architecture.
  </description>

  <longdescription>

    <p>The Gentoo/PPC Project works to keep Gentoo the most up to date and
    fastest PowerPC distribution available. We are responsible for the
    maintainance of all powerpc specific meta-data and the testing of all other
    non powerpc specific meta-data on the PowerPC architecture to ensure
    portability. Portability implies reuseable meta-data.</p>

    <p>Bugs are tracked and resolved from the <uri
    link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo bug tracker</uri> (for only ppc related bugs 
    check this <uri link="http://tinyurl.com/34byx">
    link</uri>) and correspondence is
    maintained on the various PowerPC related mailinglists.  (gentoo-ppc-user,
    gentoo-ppc-dev and those belonging to the sub-projects).</p>

  </longdescription>

  <goals>

    <p>The goal of the Gentoo PowerPC development project is to guarantee that
    the PowerPC packages build using Gentoo meta-data are up to date.  By
    continuously enhancing the meta-data, we provide the PowerPC user with the
    Gentoo community feeling, performance, freedom and up to dateness.  The
    meta-distribution notion allows for a user to to be as bleeding edge as
    he/she wants:</p>

    <p>Gentoo is unique because of its interpretation of the Meta-Distribution
    notion: all architectures share the same 'generic' meta-data (information
    about how to build packages - how to build a distribution). The PowerPC
    developers are responsible for building and testing packages using this
    meta-data.  The meta-data gets marked 'tested' or 'stable' afterwards,
    depending on the building and testing expierience. Our users can use (but
    don't have to use) this information to build a system that suits their
    needs.</p>

  </goals>

  <extraproject name="LiveCD/DVD" lead="pvdabeel">

    <p>The development and maintenance of LiveCD related tools. A livecd is a
    bootable wrapper around a live gentoo environment. A live gentoo environment
    is applied meta-data. This project gives people an opportunity to build and
    create their own bootable Gentoo LiveCD or LiveDVD. A liveCD/DVD primary
    purpose is to showcase what a concrete realisation of the meta-data will
    look like. Often Specialized livecds are build; automated distributed cross
    compile no livecds, Livecds that allow people working on PowerPC hardware
    development to write and test drivers without having to install...</p>

    <p>The livecd project works closely together with other architectures,
    developing a generic multi-architecture and multi-platform liveCD/DVD
    building tool.</p>

  </extraproject>

  <extraproject name="Stages" lead="pvdabeel">

    <p>The development and maintenance of 'stage' tarballs. A stage tarball is a
    live environment, packed and compressed into a UNIX tarball. A live
    environment is applied meta-data. (some packages forming a concrete Gentoo
    system).</p>

    <p>The Stages project works closely together with other architectures,
    developing a generic multi-architecture and multi-platform live environment
    building tool.</p>

    <p>
    This project has a GLEP pending:
    <ul>
      <li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/portage/">Portage
      enhancement</uri>: allow users to create their own virtual stage (for
      instance a desktop stage or a server stage ... ). This functionality will
      be demo-ed in the <uri
      link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/portage/portage-ng/systemspec.xml">portage-ng</uri>
      prototype core.</li>
    </ul>
    </p>

  </extraproject>

  <subproject ref="/proj/en/base/ppc/stable.xml"/>
  <subproject ref="/proj/en/base/ppc/doc.xml"/>

  <extraproject name="Kernels" lead="dholm">

    <p>Responsible for creating and maintaining PowerPC kernels. This includes
    creating and maintaining the kernel configuration for use on the
    LiveCD/DVDs.</p>

    <p>ppc-kernel-developers:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>dholm</li>
      <li>sejo</li>
      <li>johnm</li>
      <li>lu_zero</li>
    </ul>

  </extraproject>

  <dev role="Operational Manager" description="Gentoo/PPC">lu_zero</dev>
  <dev role="Tactical Manager" description="Gentoo/PPC">Pylon</dev>
  <dev role="subproject lead" description="LiveCD/DVD">pvdabeel</dev>
  <dev role="subproject lead" description="Stages">pvdabeel</dev>
  <dev role="subproject lead" description="Stable">dostrow</dev>
  <dev role="subproject lead" description="Kernel">dholm</dev>
  <dev role="subproject lead" description="Documentation">SeJo</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="Gentoo Compressed Loop filesystem, core system">lu_zero</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="Pegasos port, kernel">dholm</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="kernel">sejo</dev>
 
  <extrachapter position="top">
    <title>News</title>
    <section>
	<title>2004-08-10: Strategic Lead</title>
	<body>
	 <p>
	   Since 2004-07-22 Pylon has been taking over Pieters Strategical Lead. In fact it was with great pleasure that Pieter proposed Pylon as "The man for the job" in our meeting. We thank Pieter or his support, motivation and continuous effort for PPC. 
	   We wish to thank Pylon for taking on the effort and are happy to know PPC is in good hands. 
	 </p>
	</body>
    </section>
    <section>
	<title>2004-05-20: ppc64</title>
	<body>
	 <p>
	   The ppc64 efforts and development is brought to you by tgall you can check his <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~tgall/">site</uri> for 
	   changes and informations. He is also helping other subprojects with his expertise on powerpc and specific hardware. 
	 </p>
	</body>
    </section>
    <section>
	<title>2004-05-20: New roles</title>
	<body>
	 <p>The ppc-team has changed some roles and assigned new persons to the subproject. First of all
	    we wish to thank the developers who have helped us so far. They have done an excellent job and have made
            ppc as it is now. <br/>
	    We wish to thank dostrow for taking the stable project under his wings. He has recently become a developer but has 
	    already served ppc with great motivation and effort. <br/>
	    dholm will be leading the kernel branch and johnm, lu_zero and sejo will be helping him. We all know that dholm is a great teamplayer
	    and we are proud that he wishes to take the lead on this subproject.<br/>
	    This website will be taken care of by sejo, and he'll be taking on the documentation subproject. Bear with him as he might overlook
	    some spelling errors :-).
	    Currently we would like to ask any of you who are interested in working with this team to step forward in the irc channel and ask
	    one of us to help out. We are still looking for some hard workers to join our team. 	
	 </p>
	</body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>2004-05-20: New operational manager</title>
      <body>
        <p>The ppc-team voted for Luca Barbato (lu_zero) as the operational
        manager.  He takes care and makes decisions on the daily work on
        Gentoo/PPC. He will also keep helping the kernel team and other subprojects
	where he can. 
        Usually you can find him in the channel #gentoo-ppc in the
        freenode-IRC-Net. 
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

  <extrachapter position="bottom">
    <title>How to Participate</title>
    <section>
      <body>

        <p>Can you make computers do amazing things? Are you excited about
        exploring areas of computing never explored before? We are continuously
        looking for volunteers willing to spend some of their free time on this
        project. In return for your work, you get the respect of the PPC
        community.</p>

        <p>If you are interested in helping, but don't have a niche that you are
        interested in filling, you can always look through <uri
        link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>. There are many many
        bugs waiting to be found and fixed and many enhancements looking to find
        someone to code them. Figure out a fix, implement it, test it, and then
        keep trying to make the patch smaller. Post it for review on <uri
        link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>, and keep working on
        it. If it seems ignored, make a new comment in the bug and/or mention it
        in #gentoo-ppc in the freenode-IRC-Net.</p>
        <p>for more information on how the PPC team recruits please read <uri link="recruitement.xml">this</uri> doc.
        </p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

<herd name="ppc"/>

</project>
