<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>PPC Recruitment Documentation</title>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="sejo@gentoo.org">Jochen Maes</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="josejx@gentoo.org">Joseph Jezak</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document provides Gentoo/PPC users information about joining the 
development team.  This will also give the PPC team, and its users 
criteria for becoming a Gentoo/PPC Developer.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/license/by-sa/1.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2005-06-17</date>
  
<chapter>
<title>Becoming a Gentoo/PPC Developer</title>
<section>
<title>Who can be a developer?</title>
<body>
	
<p>
The answer is simple: Anyone who puts effort in Gentoo/PPC.  As long
as you are contributing to the project in one way or another, you can 
join the team. The more active developers we have, the better we can 
provide our userbase with documentation, support and up to date 
packages.  We expect you  to provide your knowledge, time and effort to
the community. If you are only interested in having a gentoo.org email 
address or a title for your resume, please walk away. We'll notice and 
if necessary, we'll apply to remove your status.  Only the dedicated 
need apply!
</p>
    
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Why be a developer?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are passionate about Gentoo/PPC, and you know you are able 
to help out in some area's why not help us improve? Gentoo is all about
the community, our users (even the developers are users!). If nobody put
in any effort, Gentoo would cease to exist.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
  
<chapter>
<title>Steps to Becoming a Developer</title>
<section>
<title>Step 1: Get Involved</title>
<body>

<p>
It sounds simple, but the first step in becoming a Gentoo Developer 
is to get involved! Speak with us on our IRC channel, #gentoo-powerpc on 
<uri link="http://www.freenode.net">freenode</uri>, help users on the 
forums and aid the Gentoo/PPC team by submitting patches and testing 
packages that are missing keywords.  Use the project to help others, 
thereby helping yourself. All good developers know that helping other 
users always provides learning opportunities, make the most of it! 
<e>"By learning you will teach, by teaching you will learn."</e>
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Step 2: Make Yourself Known</title>
<body>

<p>
Make the developers notice you by helping out, working hard and being
a team player, not by making trouble.  Once you've been noticed, an
existing developer will ask if you are interested in becoming a member
of the team.  This person will probably become your mentor and will open
a bug in bugzilla stating that that they are training you to become a
developer.   From that moment on the whole administrative process has
been started and you are on your way to becoming a Gentoo Developer! 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Step 3: Get Busy!</title>
<body>

<p>
This step begins once you have received your shiny new developer 
status! From now on, you are part of the team. You'll be attending
meetings, you'll keep a presence on IRC, you'll be committing things to
CVS and fixing bugs. If you're not busy, you are on the wrong track. But
it's not all work.  Being a developer is having fun while improving your
favorite OS, Gentoo! Go forth and squash bugs <e>new</e> Developer!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
