<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/proj/en/base/ppc/recuitement.xml">
	<title>PPC Recruitement Documentation</title>
	<author title="Creator">
		<mail link="sejo@gentoo.org">Jochen Maes</mail>
	</author>
	<abstract>Recuitement</abstract>
	<version>1.0</version>
	<date>28 May 2004</date>
	<chapter>
		<title>General Information</title>
		<section>
			<title>Purpose of this document</title>
			<body>
				<p>
					The purpose is to provide Gentoo PPC Users the needed information for joining the team.
					This will give the leads, as the users a kind of checklist.
				</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Who can be a developer?</title>
			<body>
				<p>
					Anyone who puts effort in PPC. This is very simple are you contributing to the project in one way or the other, 
					you can join the team. The more the better we can provide the userbase with usefull apps, documentation, support, etc.
					The fact that you want to become a developer is already a sign you are really using the system and trying to provide your knowledge 
					time and effort to the community. If however you are more interested in having a gentoo.org email addy or having the status for your resume, 
					please walk away. We'll notice straight away and if necessary we will apply to remove your status.
				</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Why be a developer?</title>
			<body>
				<p>
					This is a simpel one :p. If you are passionate about Gentoo/PPC, and you know you are able to help out in some area's why wouldn't you? 
					Gentoo is all about the community, the users (devs are also users!). If they don't do the effort then Gentoo ceases to exist. 
				</p>
			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	<chapter>
		<title>Steppy thingie</title>
		<section>
			<title>Step one: get involved</title>
			<body>
				<p>
					How stupid it might look but the first step is get involved! Be there on the irc channel, forum and help where you can. 
					Use bugzilla and try helping out with bugfixing. Provide assistance to people who are in need of assistance whereever you can. 
					Use the project to help others, and thus yourself. All developers know that helping other users always provide learning opportunities, 
					that can be very usefull. <b>"By learning you will teach, by teaching you will learn."</b>
				</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Step two: get yourself known</title>
			<body>
				<p>
					If the developers notice you, and find out you are a hard worker and a good teamplayer you will be instantly be asked to join the team. 
					At that moment the person asking you to be developer will probably be your mentor. You will need a mentor, 
					one you can hassle with all the questions you might need to ask. Off course it is up to you to try to find the answers somewhere else (read documentation)
					before hassling your mentor. The mentor will open a bug in bugzilla stating his will to add you to the developer team and being your mentor/promotor. 
					From that moment on the whole administrative process is started. 
				</p>
			</body>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Step three: get yourself busy</title>
			<body>
				<p>
					This step starts when you received your dev status. This means from now on you are part of the team. 
					You'll be attending the meetings, you'll be committing things to CVS etc. If you don't do that you are on the wrong track. 
					Being a developer is having fun while improving your favourite OS. A developer is supposed to help out and provide 
					solutions for Gentoo. 
				</p>
			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</guide>
