<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
	<name>kernel</name>
	<longname>Gentoo Kernel Project</longname>
	<description>The Gentoo Kernel project has the goal of bringing a stable and consistent
kernel feature set across all architectures supported by Gentoo Linux</description>
	<longdescription>
<p>
With an ever increasing userbase, which is constantly demanding a higher quality distribution
the demand for stable, professionally managed kernel sources are very important. Because we
as users want the best from Gentoo Linux we supply a selection of generic and specialised
sources.
</p>
<p>
In order to provide a rich choice of high quality kernel trees Gentoo
Linux must combine and test several kernel patches before they can offer
finished ebuilds to the users. This is where the Gentoo Kernel
Project comes into play.
</p>
	</longdescription>
<goals><p>
The Gentoo Kernel Project aims to deliver the best possible experience from its sources
across all supported architectures.
By having a clearly set management team with published objectives, established time lines, and
project accountability, the project will help bring the end-user
experience for our kernels to even higher levels.
</p></goals>
	<extraproject name="alpha-sources" lead="wwoods">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting alpha processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="gentoo-sources" lead="plasmaroo">
		Feature-rich, high-performance Gentoo Kernel based from the 2.4 branch for x86 processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="gentoo-dev-sources" lead="dsd">
		Reliable, highly compatible Gentoo Kernel based from the 2.6 branch for x86, sparc, ppc and others
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="hppa-sources" lead="gmsoft">
		Gentoo Kernel based from the 2.4 branch supporting pa-risc processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="hppa-dev-sources" lead="gmsoft">
		Gentoo Kernel based from the 2.6 branch supporting pa-risc processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="mips-sources" lead="kumba">
		Gentoo Kernel based from the 2.4 branch supporting MIPS processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="pegasos-dev-sources" lead="dholm">
		Gentoo Kernel based from the 2.6 branch for the pegasos architecture
	</extraproject>
	
	<extraproject name="sparc-sources" lead="joker">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting SPARC processors
	</extraproject>

	<extrachapter position="subproject">
	<title>Other Kernels (not patched by Gentoo Kernel Project)</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>
	The Gentoo Kernel project provides ebuilds for other linux kernels such as vanilla-sources,
	ck-sources, mm-sources, usermode-sources etc. Most of these are not patched by Gentoo
	in any way, and therefore are provided as a courtesy.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>
	<dev role="lead" description="kernel lead">johnm</dev>
	<dev description="alpha-sources">wwoods</dev>
	<dev description="gentoo-sources">plasmaroo</dev>
	<dev description="gentoo-dev-sources">dsd</dev>
	<dev description="gentoo-dev-sources, udev, hotplug etc.">gregkh</dev>
	<dev description="hppa-sources, hppa-dev-sources">gmsoft</dev>
	<dev description="mips-sources">kumba</dev>
	<dev description="pegasos-dev-sources">dholm</dev>
	<dev description="sparc-sources">joker</dev>
	<dev description="various sources, vesafs-tng and gensplash">spock</dev>
	<dev description="hardened-sources and various other things">tseng</dev>
	<dev description="Documentation liaison">swift</dev>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Other info</title>
<section>
<title>Quality Objectives</title>
<body>
<p>
Each subproject must make sure that the kernel ebuilds they provide
adhere to the following quality demands:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Each kernel ebuild must compile and work on as many systems as possible before committing to the Portage tree (even if <path>package.mask</path> is used).</li>
<li>Each kernel ebuild should not have Gentoo-specific bugs on <uri>http://bugs.gentoo.org/</uri> in the last 1-2 weeks after being released before moving from <path>~ARCH</path> to <path>ARCH</path></li>
<li>Every kernel-tree released by the Gentoo Kernel Project must have a clear description on what it provides and what philosophy is behind it's existence</li>
<li>Any kernel feature that has a userspace utility, must have the appropriate userspace utility ready for inclusion in portage before the kernel is released (ie. evms2, freeswan, USAGI,...). All packages should be released at the same time.</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Time line Objectives</title>
<body>

<p>
As kernels continue to develop in a vast pace, the Gentoo Kernel Project
must make sure that it keeps track of all kernel trees it provides so
that our users will receive the latest and greatest kernel trees in a
timely fashion without losing the quality they are accustomed to.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Accountability</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo Kernel Project cannot guarantee that the provided
kernel ebuilds work on your system, but will rectify any faults with supported sources.
Some sources (upstream sources) cannot be supported.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<extrachapter>
<title>Project Documentation</title>
<section>
<title>Roadmap</title>
<body>
<p>
As with most projects, the Gentoo Kernel Project and it's subprojects
use a roadmap to inform the users and developers about current
development items, near-future integrations, seeable future enhancements
and far future proposals.
</p>
<!-- <p>
You can view our roadmap <uri link="roadmap.xml">here</uri>.
</p> -->

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Kernel Documentation</title>
<body>
<p>
In order for our users to be able to pick the best kernel ebuild we
provide them with a <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-kernel.xml">Kernel Guide</uri>
in which all available kernel ebuilds are listed and described.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!--

<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux Enhancement Proposals</title>
<body>
<p>
The following GLEPs handle kernel-specific items and are therefor aimed
at the Gentoo Kernel Project:
</p>
<p>
No GLEPs so far.
</p>

<table>
 <tr>
  <th>GLEP</th>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>Involved Developers</th>
  <th>Status</th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <ti><uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-XXXX.html">XX</uri></ti>
  <ti>Proposal to foo bar bleh bla bla.</ti>
  <ti>john doe, mike bike</ti>
  <ti>Working on it, Implemented, No Implementation Needed,
  Dismissed</ti>
 </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>

-->

</extrachapter>
<extrachapter>
<title>Mailing lists</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-kernel@gentoo.org</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo Kernel Mailing List
</p>
<p>
Subscription information: Closed for now
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<herd name="x86-kernel"/>
</project>
