<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
	<name>kernel</name>
	<longname>Gentoo Kernel Project</longname>
	<description>The Gentoo Kernel project has the goal of bringing a stable and consistent
kernel feature set across all architectures supported by Gentoo Linux</description>
	<longdescription>
<p>
With an ever increasing userbase demanding a higher quality of stable, production-ready kernel sources and featureful desktop support the professionalism and staffing of the kernel project is very important. Because we as users want the best from Gentoo Linux we supply a selection of both generic and specialised sources capable of handling the day-to-day grind to make life a little easier.
</p>
<p>
In order to provide a rich choice of high quality kernel trees Gentoo Linux must apply, write and test several kernel patches to the official upstream releases before they can offer finished ebuilds to the users. This is where the Gentoo Kernel project comes into play.
</p>
	</longdescription>
<goals><p>
The Gentoo Kernel Project aims to deliver the best possible experience from its sources across all supported architectures. By maintaining quality control, clearly defined road maps, highly skilled developers and a standard base across all of our kernels the project will help bring the end-user experience of our kernels to even higher levels.
</p></goals>
	<extraproject name="gentoo-sources" lead="mpagano">
		Full sources including the Gentoo patchset for the 2.6 kernel tree. [2.6]
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="mips-sources" lead="kumba">
		Gentoo Kernel based from the 2.4 branch supporting MIPS processors [2.4/2.6]
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="sparc-sources" lead="joker">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting SPARC processors [2.4]
	</extraproject>
	<extrachapter>
	<title>Genpatches</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>
	Many kernels in Gentoo include part or all of the genpatches patchset. genpatches is focused on being a minimal patchset mostly focused on bugfixes, with minimal deviation from the upstream Linux kernel.
	</p>
	<p>
	The genpatches homepage can be found at <uri>http://dev.gentoo.org/~mpagano/genpatches</uri>.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>
	<extrachapter>
	<title>Maintainers guide</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>
	In order to encourage new contributors, we have documented the procedures used when maintaining gentoo-sources-2.6. The document can be found <uri link="maintenance.xml">here</uri>.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>
	<extrachapter position="subproject">
	<title>Other Kernels</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>
	The Gentoo Kernel herd maintains the following list of kernels currently in portage. 
	Additional kernels in portage that are not listed below are not maintained under the kernel herd.
	</p>
	<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Kernel</th><th>Description</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>ck-sources</ti><ti>Con Kolivas' kernel sources.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>git-sources</ti><ti>git sources, the absolute latest kernel available.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>hardened-sources</ti><ti>Sources based upon genpatches-base along with the grsecurity patch which includes Pax.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>mm-sources</ti><ti>Andrew Morton's patchset for 2.6 consisting of experimental features, cleanups, and other interesting patches.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>tuxonice-sources</ti><ti>TuxOnIce (formerly Suspend2) sources and the Gentoo patchset.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>usermode-sources</ti><ti>Full sources for the User Mode Linux kernel.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>vanilla-sources</ti><ti>Full prepatched/rc sources for the Linux kernel.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>xbox-sources</ti><ti>Full sources for the Xbox Linux kernel.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>pf-sources</ti><ti>Linux kernel fork with new features, including the -ck patchset (BFS), BFQ, TuxOnIce and UKSM.</ti>
	</tr>
	</table>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>
	<dev description="Kernel, git-sources, gentoo-sources, udev, hotplug etc.">gregkh</dev>
	<dev description="Kernel, hppa-sources">gmsoft</dev>
	<dev description="Kernel, mips-sources">kumba</dev>
	<dev role="lead" description="Kernel, gentoo-sources, genpatches">mpagano</dev>
	<dev description="Kernel, sparc-sources">joker</dev>
	<dev description="Kernel, vesafb-tng, gensplash and splashutils">spock</dev>
	<dev description="Kernel, mm-sources, vanilla-sources">chainsaw</dev>
	<dev description="Kernel, User Mode Linux">dang</dev>
	<dev description="Kernel, tuxonice-sources, ck-sources">nelchael</dev>
    <dev description="Kernel, hardened">blueness</dev>
    <dev description="Kernel, hardened">gengor</dev>
    <dev description="Kernel, hardened">nixnut</dev>
    <dev description="Kernel, hardened">pebenito</dev>
	<dev description="Kernel, gentoo-sources, genpatches">psomas</dev>
    <dev description="Kernel, hardened">solar</dev>
    <dev description="Kernel, hardened">zorry</dev>
<extrachapter>
<title>Project Documentation</title>
<section>
<title>Kernel Documentation</title>
<body>
<!--In order for our users to be able to pick the best kernel ebuild we provide them with a <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-kernel.xml">Kernel Guide</uri> in which all available kernel ebuilds are listed and described.-->
<dl>
  <dt><b>Gentoo Linux Kernel Documentation:</b></dt>
  <dd>
    <ul>
      <li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-kernel.xml">Gentoo Linux Kernel Guide</uri></li>
      <li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/kernel-upgrade.xml">Gentoo Linux Kernel Upgrade Guide</uri></li>
      <li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/kernel-config.xml">Gentoo Linux Kernel Configuration Guide</uri></li>
      <li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/migration-to-2.6.xml">Gentoo Linux 2.4 to 2.6 Kernel Migration Guide</uri></li>
    </ul>
  </dd>
</dl>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<extrachapter>
<title>Kernel Stablization</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
The following policy is in place for kernel stabilization that can be performed by members of the kernel team without opening a stabilization bug.  For this to occur, the following procedures must be followed:
</p>
<dl>
  <dt><b>For new kernel major point releases (e.g. 2.6.X)</b></dt>
  <dd>
    <ul>
      <li>A stable request bug is opened and arch teams stabilize as per existing policy. No auto stabilizing occurs here as only the arch teams can really determine if the kernel is working on their own arch.</li>
    </ul>
  </dd>
  <dt><b>For subsequent security related releases of a kernel point release 2.6.X.Y</b></dt>
  <dd>
    <ul>
      <li>If the kernel team determines a significant security fix is included for a kernel release of 2.6.X.y where 2.6.X or 2.6.X.(Y-1) has already been stabilized per the first bullet, the kernel team can auto stabilize that specific version</li>
      <li>Dependant upon the severity of the security bug, (root exploit, minor module) the kernel team will remove stable keywords from earlier versions of the same 2.6.X series within a reasonable timeframe. </li>
    </ul>
  </dd>
</dl>
</body>
</section>

<!--

<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux Enhancement Proposals</title>
<body>
<p>
The following GLEPs handle kernel-specific items and are therefor aimed
at the Gentoo Kernel Project:
</p>
<p>
No GLEPs so far.
</p>

<table>
 <tr>
  <th>GLEP</th>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>Involved Developers</th>
  <th>Status</th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <ti><uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-XXXX.html">XX</uri></ti>
  <ti>Proposal to foo bar bleh bla bla.</ti>
  <ti>john doe, mike bike</ti>
  <ti>Working on it, Implemented, No Implementation Needed,
  Dismissed</ti>
 </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>

-->
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Mailing lists</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-kernel@gentoo.org</title>
<body>
<p>The <uri link="http://archives.gentoo.org/gentoo-kernel/">Gentoo Kernel Mailing List</uri> is a public mailing list for the discussion of project related topics and release announcements for genpatches, vesafb-tng and fbsplash.
</p>
<p>
Gentoo maintains a a full listing of all public <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml">Gentoo Mailing Lists</uri> as well as information on how to subscribe and unsubscribe.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Useful Links</title>
<section>
<body>
<dl>
  <dt><b>Additional Information and External Links:</b></dt>
  <dd>
    <ul>
      <li><uri link="http://www.reactivated.net/weblog/archives/2006/01/using-git-bisect-to-find-buggy-kernel-patches/">Using git-bisect to find buggy kernel patches</uri></li>
      <li><uri link="http://www.reactivated.net/weblog/archives/2007/04/using-ketchup-to-quickly-install-kernel-sources/">Using ketchup to quickly install kernel sources</uri></li>
    </ul>
  </dd>
</dl>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<herd name="kernel"/>
<herd name="kernel-misc"/>
</project>
