<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd"> 

<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Programming">
<name>Gentoo Programming Resources</name>
<longname>Gentoo Resources for Programming Languages</longname>

<date>22 Jul 2008</date>

<author title="Developer">
<mail link="george@gentoo.org">George Shapovalov</mail>
</author>


<description>
Gentoo Specific Support for Programming Environments.
</description>

<longdescription><p>
The project provides coverage for Gentoo specific issues associated with 
various programming languages that can be found in portage. Right now the 
top level is mostly a placeholder for all the individual subprojects. However
common initiatives covering the topic are wellcome! Everybody interested is 
invited to take a look at the
<uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=151118">bug #151118</uri>
and take part in discussion.
</p></longdescription>

<goals>
<p> 
The overal goal is to provide necessary resources supporting "The Gentoo
Way" of dealing with programming environments. That is, flexible setup
and, where it makes sense, coexisting multiple versions/realizations of
compilers with an easy way to switch between those, while automating
mundane tasks.
</p>

<p>
Often it happens that multiple compiler suits can be used to compile
existing libraries.  However the resulting libs are usually ABI
incompatible, meaning that code utilizing these libs should be compiled
with the same compiler. This situation can be further complicated by
interdependencies between the provided libs. To address this situation it
is necessary to introduce some kind of "ABI tracking" ability. Ideally
this would be done by providing some extra dependency info and having
portage deal with it. However this requires support on the portage side
and as it is not going to happen soon.  There is a discussion under way on
how this can be done now. Those interested please take a look at <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=151343">bug
#151343</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Another issue common to multiple language implementations is that quite a
few of them have a compiler that is a gcc frontend. As such their build
procedure is quite similar and so it would make sense to work on a common
eclass, possibly even combining everything with toolchain.eclass. The
affected compilers that I had to deal with are: gpc (Pascal, in portage),
gdc (D, not in portage but has may interested users) and gnat (Ada). The
last one in fact is further subdivided into gnat-gcc for version produced
by FSF and gnat-gpl produced by AdaCore.  These gnat versions have a
proper eclass common to all of them, and thus other compilers can be based
on that one.
</p>

</goals>

<dev role="Lead">george</dev>

<subproject ref="/proj/en/prog_lang/ada/index.xml"/>
<subproject ref="/proj/en/prog_lang/haskell/index.xml"/>
<subproject ref="/proj/en/prog_lang/ruby/index.xml" />

</project>
