<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>PostgreSQL</name>
<longname>Gentoo PostgreSQL Team</longname>
<date>2006-12-07</date>

<description>
The Gentoo PostgreSQL Team is responsible for delivering high-quality support for
the PostgreSQL RDBMS (Relational DataBase Management System) for Gentoo Linux.
</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
<b>What we do, and who we are</b>
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo PostgreSQL Team looks after the packages for the PostgreSQL RDBMS.
PostgreSQL is one of the most important and popular opensource RDBMS for
web-based applications.
</p>

<p>
We're also onhand to provide information and support on PostgreSQL to other Gentoo 
developers.
</p>

</longdescription>

<goals><p>
Our goal is to ensure that Gentoo provides the best environment possible for 
developing and running software based on PostgreSQL.
</p></goals>

<!-- Developer Roles -->
<dev role="Member">dev-zero</dev>

<!-- Project Specific Pages/Documentation -->
<resource link="http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/postgresql/">The Gentoo PostgreSQL Overlay &amp; Wiki</resource>

<!-- Subprojects -->
<!--subproject ref="/proj/en/gdp/international.xml"/-->

<!-- herds -->
<herd name="postgresql" />

<!-- Status updates -->
<extrachapter>
<title>Status Updates</title>
<section>
<title>What are Status Updates?</title>
<body>

<p>
We provide regular status updates covering what the Gentoo PostgreSQL Team has
accomplished since the previous status update. It is written by one of
the team members and contains a quick overview of recent progress.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Listing</title>
<body>

<p>
The following status updates are available:
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo PostgreSQL Team has not published any status updates at this time.
</p>

<!--
<ul>
  <li><uri link="status/status_2006Q1.xml>Jan-March, 2006</uri></li>
</ul>
-->

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<!-- Chapter regarding mailing list & participation -->
<extrachapter>
<title>Participating</title>
<section>
<title>#gentoo-db on irc.freenode.net</title>
<body>

<p>
The best way to reach us is on IRC in the <uri
link="irc://freenode/gentoo-db">#gentoo-db</uri> channel on irc.freenode.net.
Please feel free to stop by to talk about PostgreSQL on Gentoo. We welcome any
suggestions for improvement.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Participating</title>
<body>

<p>
The best way to get involved with what we do is to hang out in #gentoo-db.
There are always things to be done (and exciting new ideas to turn into
reality), and we're always looking for new ways to make Gentoo the first
choice for developers working with PostgreSQL, and for system administrators
running it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
