<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- $Header $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide disclaimer="draft" link="announcement-guide.xml" lang="en">
  <title>Annonucement Guide</title>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="nichoj@gentoo.org">Josh Nichols</mail>
  </author>
  
  <abstract>
    This guide documents the proccess of posting announcements to the front page. It also provides guidelines, suggestions, tips, and references for writing effective announcements.
  </abstract>
  <version>0.1</version>
  <date>2008-02-08</date>
  
  <chapter>
    <title>Creating announcements</title>
    <section>
      <title>Initial setup</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          To start, you'll need to go through all the setup you would need to do other documentation. This is already well documented <uri link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-tipsntricks.xml">here</uri>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Announcements live in <path>xml/htdocs/proj/en/pr/docs</path>, relative to the root of the 'gentoo' CVS module.
        </p>
        <p>
          To create a new announcement, just create a new XML file. The naming schema is <path>YYYYmmdd-some-title-here.xml</path>. Of course, fill in the appropriate date for YYYYmmdd, and a hyphen-delimited title.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>File format</title>
      <body>
        <p>
          Announcements are of a slightly different than your typical <uri link="">GuideXML</uri>, although they aren't that different.
        </p>
        <p>
          Best to teach by example, so here's a skeleton:
        </p>
        <pre caption="Announcement example">
<![CDATA[          
<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<news gentoo="yes" category="linux">
  <poster>your_nick_here</poster>
  <date>YYYY-mm-dd</date>
  <title>First post!</title>
  <body>
    <p>
      Here there be content!
    </p>
  </body>
</news>
]]>
        </pre>
        <p>Here's what's really important:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Gentoo equals very yes</li>
          <li>
            Category should be specified. Eventually XSL uses this to generate an image for the announcement. Some valid categories include:
            <ul>
              <li>gentoo</li>
              <li>kde</li>
              <li>main</li>
              <li>linux</li>
              <li>moo</li>
              <li>plans</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>Poster... that's you, writing the announcement</li>
          <li>Date of the announcement</li>
          <li>Full title of the announcement</li>
          <li>Body of the announcement. You can use the same XML you would be able to in an body tag for GuideXML</li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  <chapter>
    <title>Writing effective announcements</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
          Now that you have the basics of creating an announcement, we can focus on <b>writing effective announcements</b>.
        </p>
        <p>
          Certainly, at the most basic level we want to <b>inform our audience of something</b>. We also want to make it <b>easy to understand</b> what we're trying to say. We want to explain things in a way that they see <b>why they should care</b> about the announcement. And lastly, we want to <b>engage the audience</b>. Community has always been an important part of Gentoo, and we hope that well-written, timely announcements can help maintain and improve our community.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Tips</title>
      <body>
        <ul>
          <li>Bold key words and phrases.</li>
          <li>
            Avoid over-emphasizing unimportant thing. Doing so takes away from things that are important.
            <ul>
              <li>Example: including specific dates. For things in the recent past, does it matter which day it specifically happened?</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            Be specific about what you are talking about, and avoid ambiguity
            <ul>
              <li>Before: "Here are some stats before and after removing the digest files"</li>
              <li>After: "Here are some stats showing the size of the tree before and after removing the digest files"</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            Avoid overly long paragraphs.
          </li>
          <li>
            Use bullet points and tables when appropriate. It is a lot easier to read a list of bullet point list, than an equivilant sentence.
          </li>
          <li>
            Speak directly to the user.
            <ul>
              <li>Use "You" instead of "a user"</li>
              <li>Trying to have a conversation with the audience</li>
              <li>This is supported by having a forum thread go along with an announcement</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            When listing references:
            <ul>
              <li>List items most relevant to the user first</li>
              <li>
                Use appropriate text to encourage the user to want to read the reference
                <ul>
                  <li>Explain why the user should care</li>
                  <li>Before: "DevManual entry on Digest and Manifest"</li>
                  <li>After: "Understanding digest and manifest files"</li>
                </ul>
              </li>
            </ul>
          </li>
          <li>
            Explanations are key.
            <ul>
              <li>Think about every word or concept you use. Try to anticipate what the audience might not be familar with.</li>
              <li>This is crucial if you want your announcements to be valuable to the audience.</li>
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>References</title>
      <body>
        <ul>
          <li>
            <uri link="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/">Alertbox:
          Current Issues in Web Usability</uri>
            <ul>
              <li><uri link="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/passive-voice.html">Passive Voice Is Redeemed For Web Headings</uri></li>
              <li><uri link="http://www.useit.com/alertbox/9710a.html">How Users Read on the Web</uri></li>            
            </ul>
          </li>
        </ul>
        
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</guide>