<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/tex/texlive-migration-guide.xml,v 1.8 2012/10/28 15:21:16 swift Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>TeX Live 2008 guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="aballier@gentoo.org">Alexis Ballier</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide aims to show you how to install TeX Live 2008 on Gentoo,
more specifically what you need to take care of if you already have a
TeX distribution installed (like tetex or TeX Live 2005).
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.5</version>
<date>2009-04-15</date>

<chapter id="uninstall">
<title>Clean uninstall</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
In this section we will assume that you have <c>>=app-text/tetex-3</c>
installed. This also applies if you had <c>app-text/texlive-2005</c>
installed. In a perfect world it would be as simple as unmerging it,
but unfortunately it is not.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Saving your old configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
If you have modified your configuration of <c>tetex</c> editing the
files in <path>/etc/texmf</path>, you should save them first:
</p>

<pre caption="Save your old configuration files">
$ <i>cp -rf /etc/texmf ~/tetex-texmf</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Removing tetex</title>
<body>

<p>
Now you can safely unmerge <c>tetex</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Remove tetex">
# <i>emerge -C tetex</i>
</pre>

<p>
Some weird errors have been reported when stray configuration files
were left behind in <path>/etc/texmf</path>. For safety and for a
clean install of <c>TeX Live</c> it is recommended to remove the
<path>/etc/texmf/texmf.d/00texmf.cnf</path> file:
</p>

<pre caption="Cleanup /etc/texmf">
# <i>rm /etc/texmf/texmf.d/00texmf.cnf</i>
</pre>

<note>
You have not lost anything since you just saved your old configuration files.
</note>

<p>
Due to <c>tetex</c> using <c>texlinks</c> outside of the scope of the
package manager, simply unmerging it will have left behind some stray
symlinks:
</p>

<pre caption="tetex stray symlink">
$ <i>ls -l /usr/bin/pdftex</i>
lrwxrwxrwx 1 root root 7 2007-07-09 07:34 /usr/bin/pdftex -> pdfetex
</pre>

<p>
Of course, pdfetex has gone with <c>tetex</c>'s removal, so the pdftex symlink
is dead and can be safely removed. The <c>find</c> command (with a GNU
extension though) can help us find and remove dead symlinks interactively:
</p>

<pre caption="Eliminate dead symlinks interactively">
# <i>find /usr/bin -type l ! -xtype f ! -xtype d -ok rm -f {} \;</i>

&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/pdflatex &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/amstex &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/pdftex &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/eplain &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/jadetex &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/lambda &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/pdfamstex &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/elatex &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/lamed &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/pdfjadetex &gt; ? y
&lt; rm ... /usr/bin/latex &gt; ? y
</pre>

<p>
These were the files left over by my <c>tetex</c> installation.
</p>

<p>
<c>tetex</c> was also using <c>fmtutil</c> outside of the scope of the package
manager to generate the format files. With <c>TeX Live 2008</c> we now
build most of the format files while compiling the packages; which format
files will be installed in <path>/var/lib/texmf</path>. That means you have to
make sure that there are no stray format files:
</p>

<pre caption="Remove stray format files">
# <i>rm -rf /var/lib/texmf/web2c</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Installing TeX Live 2008</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
If you have passed through all the above steps, installing <c>TeX Live
2008</c> now should be very easy.
</p>

<pre caption="Install TeX Live 2008">
# <i>emerge texlive</i>
</pre>

<p>
In theory this should just go smoothly and install everything. You
might want to tune <c>app-text/texlive</c> USE flags to install extra
TeX packages, but you can do it later; <c>app-text/texlive</c> is just
a meta-ebuild that pulls the real packages depending on its USE flags.
</p>

<p>
Nevertheless, it is possible to get dependency problems, errors while
installing a package, etc. In that case, you are advised to file a bug
on <uri>https://bugs.gentoo.org</uri>. If you file a bug, please
include at least the output of <c>texconfig conf</c> (run as the same
user that failed to install, because some environment variables might
be important) in addition to the error; this output will most often be
requested.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuration</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
As was the case for <c>tetex-3</c>, <c>TeX Live</c> on <c>Gentoo</c> has its
three main configuration files separated and handled by <c>texmf-update</c>.
These files are, namely, <path>texmf.cnf</path>, <path>fmtutil.cnf</path>,
<path>updmap.cfg</path>. They lie in <path>/etc/texmf/web2c</path>; you should
not modify them directly because the changes will be lost the next time
<c>texmf-update</c> is run.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title> texmf.cnf </title>
<body>

<p>
The <path>texmf.cnf</path> file is the main TeX installation
configuration file. It contains variable definitions that will be used
by a lot of programs.
</p>

<p>
The <path>texmf.cnf</path> file is the result of concatenating files
in <path>/etc/texmf/texmf.d</path>. In order to modify your TeX environment
configuration, you should modify the files there. At the time of writing,
<c>Gentoo TeX Live</c>'s ebuild install six files there:
</p>

<pre caption="texmf.d installed files">
00header.cnf
05searchpaths.cnf
10standardpaths.cnf
15options.cnf
20sizes.cnf
25misc.cnf
</pre>

<p>
This is the result of the splitting in their respective sections of a
(lightly) modified <path>texmf.cnf</path> file from <c>TeX Live
2008</c> DVD.
</p>

<p>
The <path>00header.cnf</path>, <path>05searchpaths.cnf</path>,
<path>10standardpaths.cnf</path> and <path>25misc.cnf</path> files
should not be modified. If the defaults can be improved, please file a
bug.
</p>

<warn>
The <c>TeX Live</c> ebuilds are not aware of path changes of those
files, so if you change any path there, make sure you know what you
are doing.
</warn>

<p>
The <path>15options.cnf</path> and <path>20sizes.cnf</path> files can
be modified with caution. The comments in these files should explain
what options mean. For example, in <path>20sizes.cnf</path> you can
increase TeX memory, in case you are trying to compile a document that
is too big and runs into <c>TeX capacity exceeded, sorry</c> errors.
</p>

<p>
If you wish to append additions to the <path>texmf.cnf</path> file,
you can also create a new file in <path>/etc/texmf/texmf.d</path>,
called for example <path>99myadditions.cnf</path>. Beware not to give
it a higher priority than the core configuration files, so it should
begin with a two digit number greater than <c>25</c>.
</p>

<p>
Packages that need to append something to the <path>texmf.cnf</path>
file get the same treatment, they should install a
<path>texmf.d</path> file instead:
</p>

<pre caption="Sample code for installing a texmf.d file">
<keyword>insinto</keyword> <const>/etc/texmf/texmf.d</const>
<keyword>doins</keyword> <const>40mytexmfadditions.cnf</const>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>updmap.cfg</title>
<body>

<p>
The <path>updmap.cfg</path> file is the configuration file used by
<c>updmap</c> (and <c>updmap-sys</c>), unless otherwise specified. It
tells it which font maps to update for the various TeX output drivers.
</p>

<p>
The <path>updmap.cfg</path> file in <path>/etc/texmf/web2c</path> is
the result of concatenating the files in
<path>/etc/texmf/updmap.d</path>. The initial
<path>00updmap.cfg</path> file installed by
<c>app-text/texlive-core</c> is the result of running <c>updmap
--syncwithtrees</c> on the the installed <c>texmf</c> tree (in fact,
it just mimics what <c>updmap --syncwithtrees</c> would do, but it is
only a technical detail).
</p>

<p>
Various <c>TeX Live</c> ebuilds will add files to the
<path>/etc/texmf/updmap.d</path> directory when they install
fonts. While you can edit those files to disable some font maps to be
updated, it would probably be wiser to remove the relevant package.
</p>

<p>
If a third party package wants to add font maps, it should
install a file in <path>/etc/texmf/updmap.d</path> and let
<c>texmf-update</c> handle it.
</p>

<warn>
Sometimes you can see <c>updmap-sys --enable Map=mymap.map</c> in some
ebuilds or some installation instructions of a third party font
package, while this might work at first, these changes will be
reverted the next time <c>texmf-update</c> is run.
</warn>

<p>
A better way of handling this would be to create a file to be
installed in <path>/etc/texmf/updmap.d</path> and install it for TeX
distributions that support the <c>texmf-update</c> way:
</p>

<pre caption="How to enable a font map">
<keyword>inherit</keyword> <ident>latex-package</ident>
...
<stmt>src_install()</stmt> {
    ...
    <keyword>if</keyword> <stmt>latex-package_has_tetex_3</stmt>; then
        <keyword>insinto</keyword> /etc/texmf/updmap.d
        <keyword>doins</keyword> myfontmapconfig.cfg
    <keyword>fi</keyword>
    ...
}
...
<stmt>pkg_postinst()</stmt> {
    <stmt>latex-package_pkg_postinst</stmt>
    <stmt>latex-package_has_tetex_3</stmt> || updmap-sys --enable Map=mymap.map
}

<stmt>pkg_postrm()</stmt> {
    <stmt>latex-package_pkg_postinst</stmt>
    <stmt>latex-package_has_tetex_3</stmt> || updmap-sys --disable Map=mymap.map
}
</pre>

<p>
The files in <path>/etc/texmf/updmap.d</path> should respect <c>updmap</c>
syntax:
</p>

<pre caption="Snippet of updmap.cfg explaining the syntax">
There are two possible entries: Map and MixedMap. Both have one additional
argument: the file name of the map file. MixedMap ("mixed" means that the font
is available as bitmap and as outline) lines will not be used in the default map
of dvips if dvipsPreferOutline is false. Inactive Map files should be marked by
"#! " (without the quotes), not just #.
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>fmtutil.cnf</title>
<body>

<p>
The <path>fmtutil.cnf</path> file contains information on how to
build and handle a format file.
</p>

<p>
The <path>fmtutil.cnf</path> file is the result of concatenating the
files in <path>/etc/texmf/fmtutil.d</path>. Various <c>TeX Live</c>
ebuilds install files there. Those files come with the formats they
add support for and the symlink to the relevant engine.
</p>

<pre caption="Snippet of the fmtutil.cnf(5) man page that explains the syntax">
The fmtutil.cnf file contains the configuration information for fmtutil(8).
Each line contains the name of the format (e.g., "tex", "latex", "omega"), the
name of the engine that is used by that format (e.g., "tex", "etex", "omega"),
the pattern file (e.g., language.dat, language.def), and any arguments (name of
an .ini file).

Fields are separated by whitespace and complete lines can be commented out with
"#".  The "pattern file" field cannot be used to define a file that is used
while building the format. It tells fmtutil which file the format creation
procedure reads and it has an effect to the options --showhyphen and --byhyphen.
If the format has no way to customize hyphenation, a "-" can be used to indicate
this.
</pre>

<p>
<c>TeX Live</c> ebuilds that install a <path>fmtutil.d</path> file,
install the relevant format files in <path>/var/lib/texmf/web2c</path>
and create the symlink from the format to the engine.
</p>

<p>
Note that when a support file for a language gets added,
<c>texmf-update</c> takes care of adding it to the
<path>language.dat</path> file and regenerates the format files to
support the newly installed language.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Updating your configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that you know how <c>TeX Live</c> configuration is managed, you
should be able to port the changes you had made to your older TeX
distribution configuration to the <c>TeX Live</c> configuration
layout.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Common errors</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
In this chapter we will try to give a short summary of the most common
errors and explain what has gone wrong.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Format was written by (pdf)etex</title>
<body>

<p>
Sometimes when installing some packages that requires latex, you'll
get this error:
</p>

<pre caption="Format was written by pdfetex">
---! //var/lib/texmf/web2c/latex.fmt was written by pdfetex
</pre>

<p>
This is due to old files remaining from an old installation of a <c>TeX</c>
distribution based on <c>etex</c>. This most likely means you did not follow
entirely this guide, especially the <uri link="#uninstall">Clean uninstall
chapter</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Nevertheless, it is still possible to fix it quickly without having to
reinstall anything, just run as root:
</p>

<pre caption="Remove old formats">
# <i>rm -rf /var/lib/texmf/web2c</i>
# <i>texmf-update</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Format directory does not exist</title>
<body>

<p>
When installing e.g., <c>texlive-latex</c>, you might encounter the error:
</p>

<pre caption="Format directory does not exist">
fmtutil: format directory
`/var/tmp/portage/dev-texlive/texlive-latex-2008/work/texmf-var/web2c' does not
exist.
</pre>

<p>
This is most likely due to a wrong configuration. Try to run the
following command and get the same results:
</p>

<pre caption="TEXMFMAIN definition">
$ <i>kpsewhich --var-value=TEXMFMAIN</i>
/usr/share/texmf
</pre>

<p>
This is very important, since <c>fmtutil</c> looks for <c>mktexdir</c>
at this location; if you have a different result then <c>fmtutil</c>
will not find <c>mktexdir</c> and thus will fail to create the
directory where to temporarily store the compiled formats.
</p>

<p>
There is no magic command to fix this one, you should check that your
configuration is correct, that there are no stray configuration files
in <path>/etc/texmf/texmf.d</path>. This will most likely be due to an
old <path>00texmf.cnf</path> being still there and thus setting wrong
definitions for the <path>texmf.cnf</path> file. Please refer to the
<uri link="#uninstall">Clean uninstall chapter</uri> and remember that when you
modify or remove a file in <path>/etc/texmf/*.d</path> you need to run
<c>texmf-update</c> to have the changes taken into account.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Missing .tex files</title>
<body>

<p>
When installing <c>texlive-latex</c> (or any other format that has
babel hyphenation support), you might encounter an error like:
</p>

<pre caption="missing bghyphen.tex">
===========================================
Local configuration file hyphen.cfg used
===========================================

(/var/tmp/portage/dev-texlive/texlive-latex-2008/work/texmf-dist/tex/generic/ba
bel/hyphen.cfg (/usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/hyphen/hyphen.tex)
(/usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/hyphen/ushyphmax.tex)
(/usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/hyphen/dumyhyph.tex)
(/usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/hyphen/zerohyph.tex)
(/usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/hyphen/zerohyph.tex)
(/usr/share/texmf-dist/tex/generic/xu-hyphen/xu-bahyph.tex
(/usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/hyphen/bahyph.tex))
(/usr/share/texmf-dist/tex/generic/xu-hyphen/xu-bghyphen.tex
! I can't find file `bghyphen.tex'.
l.10   \input bghyphen.tex

Please type another input file name:
! Emergency stop.
l.10   \input bghyphen.tex

No pages of output.
Transcript written on latex.log.
Error: `pdftex -ini  -jobname=latex -progname=latex
-translate-file=cp227.tcx *latex.ini' failed
</pre>

<p>
In that case, you will have to check which <path>language.dat</path>
file is being used:
</p>

<pre caption="find language.dat">
$ <i>kpsewhich language.dat</i>
/usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/config/language.dat
</pre>

<p>
This file is automatically generated by <c>texmf-update</c> and is the
result of concatenating <path>language.*.dat</path> files present in
the directory with <path>language.us</path> (for TeX Live 2008, the
<path>language.*.dat</path> files are taken from
<path>/etc/texmf/language.dat.d/</path>). This directory should be
<path>/usr/share/texmf/tex/generic/config/</path>. So you should check
that there are no other <path>language.*.dat</path> files in that
directory other than the ones installed by the various
<c>dev-texlive/texlive-lang*</c> ebuilds. A file present in that
directory means that you want to enable hyphenation support for a
specific language; if you don't have the hyphenation support files the
formats that use this extra hyphenation support will fail to build.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
