<?xml version="1.1" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>planet</name>
<longname>Planet Gentoo</longname>
<date>2006-06-09</date>

<author title="Author"><mail link="christel@gentoo.org">Christel Dahlskjær</mail></author>
<author title="Author"><mail link="beandog@gentoo.org">Steve Dibb</mail></author>

<description>Planet Gentoo provides a central aggregation of developers' blogs, to keep users
and other developers informed of what they are working on</description>

<longdescription>
<p>For a long time, users have been asking for a better way to find out about what developers
are working on within Gentoo, and developers have been wanting a way to communicate with the
user and developer communities. Planet Gentoo aims to provide a partial solution to both of
these, by aggregating developers' weblogs in one place.</p>

<p>This aggregation is currently available in two forms. Planet Gentoo shows only posts marked
as 'on-topic', and related to Gentoo development. Gentoo Universe shows all posts to that
developer's blog, for those who are interested in more than strictly Gentoo-related news.</p>

</longdescription>

<extrachapter>
<title>Blog Hosting</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Using <uri link="http://www.b2evolution.net">b2evolution</uri>, Planet Gentoo hosts blogs for any Gentoo developers who are in need of a home.</p>

<p>Contact one of the Planet Gentoo admins to setup an account.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Hackergotchis</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Planet Gentoo and Gentoo Universe can display an icon or headshot of the developer on the website, and submissions are encouraged.  We enjoy being able to put a name to the face of our bloggers.</p>

<p>See the <uri link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hackergotchi">Wikipedia entry</uri> for more information and links on how to create your own.  Send your image in an e-mail to one of the Planet Gentoo admins when finished.</p>

<p>If you are not interested in making one yourself, you can write an entry in your blog including a photo and request that someone make one for you.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Google Summer of Code</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Gentoo is hosting a planet feed especially for developers working on projects hired by Google's Summer of Code.</p>

<p>The planet feed can be found at <uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/soc">http://planet.gentoo.org/soc</uri></p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<dev role="Lead">dsd</dev>
<dev role="Lead">beandog</dev>

<resource link="http://planet.gentoo.org">Planet Gentoo</resource>
<resource link="http://planet.gentoo.org/universe">Gentoo Universe</resource>
<resource link="http://planet.gentoo.org/soc">Planet Gentoo Summer of Code</resource>
<resource link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers">Gentoo Developer Blogs</resource>

</project>
