<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/foundation/en/articles.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Foundation Inc. Articles of Incorporation</title>
<author title="Transcriber">
  <mail link="g2boojum@gentoo.org">Grant Goodyear</mail>
</author>
<author title="OCR">
  <mail link="carpaski@gentoo.org">Nicholas Jones</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Articles of Incorporation of Gentoo Foundation, Inc.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2005-04-28</date>

<chapter>
	<title>[preamble]</title>
	<section>
		<body>
			<p>
				The undersigned, for the purposes of forming a nonprofit
				corporation under the provisions of the New Mexico Nonprofit
				Corporation Act, Section 53-8-1, et seq., N.M.S.A. 1978, hereby
				adopts the following Articles of Incorporation for such
				corporation.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article I</title>
	<section>
		<title>Name</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				The name of the corporation (hereinafter referred to as the
				Corporation) is: GENTOO FOUNDATION, Inc.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article II</title>
	<section>
		<title>Duration</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				The Corporation shall have perpetual existence.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article III</title>
	<section>
		<title>Purpose</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				The Corporation is organized and at all times shall be
				operated, on a non-profit basis exclusive far the advancement
				and education and promotion of software development in an open
				environment.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article IV</title>
	<section>
		<title>Members</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				There shall be one class of members as fixed by the bylaws
				of this corporation Only those persons who meet the criteria
				established by the board of trustees may be a member of the
				organiaation. Each member shall be entitled to one vote
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article V</title>
	<section>
		<title>Restrictions</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				(a) No part of the net earnings of the Corporation shall inure
				to the benefit of, or be distributable to, its directors,
				trustees, officers, or other private persons, except that the
				Corporatian shall be authorired and empowered to pay reasonable
				Compensation for services rendered and property.
				Notwithstanding any other provision of these articles, the
				Corporation shall not carry on any activities not permitted to
				be carried on by a Corporation exempt from Federal income tax
				under section 501(c)(1) of the internal Revenue Code of 1986 or
				the corresponding provision of any future United States
				Internal Revenue Law (hereinafter, the "Code").
			</p>
			<p>
				(b) This Paragraph (b) shall apply only if the Corporation is
				or becomes a private foundation as that term is defined by
				Section 509 of the Code. The Corporation shall expend or
				distribute its income for each year at such time and in such
				amount and manner as not to subject it to tax under Section
				4942 of the Code; and shall refrain from any act of self
				dealing, any retention of excess business holdings, any
				investment and any taxable expenditure which would subject it
				to tax under sections 4941, 4943, 4944 or 4945 of the Code.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article VI</title>
	<section>
		<title>Dissolution</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				Upon the dissolution of the corporation, the Board of Directors
				shall, after paying or making provision for the payment of all
				of The liabilities of the Corporation,  dispose of all the
				assets of the Corporation for the purposes of the Corporation,
				or to one or more organizations which are exempt under section
				501(c) of the Code, as the Board of Trustees shall determine.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article VII</title>
	<section>
		<title>Initial Registered office and Initial Registered Agent</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				The street address of the initial registered office of the
				Corporation is 205 Tulane Drive. SE, Albuquerque, NM 87106.
			</p>
			<p>
				The name of the initial registered agent of the Corporation,
				Daniel Robbins, an individual resident in New Mexico whose
				business office is at the above address, is 205 Tulane Drive,
				SE, Albuquerque, NM 87106.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article VIII</title>
	<section>
		<title>Board of Trustees</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				The number of trustees of the Corporation shall be not less
				than three or more than twenty-one. The initial Board of
				Trustees shall consist of thirteen persons. Thereafter, the
				Board of Trustees shall consist of such number of persons, not
				Less than three, as shall be fixed by the Bylaws. The initial
				Trustees who shall hold office until their successors shall
				take office, are as follows:
			</p>
<pre>
     Name                    Address


Corey Shields                410 Hickory Dr.
                             Ellettsville, IN 47429

Kurt Lieber                  329 Washington Street 81
                             Ellettsville, IN 47429

Nicholas Jones               3341 S. Wasbash Ave.
                             Chicago, IL 60616

Jay Pfeifer                  3534 Elf Cliff Pass Drive
                             San Antonio, TX 78247

Grant Goodyear               23103 Burcan Ct
                             Spring, TX 77373


Seemant Kulleen              2230-B Delaware Ave
                             Santa Monica, CA 90404

Deedra Waters                7160 Stark Ave.
                             Pensacola, FL 32514

John P. Davis                12250 Nantucket Drive
                             Chardon, OH 44024

Aron Griffis                 3 Winding Valley Road
                             Hollis, NH 03049

Sven Vermeulen               Leopold 2 lann 49
                             Burges, 8000
                             Belgium

Paul de Vrieze               Reitse Hoevenstraat 7b
                             Tilburg, 5042 EA,
                             The Netherlands

Joshua Brindle               6489 NW 63rd #351
                             Oklahoma City, OK 73132

Martin Schlemmer            17 Saxonburg Cresant
                             Oakglean, Bellville 7350
                             South Africa
</pre>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Article IX</title>
	<section>
		<title>Incorporator</title>
		<body>
			<p>
  The name and address of each Incorporator of the Corporation
is as follows:
</p>
<pre>
     Name                Address
  Daniel Robbins         205 Tulane Drive
                         Albuquerque, NM 87106
</pre>
<p>
STATE OF NEW MEXICO <br/>
COUNTY OF BERNALILLO
</p>

<p>
  The foregoing instrument was acknowledged before me this
14th day of May. 2004. by Daniel Robbins as the Incorporator of
said Corporation.
	</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>

