<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/foundation/en/BylawsAdopted.xml,v 1.5 2014/07/22 20:17:26 dabbott Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Foundation Bylaws</title>

<author title="Foundation Bylaws">
  <mail link="trustees@gentoo.org"></mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document sets out the Bylaws governing the Gentoo Foundation. The Gentoo
Foundation is an American not for profit entity originally incorporated in the
state of New Mexico.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>4</version>
<date>2014-07-22</date>

<chapter>
<title>Article I Business offices</title>
<section>
<title>Business offices</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Foundation shall not maintain offices other than the registered
office described in Section 2.1
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Article II Registered offices and registered agents</title>
<section>
<title>Section 2.1. New Mexico</title>
<body>

<p>
The address of the initial registered office in the State of New Mexico and the
name of the initial registered agent of the foundation at such address are set
forth in the Certificate of Incorporation. 
</p>

<p> 
The foundation may, from time to time, designate a different address as its
registered office or a different person as its registered agent, or both;
provided, however, that such designation shall become effective upon the filing
of a statement of such change with the Secretary of State of the State of New
Mexico as is required by law. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>3. Article III Meetings of members</title>

<section>
<title>Section 3.1. Place of Meetings</title>
<body>

<p>
Meetings of the members shall be held electronically in the manner specified by
the Secretary in the meeting calling notice. Normally in #gentoo-trustees on
irc.freenode.net
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.2. Annual Meeting</title>
<body>
  
<p>
A meeting of the members shall be held annually at such time as the Board of
Trustees may determine (which shall be, in the case of the first annual meeting,
not more than thirteen (13) months after the organization of the foundation and,
in the case of all other meetings, not more than thirteen (13) months after the
date of the last annual meeting), at which annual meeting the members shall
elect a Board of Trustees and transact other proper business.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.3. Special Meetings</title>
<body>

<p>
Special meetings of the members shall be held when directed by the Chairman,
President or the Board of Trustees, or when requested in writing by not less
than ten percent (10%) of all members.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.4. Notice</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Notice stating the place, date and hour of the meeting and in the case of a
special meeting, the purpose or purposes for which the meeting is called, shall
be delivered not less than ten (10) nor more than sixty (60) days before the
date of the meeting. Notices will be posted on appropriate mailing lists and in
the /topic of the IRC channel to be used for the meeting.
</p>

<p>
If any such member delivers to the foundation a written notice setting forth his
or her then current address, the requirement that notice be given to such member
shall be reinstated. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Section 3.5. Notice of Adjourned Meetings</title>
<body>

<p>
When a meeting is adjourned to another time or place, the foundation shall not
be required to give any notice of the adjourned meeting if the time and place to
which the meeting is adjourned are announced at the meeting at which the
adjournment is taken. 
</p>

<p>
At the adjourned meeting, any business may be transacted that might have been
transacted at the original meeting.  If, however, the adjournment is for more
than thirty (30) days, or if after the adjournment the Board of Trustees fixes a
new record date for the adjourned meeting, a notice of the adjourned meeting
shall be given as provided in Section 3.4 above, to each member of record on the
new record date entitled to vote at such meeting
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.7. Fixing Record Date.</title>
<body>

<p>
For the purpose of determining members entitled to vote at any meeting of
members or any adjournment thereof, the Board of Trustees may fix a record date,
which record date shall not precede the date upon which the resolution fixing
the record date is adopted by the Board of Trustees, and which record date shall
not be more than 60 nor less than 10 days before the date of such meeting.
</p>

<p>
The record date shall be the date of poll opening, unless stated otherwise.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.8. Record of Members Having Voting Rights</title>
<body>
  
<p>
The officer or agent having charge of the membership records of the foundation
shall prepare and make, at least ten (10) days before each meeting of members, a
complete list of the members entitled to vote at such meeting, arranged in
alphabetical order, and showing the name, electronic signature (gpg key), and
electronic mail address of each member. This list is to be made publicly
available on line. Upon the willful neglect or refusal of the Trustees to produce
such a list at any meeting for the election of Trustees, such Trustees shall be
ineligible for election to any office at such meeting.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.9. Member Quorum</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Except as otherwise required by law, by the Certificate of Incorporation or by
these Bylaws, one-third (1/3) of the members entitled to vote, represented in
person, shall constitute a quorum at a meeting of members. 
</p>

<p>
After a quorum has been established at a members' meeting, the subsequent
withdrawal of members, so as to reduce the number of members in person entitled
to vote at the meeting below the number required for a quorum, shall not affect
the validity of any action taken at the meeting or any adjournment thereof.   
</p>

<p>
After a quorum has been established at a members' meeting, the subsequent
admission of new members, so as to increase the number of members required for a
quorum above the number of members present in person entitled to vote at the
meeting, shall not affect the validity of any action taken at the meeting or any
adjournment thereof.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.10. Voting </title>
<body>
  
<p>
Each member shall be entitled to one vote on each matter submitted to a vote at
a meeting of the members, except as may otherwise be provided in the law of the
State of New Mexico. 
</p>

<p>
Members shall vote in person electronically
</p>

<p>
At any regular or special meeting as provided in Section 3.3, any question may
be voted upon in the manner and style deemed appropriate by the Secretary of the
organization or chairman of the meeting. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.11. Proxies - Deleted </title>
<body>
  
<p>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 3.12. Action by Members Without a Meeting.</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Any action required to be taken or which may be taken at any annual or special
meeting of members of the foundation, may be taken without a meeting, without
prior notice and without a vote, if a written consent setting forth the action
so taken shall be signed by members having not less than the minimum number of
votes that would be necessary to authorize or take such action at a meeting at
which all members entitled to vote thereon were present and voted; provided,
however, that no written consent shall be effective unless such consent
</p>

<ol> 
  <li>bears the date of signature by each member signing such consent and </li>
  <li>is delivered to the foundation within sixty (60) days of the date on which
    the earliest consent was delivered to the foundation.</li>
</ol>

<p>
Prompt notice of the taking of the corporate action without a meeting by less
than unanimous written consent shall be given to those members who have not
consented in writing.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Article IV Members</title>
<section>
<title>Section 4.1. Member Classes.</title>
<body>
  
<p>
There shall be one class of members, hereinafter referred to as full members. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 4.2 Full Members</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Reserved
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 4.3. Admission of Members</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Full members are admitted by petitioning the trustees for membership, providing
verifiable evidence of their contribution to Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
Active Gentoo developers who are not members of the Foundation may apply for
membership.  Any developer applying for membership in the Foundation will
become a member of the Foundation immediately after the next Trustee meeting
following the application unless an absolute majority of the trustees
(currently 3 out of 5) oppose membership for the developer at this meeting.
</p>
<p>
Applicants who are not Gentoo developers need to cite verifiable evidence of contributing to 
Gentoo or to the stated aims of the Gentoo Foundation Inc.
</p>
<p>
Examples of contributing include but are not limited to, arch testing, bugzilla, Gentoo forums, working with existing developers. 
Contributions will be verified. The decision of the trustees is final.
</p>
<p>
Monetary contributions will be discounted - Gentoo Foundation membership cannot be bought.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 4.4. Continuation of Membership</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Full members who remain Gentoo developers shall have their membership continued
until it is terminated in accordance with 4.8 or 4.9.
</p>

<p>
Full members who retire from the Gentoo project shall have there membership
continued while they indicate that they remain interested in the affairs of the
Foundation unless their membership is terminated in accordance with 4.8 or 4.9.
</p>

<p>
Criteria for loss of interest in the foundation shall be determined by the
trustees, from time to time.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 4.5 to 4.7 Inclusive</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Reserved
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 4.8. Voluntary Withdrawal from Membership </title>
<body>
  
<p>
Members  may withdraw from membership in the foundation at any time upon thirty
(30) days' written, signed notice delivered to an officer of the foundation,
which notice may be by cryptographically signed electronic mail with a valid
signature. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 4.9. Termination from Membership.</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Membership may be terminated by a majority vote of the board of trustees in the
event that any member acts contrary to the purpose(s) of the Gentoo Foundation.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 4.10. Effect of Withdrawal or Termination of Membership.</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Upon any withdrawal or termination of the membership of any member, the
membership, including all related 
voting rights, of such member shall be terminated. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Article V Trustees</title>
<section>
<title>Section 5.1. Powers.</title>
<body>

<p>
The business and affairs of the foundation shall be managed by or under the
direction of the Board of Trustees, the "Trustees", which may exercise all such
powers of the foundation and do all such lawful acts and things as are not by
statute or by the Certificate of Incorporation or by these Bylaws specifically
reserved to the members. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 5.2. Qualification</title>
<body>

<p>
Trustees need not be residents of New Mexico or of the United States, but they
must be members of the foundation.
</p>

<p>
No individual shall serve as a Gentoo Foundation Trustee and Gentoo Council
Member concurrently
</p>


</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 5.3. Compensation</title>
<body>

<p>
The positions of all Trustees are Honorary - No compensation, monetary or in
kind shall be paid.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 5.4. Number</title>
<body>

<p>
The foundation shall initially have five (5) Trustees. Thereafter, the number of
Trustees shall be fixed by the members at each annual meeting of members. The
initial Trustees who shall hold office until their successors shall take office,
are as follows:
 </p>
 
<ul>
  <li>Roy Bamford (neddyseagoon)</li>
  <li>Ferris McCormick (fmccor)</li>
  <li>Joshua Jackson (tsunam)</li>
  <li>Tom Gall (tgall)</li>
  <li>William Thomson (wltjr)</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 5.5. Election and Term</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Trustees shall be elected by secret ballot of the members using the condorcet
voting system or other such suitable system.  Elections shall be held nominally
annual.
</p>

<p>
Trustees shall normally hold office for a period not exceeding two electoral
periods.  Trustees shall retire annually by rotation (and may be re-elected).
The first rotation shall be determined by the meeting of the Trustees held to
adopt these Bylaws.
</p>

<p>
Each Trustee shall hold office for the term for which he or she is elected and
until his or her successor shall have been elected and qualified or until his or
her earlier resignation, removal or death. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section><title>Section 5.6. Resignation and Removal of Trustees</title>
<body>

<p>
A director may resign at any time upon written request to the foundation.
Furthermore, any director or the entire Board of Trustees may be removed, with
or without cause, by a vote of the majority of the members entitled to vote for
the election of Trustees or as otherwise provided in the General Foundation Law
of the State of New Mexico. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 5.7. Vacancies</title>
<body>

<p>
Any vacancy occurring in the Board of Trustees, including any vacancy created by
reason of an increase in the authorized number of Trustees, may be filled by the
affirmative vote of a majority of the remaining Trustees though less than a
quorum of the Board of Trustees or by a sole remaining director.  A director
elected to fill a vacancy shall hold office only until the next election of
Trustees by the members. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 5.8. Quorum and Voting</title>
<body>

<p>
A majority of the number of Trustees fixed in accordance with these Bylaws shall
constitute a quorum for the transaction of business. The vote of a majority of
the Trustees present at a meeting at which a quorum is present shall be the act
of the Board of Trustees. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section><title>Section 5.9. Executive and Other Committees</title>
<body>

<p>
The Board of Trustees, by resolution adopted by a majority of the full Board of
Trustees, may designate an Executive Committee from among its members and such
other committees consisting of at least one director as determined by the Board
of Trustees from time to time. Each committee, to the extent provided in such
authorizing resolution, shall have and may exercise all the power and authority
of the Board of Trustees in the management of the business and affairs of the
foundation, as limited by the laws of the State of New Mexico. 
</p>

<p>
The Board of Trustees, by resolution adopted in accordance with this section,
may designate one or more Trustees as alternate members of any such committee,
who may act in the place and stead of any absent or disqualified member or
members at any meeting of such committee. In the absence or disqualification of
any member of any such committee or committees, the member or members thereof
present at any meeting and not disqualified from voting, whether or not they
constitute a quorum, may unanimously appoint another member of the Board of
Trustees to act at the meeting in the place of any such absent or disqualified
member. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section><title>Section 5.10. Place of Meetings.</title>
<body>

<p>
All meetings of the Board of Trustees may be held in person or electronically,
within or outside the State of New Mexico and within or outside the United
States. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 5.11. Time, Notice and Call of Meetings</title>
<body>

<p>
Regular meetings of the Board of Trustees shall be held immediately following
the annual meeting of members each year and at such times thereafter as the
Board of Trustees may fix. No notice of regular Trustees' meetings shall be
required. 
</p>

<p>
Special meetings of the Board of Trustees shall be held at such times as called
by the Chairman of the Board, the President of the foundation, or any two (2)
Trustees. Written notice of the time and place of special meetings of the Board
of Trustees shall be given to each director by electronic mail at least two (2)
days before the meeting.
</p>

<p>
Notice of a meeting of the Board of Trustees need not be given to any director
who signs a waiver of notice, either before or after the meeting. Attendance of
a director at a meeting shall constitute a waiver of notice of such meeting and
waiver of any and all objections to the place of the meeting, the time of the
meeting, or the manner in which it has been called or conveyed, except when a
director states, at the beginning of the meeting, any objection to the
transaction of business because the meeting is not lawfully called or convened. 
</p>

<p>
Members of the Board of Trustees may participate in a meeting of such Board or
of any committee designated by such Board by conference telephone or similar
communications equipment by means of which all persons participating in the
meeting can hear each other at the same time. Participating by such means shall
constitute presence in person at a meeting. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section><title>Section 5.12. Action Without a Meeting.</title>
<body>

<p>
Any action required or permitted to be taken at a meeting of the Board of
Trustees or of any committee thereof may be taken without a meeting if all the
members of the board or committee, as the case may be, consent thereto in
writing, and such writing is filed with the minutes of the proceedings of the
board or committee. Such consent shall have the same effect as a unanimous vote. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section><title>Section 5.13. Director Conflicts of Interest.</title>
<body>

<p>
No contract or other transaction between the foundation and one or more of its
Trustees or between the foundation and any other foundation, partnership,
association or other organization in which one or more of the Trustees of the
foundation are Trustees or officers or are financially interested, shall be void
or voidable solely because of such relationship or interest or solely because
such director or Trustees are present at or participate in the meeting of the
Board of Trustees or a committee thereof which authorizes, approves or ratifies
such contract or transaction or solely because his or her or their votes are
counted for such purpose, if:
</p>

<ol>
<li>
The material facts as to the director's relationship or interest and as to the
contract or transaction are disclosed or are known to the Board of Trustees or
committee, and the Board of Trustees or committee in good faith authorizes,
approves or ratifies the contract or transaction by the affirmative votes of a
majority of the disinterested Trustees, even though the disinterested Trustees
be less than a quorum; or 
</li>
<li>
The material facts as to their relationship or interest and as to the contract
or transaction are disclosed or known to the members entitled to vote thereon,
and the contract or transaction is specifically approved in good faith by vote
of such members; or 
</li>
<li>
The contract or transaction is fair as to the foundation at the time it is
authorized, approved or ratified by the Board of Trustees, a committee of the
Board of Trustees or the members. 
</li>
</ol>

<p>
Common or interested Trustees may be counted in determining the presence of a
quorum at a meeting of the Board of Trustees or a committee thereof which
authorizes, approves or ratifies such contract or transaction. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter><title>Article VI Officers</title>
<section><title>Section 6.1. Officers.</title>
<body>

<p>
The officers of the foundation shall consist of a President, a Secretary and a
Treasurer, each of whom shall be elected by the Board of Trustees. A Chairman of
the Board, one or more Vice Chairmen, one or more Vice Presidents, and such
other officers and assistant officers and agents as may be deemed necessary may
be elected or appointed by the Board of Trustees from time to time. Any two (2)
or more offices may be held by the same person, except the offices of President
and Secretary
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section><title>Section 6.2. Duties</title>
<body>

<p>
The officers of the foundation shall have the following duties: 
</p>

<ol>
<li>
Chairman of the Board. The Chairman of the Board, if one is elected, shall
preside at all meetings of the Board of Trustees and members and shall have such
other duties and authority as may be conferred by the Board of Trustees.
</li>
<li>
Vice Chairman. The Vice Chairman, if one is elected, shall, in the absence or
disability of the Chairman of the Board, perform the duties and exercise the
powers of the Chairman of the Board. The Vice Chairman shall also perform
whatever duties and have whatever powers the Board of Trustees may from time to
time assign him/her.  If more than one Vice Chairman is elected and the Chairman
is absent or becomes disabled, the Board of Trustees shall choose one Vice
Chairman to perform the duties and exercise the powers of the Chairman.
</li> 
<li>
President. The President shall be the chief executive officer of the foundation
and shall have general and active management of the business and affairs of the
foundation , subject to the direction of the Board of Trustees. If a Chairman of
the Board is not elected, the President shall preside at all meetings of the
Board of Trustees and members. 
</li>
<li>
Vice President. The Vice President, if one is elected, shall, in the absence or
disability of the President, perform the duties and exercise the powers of the
President. He or she also shall perform whatever duties and have whatever powers
the Board of Trustees may from time to time assign him or her. If more than one
Vice President is elected, one thereof shall be designated as Executive Vice
President and shall, in the absence or disability of the President, perform the
duties and exercise the powers of the President and each other Vice President
shall only perform whatever duties and have whatever powers the Board of
Trustees may from time to time assign him or her.
</li>
<li>
Secretary and Assistant Secretary. The Secretary shall keep accurate records of
the acts and proceedings of all meetings of the members and Trustees. The
Secretary shall give all notices required by law and by these Bylaws. In
addition, the Secretary shall have general charge of the corporate books and
records and of the corporate seal, and he or she shall affix, or attest the
affixing of, the corporate seal to any lawfully executed instrument requiring
it. The Secretary shall have general charge of the membership records of the
foundation and shall keep, at the registered or principal office of the
foundation, a record of the members showing the name, address, telephone number,
and electronic mail address of each member. The Secretary shall sign such
instruments as may require his or her signature and, in general, shall perform
all duties as may be assigned to him or her from time to time by the Chairman,
the President or the Board of Trustees.  The Assistant Secretary, if one is
appointed, shall render assistance to the Secretary in all the responsibilities
described above.
</li>
<li>
Treasurer and Assistant Treasurer. The Treasurer shall have custody of all
corporate funds and financial records, shall keep full and accurate accounts of
receipts and disbursements and render accounts thereof at the annual meetings of
members, and shall perform such other duties as may be prescribed by the
Chairman, the President or the Board of Trustees. The Assistant Treasurer, if
one is appointed, shall render assistance to the Treasurer in all of the
responsibilities described above. 
</li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>

<section><title>Section 6.3 - Requirements for Chairman and Vice Chairman</title>
<body>
  
<p>
The Chairman and Vice Chairman, if elected by the board, must be trustees.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 6.4. Election and Term</title>
<body>

<p>
Each officer shall be appointed by the Board of Trustees and shall hold office
until such time as the officer resigns or is removed by the Board of Trustees
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 6.5. Removal of Officers.</title>
<body>

<p>
Deleted
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 6.6. Vacancies.</title>
<body>

<p>
Any vacancy, however occurring, in any office  may be filled by the Board of
Trustees. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section><title>Section 6.7. Compensation.</title>
<body>

<p>
The positions of all officers are Honorary - No compensation, monetary or in
kind shall be paid.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Article VII Books and Records</title>
<section>
<title>Section 7.1. Books and Records</title>
<body>

<p>
The foundation shall keep correct and complete books and records of accounts and
shall keep minutes of the proceedings of its members, Board of Trustees and
committees of Trustees. 
</p>

<p>
The foundation shall keep at its registered office or principal place of
business, or at the office of its transfer agent or registrar, or in the custody
of the Secretary a record of the name,  electronic mail address and public gpg
key of each member, together with the date of any withdrawal or termination of
such member's membership. 
</p>

<p>
Each member shall be responsible for notifying the foundation of changes to such
member's, electronic mail address and public gpg key.
</p>

<p>
Any books, records and minutes may be in written form or in any other form
capable of being converted into clearly legible written form within a reasonable
time.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 7.2. Members' Inspection Rights</title>
<body>

<p>
Members' Inspection Rights. Any person who is a member, upon written demand
under oath stating the purpose thereof, shall have the right to examine, in
person or by agent or attorney, at any time during the foundation's usual hours
for business, for any proper purpose as determined under the law of the State of
New Mexico, the foundation's membership records and its other books and records
and to make copies or extracts therefrom. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Article VIII Nonprofit Status</title>
<section>
<title>Nonprofit Status</title>
<body>

<p>
The foundation is organized and shall be operated as a not-for-profit membership
foundation organized under New Mexico law. If the Board of Trustees of the
foundation elects to seek and obtains an exemption for the foundation from
federal taxation pursuant to Section 501(a) of the Internal Revenue Code, as
amended (the "IRC"), and until such time, if ever, that such exemption is denied
or lost, the foundation shall not be empowered to engage directly or indirectly
in any activity which the foundation believes would be likely to invalidate its
status as an organization exempt from federal taxation under Section 501(a) of
the IRC as an organization described in Section 501(c) of the IRC. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Article IX Corporate Seal</title>
<section>
<title>Corporate Seal</title>
<body>

<p>
The Foundation shall not have a corporate seal
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Article X Amendment</title>
<section>
<title>Amendment</title>
<body>

<p>
These Bylaws may be altered, amended or repealed by the Board of Trustees or by
the members, and new Bylaws may be adopted by the Board of Trustees or by the
members. No alteration, amendment or repeal of these Bylaws shall be effective
unless and until the foundation attempts, in good faith, to give notice to the
members of the foundation of such alteration, amendment or repeal at least
fifteen (15) days prior to the effective date of such alteration, amendment or
repeal, which notice shall be to each members electronic mail address. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Article XI Limits on liability of Trustees</title>
<section>
<title>Limits on liability of Trustees</title>
<body>

<p>
To the fullest extent permitted by the law of the State of New Mexico, as the
same exists or may hereafter be amended, a director of the foundation shall not
be personally liable to the foundation or its members for monetary damages for
breach of fiduciary duty as a director.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Article XII Indemnification of officers and Trustees</title>
<section>
<title>Section 12.1. Right to Indemnification</title>
<body>

<p>
Each person who was or is a party or is threatened to be made a party to any
threatened, pending or completed action, suit, or proceeding, whether civil,
criminal, administrative, or investigative (other than an action by or in the
right of the foundation), by reason of the fact that he or she is or was a
director, officer or member of the foundation, or is or was serving at the
request of the foundation as a director, officer, employee, or agent of another
foundation, partnership, joint venture, trust, or other enterprise, shall be
entitled to indemnification against expenses (including attorneys' fees),
judgments, fines, and amounts paid in settlement to the fullest extent now or
hereafter permitted by applicable law as long as such person acted in good faith
and in a manner that such person reasonably believed to be in or not be opposed
to the best interests of the foundation; provided, however, that the foundation
shall indemnify any such person seeking indemnity in connection with an action,
suit or proceeding (or part thereof) initiated by such person only if such
action, suit or proceeding (or part thereof) was authorized by the Board of
Trustees. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 12.2. Advance Payment of Expenses.</title>
<body>

<p>
Expenses (including reasonable attorneys' fees) incurred by any person who is or
was an officer, director or member of the foundation, or who is or was serving
at the request of the foundation as an officer or director of another
foundation, partnership, joint venture, trust or other enterprise, in defending
any civil, criminal, administrative or investigative action, suit or proceeding,
shall be paid by the foundation in advance of the final disposition of such
action, suit or proceeding upon receipt of an undertaking by or on behalf of
such person to repay such amount if it is ultimately determined that he or she
is not entitled under applicable law to be indemnified by the foundation. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 12.3. Right of Claimant to Bring Suit</title>
<body>

<p>
If a claim under this Article is not paid in full by the foundation within
ninety (90) days after a written claim has been received by the foundation, the
claimant may at any time thereafter bring suit against the foundation to recover
the unpaid amount of the claim and, if successful in whole or in part, the
claimant shall be entitled to be paid also the expense of prosecuting such
claim. It shall be a defense to any such action (other than an action brought to
enforce a claim for expenses incurred in defending any action or proceeding in
advance of its final disposition where the required undertaking has been
tendered to the foundation unless such action is based on the claimant having
committed an act involving moral turpitude) that the claimant has not met the
standards of conduct which make indemnification permissible under the General
Foundation Law of the State of New Mexico, but the burden of proving such
defense shall be on the foundation. Neither the failure of the foundation
(including its Board of Trustees, independent legal counsel, or its members) to
have made a determination prior to the commencement of such action that
indemnification of the claimant is proper in the circumstances because he or she
has met the applicable standard of conduct set forth in the law of the State of
New Mexico, nor an actual determination by the foundation (including its Board
of Trustees, independent legal counsel, or its members) that the claimant has
not met such applicable standard of conduct, shall be a defense to the action or
create a presumption that the claimant has not met the applicable standard of
conduct. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 12.4. Contract Rights.</title>
<body>

<p>
The provisions of this Article shall be a contract between the foundation and
each director, officer or member to which this Article applies. No repeal or
modification of these Bylaws shall invalidate or detract from any right or
obligation with respect to any state of facts existing prior to the time of such
repeal or modification.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 12.5. Rights Non-exclusive</title>
<body>

<p>
The indemnification and advancement of expenses provided by or granted pursuant
to this Article shall not be deemed exclusive of any other rights to which those
seeking indemnification or advancement of expenses may be entitled under any
Bylaw, agreement, vote of members or disinterested Trustees or otherwise, both
as to action in his or her official capacity and as to action in another
capacity while holding such office.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 12.6. Insurance</title>
<body>

<p>
The foundation may purchase and maintain insurance on behalf of any person who
is or was a director, officer, member, employee or agent of the foundation, or
is or was serving at the request of the foundation as a director, officer,
employee or agent of another foundation, partnership, joint venture, trust or
other enterprise against any liability asserted against him or her and incurred
by him or her in any such capacity, or arising out of his or her status as such,
whether or not the foundation would have the power to indemnify him or her
against such liability under the provisions of this Article or of applicable
law. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 12.7. Definitions</title>
<body>

<p>
For purposes of this Article, references to "the foundation" shall include, in
addition to the resulting foundation, any constituent foundation (including any
constituent of a constituent) absorbed in a consolidation or merger which, if
its separate existence had continued, would have had power and authority to
indemnify its Trustees, officers, and employees or agents, so that any person
who is or was a director, officer, employee or agent of such constituent
foundation, or is or was serving at the request of such constituent foundation
as a director, officer, employee or agent of another foundation, partnership,
joint venture, trust or other enterprise, shall stand in the same position under
this Article with respect to the resulting or surviving foundation as he or she
would have with respect to such constituent foundation if its separate existence
had continued, and references to "other enterprises" shall include employee
benefit plans; references to "fines" shall include any excise taxes assessed on
a person with respect to any employee benefit plan; and references to "serving
at the request of the foundation" shall include any service as a director,
officer, employee or agent of the foundation which imposes duties on, or
involves services by, such director, officer, employee, or agent with respect to
an employee benefit plan, its participants, or beneficiaries; and a person who
acted in good faith and in a manner he or she reasonably believed to be in the
interest of the participants and beneficiaries of an employee benefit plan shall
be deemed to have acted in a manner "not opposed to the best interests of the
foundation" as referred to in this Article. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 12.8. Continued Coverage</title>
<body>

<p>
The indemnification and advancement of expenses provided by, or granted pursuant
to this Article shall, unless otherwise provided when authorized or ratified,
continue as to a person who has ceased to be a director, officer or member and
shall inure to the benefit of the heirs, executors and administrators of such
person
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Article XIII General provisions</title>
<section>
<title>Section 13.1. Checks</title>
<body>

<p>
All checks or demands for money and notes of the foundation shall be signed by
such officer or officers or such other person or persons as the Board of
Trustees may from time to time designate. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 13.2. Fiscal Year.</title>
<body>

<p>
The fiscal year of the foundation shall be fixed by resolution of the Board of
Trustees. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 13.3. Loans. </title>
<body>

<p>
No loans shall be contracted on behalf of the foundation and no evidence of
indebtedness shall be issued in its name unless authorized by a resolution of
the Board of Trustees. Such authority may be general or confined to specific
instances.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 13.4. Deposits. </title>
<body>

<p>
All funds of the foundation not otherwise employed shall be deposited from time
to time to the credit of the foundation in such depositories as the Board of
Trustees shall direct.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 13.5. Contracts. </title>
<body>

<p>
The Board of Trustees may authorize any officer or officers, agent or agents, to
enter into any contract or execute and deliver any instrument on behalf of the
foundation, and such authority may be general or confined to specific instances.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Section 13.6. Counterpart Execution: Facsimile Execution.</title>
<body>

<p>
Any document requiring the signature of the Trustees and/or members may be
executed in any number of counterparts with the same effect as if all of the
required signatories had signed the same document.  Such executions may be
transmitted to the foundation and/or the other Trustees and/or members by
facsimile and such facsimile execution shall have the full force and effect of
an original signature.  All fully executed counterparts, whether original
executions or facsimile executions or a combination, shall be construed together
and shall constitute one and the same agreement.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
