<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<news gentoo="yes" category="gentoo">

<!-- Enter your name here -->
<poster>NeddySeagoon</poster>

<!-- Date to be displayed - usually the GWN release date -->
<date>2010-10-17</date>

<!-- Title of the news item - don't forget to change the date -->
<title>Cash Sponsors Policy</title>
<body>

<!-- Alter to your own likings -->
<p>
<b>Introduction</b>
</p>

<p>
After being approached by a few large Gentoo users who wanted to purchase
advertising on the gentoo.org side bar, the trustees put a motion to the
Foundation members.
</p>

<p>
The motion was "Should major Gentoo users be permitted to purchase ads on the
sidebar". It was carried by a large majority of members who voted. 
</p>

<p>
There is thus a mandate for the break with tradition that only infrastructure
donations qualify for gentoo.org side bar space. 
</p>

<p>
This policy document is intended to ensure that the intent of the mandate is
implemented consistently across all applicants.
</p>

<p>
<b>How will the Trustees Determine That an Applicant actually uses Gentoo</b>
</p>

<p>
Applicants will be required to submit a document in two parts
</p>

<ul>
	<li>Briefly describing how many installs they have and what they are used for</li>
	<li>Describing how the above installs are maintained</li>
</ul>

<p>
The text describing how many installs and their uses may be published on
gentoo.org. The exact wording of any material to be made public will be agreed
with applicants on a case by case basis as a part of the accepence process of
any advertising.
</p>

<p>
The approach to maintenance will be kept private to the trustees. There are no
right and wrong answers.
</p>

<p>
<b>The Fee</b>
</p>

<p>
The fee will be calculated based on its relationship to the value of the more
usual data centre sponsors donations, had the Gentoo Foundation Inc needed to
purchase these data centre services. 
</p>

<p>
<b>Fractional Fees</b>
</p>

<p>
Its possible that ads will not be shown every hit - thus space can be shared by
a number of ads and the fee reduced in proportion.
</p>

<p>
In this case, a simple random weighted subset of available ads will be shown.
</p>

<p>
<b>Format of Ads</b>
</p>

<p>
Sidebar ad details
</p>

<ul>
	<li>Maximum 50 characters of mouseover text</li>
	<li>Translations of mouseover text are supported</li>
	<li>Image dimensions: </li>
	<li>Max height: 125 pixels</li>
	<li>Exact width 125 pixels</li>
	<li>File formats: PNG, JPG</li>
	<li>Max Filesize: 25KiB</li>
	<li>No animations are permitted</li>
</ul>

</body>
</news>
