<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/foundation/en/cd-dvd-guidelines.xml,v 1.1 2010/01/17 20:54:30 dabbott Exp $ -->

<guide link="/main/en/cd-dvd-guidelines.xml" lang="en">
	<title>Vendors Selling CD/DVD Guidelines</title>

<author>
  The Gentoo Foundation
</author>

<abstract>
This document covers the guidelines for vendors selling Gentoo CDs and DVDs.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2010-01-17</date>

<chapter>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This document describes the policy for vendors to sell Gentoo CDs and DVDs.<uri
	link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/name-logo.xml"> This document</uri>
describes proper use of the Gentoo name, the "g" logo and anyother associated
marks for software and computer-related efforts that are not under the direction
of the Gentoo Foundation, Inc. If you have any questions about these guidelines,
please contact <mail
link="trustees@gentoo.org">Gentoo Foundation, Inc.</mail>
</p>

<p>
Gentoo Foundation, Inc. reserve the right to change these terms from time to
time at their sole discretion. For that reason, we encourage you to review this
statement periodically.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo creates and provides its entire distribution free of charge. Gentoo does
not manufacture its own CDs and DVDs, but relies on third-party vendors. To make
it easier for vendors to provide a high quality disk, we provide <uri
	link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/where.xml">Official CD/DVD images</uri>
for them.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Definitions</title>
<section>
<title>The Gentoo project</title>
<body>

<p>
The volunteer development efforts currently supported by Gentoo Foundation, Inc.,
a not-for-profit corporation.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Content produced by the Gentoo project</title>
<body>

<p>
Any content that is copyright Gentoo Foundation, Inc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>CD DVD Guidelines</title>
<body>

<p>
Vendors selling media at or close to costs need only acknowledge the Gentoo
Foundation.  Vendors selling media at a profit need our permission.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
