<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/foundation/en/funding-request-policy.xml,v 1.4 2013/12/15 20:24:05 dabbott Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title></title>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="quantumsummers"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="dabbott"/>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo Funding Request Policies
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>3</version>
<date>2012-12-16</date>

<chapter>
<title>Requests</title>
<section>
<title>Requests for Funds, Project Support, or Equipment</title>
<body>

<p>
Requests for funds, project support, or equipment need to be sent to the
Foundation in the form of a proposal. This proposal is to inform all trustees of
the need (not all of them will be aware of the need or the background of the
situation). The proposal process will also help to maintain a trusting
relationship between the Foundation and it's donors. Donors know and expect that
without exception money will only be spent after a proposal and vote by the
Board of Trustees. Additionally, the proposals will be archived to provide
accountability for money spent.
</p>

<p>
Here is an example <uri link="funding-request-form.txt">funding request
  form</uri> you can use.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Proposals</title>
<section>
<title>Proposals for Project Support</title>
<body>

<p>
Proposals for 'Special Project Support' should include the following components,
must be single-spaced, typed in no less than 12 point Times New Roman font, and
not exceed 5 total pages.
</p>

<p>
Summary: One-Line Summary of the Request.
</p>

<p>
Personnel: List the names and titles of all key individuals involved in this
request. Please provide a phone number and email for each individual. At least
one of them must be noted as the 'Project Manager.' This will be the person that
will be contacted regarding all proposal related questions or activities.
</p>

<p>
Deadline: Deadline for Funding (Day/Month/Year). Please note that requests must
be 6 weeks in advance.
</p>

<p>
Amount: Amount Requested (in local currency, please specify).
</p>

<p>
Project Description: Please address the following components in your description.
</p>

<p>
Objectives: Objective or Purpose of the Project A Description of the Project
Deliverables. What will the project consist of when it is finished? Source code,
documentation, a build system, libraries, binaries; these should all be
enumerated in your proposal where applicable. Timeline: When will the
deliverables be done?
</p>

<p>
Reporting Methodology: Please indicated your compliance with the reporting
methodology for the project.  The reporting methodology requires a mid-grant and
final grant interview with a member of the Board of Trustees and mid-grant and
final grant narrative report (no more than 3 single-spaced pages) indicating if
deliverable and deliverable time lines are being met, any barriers that are
presenting in the project, and any project successes. The report may be
organized in this way and with such headings.
</p>

<p>
Supporting information: Feel free to attach or add additional information of
relevance here. Please note that any information exceeding the five page total
page limit will not be considered.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Procedure</title>
<section>
<title>Funding Request Procidure</title>
<body>

<p>
Please email your request to trustees at gentoo.org. Attach the funding 
request form to the email. The trustees will open a bug and add you to the cc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Funding</title>
<section>
<title>Project Funding Support</title>
<body>

<p>
Any 'special project support' request must  be approved by a majority vote from
the Board of Trustees. They will discuss how the request fits in to the
financial needs of Gentoo and whether or not the request is appropriate to
fulfill at the time. If chosen for support, a contract will be issued and must
be signed by an individual at the entity receiving funds (where applicable) that
has the authority to sign official legal documents. The contract will contain
terms of use, funding requirements, and reporting requirements (pursuant to the
proposal submitted where applicable) and will serve as the legally binding
document of both entities in the event of funding.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Distributing Funds</title>
<body>

<p>
In the case that funds will be distributed, in addition to reporting
requirements, receipts will need to be turned in within 2 weeks of the purchase.
The address to send the receipts to can be obtained by mailing the Board of
Trustees. This MUST be done for tax purposes. Failure to do so will jeopardize
the acceptance of future proposals from you or your team. Any excess funds (not
utilized for the project) will need to be returned along with the receipts from
items purchased.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
