<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>Gentoo Foundation Charter</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@siphos.be">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="cshields@cshields.org">Corey Shields</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="neddyseagoon@gentoo.org">Roy Bamford</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="dabbott@gentoo.org">David Abbott</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document describes the goals, structure and tasks of the Gentoo Foundation.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->
<license/>

<version>56</version>
<date>2013-05-09</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>About this document</title>
<body>

<p>
The purpose of this document is to elaborate on the Gentoo Foundation goals,
structure and tasks. It does not describe the goals of the Gentoo project and
does not contain any policies about the Gentoo development process.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Why a Gentoo Foundation?</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo distribution is maturing rapidly. Since its birth in 1999 the
distribution has evolved to one of the top Linux distributions available today.
The incorporated technologies including Portage, the software management
system, are frequently seen as major software breakthroughs. 
</p>

<p>
In order to sustain the current quality and development swiftness the Gentoo
project needs a framework for intellectual property protection and financial 
contributions while limiting the contributors' legal exposure. The Gentoo
Foundation will embody this framework without intervening in the Gentoo 
development. This latter aspect should be seen as a clear separation between 
coordinating the Gentoo development and protecting Gentoo's assets. Both are 
distinct concepts requiring different skills and working methods.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Foundation decouples necessary bureaucracy from development,
providing faster and higher quality results as the developer can now focus his
attention completely at the community and his responsibilities (being software,
documentation, infrastructure or others).
</p>

<p>
The bureaucracy we mention includes:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    financial caretaking: accepting donations, managing financial assets and
    investing in required resources or entities that benefit the Gentoo
    development
  </li>
  <li>
    juridical protection: backing up the licenses Gentoo uses, maintaining the
    copyrights on Gentoo's software, documentation and other assets and 
    protecting Gentoo's intellectual property
  </li>
  <li>
    Gentoo caretaking: protecting the community by requiring total adherence to
    the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/contract.xml">Gentoo Social
    Contract</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
In other words, the Gentoo Foundation will:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    protect the use of the Gentoo trademark and logo
  </li>
  <li>
    protect the developed code, documentation, artwork and other material
    through copyright and licenses
  </li>
  <li>
    sponsor Gentoo-related conferences and technical development resources
  </li>
  <li>
    oversee development so it adheres to the social contract
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Principles of the Gentoo Foundation</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Foundation keeps four pillars in mind:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>Gentoo provides choices</li>
  <li>Gentoo is open</li>
  <li>Gentoo lives for the community, by the community</li>
  <li>Gentoo is independent</li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo provides choices</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo is a metadistribution, providing choices to its users. This important
idea forms the basis of Gentoo's development: not a single feature will be
dismissed in favor of a different one when both can be maintained. Skills
learned today will still be relevant in the future.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo is open</title>
<body>

<p>
Every aspect of Gentoo is and remains open. Gentoo does not benefit from hiding
any of its development processes (whether it is source code or documentation,
decisions or discussions, coordination or management).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo lives for the community, by the community</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo strives to please its users. The Gentoo community is Gentoo's goal of
life. Without community there is no Gentoo. To help Gentoo's development, the
community provides a continuous stream of feedback and contributes to the
various aspects of the Gentoo distribution. This cooperative model will remain
valid for Gentoo's entire lifespan.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo is independent</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo will never be reigned by a company nor be dictated by an organisation.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Tasks of the Gentoo Foundation</title>
<section>
<title>Intellectual Property Protection</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Foundation is the legal owner of the Gentoo trademark and logo. To
protect Gentoo it will oversee the use of the Gentoo name and logo and take
appropriate action when the Gentoo Foundation feels that the name or logo is
wrongfully used.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Support the Gentoo Development</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Foundation has revenues gathered from donations, sold Gentoo items
and other sources. This financial income will be used to support the Gentoo
development in any way possible, as decided by the trustees.
</p>

<p>
The primary use of the funds are to support Gentoo's infrastructure as it is the
backbone of the project. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Oversee adherence to the Social Contract</title>
<body>

<p>
To keep the spirit of Openness and Freedom alive within Gentoo, the Gentoo
Foundation continues to keep an active eye on the Gentoo development to make
sure it adheres to the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/contract.xml">Gentoo Social Contract</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>The Board of Trustees</title>
<section>
<title>Current Board Members</title>
<body>
<p>
  (alphabetical order by last name)
</p>
<ul>
  <li>David Abbott, dabbott</li>
  <li>Roy Bamford, NeddySeagoon</li>
  <li>Richard Freeman, rich0</li>
  <li>Robin H Johnson, robbat2</li>
  <li>Matthew Summers, quantumsummers</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Board Minutes</title>
<body>
<ul>
  <li><uri link="minutes08/index.xml">2008 Minutes</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="minutes09/index.xml">2009 Minutes</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="minutes/2010/index.xml">2010 Minutes</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="minutes/2011/index.xml">2011 Minutes</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="minutes/2012/index.xml">2012 Minutes</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="minutes/2013/index.xml">2013 Minutes</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Election Process</title>
<body>

<p>
The mathematical election method the Gentoo Foundation uses is called the <uri
	link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Condorcet_method">Condorcet Voting</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Each member of the Gentoo Foundation at the moment the roll for the election closes may vote.
Each member is able to rank all candidates in the preferred order of election.
Multiple entries for the same position are allowed.  Currently, all who have ever voted
in any Foundation election are members of the Foundation unless they have officially
resigned.  If you are not a member (or do not know if you are a member), you may
petition the Trustees for admittance.  Please see
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/BylawsAdopted.xml">the Bylaws</uri>
Article IV for a complete explanation of membership in the Foundation.
</p>

<p>
The Condorcet Voting then takes two candidates and counts how many times
candidate A was ranked higher than candidate B and vice versa. Then, based on
this numbers, it looks for the candidate that is not beaten by any other
candidate and ranks him on top. It then removes this candidate from the list and
starts the process again to find the subsequent "winners".
</p>

<p>
When no candidate in a set of candidates is unbeaten, the least decisive defeat 
is dropped, again and again, until either one candidate remains (who is then
marked as a "winner") or a true tie exists. In case of the Gentoo Foundation,
only when a true tie exists for the final (5th) position the President of the
board has the final saying (otherwise both candidates are welcomed as
"winners").
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Trustee Responsibilities</title>
<body>

<p>
As a group, the Trustees each have an equal vote to decide upon issues outlined
in the tasks above. A majority vote (3 of 5) is required for all decisions.  The
trustees must uphold the principles of the Gentoo Foundation, its bylaws, and
help to maintain a good reputation for the Foundation.
</p>

<p>
In common with the organisation of other corporations the Gentoo Foundation Inc
has directors (the trustees) and officers that work at the direction of the
trustees. Meanwhile, the trustees also fulful most of the roles of officers,
current appointments being:-
</p>

<ul>
  <li>President - Roy Bamford, NeddySeagoon</li>
  <li>Vice President - Matthew Summers, quantumsummers</li>
  <li>Treasurer - Matthew Summers, quantumsummers</li>
  <li>Secretary - David Abbott, dabbott</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section>
<title>Links</title>
<body>
<p>
The following are links to other pages of information regarding the Gentoo
Foundation and it's tasks:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="BylawsAdopted.xml">
      Bylaws for the Gentoo Foundation</uri></li>
  <!--  <li><uri link="funds.xml">
      Foundation funding and expenditures</uri></li> -->
  <li><uri link="cash-sponsors-policy.xml">
      Cash Sponsor Policy</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="funding-request-policy.xml">
      Requesting funds from the Gentoo Foundation</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.nmprc.state.nm.us/index.html">
      Articles of Incorporation of Gentoo Foundation, Inc.</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="secretary/activities/activity_tracker.xml">
      Foundation Activity Tracker</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="20130519_members_list.xml">
      Gentoo Foundation Members List</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="cd-dvd-guidelines.xml">
      Vendors Selling CD/DVD Guidelines</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="sponsorship-and-advertising-guide.xml">
      Sponsorship and Advertising Guide</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="finances/index.xml">
      Financial Reports</uri></li>
</ul>

<p>
<b>Gentoo Consultants</b>
</p>

<p>
As a service to the Gentoo community and to advance the use of Gentoo in the
corporate sector the Gentoo Trustees Maintain a referral page for your
convenience. The companies and individual consultants are not officially
endorsed by the Gentoo Foundation.
</p>

<ul>
	<li><uri link="consultants.xml">Consultants</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Contact</title>
<body>
	
<p>
You may contact the Board of Trustees by e-mailing trustees at gentoo.org
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
