<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/foundation/en/requesting-funds.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Foundation Funding - Requesting Funds</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="cshields@gentoo.org">Corey Shields</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Procedures for requesting funds from the Gentoo Foundation
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2005-04-2</date>

<chapter>
<title>Requesting funds from the Gentoo Foundation</title>
  <section>
  <title>Acceptable requests</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        Before sending requests for money, please take a moment to understand how funding for the Foundation works.  A good place to start would be to read the Foundation funds overview at <uri>http://foundation.gentoo.org/funds.xml</uri>.  Also, please take a look at previous quarterly reports, along with any posted budgets to get an idea of whether or not there may be money available for your request.
      </p>
      <p>
        Keep in mind that not all requests will be accepted, and just because a request is not accepted does not necessarily mean that it is a bad request or that the need is not there.  Also know that just because the Foundation may have money available, it does not all have to be spent.  Some money needs to be held on to for a rainy day (ie: hardware failures, legal fees, etc).
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
  <title>Procedure for expenditures</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        Any Foundation money spent needs to be approved by a majority vote from the Board of Trustees.  They will discuss how the request fits in to the financial needs of Gentoo and whether or not the request is appropriate to fulfill at the time.  Also, the foundation must be accountible to the users, members, and donators by reporting all money received and spent.
      </p>
      <p>
        Requests for funds need to be sent to the Foundation in the form of a proposal.  This proposal is to inform all trustees of the need (not all of them will be aware of the need or the background of the situation).  The proposal process will also help to maintain a trusting relationship between the Foundation and it's donators. Donators know and expect that without exception money will only be spent after a proposal and vote by the Board of Trustees.  Additionally, the proposals will be archived to provide accountability for money spent.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
  <title>Request proposal</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        Your request will need to be as detailed as possible.  Keep in mind that the more detailed your request is, the fewer questions will need to be asked after the proposal is submitted, and therefore the quicker the process will be.
      </p>
      <p>
        The proposal needs to include the following:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>How much is being requested, in US dollars</li>
        <li>Why is it being requested?</li>
        <li>What need is being fulfilled by this request and what is the motivation for this request?</li>
        <li>What are the alternative solutions to spending this money, and what makes your request the best option?</li>
        <li>If this is a specific purchase (like a piece of hardware), shop around and send a URL of the product.</li>
        <li>If this is a budget request, send a list of items that will need to be covered by your budget, along with the reason for an open budget versus individual specific purchases.  A time period for your budget will be necessary as well, at the end of which time any excess funds will need to be returned along with receipts of purchases.  Also note who will be responsible for handling the budget funds if they can not be handled by the Foundation directly.  Note how the funds will be handled.</li>
        <li>Who are the requestees?  This should always include the support of a manager</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        When your proposal is ready for submission, e-mail it to trustees at gentoo, and cc the requestors listed in the proposal.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
  <title>After the proposal is accepted</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        The trustees will decide how the funds will be distributed to fulfill the proposal.  If at all possible, this will be done through the Foundation itself.  In the case that funds will be distributed for any purpose (outside purchases, budget, etc), receipts will need to be turned in within 2 weeks of the purchase.  The address to send the receipts to can be obtained by mailing the Board of Trustees.  This MUST be done for tax purposes.  Failure to do so will jeopardize the acceptance of future proposals from you or your team.
      </p>
      <p>
        If this is an open budget for a period of time, excess funds will need to be returned along with the receipts from items purchased.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
  <title>Questions?</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        If you have any questions please contact the Board of Trustees by e-mailing trustees at gentoo.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
</chapter>

</guide>

