<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<guide link="/proj/en/gsp/index.xml">
<title> Gentoo Server Project</title>
<subtitle>Main Page</subtitle>
<author title="Author">
   <mail link="wmealingd@gentoo.org">Wade Mealing</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
   <mail link=""></mail>
</author>
<abstract>
  The Gentoo server project is an official project of Gentoo.org with the target of
  bringing Gentoo Linux to the enterprise.
</abstract>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>28 July 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is the Gentoo Server Project</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
   The aim of the Gentoo Server Project is to make Gentoo Linux more
   appealing to the enterprise market.  Large institutions have
   different needs than small business and home users.  The network
   in these institutions are more complex and have different
   demands.

</p>
<p>
   The Gentoo Server Projects goal is to make administration
   of a single Gentoo host, to a fleet of machines easier and
   more cost effective for the administrator and the business.

</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Server Status</title>

<section>
<title>Active Development</title>
<body>
<p>
   The current active development in the Gentoo Server Project are are:
<table>
        <tr>
                <th>Project:</th>
                <th>Description:</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Installation</ti>
                <ti>Documentation on installing and configuring a Gentoo machine</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Configuration</ti>
                <ti>Configuring a machine to meet the demands in a server environment</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Administration</ti>
                <ti>Good practices when administrating a server</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Documentation</ti>
                <ti>Documenting all the above, as well as internal documentation of this project</ti>
        </tr>
</table>

</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Planned Development</title>
<body>
<p>
   The current planned development in the Gentoo Server Project are:
   <table>
        <tr>
                <th>Project:</th>
                <th>Description:</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Stable Portage Tree</ti>
                <ti>Developing a stable portage tree for use in servers, and only updating when a bugfix or security issue arrises.
                    Increasing the life of the operating system and providing a stable platform for applications</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Centralised Configuration Management</ti>
                <ti>Formalising a methodology to manage the configuration of servers and desktop configuration </ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Rapid Deployment</ti>
                <ti>By using a base system, and Centralised Configuration Management, system rollouts for both workstations and servers can be deployed quickly and easily<uri link="http://www.infrastructures.org/papers/bootstrap/bootstrap.html"> as per the infrastructures.org </uri> paper</ti>
        </tr>
   </table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Server Project Developers</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
ach developer working on Gentoo Server Project is listed here, full time indicates that their main Gentoo position is on this project, part time indicates that their main position lies in another area but they do additional work on the Gentoo Server Project.
<table>
        <tr>
                <th>Developer Name</th>
                <th>Username</th>
                <th>Full/Part Time</th>
                <th>Areas of Responsibilty</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Wade Mealing</ti>
                <ti>wmealing</ti>
                <ti>Full</ti>
                <ti>Project Developer</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Kurt Lieber</ti>
                <ti>klieber</ti>
                <ti>part</ti>
                <ti>Project Sponsor</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Brett Henrich</ti>
                <ti>bhenrich</ti>
                <ti>Full</ti>
                <ti>Documentation and testing</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Steven White</ti>
                <ti>swhite</ti>
                <ti>Full</ti>
                <ti>Infrastucture and Development</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
                <ti>Matt Tesauro</ti>
                <ti>mtesauroe</ti>
                <ti>Full</ti>
                <ti>Mail me your part</ti>
        </tr>

        <tr>
                <ti>Ken (antifa)</ti>
                <ti>antifa</ti>
                <ti>Part</ti>
                <ti>Documenter</ti>
        </tr>

</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To participate in the Gentoo server project first join the mailing list at <i>gentoo-server@gentoo.org</i>. Then ask if there are plans to support something that you are interested in, propose a new subproject that you are interested in or choose one of the planned subprojects to work on. You may talk to the developers and users in the IRC channel <i>#gentoo-server</i> on <i>irc.freenode.net</i> for more information or just to chat about the project or any subprojects. If you don't have the ability to actively help by contributing work we will always need testers to maintain the security and stability of the overall product. All development, testing, and productive comments and feedback will be greatly appreciated.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
