<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Webapps">
<name>Web-apps</name>
<longname>Gentoo web applications herd</longname>
<date>2013-10-29</date>

<description>
The web-apps team maintains web applications, an eclass to facilitate writing
ebuilds for these packages, and the webapp-config tool.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
The Gentoo webapp team maintains most web applications available via Portage.
In addition, we provide the webapp-config utility that allows users to
install ebuilds into different virtual hosts.
</p>

<p>
We are also responsible for the webapp.eclass that allows to prepare
web applications for installation with webapp-config.
</p>
</longdescription>

<goals><p>
Our goal is to make Gentoo the best platform for installing and maintaining web
applications. To achieve this goal, we work closely with several other herds
such as Apache and PHP.
</p></goals>

<!-- developers: add yourself -->
<dev>robbat2</dev>
<dev>trapni</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="Moodle and webapp-config">blueness</dev>

<!-- links to documentation -->
<resource link="/proj/en/webapps/webapp-config.xml">webapp-config Documentation</resource>
<resource link="/proj/en/webapps/webapp-eclass.xml">webapp.eclass Documentation</resource>

<!-- Status updates
<extrachapter>

<title>Status Updates</title>

<section>
<title>What are Status Updates?</title>
<body>
<p>
We provide regular status updates covering what the webapp team has
accomplished since the previous status update. It is written by one of the team
leaders and contains a quick overview of recent progress.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Listing</title>
<body>
<p>
The following status updates are available:
</p>
<ul>
<li><uri link="status/status_20060222.xml">February 22nd, 2006</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

</extrachapter>
-->

<extrachapter>

<title>Participating</title>

<section>
<title>#gentoo-web on irc.freenode.net</title>
<body>
<p>
The best way to reach us is on <uri link="irc://freenode/gentoo-web">IRC</uri>.
Please feel free to stop by to talk about <c>webapp-config</c> or about web
applications on Gentoo. We also welcome any suggestions for improvement.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>gentoo-web-user@gentoo.org</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo web applications team uses the <mail
link="gentoo-web-user@gentoo.org">gentoo-web-user</mail> mailing list for
discussions related to web applications and <c>webapp-config</c>. This is a
low-volume list.
</p>

<p>
To subscribe to this mailing list, send an empty e-mail to <mail
link="gentoo-web-user-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-web-user-subscribe</mail>.
Once subscribed, you can post by sending an e-mail to <mail
link="gentoo-web-user@gentoo.org">gentoo-web-user@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Web application overlay</title>

<body>

<p>
Web applications in general tend to be a severe security liability. They are
designed to communicate with the outside world and need to deal with a range of
input from the Internet. Since it is often hard for developers to foresee all
types of malicious input, security flaws are being detected rather frequently
in the apps we maintain.
</p>

<p>
To reduce the impact of such incidents while still offering a wide range of
different web applications, we created a Portage <uri
link="http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/webapps/">overlay</uri>
that contains ebuilds for applications that we do not want to maintain in the
main tree. Such applications either lack a developer willing to maintain it in
Portage or have not been reviewed for security.
</p>

<warn>
Please remember that the applications available through the overlay might
compromise the security of your server!
</warn>

<p>
The overlay is an ideal playground for new developers wishing to join our
team. Once we see that you are capable of writing ebuilds of reasonable
quality, we can provide you with commit rights to the overlay.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</extrachapter>

<!-- herds -->
<herd name="web-apps" />

</project>
