<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/release/2004.0/x86/hardened-x86-release-notes.xml,v 1.2 2012/10/28 15:21:14 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>x86 Release Notes for Hardened Gentoo Linux 2004.0</title>

<author title="Author">
 <mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo 2004.0 Release Notes
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>28 February 2004</date>

<chapter>
	<title>The Gentoo Linux Project</title>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<body>
			<p>Gentoo Linux is a community driven project committed to producing
			high quality opensource software. These release notes for Gentoo Linux 2004.0
			summarize important package updates, security updates, and many other changes
			that have happened since Gentoo Linux 1.4. </p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Table of Contents</title>
		<body>
		<ul>
			<li>1. Overview</li>
			<li>2. Important Changes</li>
			<li>	2.1 Security Updates</li>
			<li>	2.2 Errata</li>
			<li>	2.3 Critical Package Updates</li>
			<li>	2.4 Portage Updates</li>
			<li>	2.5 Userland Updates</li>
			<li>	2.6 Documentation Updates</li>
			<li>3. Upgrading from previous versions of Gentoo Linux</li>
		</ul>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Important Changes for 2004.0</title>
	<section>
		<title>Security Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>Gentoo Linux 2004.0 contains security updates to address GLSAs 
			(Gentoo Linux Security Advisories) numbered 200308-01 to 200402-07.
			</p>
			
			<p>Individual GLSAs can be referenced by going to
			<c>http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-$x.xml</c>, and substituting <c>$x</c>
			with the desired GLSA number. </p>
			
			<p>For more information, please consult the the gentoo-security mailing list
			<uri link="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.security">archive</uri>. </p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Errata</title>
		<body>
			<table>
			<tr>
				<th>Errata</th>
				<th>Workaround</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti>Emerge system stops after emerging hardened-gcc.</ti>
				<ti>Run <c>etc-update</c>, then <c>hardened-gcc -a</c> and
				restart the emerge.</ti>
			</tr>
			</table>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Critical Package Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>Important package-versions in this release:</p>

			<ul>
				<li>hardened-gcc 3.3.2.1-r2</li>
				<li>gcc 3.3.2-r5</li>
				<li>glibc 2.3.2-r9</li>
				<li>aa-sources-2.4.23-r1</li>
				<li>ck-sources-2.4.23-r1</li>
				<li>development-sources-2.6.3</li>
				<li>gaming-sources-2.4.20-r8</li>
				<li>gentoo-dev-sources-2.6.3-r1</li>
				<li>gentoo-sources-2.4.22-r7</li>
				<li>grsec-sources-2.4.25.1.9.14</li>
				<li>gs-sources-2.4.25_pre7-r2</li>
				<li>mm-sources-2.6.3-r4</li>
				<li>openmosix-sources-2.4.22-r4</li>
				<li>planet-ccrma-sources-2.4.21-r5</li>
				<li>usermode-sources-2.6.3-r1</li>
				<li>vanilla-sources-2.4.25</li>
				<li>win4lin-sources-2.4.23-r2</li>
				<li>wolk-sources-4.9-r4</li>
				<li>xfs-sources-2.4.24-r3</li>
				<li>Portage 2.0.50-r1</li>
				<li>XFree86 4.3.0-r5</li>
				<li>KDE 3.2.0</li>
				<li>GNOME 2.4.2</li>
				<li>XFCE4 4.0.1</li>
			</ul>

			<p>Coreutils is now available in Version 5.0.91-r4 with ACL
			patches.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Portage Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>The Portage version included in this release is 2.0.50-r1 and
			the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/portage/ChangeLog?root=gentoo-src">ChangeLog</uri>
			can be found via our online CVS repository.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Userland Updates</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li>Genkernel has been updated. Its behaviour is different
				to previous versions in previous releases.</li>
				<li>Gentoo Linux 2004.0 is fully compatible with Linux kernel 2.6.
				To use kernel 2.6, just <c>emerge gentoo-dev-sources</c>. </li>
				<li>Catalyst, the Gentoo Release Metatool, is stable in Portage as version
				1.0.2. To use Catalyst, simply <c>emerge catalyst</c>. </li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Documentation Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			Gentoo Linux 2004.0 on deprecates all single arch installation manuals in favor
			of the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo Linux Handbook</uri>.
			The Gentoo Linux Handbook offers the most up-to-date information on all aspects of the
			Gentoo Linux installation process.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Upgrading and Installation of Gentoo Linux 2004.0</title>
	<section>
		<title>Installing Gentoo Linux 2004.0</title>
		<body>
			<p>The entire Gentoo Linux installation process is documented 
			in the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>. </p>
			
			<p>Each architecture offers three LiveCDs. The first one being a universal
			bootable LiveCD which can be used to install with or without an Internet connection.
			The second LiveCD is a non-bootable subarch-optimized LiveCD which contains precompiled binaries of popular
			programs such as XFree86, KDE, and GNOME. The third LiveCD is a bootable minimal LiveCD
			that is smaller in size and includes only the basics needed to simply boot a machine.</p>
			
			<p>At minimum, the universal or minimal LiveCD is required to boot the machine and install Gentoo.
			The universal LiveCD requires an Internet connection to install from a stage1
			installation tarball, but does not require an Internet connection to install
			from a stage3 installation tarball. The minimal LiveCD requires an Internet connection
			to install Gentoo Linux.</p>

			<p>There are several kernels to choose from when using a Gentoo LiveCD to boot your
			machine. The two main choices, the 2.4.24 based <c>gentoo</c> kernel and the 2.6.1 based <c>smp</c> kernel
			will boot the machine into either uniprocessor or multiprocessor (SMP) mode, respectively.
			The other two options, <c>gentoo-nofb</c> and <c>smp-nofb</c> boot the machine into uniprocessor
			or multiprocessor mode without console framebuffer support. Press "F1" at the boot
			prompt to choose which kernel to boot into.</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Upgrading to Gentoo Linux 2004.0</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			If you already have a working installation of Gentoo Linux (Version
			1.4) there is no need to reinstall. You will automatically get
			Gentoo 2004.0 if you sync your Portage tree and run
			<c>emerge --update world</c>. If you still have an installation
			with a Gentoo 1.2 profile it might make sense -- in some cases -- 
			that you do a new installation.</p>
			<p>
			There is also the possibility to update your system to a 1.4 
			profile from which you -- as already stated -- can easily get to
			Gentoo 2004.0. This update includes recompiling of glibc and some
			essential system packages; it will take a very long time (possibly
			longer as a complete re-installation) and it might also fail. So if
			you still have an installation with a Gentoo 1.2 profile, it's
			your decision whether you update or reinstall.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
