<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/release/2004.0/x86/x86-release-notes.xml,v 1.6 2004/02/29 04:47:35 zhen Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="x86-release-notes.xml">
<title>x86 Release Notes for Gentoo Linux 2004.0</title>

<author title="Author">
 <mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail>
</author>

<author title="x86 Release Manager">
	<mail link="beejay@gentoo.org">Benjamin Judas</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="spyderous@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholtz</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo 2004.0 Release Notes
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>28 February 2004</date>

<chapter>
	<title>The Gentoo Linux Project</title>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<body>
			<p>Gentoo Linux is a community driven project commited to producing
			high quality opensource software. These release notes for Gentoo Linux 2004.0
			summarize important package updates, security updates, and many other changes
			that have happened since Gentoo Linux 1.4. </p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Table of Contents</title>
		<body>
		<ul>
			<li>1. Overview</li>
			<li>2. Important Changes</li>
			<li>	2.1 Security Updates</li>
			<li>	2.2 Errata</li>
			<li>	2.3 Critical Package Updates</li>
			<li>	2.4 Portage Updates</li>
			<li>	2.5 Userland Updates</li>
			<li>	2.6 Documentation Updates</li>
			<li>3. Upgrading from previous versions of Gentoo Linux</li>
		</ul>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Important Changes for 2004.0</title>
	<section>
		<title>Security Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>Gentoo Linux 2004.0 contains security updates to address GLSAs 
			(Gentoo Linux Security Advisories) numbered 200308-01 to 200402-07.
			</p>
			
			<p>Individual GLSAs can be referenced by going to
			<i>http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-$x.xml</i>, and substituting <i>$x</i>
			with the desired GLSA number. </p>
			
			<p>For more information, please consult the the gentoo-security mailing list
			<uri link="http://news.gmane.org/gmane.linux.gentoo.security">archive</uri>. </p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Errata</title>
		<body>
			<table>
			<tr>
				<th>Errata</th>
				<th>Workaround</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti>Errors at boot about not being able to umount /dev.</ti>
				<ti>Cosmetic, will be fixed for 2004.1.</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti>SMP kernel does not recognize USB keyboards</ti>
				<ti>There is a bug in the LiveCD SMP kernel that prevents this. Use
				a PS/2 keyboard or different kernel if possible. This will be fixed for 2004.1</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti>Some NForce2 based boards may not display the bootsplash
				graphics properly.</ti>
				<ti>Boot using the gentoo-nofb or smp-nofb kernels.</ti>
			</tr>
			</table>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Critical Package Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>Important package-versions in this release:</p>

			<ul>
				<li>gcc 3.3.2-r5</li>
				<li>glibc 2.3.2-r9</li>
				<li>aa-sources-2.4.23-r1</li>
				<li>ck-sources-2.4.23-r1</li>
				<li>development-sources-2.6.3</li>
				<li>gaming-sources-2.4.20-r8</li>
				<li>gentoo-dev-sources-2.6.3-r1</li>
				<li>gentoo-sources-2.4.22-r7</li>
				<li>grsec-sources-2.4.25.1.9.14</li>
				<li>gs-sources-2.4.25_pre7-r2</li>
				<li>mm-sources-2.6.3-r4</li>
				<li>openmosix-sources-2.4.22-r4</li>
				<li>planet-ccrma-sources-2.4.21-r5</li>
				<li>usermode-sources-2.6.3-r1</li>
				<li>vanilla-sources-2.4.25</li>
				<li>win4lin-sources-2.4.23-r2</li>
				<li>wolk-sources-4.9-r4</li>
				<li>xfs-sources-2.4.24-r3</li>
				<li>Portage 2.0.50-r1</li>
				<li>XFree86 4.3.0-r5</li>
				<li>KDE 3.2.0</li>
				<li>GNOME 2.4.2</li>
				<li>XFCE4 4.0.1</li>
			</ul>

			<p>Coreutils is now available in Version 5.0.91-r4 with ACL
			patches.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Portage Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>The Portage version included in this release is 2.0.50-r1 and
			the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/portage/ChangeLog?root=gentoo-src">ChangeLog</uri>
			can be found via our online CVS repository.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Userland Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>
				<ul>
					<li>
						Genkernel has been updated. Its behaviour is different
						to previous versions in previous releases.
					</li>
				</ul>
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Documentation Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			Gentoo Linux 2004.0 on deprecates all single arch installation manuals in favor
			of the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo Linux Handbook</uri>.
			The Gentoo Linux Handbook offers the most up-to-date information on all aspects of the
			Gentoo Linux installation process.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Upgrading and Installation of Gentoo Linux 2004.0</title>
	<section>
		<title>Installing Gentoo Linux 2004.0</title>
		<body>
			<p>The entire Gentoo Linux installation process is documented 
			in the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>.
			Each architecture offers two CDs; the first one being a "universal"
			bootable LiveCD that contains a generic stage1 tarball, stage3 tarballs for each supported
			subarch, and the necessary distfiles needed to install a complete Gentoo Linux system without
			a network connection. In addition the to the "universal" bootable LiveCD, each architecture
			offers a second non-bootable LiveCD which contains precompiled binaries of popular
			programs such as XFree86, KDE, and GNOME optimized for a specific subarch, such as athlon-xp.
			At minimum, you will need the universal LiveCD to boot your machine to install Gentoo. Use
			of the second LiveCD is not necessary, although it may speed up your installation time
			considerably.
			</p>

			<p>There are several kernels to choose from when using a Gentoo LiveCD to boot your
			machine. The two main choices, <i>gentoo</i> and <i>smp</i> boot your machine
			into either uniprocessor or multiprocessor (SMP) mode, respectively. The other two options,
			<i>gentoo-nofb</i> and <i>smp-nofb</i> boot your machine into uniprocessor
			or multiprocessor mode without console framebuffer support. </p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Upgrading to Gentoo Linux 2004.0</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			If you already have a working installation of Gentoo Linux (Version
			1.4) there is no need to reinstall. You will automatically get
			Gentoo 2004.0 if you sync your Portage tree and run
			<c>emerge --update world</c>. If you still have an installation
			with a Gentoo 1.2 profile it might make sense -- in some cases -- 
			that you do a new installation.</p>
			<p>
			There is also the possibility to update your system to a 1.4 
			profile from which you -- as already stated -- can easily get to
			Gentoo 2004.0. This update includes recompiling of glibc and some
			essential system packages; it will take a very long time (possibly
			longer as a complete re-installation) and it might also fail. So if
			you still have an installation with a Gentoo 1.2 profile, it's
			your decision wether you update or reinstall.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
