<?xml version='1.0' ?>
<mainpage id="docs">
<title>Gentoo Linux Documentation</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>

<version>1.0.0</version>
<date>04 Jan 2002</date>

<chapter>
<section>
<body>
		<fig link="http://www.ibiblio.org/gentoo/images/znurt.jpg"/><br/>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux User Documentation Resources</title>
<body>

<p><ul>
	<li><uri link="/doc/faq.html">The Gentoo Linux FAQ</uri> answers Gentoo Linux frequently-asked questions.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/build.html">The Gentoo Linux CD Installation Guide</uri> explains how to install Gentoo Linux/x86 using our installation CD.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/gentooppc-quickstart.html">The Gentoo Linux/PPC QuickStart Guide</uri> explains how to set up Gentoo Linux/PPC.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/portage-user.html">The Portage User Guide</uri> explains how to start using our ports system called Portage.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/portage-manual.html">The Portage Manual</uri> aims to be a comprehensive manual for Portage.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/desktop.html">The Desktop Configuration Guide</uri> shows you how to set up a fully-functional desktop system after installation.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/use-howto.html">The USE Variable HOWTO</uri> explains what all those interesting USE variables do.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/gentoo-security.html">The Gentoo Security Guide</uri> shows you how to harden your Gentoo Linux system against intruders and attacks.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/gentoo-security.html">The Gentoo Java Guide</uri> explains how Java is handled under Gentoo Linux.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/altinstall.html">The Gentoo Alternative Installation Guide</uri> shows you how to install Gentoo Linux/x86 using various alternative methods.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/openafs.html">The OpenAFS Guide</uri> guides you through the process of getting OpenAFS configured on your system.  OpenAFS is a distributed network-based file sharing technology.</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux Developer Documentation Resources</title>
<body>
<p><ul>
	<li><uri link="/doc/gentoo-howto.html">The Developers HOWTO</uri> gives you the information you need to get started creating your own ports (ebuilds).</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/cvs-tutorial.html">The CVS tutorial</uri> will be of assistance if you are new to CVS, the concurrent versions system.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/eclass-howto.html">The Eclass HOWTO</uri> shows you how to create ebuilds that support OOP-like inheritance features.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/uml.html">The User-Mode Linux Guide</uri> shows you how to use User-Mode Linux under Gentoo Linux.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/xml-guide.html">The Documentation Guide</uri> will introduce you to the XML syntax used for the creation of our Web documentation.</li>
	<li><uri link="/doc/ebuild-submit.html">Contributing ebuilds</uri> will show you how to use Bugzilla to submit new Gentoo Linux ebuilds that you have created.</li>
	<li><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi">View our CVS repository</uri> if you need to look at our code and ebuilds.</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>
