<?xml version='1.0'?>
<guide link="/doc/use-howto.xml">
<title>Gentoo Guide to USE flags</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">
	Seemant Kulleen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="meekrob@gentoo.org">
	Sherman Boyd</mail>
</author>

<abstract>This guide introduces you to the ultimate tool for
customizing Gentoo -- USE settings.   Not only is there a description of
each USE flag in current use, there is also a helpful guide to help you to
determine which USE flags you will need to use.</abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>24 Apr 2002</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>What is the use of <c>USE</c> flags anyway?</title>
<body>
<p>One of the things which attracted me, as a user, to Gentoo was the fact
that it is a highly customisable distribution.  The fact that it is a source
based distribution allows the user complete control over what kinds of
features and support are built in to the installed applications.  Moreover,
the idea of bloat reduction appealed to me -- I like not having to install
things which I do not <e>really</e> need.</p>

<p>And how, exactly, does Gentoo achieve this?  By defining <c>USE</c> settings.
Essentially, these are keywords that define options used on a system-wide
basis to configure applications during their respective compilation
procedures.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Default <c>USE</c> flags</title>
<body>
<p>Of course, Gentoo defines a set of safe default flags for you.  You will
find these in your <path>/etc/make.profile/make.defaults</path> file.</p>


<p>From the Gentoo-1.1a release, the <c>USE</c> settings are:</p>

<pre>USE="xv slang readline gpm berkdb mmx 3dnow gdbm tcpd pam libwww ssl nls
     mitshm arts lame perl python esd gif imlib sdl oggvorbis gnome gtk X qt
     kde motif opengl avi png tiff gif"</pre>


<warn>Instead of writing to this file, as I can see many of you scrambling to do,
it is advisable procedure to edit your <path>/etc/make.conf</path> file

In that file, you will see:</warn>

	<pre>#USE=""</pre>
<p> You would uncomment it by removing the # and adding your own custom USE
flags to that string between the quotes.</p>

<impo>Remember that <c>-flag</c> disables a flag and <c>flag</c> adds a flag.  If a flag is neither in <path>/etc/make.profile/make.defaults</path> nor in <path>/etc/make.conf</path> then its functionality is disabled.</impo>

<p>Simply uncomment that, and add whatever other flags you want to add.
"But what if I want to remove things from the make.defaults file?" I hear
you ask.  That is simply done by putting "-flag" in your
<path>/etc/make.conf</path>
file.  Mine, for example, looks like this:</p>

<pre>USE="-gnome -kde qt -arts -nls python perl oggvorbis opengl sdl
     -postgres jpeg png truetype xml xml2 dvd avi aalib mpeg encode fbcon
     mmx"</pre>

<p>Now that you know how to enable extra flags, and disable existing flags,
let us examine what these flags actually do.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Available <c>USE</c> flags</title>

<section>
<title>HARDWARE FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p>For your processor, you have three flags: <c>mmx</c>, <c>3dnow</c>, and
<c>sse</c>.
<c>3dnow</c> is applicable to certain AMD K-6 cpus and Athlon and higher cpus.
<c>mmx</c> is applicable to Pentium-MMX class and higher cpus, including Athlons.
<c>sse</c> is a feature for higher Pentiums.  If you have a Pentium4 with SSE2, you
want this flag as well.</p>

<p>Now, for your video card. 
If you have a 3dfx card, you want to enable the <c>3dfx</c> flag.  If your card
is a voodoo3 then you want to enable the <c>voodoo3</c> flag.

If you have a matrox card, you want the <c>matrox</c> flag enabled.</p>

<p>Laptop users will probably want to enable the <c>apm</c> flag and the <c>pcmcia</c>
flag.  If you do <em>not</em> want CardBus support, then enable the <c>nocardbus</c>
flag as well.  The <c>pnp</c> support gives you PNP in pcmcia-cs.</p>

<p>If you have a Palm Pilot or PDA that you like to interface with your Gentoo
machine, then the <c>pda</c> flag is for you.</p>

<p>If you intend to attach a digital camera, then the <c>gphoto2</c> flag will cause
support for it to be compiled into relevant applications.</p>

<p>Finally, if you have a printer, then the <c>cups</c> flag will build printer
support.
And <c>slp</c> will add Service Locator Protocol support to CUPS.</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>DISPLAY FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p>If you intend to use the XFree86 system, then the flag <c>X</c> is a good idea.
With X, you can enable the <c>dga</c> flag to get Direct Graphic Access
optimisation.  
The <c>opengl</c> flag exists for enabling the OpenGL support in many
applications.
XFree86 can be made to support the XVideo extension if you enable the <c>xv</c>
<em>USE</em> flag.  According to one of
the visitors in the #gentoo IRC channel at openprojects.net ([Nagash]), "xv makes
Mplayer good."</p>

<p>If you want to have support for the framebuffer console (as provided by the
kernel -- the penguin at boot time is an example), then enable
the <c>fbcon</c> flag.</p>

<p>If you would like to be able to use certain applications with DirectFB, then
the <c>directfb</c> flag needs to be enabled.</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>DESKTOP FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p>Are you a KDE user?  Then the following flags are for you:</p>
<p><c>kde</c> -- to build KDE support</p>
<p><c>qt</c> -- to allow linking to the Qt libraries</p>
<p><c>qtmt</c> -- to allow linking to the multi-threaded version of the Qt libraries</p>
<p><c>arts</c> -- the KDE sound system</p>

<impo>Please note that if you do not want KDE support, you must disable at least
<c>kde</c> and <c>arts</c> support.</impo>

<p>Do you prefer GNOME?  Then use:</p>
<p><c>gnome</c> -- to build apps with GNOME support</p>
<p><c>gtk</c> -- to build apps with GTK+ support</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>GNOME FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p>There are many more flags for GNOME users.</p>
<p><c>bonobo</c> -- support for GNOME's CORBA interface through Bonobo</p>
<p><c>evo</c> -- support for Evolution (Gnome's Outlook-like
application)</p>
<p><c>gb</c> -- support for Gnome Basic (such a thing actually exists??)</p>
<p><c>gtkhtml</c> -- support for the mis-named GTK-HTML library </p>

<warn>To disable GNOME support, simply add  <c>-gnome</c> to your USE string in <path>/etc/make.conf</path></warn>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>GRAPHICS LIBRARIES</title>
<body>
<p>There are many many libraries that provide multimedia.  Let us deal with the
graphics libraries first.  
In the previous section we saw GTK and Qt toolkit library support.  Other
available options are:</p>

<p><c>motif</c> -- for OpenMotif support</p>
<p><c>tcltk</c> -- for Tcl and/or Tk support</p>
<p><c>aalib</c> -- support for ascii graphics.</p>
<p><c>imlib</c> -- support for the Imlib image loading and rendering
library.</p>
<p><c>ncurses</c> -- support for the ncurses console display - many applications offer
the user a choice of front-ends, and ncurses is a popular (and safe) one</p>
<p><c>readline</c> -- another console based library.</p>
<p><c>sdl</c> -- this is the Simple Direct Layer media library -- many excellent games
are compiled against this library.</p>
<p><c>svga</c> -- Some applications can offer SVGAlib support</p>
<p><c>lcms</c> -- offers color management support to the imagemagick
library</p>

<p>You can add support for different graphics formats with the following
flags:</p>
<p><c>gif</c> -- support for GIF image format using libungif or giflib</p>
<p><c>jpeg</c> -- support for JPEG image format using libjpeg</p>
<p><c>png</c> -- support for PNG image format</p>
<p><c>tiff</c> -- support for TIFF image format</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>MOVIE LIBRARIES</title>
<body>
<p>So you like to watch movies?  Then you might be interested in enabling some
of the optional support offered with the following flags:</p>

<p><c>avi</c> -- adds support from the avifile library, and optionally the Win32
codec library</p>
<p><c>mpeg</c> -- adds support from the libmpeg3 library</p>
<p><c>quicktime</c> -- adds support from the OpenQuickTime and Quicktime4Linux
libraries.</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SOUND LIBRARIES</title>
<body>
<p>There are many sound layer libraries on offer.</p>
<p><c>alsa</c> -- the Advanced Linux Sound Architecture</p>
<p><c>esd</c> -- the Enlightened Sound Daemon</p>
<p><c>mikmod</c> -- a library to allow MikMod sound modules support</p>
<p><c>oss</c> -- the Open Sound System</p>
<p><c>nas</c> -- Network Audio Sound</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>OTHER MULTIMEDIA FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p><c>ggi</c> -- support for non-X video drivers for movie playing</p>
<p><c>dvd</c> -- adds support for playing and decrypting DVDs using the
libcss library</p>
<p><c>xmms</c> - the X MultiMedia System</p>
<p><c>oggvorbis</c> -- support for the Ogg Vorbis audio format</p>
<p><c>flash</c> -- support for creating flash files usng Ming</p>
<p><c>encode</c> -- if you like to be able to encode various multimedia
formats</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>NETWORK FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p>Of course, you want to connect your Gentoo box to a net of some sort.</p>
<p><c>ipv6</c> -- builds support for IPv6</p>
<p><c>snmp</c> -- support for Simple Network Management Protocol, which
allows you to manage remote machines.</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SECURITY FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p>If you are concerned about security, we recommend PAM support provided
by:</p>
<p><c>pam</c> -- Pluggable Authentication Modules</p>
<p><c>ssl</c> -- Secure Socket Layer -- necessary for ssh. Apache also supports this,
as do mail readers to establish secure connections.</p>
<p><c>crypt</c> -- To provide mcrypt, mhash and gpg encryption library
support</p>
<p><c>socks5</c> -- build Socks5 support</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>MAIL FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p><c>imap</c> -- support for IMAP</p>
<p><c>ldap</c> -- adds Lightweight Directory Accesss Protocol support</p>
<p><c>tcpd</c> -- support for TCP wrappers</p>
<p><c>xface</c></p> -- support for xface (images sent along with e-mail messages) support to sylpheed and sylpheed-claws

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>MOZILLA FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p><c>mozilla</c> -- Adds Mozilla support to other applications</p>

<p>When emerging mozilla, you may want to keep the following flags in
mind:</p>
<p><c>mozaccess-builtin</c> -- Adds to text-to-speech and eventually braille
support</p>
<p><c>mozctl</c> -- Adds Pango like module to mozilla</p>
<p><c>mozirc</c> -- adds an IRC (Internet Relay Chat) module</p>
<p><c>mozxmlterm</c> -- Adds an xterm like terminal with XML support</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>OFFICE PRODUCTIVITY FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p><c>spell</c> -- to add ispell/aspell/pspell support for
spell-checking</p>
<p><c>truetype</c> -- to add support for FreeType and FreeType2 fonts</p>
<p><c>xml</c> -- adds support for XML library (version 1)</p>
<p><c>xml2</c> -- adds support for GNOME's XML library (version 2)</p>
<p><c>pdflib</c> -- adds support for Adobe's Portable Document Format</p>
<p><c>plotutils</c> -- to add plotting in gnuplot</p>
<p><c>tetex</c> -- adds support for TeTeX the best thing for publishing</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>LANGUAGE FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p><c>guile</c> -- Guile is an interpreter for Scheme</p>
<p><c>java</c></p>
<p><c>perl</c></p>
<p><c>python</c></p>
<p><c>ruby</c></p>
<p><c>slang</c> -- S-Lang is a powerful interpreted language</p>
<p><c>libwww</c> -- general purpose web api</p>
<p><c>libg++</c> -- adds C++ modules</p>
<p><c>atlas -- Adds support for Automatically Tuned Linear Algebra Software
instead of BLAS (Basic Linear Algebra Subprograms) for the R language.  ATLAS is highly optimised for its architecture</c></p>
<p><c>pic</c></p>

</body>
</section>


<section>
<title>DATABASE FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p>You have a choice of database types that you get support for:</p>
<p><c>berkdb</c> -- BerkleyDB for MySQL</p>
<p><c>mysql</c> -- MySQL</p>
<p><c>postgres</c> -- PostgreSQL</p>
<p><c>odbc</c> -- Support for UnixODBC (Open Database Connectivity)</p>
<p><c>innodb</c> -- MySQL transaction support</p>
<p><c>gd</c> -- GNU database libraries</p>
<p><c>gdbm</c> -- ditto</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>FILESYSTEM FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p><c>acl</c> -- Support for SGI's XFS dump/restore utilities</p>
<p><c>afs</c> -- OpenAFS, which is a distributed file system</p>
<p><c>samba</c> -- Support for SAMBA (windows/unix interconnectivity)</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>OTHER USEFUL FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p><c>nls</c> -- Adds Native Language Support (usually using GNU's gettext
libs); this
is just bloatware if you only need one language.</p>
<p><c>doc</c> -- causes extra documentation to be generated</p>
<p><c>gpm</c> -- Adds General Purpose Mouse support for the console</p>

</body>
</section>


<section>
<title>UNKNOWN PURPOSE FLAGS</title>
<body>
<p>The flags in this section are used in some ebuilds, but as of this
writing, their meanings are unknown to the author.  For any feedback
regarding them or any other USE flags, please fill out a bug report at
<uri>http://bugs.gentoo.org</uri> and assign it to seemant@gentoo.org</p>
<p><c>trusted</c></p>
<p><c>zeo</c> -- Adds support for Zope Enterprise Objects</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
