<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>Proctors</name>

<longname>Gentoo Code of Conduct - Proctors</longname>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="amne@gentoo.org">Wernfried Haas</mail>
</author>

<description>
The Gentoo proctors are responsible to make Gentoo a friendly and productive
place by enforcing the Code of Conduct.
</description>

<longdescription>
Gentoo uses many public media such as mailing lists, forums, irc, bugzilla,
etc. Following the <uri link="/proj/en/council/coc.xml">Code of Conduct</uri>
is a minimum requirement for all of them. The proctors are responsible to make
sure it is followed, especially on the mailing lists. They work together with
moderators of other media such as the #gentoo operators and the forum
moderators. Additionally, members of the council (who are not acting as
proctors) are here helping with advice and looking that things are done
properly according to the intentions of the council.
</longdescription>

<dev role="Member" >tsunam</dev>
<dev role="Member" >NeddySeagoon</dev>
<dev role="Member" >blackace</dev>
<dev role="Member" >marienz</dev>
<dev role="Member" >mark_alec</dev>
<dev role="Council contact" >kloeri</dev>
<dev role="Council contact" >KingTaco</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Seeking help from the proctors</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
A lot of things are being said and posted in the community every day. While
the more prominent violations of the CoC may be spotted by the proctors
themselves, it is impossible to keep up with every post. If you think the CoC
is not followed somewhere, you have the following options:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>You can report <uri
  link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-28820.html">Guideline
  violations</uri> on the forums directly to the forum moderators.
  </li>
  <li>For #gentoo, please talk to the people in #gentoo-ops.</li>
  <li>If it is in another medium like the mailing lists, you have the feeling
  the issue is not only limited to one of the media already moderated
  primarily by another group of moderators, or not taken seriously enough by
  them, please contact us using the alias proctors@gentoo.org.</li> 
  <li>The proctors are usually in #gentoo-proctors, but since they are not
  reading along all the time, it is usually better to use email so your issue
  does not get lost.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Requirements for proctors</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Executing Gentoo's Code of Conduct is a sensitive issue. As a consequence
proctors are carefully selected. These are some minimum requirements that can
be evaluated on a case by case basis:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Must be a respected member of the Gentoo community. Of course this is
  hard to put into numbers or other hard facts, but new additions to the team
  need to be acknowledged by the existing team members first.</li>
  <li>All proctors have to be impartial. We realize it may sometimes be hard
  to do this, but acting as a team fair decisions should be
  made. However, every proctor should be as neutral as possible.</li>
  <li>Must be Gentoo staff for at least 6 months. Proctors gain access to
  sensitive infrastructure and are therefor required to already have
  developer/staff status. Recruiting new people only for being a proctor is
  not encouraged in general.</li>
  <li>Must not be a member of the Gentoo Council due to conflicts of
  interest.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>
