<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link = "clusters.xml">
<title>Clusters running Gentoo</title>
<author title="Author">
    <mail link="cluster@gentoo.org">Cluster Team</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
This document lists clusters that are running Gentoo all around the world.
</abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2010-09-09</date>

<chapter>
<title>Medium to large clusters</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
This is a brief list of known clusters running Gentoo that have at least
32 cores. Please contact <mail link="cluster@gentoo.org">the clustering team</mail>
if you know of one not yet on this list or have updated information for one
already on this list.
</p>
<ul>
   <li>7783 cores in 2284 mixed nodes (AMD64, Pentium-4 and Xeon), at 
   2009-02-20 and expanding by Hyves (Startphone Ltd) for www.hyves.nl</li>
   <li>5832 cores in 972 6 GFlops MIPS nodes in the SiCortex SC5832</li>
   <li>1200 cores in 75 mixed nodes (Xeon E5520 @ 2.27 GHz and W5590 @ 3.33 GHz), at <uri link="http://www.uottawa.ca/">University of Ottawa</uri> - <uri link="http://mysite.science.uottawa.ca/lramunno/">Physics Department - Computational Nanophotonics Group</uri></li>
   <li>1200 cores in 125 mixed nodes (2.2 GHz and up) at <uri link="http://beocat.cis.ksu.edu/">Kansas State University</uri></li>
   <li>960 cores in 224 mixed nodes (2.6GHz, 2.2GHz Opteron single/dual/quad core, 
   3.0GHz Xeon dual core) at the University of Bern Central IT Services</li>
   <li>512 cores in 256 Apple Xserve G5 nodes at the University of Maine</li>
   <li>440 cores in 86 mixed nodes (20 x 2.1 GHz Opteron 2352, 64 x 2.4 GHz Opteron 280, 2 x Xeon X5650, tot. 1TB RAM) at St.Petersburg State Polytechnic University</li>
   <li>408 cores in 9 mixed nodes (8 x Quad AMD Opteron 6174 Twelve core, 2.2GHz, 1 x Dual AMD Opteron 6174 Twelve core, tot. 1TB RAM) at St.Petersburg State Polytechnic University</li>
   <li>408 cores in 88 mixed nodes (Quad Opteron and Xeon) at <uri link="http://zymeworks.com">Zymeworks Inc.</uri></li>
   <li>296 cores in 135 mixed nodes (2.8 GHz Opteron and 2.8 GHz Xeon) at the 
   University of Delaware's Delaware Biotechnology Institute</li>
   <li>268 cores in 134 2.8 GHz Xeon nodes at the University of Idaho</li>
   <li>256 cores in 128 Opteron nodes at Indiana University</li>
   <li>256 cores in 3.0 GHz Pentium-4 nodes at Simon Fraser University-Surrey (TechBC)</li>
   <li>200 cores in IBM xSeries rendering cluster at Attitude Studio</li>
   <li>160 cores in 80 Pentium-3 933 MHz nodes at SUNY-Stony Brook</li>
   <li>120 cores in 5 nodes (AMD Magny-Cours 6168 @ 1.9 GHz), at <uri link="http://www.siue.edu/">Southern Illinois University Edwardsville</uri> - Physics Department - <uri link="http://www.siue.edu/~eackad/">Computational Nanophotonics group</uri></li>
   <li>130 cores in mixed nodes (2.20 GHz Opteron, 3.00 GHz Dual Core Xeon, 2.66 GHz Quad Core Xeon) at Laval University in Québec City</li>
   <li>80 cores in 10 Sun Fire X2200 (2.7 GHz Opteron 2384, tot. 176GB RAM) at <uri link="http://zero.ift.uni.wroc.pl/">Institute for Theoretical Physics</uri> University of Wroclaw, Poland</li>
   <li>72 cores in mixed nodes (1.4 GHz and up) at the University of Edinburgh</li>
   <li>68 cores at Tufts University</li>
   <li>64 cores in 32 mixed nodes (27 1.4 GHz Athlon MP, 5 2.0 GHz Athlon MP) at the University of Edinburgh</li>
   <li>64 cores in 32 nodes (IBM eServer) at the University of Manchester</li>
   <li>64 cores in 8 nodes (Xeon E5430) at the University of Aveiro, Portugal</li>
   <li>54 cores in 1.2 GHz Athlon nodes at the University of Idaho</li>
   <li>40 cores in 20 Pentium-2 nodes at the University of Trollhättan/Uddevalla</li>
   <li>36 cores in 18 mixed nodes (6 Dual Xeon 2.0GHz, 12 Dual PIII 866MHz) at Montana State University</li>
   <li>32 cores in 16 2.4 GHz Xeon nodes at the University of Pennsylvania Chemistry Department</li>
   <li>32 cores in mixed MIPS nodes (25 R4400 SGI Indigo2 &amp; 7 R5000 SGI Indy) at Simon Fraser University-Surrey (TechBC)</li>
   <li>32 cores in 8 nodes (Intel Q9550 2.83 Ghz) at <uri link="http://supercomputing.univpm.it">Università Politecnica delle Marche</uri> - Italy.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
