<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>proxy-maint</name>
<longname>Proxy Maintainers</longname>
<date>2006-03-28</date>
<author title="Author"><mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail></author>
<description>
Proxy Maintainers is a project to coordinate and maintain relationships 
between developers with tree access and an interest in a wide variety of 
packages and users who wish to keep select packages up to date.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>The primary goal of the Proxy Maintainers project is to 
create and maintain relationships between developers and users in order 
to ensure packages in the Gentoo tree stay up to date.  This involves a 
few main tasks:

<ul>
   <li>List Interested Developers who are interested in being Commiters.</li>
   <li>Recruit Interested Users for Proxy Maintainers.</li>
   <li>Maintain a list of pairings between
       Commiters/Proxy Maintainers.</li>
</ul>
Proxy-Maint members are available via <uri 
link="mailto://proxy-maint@gentoo.org">proxy-maint@gentoo.org</uri>
</p>
</longdescription>

<dev role="Dictator">antarus</dev>
<dev role="Commiter">jokey</dev>
<dev role="Vice Dictator">masterdriverz</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>What it takes to be a Proxy Maintainer</title>
<section>
<title>Enthusiasm</title>
<body>
<p>
Proxy Maintainers should be interested in the packages that they are maintaining.
By becoming a Proxy Maintainer you are essentially the person in charge of that package
in Gentoo.  When users have questions regarding a package and how it works in Gentoo, you
and your Commiter will be the people that those questions are directed towards.  We would
like you to enjoy the maintaince and not feel as though it is a chore.  To that end we are
looking for enthusiastic people.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Teamwork</title>
<body>
<p>
At a minimum you will be assigned one Commiter who is your partner with regards to a specific
package.  Your work will be reviewed by your Commiter for violations of Gentoo QA policy;
much of the policy is based more on common sense and less on specific rules.  If your work
does not meet QA your Commiter will notify you of where this occurs and will help you fix
the problems to ensure that you work meets guidelines and can be included in the Gentoo
package repository.  Please do not take offense to these suggestions; all criticism should
be intended as constructive criticism.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Interest</title>
<body>
<p>
Similarly in the vein above, don't Proxy-Maintain a package you have no interest in keeping
up to date.  Many packages are small and easily kept up to date; however larger packages may
take up more of your time to bump and bugfix.  Bugs for the package will be directed toward 
you (and also your Commiter).  However as Proxy-Maintainer you are responsible for responding
to the bugs with patches/comments/etc.  Be prepared to do this.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Patience</title>
<body>
<p>
Sometimes the Gentoo Developer with whom you are collaborating goes MIA.  Preferably
they will inform the Proxy-Maintainer project ahead of time (or via devaway) and we will
notify you and attempt to find a replacement Committer during their absense.  This may
take some time; please be patient with us while we find a replacement.  However don't be
afraid to prod every once in a while on the status of your Committer if they are not
responsive.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>What it takes to be a Commiter</title>

<section>
<title>CVS access to gentoo-x86</title>
<body>
<p>Being a Commiter for this project requires commit access to the Gentoo
package repository.  CVS access will be granted only to full Gentoo Developers
who have passed all their quizes (ebuild + end quiz).
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Experience</title>
<body>
<p>
Potential Commiters should have a decent amount of tree experience.  Reviewing
work is an important part of being a Commiter; as a Commiter you are still
responsible for everything that you commit.  As such, reviewing the work of
Proxy Maintainers is required.  As a Commiter, you should also be prepared to
critique the work of the Proxy Maintainer in a constructive manner.  To this
end a wide range of experience with Gentoo, ebuilds, bash, awk, sed, and so
forth is required.  As a Gentoo Developer, you should already have many of these
skills.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>QA Violations</title>
<body>
<p>
If many QA violations are reported by either your Maintainer or users regarding
a package for which you are a listed Commiter, the Proxy-Maint lead has the option of
discussing these issues with you.  If you are intentionally violating QA, please be
prepared to make your case to the Proxy-Maint lead regarding the nature of the violations.
If you continually ignore QA without good reasoning behind it, the Proxy-Maint lead
maintains the option of reporting your activities to QA and devrel.  This section is
not designed to scare potential Commiters, however commiting for people requires a high
level of knowledge as potential security problems could be embedded in a number of places.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Reporting Problems</title>
<section>
<title>Problems between a Proxy Maintainer and a Commiter</title>
<body>
<p>
If a Proxy Maintainer has a problem with their Commiter, or a Commiter has a
problem with their Proxy Maintainer they should attempt to work it out amongst
themselves.  Often things end up being a misunderstanding; please try not to get
angry at each other.  If things cannot be resolved satisfactorily for each party
please contact the Proxy-Maintainer lead.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Contributors</title>
<section>
<body>
<table>
   <tr>
      <th>Committer</th>
      <th>Proxy-Maintainers</th>
      <th>Packages Maintained</th>
   </tr>
   <tr>
      <ti>Alec Warner (antarus@gentoo.org)</ti>
      <ti>None</ti>
      <ti>None</ti>
   </tr>
   <tr>
      <ti>Charlie Shepherd (masterdriversz@gentoo.org)</ti>
      <ti></ti>
      <ti></ti>
   </tr>
   <tr>
      <ti>Markus Ullmann (jokey@gentoo.org)</ti>
      <ti>codestrom (cbergstrom (AT) netsyncro.com)</ti>
      <ti>nsd</ti>
   </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>
