<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/release/2004.3/x86-release-notes.xml,v 1.1 2004/10/26 15:57:09 beejay Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="x86-release-notes.xml">
<title>x86 Release Notes for Gentoo Linux 2004.3</title>

<author title="Author">
 <mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail>
</author>

<author title="x86 Release Coordinator">
	<mail link="beejay@gentoo.org">Benjamin Judas</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo 2004.3 Release Notes.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>15 July 2004</date>

<chapter>
	<title>The Gentoo Linux Project</title>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<body>
			<p>Gentoo Linux is a community driven project committed to producing
			high quality opensource software. These release notes for Gentoo Linux 2004.3
			summarize important package updates, security updates, and many other changes
			that have happened since Gentoo Linux 2004.2</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Table of Contents</title>
		<body>
		<ul>
			<li>1. Overview</li>
			<li>2. Important Changes</li>
			<li>	2.1 Security Updates</li>
			<li>	2.2 Errata</li>
			<li>	2.3 Critical Package Updates</li>
			<li>	2.4 Portage Updates</li>
			<li>	2.5 Userland Updates</li>
			<li>	2.6 Documentation Updates</li>
			<li>3. Upgrading from previous versions of Gentoo Linux</li>
		</ul>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Important Changes for 2004.3</title>
	<section>
		<title>Security Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>Gentoo Linux 2004.3 contains security updates to address GLSAs 
			(Gentoo Linux Security Advisories) numbered 200407-13 to 200410-26.
			</p>
			
			<p>Individual GLSAs can be referenced by going to
			<c>http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-$x.xml</c>, and substituting <c>$x</c>
			with the desired GLSA number. </p>
			
			<p>For more information, please consult the the 
			<uri link="http://security.gentoo.org/">Gentoo Linux Security Project home page</uri>.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Errata</title>
		<body>
			<table>
			<tr>
				<th>Errata</th>
				<th>Workaround</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti>Some NForce2 based boards may not display the bootsplash
				graphics properly.</ti>
				<ti>Boot using the gentoo-nofb kernel.</ti>
			</tr>
			</table>
			
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Critical Package Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>Important package-versions in this release:</p>

			<ul>
				<li>gcc 3.3.4-r1</li>
				<li>glibc 2.3.4-20040808</li>
				<li>development-sources 2.6.9</li>
				<li>gentoo-dev-sources 2.6.9-r1</li>
				<li>gentoo-sources 2.4.26-r9</li>
				<li>grsec-sources 2.4.27.2.0.1-r1</li>
				<li>openmosix-sources 2.4.24-r4</li>
				<li>usermode-sources 2.4.24-r9</li>
				<li>vanilla-sources 2.4.27</li>
				<li>win4lin-sources 2.4.26-r6</li>
				<li>wolk-sources-4.14-r7</li>
				<li>Portage 2.0.51-r2</li>
				<li>x.org-x11 6.8.0-r1</li>
				<li>KDE 3.3.0</li>
				<li>GNOME 2.6.2-r1</li>
				<li>XFCE4 4.0.6</li>
			</ul>

			<p>Coreutils is available in Version 5.2.1 with ACL patches. 
			X.org-X11 is now the default XServer (current version is 6.8.0-r1).
			See also the <uri link="x86-packagelist-2004.3.xml">list of packages</uri> available for binary installation</p>

			<p>There is one kernel available on the livecd that will run on both, uniprocessor and smp machines.</p>

			<p>With this release "cascading-profiles" are officially introduced. For more information about cascading-profiles
			please read <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/docs/cascading-profiles.xml">
			http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/docs/cascading-profiles.xml</uri>. For information about how to change your
			profile please read <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml">
			http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml</uri></p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Portage Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>The Portage version included in this release is 2.0.51-r2 and
			the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/portage/ChangeLog?root=gentoo-src">ChangeLog</uri>
			can be found via our online CVS repository.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Userland Updates</title>
		<body>
			<ul>
				<li>Genkernel has been updated. Its behaviour is different
				to previous versions in pre-2004.1 releases.</li>
				<li>Gentoo Linux 2004.3 is fully compatible with Linux kernel 2.6.
				To use kernel 2.6, just <c>emerge gentoo-dev-sources</c>. </li>
				<li>Catalyst, the Gentoo Release Metatool, is stable in Portage as version
				1.1.0. To use Catalyst, simply <c>emerge catalyst</c>. </li>
				<li>The default XServer has changed from XFree86 to x.org's X-Server.
				If you want to use the new server instead of the old XFree (which is unmaintained now)
				simply emerge <c>xorg-x11</c> instead of <c>xfree</c></li>
			</ul>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Documentation Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			Much consideration and time has been spent on the Gentoo Installation Handbook in 
			order to get it more in sync with Gentoo 2004.3. Please note that it is a constant 
			work in progress, and if any bugs are encountered, please refer them to the Gentoo Linux 
			bugtracking system at http://bugs.gentoo.org.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Upgrading and Installation of Gentoo Linux 2004.3</title>
	<section>
		<title>Installing Gentoo Linux 2004.3</title>
		<body>
			<p>The entire Gentoo Linux installation process is documented 
			in the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>. </p>
			
			<p>Each architecture offers three LiveCDs. The first one being a universal
			bootable LiveCD which can be used to install with or without an Internet connection.
			The second LiveCD is a non-bootable subarch-optimized Gentoo Reference Platform (GRP)
			LiveCD which contains precompiled binaries of popular
			programs such as X.org-x11, KDE, and GNOME. The third LiveCD is a bootable minimal LiveCD
			that is smaller in size and includes only the basics needed to simply boot a machine.</p>
			
			<p>At minimum, the universal or minimal LiveCD is required to boot the machine and install Gentoo.
			The universal LiveCD requires an Internet connection to install from a stage1
			installation tarball, but does not require an Internet connection to install
			from a stage3 installation tarball. The minimal LiveCD requires an Internet connection
			to install Gentoo Linux.</p>

			<p>There is one kernel available on both bootable cds. It will run on both, uniprocessor and smp systems.
			The kernel is based on linux-2.6.9 (gentoo-dev-sources-2.6.9-r1). The alternative kernel, <c>gentoo-nofb</c>, 
			boots without console framebuffer support. Press "F1" at the boot prompt to choose which kernel to boot into.</p>

			<p>The LiveCDs are located on the mirrors as follows: </p>
			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>LiveCD Description</th>
					<th>Location on Mirrors</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Universal bootable LiveCD</ti>
					<ti>/releases/x86/2004.3/livecd/universal/install-x86-universal-2004.3.iso</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Minimal bootable LiveCD</ti>
					<ti>/releases/x86/2004.3/livecd/universal/install-x86-minimal-2004.3.iso</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Non-bootable GRP-/Packages CD</ti>
					<ti>/releases/x86/2004.3/livecd/$subarch/packages-x86-2004.3.iso</ti>
				</tr>
			</table>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Upgrading to Gentoo Linux 2004.3</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			If you already have a working installation of Gentoo Linux (Version
			1.4, 2004.0, 2004.1) there is no need to reinstall. You will automatically get
			Gentoo 2004.3 if you sync your Portage tree and run
			<c>emerge --update world</c>. If you still have an installation
			with a Gentoo 1.2 profile it might make sense -- in some cases -- 
			that you do a new installation.</p>
			<p>
			There is also the possibility to update your system to a 1.4 
			profile from which you -- as already stated -- can easily get to
			Gentoo 2004.3. This update includes recompiling of glibc and some
			essential system packages; it will take a very long time (possibly
			longer as a complete re-installation) and it might also fail. So if
			you still have an installation with a Gentoo 1.2 profile, it's
			your decision whether you update or reinstall.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
