<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gentoo-alt/contribute/arch-testers-alt.xml,v 1.4 2006/05/02 06:33:54 flameeyes Exp $ -->

<!--  The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!--  See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<sections>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2005-10-22</date>

<section>
<title>Gentoo/Alt Arch Testers Information</title>

<body>
<p>
Gentoo/Alt will maintain a pool of "Arch Testers" henceforth referred to as
ATs.  One or more Gentoo/Alt developers will take the responsiblity of 
managing the AT group.  ATs will be included on the gentoo-alt@gentoo.org alias, so 
they can be informed of all bug activity. The current AT operational lead for Gentoo/Alt
is <mail link="citizen428@gentoo.org">Michael Kohl</mail>. Any problems/suggestions/flames 
should be directed at him.
</p>

<p>
ATs will be responsible for responding to all test requests in a timely
manner (keywording, security, marking stable, requests from devs on irc,
etc...) and ensuring that the application works, as well as check that the
ebuild doesn't contain any glaring errors. ATs must keep their system up to
date, use reasonable CFLAGS, and keep with the current profile.  To mark a bug 
as tested, ATs will use the keyword "TESTED" in bugzilla (in the "keywords" field)
</p>

<p>
Gentoo/Alt developers will be able to take ATs word at their own discretion.
Ultimatly, commiting the requested changes will be the dev's responsibility .  
Feel free to ask for more than one tester if you feel the bug warrants it.
</p>

<p>
Prospective ATs will have to pass the ebuild quiz, which can be found <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz/ebuild-quiz.txt">here.</uri>
</p>

<p>
A note about arch tester's status: Gentoo/Alt Arch Testers are not official
Gentoo developers.  They are, however, a recognized part of the Gentoo/Alt team.  
All ATs are asked to keep this in mind when selecting email signatures or
other forms of communication.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<th>Current Gentoo/Alt Arch Testers</th>
<th>Nickname</th>
<th>GPG key</th>
<th>Status</th>
<th>e-mail</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>Michael Kohl</ti>
<ti>citizen428</ti>
<ti>90CA09E3</ti>
<ti>Gentoo/Alt AT operational lead</ti>
<ti>citizen428@gentoo.org</ti>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</sections>
