<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gentoo-alt/contribute/overlay.xml,v 1.3 2006/05/02 06:33:54 flameeyes Exp $ -->

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<sections>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2005-12-15</date>

<section> <!-- The overlay -->
<title>The Overlay</title>

<subsection> <!-- Reasoning -->
<title>Reasoning behind</title>
<body>

<impo>
This guide is still a <e>draft</e>. It does not contain true policies about the
use of the overlay as they are not being delineated yet, 
</impo>

<p>
Gentoo/Alt projects often need to change current ebuilds to let them know about
their userland, libc or what else. These changes can be non-trivial, and should
usually be hold until the maintainer of the ebuild can take a look to the
patches and make sure that they works as intended.
</p>

<p>
The drawback is that then Gentoo/Alt users can't make use of the ebuilds on the
fly, and developers might try to do the same thing more than one time as they
might not know what the other developers worked on.
</p>

<p>
The overlay idea is took from Gentoo/FreeBSD, that used the overlay to apply
patches that involved, for example, malloc patches, userland checks and other
things that should have been reviewed before going into main tree.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection> <!-- In and Out -->
<title>In and Out</title>
<body>

<p>
The overlay is intended to work as a cache of ebuilds while they are being
tested (for totally new packages) or while the patches are being reviewed by
ebuild maintainers.
</p>

<p>
In the case of packags that goes on the overlay just to wait for review
by ebuilds maintainers, their addition should be direct, with obviously the
same name of the original package. It's usually better, if the patch is
trivial, to open a bug and note that in the ChangeLog for the overlaid package
just before adding the package to the overlay itself, unless the patches needs
to be tested for a while before submitting them to the ebuild maintainer.
</p>

<p>
As soon as a patch is merged in main tree, the ebuilds in the overlay needs to
go, to avoid having unneeded ebuilds there. It's also important to have the
ebuilds be in sync with the main tree in case of revision bumps.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection> <!-- Where -->
<title>Where</title>

<body>

<p>
For developers, the overlay is available on Gentoo's Subversion repositories in
<path>svn+ssh://username@svn.gentoo.org/var/svnroot/gentoo-alt/trunk/overlay</path>.
It's not restricted, so please don't
go over other's changes without notifying before, unless they causes problem on
all the systems. Always try to get a solution that does work for every project
while changes the minimum quantity of code.
</p>

<p>
As the overlay is intended to be used by users, too, daily snapshots can be
found on mirrors as
<path>/experimental/snapshots/portage-alt-overlay-latest.tar.bz2</path>. The
daily snapshot can be fetched and used as portage overlay, and should be safe
to be used in both Gentoo/Alt and Gentoo/Linux systems, also if might happen
that the overlay interfere with Gentoo/Linux. In case that happens, remember
to contact Gentoo/Alt developers so that the issues can be checked and resolved.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

</section>

<section> <!-- Development -->
<title>Development</title>

<subsection> <!-- Committing -->
<title>Committing</title>

<body>

<p>
One of the reasons why Subversion was chosen instead of CVS is that it supports
atomic commits, does not expand keywords (like <c>&#36;Header: &#36;</c>) and
so we can use it without using a two-step commit for manifests.
</p>

<p>
For this reason, the third line of ebuilds is safe to remain
<c>&#36;Header: &#36;</c> so that it will be safe when it's being moved to
main portage.
</p>

<p>
When committing, it's important to use <c>echangelog</c>, also if it's an
overlay to state the reasons why the ebuild is being changed. It's simple to
write a bash function to get the commit done at one time:
</p>

<pre caption="Bash function to commit to Subversion">
svncommit() {
  [[ -n $(echo *.ebuild) ]] &amp;&amp; { echangelog "$@" }
  ebuild $(ls *.ebuild | head -n 1) manifest || return 1
  svn ci -m "$@" || return 1
}
</pre>

<p>
Repoman still has a couple of issues when used in overlays, especially with
Subversion, and with extra categories, as it's being done on Gentoo/Alt, but
these things can be easily fixed in the future, and are just side problems.
</p>

<p>
<c>echangelog</c> still does not support Subversion-reposited ebuilds, so
until it supports them fully, its output will be a bit limited, not telling
when files are added and when are removed. It also returns a failure error
to the caller, so it can't be checked against for failures.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection> <!-- Distfiles -->
<title>Distfiles</title>

<body>

<p>
Because ebuilds in the overlay are public to the users, their distfiles should
be present in the mirrors. As the overlay ebuilds are not parsed by mirroring
scripts, the distfiles loaded directly into the local
<path>dev.gentoo.org</path> distfiles directory will be removed when "dead"
distfiles are removed.
</p>

<p>
To avoid having the distfiles removed, especially for tarballs that was created
ad-hoc, it's important to whitelist the extra files. To do so, log into
<path>dev.gentoo.org</path> and open the
<path>/space/distfiles-whitelist/current</path> file. There, place one by line
all the files you put or are going to put in the mirrors that should not be
removed. The whitelist lasts for six months.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

</section>

</sections>

<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; -->
