<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
  <name>Common Lisp</name>
  <longname>The Gentoo Common Lisp Project</longname>
  <date>2006-10-08</date>
  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="mkennedy@gentoo.org">Matthew Kennedy</mail>
  </author>
  <description>The Gentoo Common Lisp Project handles all Gentoo related Common Lisp implementations, applications and libraries in Portage.  The project will also handle maintenance of non-Common Lisp ebuilds assigned to the Common Lisp Herd.</description>
  <longdescription>
  </longdescription>
  <dev role="lead" description="General maintainer">mkennedy</dev>
  <herd name="common-lisp"/>
  <plannedproject name="Gentoo Common Lisp Overview">An overview of supported Common Lisp implementations and libraries in Portage.
  </plannedproject>
  <plannedproject name="User Guide">Documentation on how to use the Common Lisp packages with ASDF and the Common Lisp Controller.</plannedproject>
  <plannedproject name="Developer Guide">Documentation on the internals of the Gentoo Common Lisp supported implementations and libraries.</plannedproject>
  <plannedproject name="FAQ">Answers to miscellaneous questions not covered in the Overview or User Guide.
  </plannedproject>
  <resource link="http://common-lisp.net/cgi-bin/darcsweb/darcsweb.cgi?r=portage-overlay-portage-overlay;a=summary">Portage Overlay</resource>
  <resource link="http://common-lisp.net/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/portage-overlay-devel">Portage Overlay Mailing List</resource>
  <resource link="http://www.cl-user.net/asp/root-dir">The Common Lisp Directory</resource>
  <resource link="http://www.cliki.net/index">The Common Lisp Wiki</resource>
  <extrachapter>
    <title>Contributing</title>
    <section>
      <title>Portage Overlay</title>
      <body>
        <p>Common Lisp development in Gentoo takes place in the <uri link="http://common-lisp.net/cgi-bin/darcsweb/darcsweb.cgi?r=portage-overlay-portage-overlay;a=summary">Portage Overlay</uri>.</p>
        <p>We recognize not everyone wants to endure the Gentoo New Developer Process in order to contribute to the project.  Therefore we intend to move the Common Lisp related ebuilds in CVS to the Darcs-managed, Portage Overlay Hosted at <uri link="http://common-lisp.net/">http://common-lisp.net/</uri>.  This will allow users to track changes and submit improvements far more easily than through the official Gentoo Bugzilla system.</p>
      <p>Users and Gentoo developers will be able to work together by pushing and pulling patch sets from their individual Darcs repositories. Periodically, Gentoo developers may update the official Portage CVS tree with ebuilds from the Darcs overlay.</p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Portage Overlay Mailing List</title>
      <body>
        <p>The <uri link="http://common-lisp.net/cgi-bin/mailman/listinfo/portage-overlay-devel">Portage Overlay Mailing List</uri> is for discussing the development and general usage of the Common Lisp related ports in Gentoo.</p>
      </body>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>IRC Channel</title>
      <body>
        <p>Join the <uri link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-lisp">irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-lisp</uri> IRC channel to discuss Common Lisp development and usage in Gentoo.</p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>
</project>

<!-- Local Variables: -->
<!-- mode: nxml -->
<!-- indent-tabs-mode: nil -->
<!-- fill-column: 80 -->
<!-- End: -->
