<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/infrastructure/ldap.xml,v 1.14 2006/08/11 21:33:41 curtis119 Exp $ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/infrastructure/ldap.xml">
<title>Gentoo Infrastructure LDAP guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="lcars@gentoo.org">Andrea Barisani</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="lmedinas@gmail.com">Luis Medinas</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="curtis119@gentoo.org">Curtis Napier</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Guide to using the Gentoo Infrastructure LDAP system for developers, recruiters
and administrators.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.4</version>
<date>2006-07-02</date>

<chapter>
<title>Key Concepts</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
LDAP stands for Lightweight Directory Access Protocol, a lightweight client-server
protocol for accessing directory services. LDAP directory service is based on a
client-server model. One or more servers contain the data making up the LDAP
directory tree. An LDAP client connects to an LDAP server and requests information.
The server responds with the data or points the client to another source.
(typically another LDAP server).
</p>

<p>
Just like a database, an entry in LDAP consists of fields of data or 'Attributes'.
This collection of attributes is called a 'Schema'. This guide will explain
which attributes are available, who can change them and give role based examples
for modifying the Gentoo LDAP Schema.
</p>

<p>
When a developer accesses a resource, like toucan (aka dev.gentoo.org), the
resource acts as an LDAP client and queries the LDAP server (ldap1 or ldap2) to
see if that user is in the database and authorized for access.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Organizational Units</title>
<body>

<p>
LDAP is used by Gentoo to secure the infrastructure. Gentoo resources are spread
across the globe and LDAP gives us a central location to manage them. There are
four levels of access or OU (organizational unit): anonymous, user, recruiters
and infra, that are used to connect or <e>bind</e> to the LDAP database.
</p>

<p>
The <e>anonymous</e> OU is used for simple <e>read only</e> informational queries.
All developers and staff can bind to LDAP as anonymous. If you don't specify an
OU when you bind anonymous is assumed.
</p>

<p>
The <e>user</e> OU is used to add or change information in your own LDAP
record. Things like your latitude and longitude, ssh public key and so on.
All developers and staff are members of the user OU.
</p>

<p>
<e>recruiters</e> is a special OU used by recruiters to create new LDAP entries
or to alter existing ones for any user including their own. If you are a
Recruiter you <e>must</e> bind to LDAP as 'recruiter' for any operation including
another users record or your own.
</p>

<p>
The <e>infra</e> OU is also a special OU that is used by members of the Infrastructure
Project to manage the various resources within Gentoo. Although this is used
mainly for managing machine accounts, the infra OU can also alter any other users
record.
</p>

<note>
All write operations performed by recruiters or infra must be performed on
ldap1.gentoo.org (roadrunner.gentoo.org).
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo LDAP Implementation</title>
<section>
<title>LDAP Servers</title>
<body>

<p>
Currently we have two LDAP servers available. The <e>master</e> server and a
<e>slave</e> server. The <e>master</e> LDAP server is reachable at
<e>ldap1.gentoo.org</e>. The <e>slave</e> server is <e>ldap2.gentoo.org</e> and
it connects every 60 seconds to the <e>master</e> looking up changes and
resyncing the database if necessary.
</p>

<p>
Every update operation must be done on <e>ldap1.gentoo.org</e>, if an update
(which means writing some entry) is performed on the <e>slave</e> a referral to
the <e>master</e> is issued. This is transparently handled and all attempts to
update against the slave will be redirected to the <e>master</e>. Connections
are validated via TLS + password. The password is your toucan one and it's going
to be the same for all LDAP_aware boxes in the future.
</p>

<p>
We use a custom script, <c>perl_ldap</c> that uses <e>Net::LDAP</e>, for accessing
and modifying the database, it allows only a predefined set of actions but it
should cover 90% of the cases. In the following chapters we explain how to use it.
</p>

<note>
<e>dev.gentoo.org</e> is currently using <e>ldap2.gentoo.org</e> as its first
server so any update you do could take up to 60 seconds for being seen on
<e>dev.gentoo.org</e>.  We use <c>nscd</c> (Name Service Caching Daemon) to cache
negative and positive lookups. This means that your changes may not become active
for some time. If you need to force the change we can restart nscd for you. Ask
in #gentoo-infra for help with this.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Available Attributes</title>
<body>

<p>
The following attributes are included in the Gentoo Schema. Note the 'Access
Level' needed for each attribute.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Attribute Name</th>
    <th>Access Level</th>
    <th>Description</th>
    <th>Type</th>
    <th>Format</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooLocation</ti>
    <ti>infra, recruiters</ti>
    <ti>developer location</ti>
    <ti>single, required</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooLatitude, lat</ti>
    <ti>user</ti>
    <ti>latitude coordinate</ti>
    <ti>single, optional</ti>
    <ti>numeric string</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooLongitude, lon</ti>
    <ti>user</ti>
    <ti>longitude coordinate</ti>
    <ti>single, optional</ti>
    <ti>numeric string</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooJoin</ti>
    <ti>infra, recruiters</ti>
    <ti>developer join date</ti>
    <ti>single, optional</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooAccess</ti>
    <ti>infra, recruiters</ti>
    <ti>developer access level</ti>
    <ti>multiple, required</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooStatus</ti>
    <ti>infra, recruiters</ti>
    <ti>developer status</ti>
    <ti>single, required</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooGPGkey, gpgkey</ti>
    <ti>user</ti>
    <ti>gpg key uid</ti>
    <ti>single, optional</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooGPGFingerprint, gpgfingerprint</ti>
    <ti>user</ti>
    <ti>gpg key fingerprint</ti>
    <ti>single, optional</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooRoles</ti>
    <ti>infra,recruiters</ti>
    <ti>developer projects</ti>
    <ti>single, optional</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gentooHerd, herd</ti>
    <ti>infra,recruiters</ti>
    <ti>developer herd</ti>
    <ti>single, optional</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>sshPublicKey</ti>
    <ti>user</ti>
    <ti>OpenSSH public key</ti>
    <ti>multiple, optional</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>birthday</ti>
    <ti>user</ti>
    <ti>developer birthday</ti>
    <ti>single, optional</ti>
    <ti>UTF-8</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>LDAP aware servers</title>
<body>

<p>
The following servers have been migrated to LDAP. All gentoo servers will eventually
be migrated and this guide will be updated as the migration is completed.
</p>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Server Name</th>
    <th>Alias</th>
    <th>Status</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>roadrunner.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>ldap1.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>LDAP Master Server, LDAP client: accounts, sudo, ssh</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>duck.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>ldap2.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>LDAP Slave Server</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>toucan.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>dev.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>LDAP client: accounts, sudo, ssh</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>robin.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>lists.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>LDAP client: accounts, sudo, ssh</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>lark.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>cvs.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>LDAP client: accounts, sudo</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>sparrow.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>torrents.gentoo.org</ti>
    <ti>LDAP client: accounts, sudo, ssh</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>LDAP management with perl_ldap</title>
<body>

<p>
These are the main concepts of the perl_ldap script used for user
administration. Invoking <e>perl_ldap</e> without arguments shows a nice help.
Your own dev.gentoo.org password is asked when binding.
</p>

<p>
The script is the infra supported method for managing entries, nothing prevents
you from using any LDAP browser you like for modifying your attributes. If you
like to use something else, ask infra for connection details but keep in mind
that we won't support and/or troubleshoot other browsers issues.
</p>

<p>
The following are the most common options.
</p>

<ul>
  <li><c>-b OU</c> used to bind to the LDAP server. If you don't specify <e>user</e>,
  the script will default to <e>anonymous</e> and be <e>read only</e></li>
  <li><c>-s UID</c> shows the entire LDAP record for the user $UID (user name
  NOT numerical UID)</li>
  <li><c>-S ATTRIBUTE</c> searches for a specific attribute across all users</li>
  <li><c>-M ATTRIBUTE NEWVALUE UID</c> overwrites the value of an attribute for the
  specified user</li>
  <li><c>-C ATTRIBUTE NEWVALUE UID</c> creates a new attribute for the
  specified user</li>
  <li><c>-E ATTRIBUTE</c> erases an attribute</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Examples</title>
<section>
<title>Users</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo Developers and Staff members (recruiters and infra please refer to the
following sections) can update their LDAP record directly. Here are examples
of the most commonly changed attributes.
</p>

<pre caption="Show attributes for a user entry">
<comment>(Substitute an actual user name for UID and not a numerical ID)</comment>
# <i>perl_ldap -s UID</i>

<comment>(binding as user will show additional information)</comment>
# <i>perl_ldap -b user -s UID</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Change your GPG key">
# <i>perl_ldap -b user -M gentooGPGkey "1AF343E" UID</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Change your public SSH key">
<comment>(substitute 'pubkey' with the path to your public SSH key. ex: "~/.ssh/id_dsa.pub")</comment>
# <i>perl_ldap -b user -M sshPublicKey "$(cat pubkey)" UID</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Recruiters</title>
<body>

<p>
Recruiters can change their own attributes or those of another user. You <b>must</b>
bind as <e>recruiters</e> to change any attributes including your own. The
following examples show how to change attributes for other users. To change
your own attributes use the examples from the "users" section above but bind as
a recruiter.
</p>

<p>
When dealing with users that belong to a sub-OU the <c>-o OU | -b OU</c> option
must be used, this will be clarified in the examples. The command <c>-b OU</c>
must be used if the <e>binding user</e> belongs to a sub-OU, the command
<c>-o OU</c> must be used if <e>the target user</e> belongs to a sub-OU.
</p>

<p>
The following examples will show you how to change attributes for users, recruiters
and infra. All write operations performed by one user against another user
must be performed on ldap1.gentoo.org (roadrunner.gentoo.org).
</p>

<p>
Some attributes, like gentooRoles and sshPublickey, allow multi_values. To append an
additional value to the exiting ones use <c>-C</c>. To overwrite the existing values
use <c>-M</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Modify (overwrite) an existing attribute for a user">
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -M gentooGPGkey "1AF343E" UID</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Modify (overwrite) an existing attribute if the target user is recruiters or infra">
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -o recruiters -M gentooGPGkey "1AF343E" UID</i>
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -o infra -M gentooGPGkey "1AF343E" UID</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Delete an attribute for a user">
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -E gentooRoles UID</i>

<comment>(If value is specified then only the matching attribute is removed, this is useful for multi_valued attributes.)</comment>
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -E gentooRoles "forums" UID</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Add a new user">
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -A UID</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Delete a user">
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -D UID</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="Create or modify multi_value attributes">
<comment>(Create a new attribute while preserving the existing ones. Use the command multiple times to add addtional attributes)</comment>
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -C gentooRoles "forums" UID</i>
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -C gentooRoles "devrel" UID</i>

<comment>(overwrite the existing values with a new one)</comment>
# <i>perl_ldap -b recruiters -M gentooRoles "forums" UID</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Infra</title>
<body>

<p>
Infra can change their own attributes or those of another user. You <b>must</b>
bind as <e>infra</e> to change any attributes, including your own. To change
your own attributes use the examples from the "users" section above. To change
another users record use the examples from the "recruiters" section.
</p>

<p>
The attribute <c>gentooAccess</c> controls which boxes a user can login to. Only
infra and a few selected recruiters are allowed to create and modify this
multi_value attribute. The FQDN must be used (ex. roadrunner.gentoo.org).
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>Master LDAP Server - ldap1.gentoo.org</li>
  <li>Slave LDAP Server - ldap2.gentoo.org</li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/html_single/LDAP-HOWTO">LDAP HOWTO</uri></li>
</ul>

<p>
If you have issues, questions or encounter errors please contact the <mail
link="gentoo-infrastructure@gentoo.org">Gentoo Infrastructure Team</mail>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
