<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/hardened/index.xml">
<title>Gentoo Infrastructure -- Setting up new Project Pages</title>
<subtitle>Main Page</subtitle>
<author title="Author">
   <mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
This page explains how to set up new pages for top level projects within the Gentoo Linux project.
</abstract>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>30 June 2003</date>
<chapter>
<title>Project Pages for the Gentoo Linux Project</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
This document describes how to set up new project pages for the Gentoo Linux project.  It is geared towards top-level projects, but may be applicable to other projects as well.  This document presupposes the following conditions:
</p>
<ul>
	<li>The user has set up a local copy of the gentoo repository.</li>
	<li>The user is familiar with cvs in general and how Gentoo Linux uses cvs, specifically.</li>
	<li>The user is familiar with basic XML and/or HTML syntax.</li>
	<li>The user has emerged libxslt on their computer</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>First Steps</title>
<section>
<title>Background information</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo Linux uses guide-xml for its documentation format.  Users will need to familiarize themselves with guide-xml syntax.  Users should start with the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">Gentoo Linux XML Guide</uri> to learn basic syntax.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Create the new CVS directory and the default index page</title>
<body>
<p>
Decide what your new project will be called and create the directory within your local CVS repository.
</p>
<pre caption="creating the initial directory">
# cd /home/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/
<comment>replace /home/cvsroot with your local CVS root path</comment>
# mkdir &lt;name of your directory&gt;
# cvs add &lt;name of your directory&gt;
# cd &lt;name of your directory&gt;
# vim index.xml
<comment>create your document using guide-xml syntax and save it</comment>
</pre>
<impo>
It is <b>critical</b> that you always run your documents through xmllint before committing to cvs.
</impo>
<pre caption="Using xmllint to validate your document">
# xmllint index.xml
<comment>fix any syntactical errors that xmllint identifies</comment>
</pre>
<p>
Next, we commit the document to CVS.
</p>
<pre caption="commit the document">
# cvs add index.xml
# cvs commit -m "your commit message here" index.xml
</pre>
<p>
At this point, your document has been committed to CVS.  It will show up on the web site at :20 past the hour during the scheduled update.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
