<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE mainpage SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<mainpage id="docs">
	<title>Gentoo Foundation Web Redesign Contest</title>
	<author title="Editor">Kurt Lieber</author>
<version>1.0</version>
<date>June 23rd, 2004</date>
	<chapter>
    	<title>Contest Rules</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Entrants should submit two images in PNG format.  The first image should show
a full mockup of the front page of www.gentoo.org.  The second image should
show a full mockup of the first page of the Gentoo Handbook.
</p>
<p>
All designs should take into consideration the existing content available on
www.gentoo.org and must allocate space for advertisements as well.
</p>
<p>
The final 5 candidates will be chosen based on a number of criteria including:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Overall design -- does it look ugly.</li>
<li>Navigation -- can people find their way around easily.</li>
<li>Integration of Advertisements -- Are the advertisements placed prominently, without taking over the entire design of the page.</li>
<li>Flexibility/scalability of design -- can we add new pages and sections easily to allow for future growth.</li>
<li>Cool factor -- totally subjective interpretation of the submission.  Does it "wow" us.</li>
</ul>
<p>
Designs relying on flash animation or other proprietary formats will be
penalized heavily.  Your best bet is to stick with open formats.
</p>
<p>
By submitting your design, you are also indicating that you are willing to
design and create the necessary graphics for our web sites (including <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org">forums.gentoo.org</uri>, <uri
link="http://packages.gentoo.org">packages.gentoo.org</uri> and all other
public web sites.)  This is a non-trivial task and will require a great deal of
time and effort, so please consider this carefully before submitting your entry.
</p>
<p>
The submitter of the winning design will have the opportunity to place a link
at the bottom of every page that says "Design provided by &lt;your name&gt;" and
links to a web page of your choosing.  (We reserve the right to change or
remove the link if it points to objectionable content, such as a porn site).
The right to display this link is contingent on the submitter actually
completing the design as described above.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Submissions</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Submissions should be sent to <uri link="mailto:www-redesign@gentoo.org">www-redesign@gentoo.org</uri>.  
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Copyrights</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
The submitter will retain all copyrights on any images they submit.  However,
in order to be selected as one of the final 5 candidates, you must be willing
to assign your copyright of that particular design to the Gentoo Foundation,
which is a non-profit group charged with caring for Gentoo Linux.  If your
design is one of the final 5, but not selected as the winner, then you may
regain copyright of your design.  (Please remember that the Gentoo logo and
stylized "G" belong to the Gentoo Foundation and may not be used without our
written consent.)
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<section>
<title>Q: Can I submit multiple designs?</title>
<body>
<p>
Yes, but only if they are each unique.  Please <b>do not</b> submit multiple
variations of a single design, such as different colors.  In that case, pick
the one you like best and submit it.  People who submit multiple variants of
the same design will be penalized during the judging.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What do you consider "ugly"?  Isn't that very subjective?</title> 
<body>
<p>
We are seeking a design that is professional, clean and is appealing to a
large group of people.  We are not seeking "fringe" designs that may be
considered beautiful by a small subset of people, but are unlikely to be
appreciated by the bulk of our user base.
</p>
<note>Look around at large corporate sites.  Those have all been done by professional graphic designers.</note> 
<note>Avoid black-on-black, lots of chrome and 8 point fonts.  You may think it's cool.  We don't.</note>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What do you mean by "Cool factor"?  Isn't that very subjective?</title> 
<body>
<p>
The "Cool factor" is something that is impossible to describe.  It simply
means that, when we look at a submission and say "wow, that's cool", then
you've achieved it.  It may be a unique feature of the site or a different way
of designing things.  It can be anything that you think will cause us to go
"wow, that's cool".  And yes, it's 100% subjective.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Why not let the community pick from all available entries instead of just 5 that are selected by a group of developers?</title> 
<body>
<p>
We expect the community to pick a site largely based on its look.  We also
need to consider other factors, such as navigation, integration of ads, etc,
so we will select the best 5 candidates that meet all of the criteria listed
above before presenting it to the community.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Who owns the copyright to these submissions?</title> 
<body>
<p>
Please see the copyright section.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Why must I give up my copyright?</title> 
<body>
<p>
If we do not own the copyright to the design, then we cannot legally prevent
other people from using it.  We want the design of our web site to be unique
to Gentoo Linux.  We have no plans to sell or sub-license the design and even
if we did, the copyright belongs to the Gentoo Foundation, so any monies
collected would go directly to the development efforts of Gentoo Linux.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Can we see the designs that were rejected after the contest?</title> 
<body>
<p>
We will not own the copyright to any of the rejected designs and thus may not legally display them.  If individual submitters wish to show their own designs on their own sites, they may do so at their own discretion.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</mainpage>

