<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/pr/releases/20140826/faq.xml,v 1.1 2014/09/04 21:20:30 robbat2 Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo 20140826 LiveDVD Frequently Asked Questions</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dabbott"/>
</author>
<author title="Reviewer">
  <mail link="email@missionaccomplish.com">Fernando Reyes</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This FAQ is a collection of questions and answers collected from the mail list
and from IRC.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>9</version>
<date>2014-08-26</date>

<faqindex>
<title>FAQ</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Linux Hybrid ISO is made by the community for the community. It was
created with the help of Gentoo developers from around the world and users
alike. Thank you all for your contributions and suggestions!
</p>

<p>
<uri link="CREDITS.txt">Your Gentoo LiveDVD Team</uri>
</p>

<p>
  Please note that this is simply a list of common questions. Please read the 
  <uri link="/doc/en/handbook">handbook</uri> and man pages to gain a greater 
  understanding of how Gentoo works. For answers to questions which may not 
  be answered here, please visit the forums, bugzilla or <uri
    link="irc://irc.gentoo.org/gentoo-ten">#gentoo-ten</uri> on <uri
    link="http://www.freenode.net/">freenode</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</faqindex>

<chapter>
<title>Getting Started</title>
<section id="arch">
<title>Download the correct ISO for your hardware</title>
<body>

<p>
The livedvd-x86-amd64-32ul ISO will work on 32-bit x86 or 64-bit
x86_64. If your architecture is x86, boot with the default. If your arch is
amd64, boot with <c>gentoo64</c>.
</p>

<p>
The livedvd-amd64-multilib ISO is only for x86_64. Boot with the default. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="default">
<title>Root privilages</title>
<body>

<pre caption="How do I become root?">
$ <i>sudo su -</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can use <c>passwd</c> to change the password for the user you are logged 
into. As root, you can change any user password by issuing the command
<c>passwd username</c> For extra options and setting, please <c>man passwd</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="usb">
<title>Can I copy the image to a usb stick?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes. To determine your device before you plug it in, open a terminal and read
<path>/var/log/messages</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Determine Device">
# <i>tail -f /var/log/messages</i>
</pre>

<note>
You will need at least a 4GB device! Keep in mind that all data on usb stick will
be lost when ISO is dd to it.
</note>

<pre caption="Copy the image">
# <i>dd if=image.iso of=/dev/sdb bs=8192k</i>
</pre>

<impo>
Do not point to a partition number!
</impo>

<warn>
Not all BIOS support booting from USB devices. Consult your motherboard
documentation first!
</warn>

</body>
</section>
<section id="autologin">
<title>Can I resume the autologin?</title>
<body>

<p>
To resume the KDM autologin, you need to press the ESC key and wait for the
timeout to pass or just hit the enter key to login.  
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Tips &amp; Tricks</title>
<section id="wireless">
<title>Can I install firmware for my wireless card?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes. You just need to copy the firmware to <path>/lib/firmware</path> and reload
your wireless card's kernel modules. The example below installs the firmware for
a Ralink RT2501USB wireless LAN chipset. It requires non-free firmware, which
cannot be included on the Live DVD because of license issues. The firmware is
copied from a 2GB usb stick.
</p>

<pre caption="Install the firmware">
<comment>(First mount the USB stick)</comment>
# <i>mkdir /mnt/pin</i>
# <i>mount /dev/sdb1 /mnt/pin</i>
<comment>(Copy the firmware)</comment>
# <i>cp /mnt/pin/firmware/rt73.bin /lib/firmware</i>
<comment>(Reload modules so that the firmware is included)</comment>
# <i>modprobe -r rt73usb  rt2x00usb  rt2x00lib</i>
<comment>(Time to insert modules amd load firmware)</comment>
# <i>modprobe rt73usb</i>
<comment>(Restart Network Manager to pickup the interface)</comment>
# <i>rc-service NetworkManager restart</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="persistence">
<title>How can I set up and enable persistence?</title>
<body>

<p>
For USB Linux users, a persistent Linux install is one that allows it's user to
save data changes back to the USB storage device instead of leaving the
information in system RAM. This data can then be recovered and used again on
subsequent boots, even when booting from different machines.
</p>

<p>
Booting with the 'aufs=&lt;DEVICE&gt;' boot option will allow you to retain your /
changes on a separate removable device or if you have space left on the usb
that the image is booting from, you can then create a partition on there then:
</p>

<note>In my testing I ran out of space on a 4GB stick. I ended up using two 4GB
  sticks, one for the image and one for persistence. I booted with the option
  "aufs=/dev/sdb4", and all was well.</note> 

<ul>
  <li>Create an extra partition on the usb stick you dd. i.e /dev/sdb4</li>
  <li>Create an EXTFS on this partition</li>
  <li>Boot with 'aufs=&lt;DEVICE&gt;' in kernel line</li>
  <li>Repeat step 3 on every reboot to persistent changes</li>
</ul>

<p>
This partition will be used to create a loopback image that will allow
persistent data on reboots.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="packages">
<title>Is there a list of packages on the DVD?</title>
<body>

<p>
  <b>Yes:</b>
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="x86-amd64-pkg.lst">x86-amd64 package list</uri>
  </li>
  <li><uri link="amd64.pkg.lst">amd64 package list</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>More Information</title>
<section id="more-info">
<title>What if my question has not been answered?</title>
<body>
  
<p>
Come join us on our IRC channel, #gentoo-ten. You can also help us fix some
bugs!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
