<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/doc/en/arch-testers-amd64.xml">
<title>AMD64 Arch Testers Information</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="gerrynjr@gentoo.org">Gerald J. Normandin Jr.</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="kingtaco@gentoo.org">KingTaco</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
This doc provides information regarding amd64 arch testing.
</abstract>
<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>17 Jan 05</date>

<chapter>
<title>Arch Testers.</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo/AMD64 will maintain a pool of "Arch Testers" hence forth referred to
AT's.  One or more amd64 Developers will take the responsiblity of managing
he AT group.  AT's will be included on the amd64@gentoo.org alias, so they
can be informed of all bug activity. The current AT head is kingtaco. Any
problems/suggestions/flames should be directed at him.
</p>

<p>
AT's will be responsible for responding to all test requests in a timely
manner(keywording, security, marking stable, requests from devs on irc,
etc...) and ensuring that the application works, as well as check that the
ebuild doesn't contain any glaring errors. AT's must keep their system up to
date, use reasonable CFLAGS, and keep with the current profile.  When marking
a bug as tested all AT's will use the keyword "TESTED" in bugzilla (in the
"keywords" field)
</p>

<p>
Gentoo/AMD64 developers will be able to take AT's word at their own discression.
Ultimatly, it's the commiting dev that is responsible.  Feel free to ask for
more than one tester if you feel the bug warrents it.
</p>

<p>
Prospective AT's will have to pass the ebuild quiz, currently <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz/ebuild-quiz.txt">here.</uri>

Additionally, All quizes should be submitted to kingtaco@gentoo.org
</p>

<p>
A note about arch testers "status": Gentoo/AMD64 Arch Testers are not official
Gentoo developers.  They are, however, a recognized part of the Gentoo/AMD64 arch
team.  I ask that all AT's keep this in mind when selecting email signatures or
other forms of communication.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<th>Current AMD64 Arch Testers</th>
<th>Nickname</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>
Andreas Pokorny   
</ti>
<ti>
DieMummie
</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>
James Stockton    
</ti>
<ti>
piolyte
</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>
Homer Parker
</ti>
<ti>
hparker
</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
