<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/dotnet/howtohelp.xml,v 1.2 2012/10/28 15:21:03 swift Exp $ -->

<guide lang="en">
<title>Mono FAQ</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="latexer@gentoo.org">Latexer</mail>
</author>
<author title="GuideXML Translation">
  <mail link="chriswhite@gentoo.org">Chris White</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This page is intended to contain the latest things people can help out with as users/devs to continue making the use Mono on Gentoo a pleasure. This page may end up becoming stale, so before trying anything, we suggest you visit the bugs involved on our bugzilla, or contact me (latexer) on IRC or via email to confirm what still needs doing.
</abstract>


<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2005-5-31</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Mono How To Help</title>
	<section>
		<title>1) Getting mono-1.1.x out of package.mask</title>
		<body>
		<p>
Not much here. The two major things are getting mono-1.0.x stable (which it now is on x86, and soon on ppc) and getting a version of monodevelop into portage which actually works with mono-1.1.x. Piece one is done, piece two is waiting on MD-0.6 to be official. Those wishing to help can mainly help stress testing any mono consuming applications/libraries using the currently package.masked mono-1.1.4 (amd64 users too!)
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>2) Getting other mono using apps into portage</title>
		<body>
		<p>
If you're not a dev, there's not much you can do besides submitting bugs with ebuilds to bugzilla, or writing ebuilds for package request bugs on bugzilla. Devs, please feel free to work on this, but I'd ask that you please confer with me if you intend to add packages with bugs assigned to the dotnet herd before commiting them.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
</guide> 
