<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/hardened/index.xml">
<title>Hardened Gentoo</title>
<subtitle>Main Page</subtitle>
<author title="Author">
   <mail link="method@gentoo.org">Joshua Brindle</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
   <mail link="pebenito@gentoo.org">Chris PeBenito</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
  Hardened Gentoo is a official project with the goal of bringing advanced security measures to the Gentoo linux distribution
</abstract>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>3 June 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is Hardened Gentoo</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
   Hardened Gentoo is an umbrella project which oversees the research, implementation, and maintainence of
   security oriented projects for Gentoo Linux. We are a team of very competent individuals dedicated
   to bringing advanced security to Gentoo with a number of subprojects.
</p>
<p>
   Hardened Gentoo's purpose is to make Gentoo viable for high security, high stability production server
   environments. This project is not a standalone project disjoined from Gentoo proper; it is intended
   to be a team of Gentoo developers which are focused on delivering solutions to Gentoo that provide
   strong security and stability. These solutions will be available in Gentoo once they've been
   tested for security and stability by the hardened team.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardened Gentoo Subprojects</title>

<section>
<title>Active Subprojects</title>
<body>
<p>
   The current active subprojects in Hardened Gentoo are:
<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>Description:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>SELinux integration</ti>
		<ti>Adding SELinux support to Gentoo and Portage, this includes providing kernels with SELinux support, 
		    providing patches to userland utilities, writing good Gentoo specific default profiles, 
		    and deploying policies via Portage. For access to the SELinux demo machine see <uri link="http://selinux.dev.gentoo.org">selinux.dev.gentoo.org</uri></ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Propolice</ti>
		<ti>Propolice is GCC stack smashing protection written by IBM. <uri link="propolice.xml">More details here</uri>.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Systrace</ti>
		<ti>Systrace is a lightweight ACL system with an easy to use policy editor and a gui for on-the-fly policy management. Additionally this allows applications which require root capabilities to run without setuid and setgid flags.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Hardened-Sources</ti>
		<ti>A kernel which provides patches for hardened subprojects, and stability/security oriented patches.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Grsecurity</ti>
		<ti>Grsecurity ACL policies, <uri link="/proj/en/hardened/grsecurity.xml">documentation</uri> outlining effective use of Grsecurity.</ti>
	</tr>

</table>

</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Planned Subprojects</title>
<body>
<p>
   The current planned subprojects in Hardened Gentoo are:
   <table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>Description:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>SAL</ti>
		<ti>Secure Auditing for Linux. This provides government level secure auditing which can be used to take legal action against attackers. This is a logging system that supports secure, encrypted, protected logs which cannot be modified easily.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>HIDS</ti>
		<ti>Host Intrusion Detection System. There are many possibilities, whichever we choose we'll provide good gentoo specific policies and documentation on tweaking it in your environment. There is also the possibility that portage will have an integrated HIDS at some point in the future.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Openwall</ti>
		<ti>Openwall provides patches to daemons which allow them to be chrooted and add privilege seperation.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Additional crypt algorithms</ti>
		<ti>Added algorithms to the unix crypt() function including blowfish and tcb.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Forum for security oriented products</ti>
		<ti>To provide a place for security oriented projects, like Kerberos, to be hosted, maintained and documented.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Security Documentation</ti>
		<ti>There are plans to maintain documentation about best practices, and general security measures such as process limiting, setting quotas, securing systems with kerberos, chrooting, tightening services, et al.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>CryptoAPI</ti>
		<ti>Cryptographic filesystem support, possibly using <uri link="http://www1.cs.columbia.edu/~ezk/research/">FiST</uri>.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Bastille</ti>
		<ti>Bastille is an interactive app which gives the user suggestions on securing their machine. It will be customized to make suggestions about other Hardened Gentoo subprojects.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>IPSec</ti>
		<ti>Documentation and ebuilds/patches for using FreeS/WAN with opportunistic encryption and tunneling between networks.</ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>How do I use this?</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
   Hardened Gentoo is a collection of subprojects. Each of these subprojects is optional, and
   you must explictly enable each subproject you wish to use. A list of projects available and 
   how to enable them is available below.
</p>
<p>
<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>How to Enable:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>SELinux</ti>
		<ti>The SELinux Quick Start Guide is available <uri link="selinux-quickstart.xml">here</uri>.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Propolice</ti>
		<ti>Propolice will be available in GCC by default soon, to enable it on compilations add -fstack-protector.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Systrace ACL's</ti>
		<ti>Merge sys-apps/systrace.  Merge sys-apps/gtk-systrace if you have GTK+.  Merge sys-kernel/hardened-sources for systrace support in your kernel.</ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardened Gentoo Developers</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Each developer working on Hardened Gentoo is listed here, full time indicates that their main Gentoo position is on this project, part time indicates that their main position lies in another area but they do additional work  on Hardened Gentoo.
<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Developer Name</th>
		<th>Username</th>
		<th>Full/Part Time</th>
		<th>Areas of Responsibilty</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Joshua Brindle</ti>
		<ti>Method</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Project lead</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Chris PeBenito</ti>
		<ti>pebenito</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>SELinux subproject lead</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Matthew Rickard</ti>
		<ti>frogger</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Propolice support, interim hardened-sources maintainer</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Ned Ludd</ti>
		<ti>solar</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Grsecurity, misc security</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Nate Underwood</ti>
		<ti>natey</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Systrace implementation</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Arun Thomas</ti>
		<ti>sindian</ti>
		<ti>Part</ti>
		<ti>SELinux/ARM</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Sven Vermeulen</ti>
		<ti>swift</ti>
		<ti>Part</ti>
		<ti>Documentation, Grsecurity</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Joachim Blaabjerg</ti>
		<ti>styx</ti>
		<ti>Part</ti>
		<ti>ACL's, encryption algorithms</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>John P. Davis</ti>
		<ti>zhen</ti>
		<ti>Part</ti>
		<ti></ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To participate in the Hardened Gentoo project first join the mailing list at <i>gentoo-hardened@gentoo.org</i>. Then ask if there are plans to support something that you are interested in, propose a new subproject that you are interested in or choose one of the planned subprojects to work on. You may talk to the developers and users in the IRC channel <i>#gentoo-hardened</i> on <i>irc.freenode.net</i> for more information or just to chat about the project or any subprojects. If you don't have the ability to actively help by contributing work we will always need testers to maintain the security and stability of the overall product. All development, testing, and productive comments and feedback will be greatly appreciated.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
