<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>hardened</name>
<longname>Hardened Gentoo</longname>
<description>
  Hardened Gentoo brings advanced security measures to Gentoo Linux.
</description>

<longdescription>
  Hardened Gentoo is a project which oversees the research, implementation, and
  maintainence of security oriented projects for Gentoo Linux. We are a team of
  very competent individuals dedicated to bringing advanced security to Gentoo
  with a number of subprojects.
</longdescription>

<goals>
  Hardened Gentoo&#39;s purpose is to make Gentoo viable for high security,
  high stability production server environments. This project is not a 
  standalone project disjoined from Gentoo proper; it is intended
  to be a team of Gentoo developers which are focused on delivering solutions
  to Gentoo that provide strong security and stability. These solutions will be
  available in Gentoo once they&#39;ve been tested for security and stability
  by the Hardened team.
</goals>

<dev role="lead" description="Hardened Gentoo project leader">method</dev>
<dev description="SELinux">pebenito</dev>
<dev description="Propolice">frogger</dev>
<dev description="PaX/Grsecurity, Project Co-Coordinator">solar</dev>
<dev description="Hardened GCC">pappy</dev>
<dev description="Stage Building">zhen</dev>
<dev description="Documentation">klasikahl</dev>
<dev description="Prelude">mboman</dev>
<dev description="SELinux">sindian</dev>

<subproject ref="/proj/en/hardened/selinux/index.xml" inheritresources="yes"/>
<extraproject name="Propolice" lead="frogger">
  Propolice is GCC stack smashing protection written by IBM.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Hardened-Sources">
  A kernel which provides patches for hardened subprojects, and
  stability/security oriented patches.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Grsecurity" lead="solar">
  Grsecurity ACL policies and documentation outlining effective use of Grsecurity.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Hardened GCC" lead="pappy">
  Transparent implementation of <uri link="http://pageexec.virtualave.net/docs/aslr.txt">PaX</uri>
  address space layout randomizations and Propolice stack smashing protection
  using ELF shared objects as executables.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Prelude" lead="mboman">
  Prelude is a hybrid intrusion detection system that tracks both network 
  intrusions and host intrusions with an lml (log monitoring lackey). 
  Integrating this on a large scale, adding support to certain apps, and adding
  rules so that lml can monitor other projects like SELinux.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Systrace">
  Systrace is a lightweight ACL system with an easy to use policy editor and a
  gui for on-the-fly policy management. Additionally this allows applications
  which require root capabilities to run without setuid and setgid flags.
</extraproject>

<plannedproject name="SAL">
  Secure Auditing for Linux. This provides government level secure auditing
  which can be used to take legal action against attackers. This is a logging
  system that supports secure, encrypted, protected logs which cannot be 
  easily modified.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Openwall">
  Openwall provides patches to daemons which allow them to be chrooted and add
  privilege seperation.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Encryption">
  Added algorithms to the unix crypt() function including blowfish and tcb.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Security Forum">
  Provide a place for security oriented projects, like Kerberos, to be hosted,
  maintained and documented.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Security Documentation">
  Maintain documentation about best practices, and general security measures
  such as process limiting, setting quotas, securing systems with kerberos,
  chrooting, tightening services, etc.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="CryptoAPI">
  Cryptographic filesystem support, possibly using <uri link="http://www1.cs.columbia.edu/~ezk/research/">FiST</uri>.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Bastille">
  Bastille is an interactive application which gives the user suggestions on
  securing their machine. It will be customized to make suggestions about other
  Hardened Gentoo subprojects.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="IPSec">
  Documentation and ebuilds/patches for using FreeS/WAN with opportunistic
  encryption and tunneling between networks.
</plannedproject>

<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/propolice.xml">Propolice Guide</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/grsecurity.xml">Grsecurity 1.9 Guide</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/prelude-ids.xml">Prelude Intrusion Detection Guide</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/etdyn-ssp.xml">Hardened GCC Guide</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/etdyn.xml">ET_DYN Intro</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/capabilities.xml">Capabilities Listing</resource>

<extrachapter position="resources">
<title>How do I use this?</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
   Hardened Gentoo is a collection of subprojects. Each of these subprojects is optional, and
   you must explictly enable each subproject you wish to use. A list of projects available and 
   how to enable them is available below.
</p>
<p>
<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>How to Enable:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>SELinux</ti>
		<ti>The <uri link="selinux-x86-install.xml">SELinux x86 Install Guide</uri>.  The <uri link="selinux-quickstart.xml">SELinux QuickStart Guide</uri> for converting a preexisting Gentoo installation.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Propolice</ti>
		<ti>Propolice is now available in GCC by default.  To enable it in compilations add -fstack-protector to your CFLAGS.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Systrace</ti>
		<ti>Merge sys-apps/systrace.  Merge sys-apps/gtk-systrace if you have GTK+.  Merge sys-kernel/hardened-sources for systrace support in your kernel.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Prelude</ti>
		<ti><uri link="prelude-ids.xml">Prelude Intrusion Detection System</uri></ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Hardened GCC</ti>
		<ti>Merge <uri link="etdyn-ssp.xml">sys-devel/hardened-gcc</uri> to enable transparent building of ET_DYN shared executables with Propolice support.</ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
  To participate in the Hardened Gentoo project first join the mailing list at 
  <i>gentoo-hardened@gentoo.org</i>. Then ask if there are plans to support 
  something that you are interested in, propose a new subproject that you are 
  interested in or choose one of the planned subprojects to work on. You may talk
  to the developers and users in the IRC channel <i>#gentoo-hardened</i> on
  <i>irc.freenode.net</i> for more information or just to chat about the project
  or any subprojects. If you don&#39;t have the ability to actively help by
  contributing work we will always need testers to maintain the security and
  stability of the overall product. All development, testing, and productive
  comments and feedback will be greatly appreciated.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<herd name="hardened"/>

</project>
