<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/hardened/pax-quickstart.xml,v 1.9 2006/05/24 19:28:36 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/hardened/pax-quickstart.xml">
<title>Hardened Gentoo PaX Quickstart</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tseng@gentoo.org">Brandon Hale</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="blackace@gentoo.org">Blackace</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="solar@gentoo.org">solar</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
A quickstart covering PaX and Hardened Gentoo.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.3</version>
<date>2005-07-11</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is Hardened Gentoo?</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Hardened Gentoo is a project interested in the hardening of a Gentoo system.
Several different solutions are supported by us and there is a fair bit of
flexibility to create your own setup. At the heart of a common Hardened Gentoo 
setup is <e>PaX</e>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>What is PaX?</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
PaX is a patch to the Linux kernel that provides hardening in two ways.
</p>

<p>
The first, <e>ASLR</e> (Address Space Layout Randomization) provides a means to
randomize the addressing scheme of all data loaded into memory. When an
application is built as a <e>PIE</e> (Position Independent Executable), PaX is
able to also randomize the addresses of the application base in addition.
</p>

<p>
The second protection provided by PaX is non-executable memory. This prevents a
common form of attack where executable code is inserted into memory by an
attacker. More information on PaX can be found throughout this guide, but the
homepage can be found at <uri>http://pax.grsecurity.net</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>An Introduction to PIE and SSP</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As mentioned above, PaX is complemented by PIE. This method of building
executables stores information needed to relocate parts of the executable in
memory, hence the name <e>Position Independent</e>.
</p>

<p>
<e>SSP</e> (Stack Smashing Protector) is a second complementary technology we
introduce at executable build time. SSP was originally introduced by IBM under
the name <e>ProPolice</e>. It modifies the C compiler to insert initialization 
code into functions that create a buffer in memory. 
</p>

<note>
In newer versions of SSP, it is possible to apply SSP to all functions,
adding protection to functions whose buffer would normally be below the size 
limit for SSP. This is enabled via the CFLAG -fstack-protector-all.
</note>

<p>
At run time, when a buffer is created, SSP adds a secret random value, the 
canary, to the end of the buffer. When the function returns, SSP makes sure 
that the canary is still intact. If an attacker were to perform a buffer 
overflow, he would overwrite this value and trigger that stack smashing 
handler. Currently this kills the target process.
</p>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.trl.ibm.com/projects/security/ssp/">Further reading on 
SSP.</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Building a PaX-enabled Kernel</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Several Gentoo kernel trees are already patched with PaX.
</p>

<p>
For 2.4/2.6 based machines, the recommended kernels are <c>hardened-sources</c>
</p>

<p>
Grab one of the recommended source trees, or apply the appropriate patch from
<uri>http://pax.grsecurity.net</uri> to your own tree and configure it as you
normally would for the target machine.
</p>

<p>
In <c>Security Options -&gt; PaX</c>, apply the options as shown below.
</p>

<pre caption="Kernel configuration">
[*] Enable various PaX features

PaX Control -&gt;

 [ ] Support soft mode
 [*] Use legacy ELF header marking
 [*] Use ELF program header marking
     MAC system integration (none)  ---&gt;

Non-executable page -&gt;

 [*] Enforce non-executable pages
 [*]   Paging based non-executable pages
 [*]   Segmentation based non-executable pages
 [*] Emulate trampolines
 [*] Restrict mprotect()
 [ ]   Disallow ELF text relocations

Address Space Layout Randomization -&gt;

 [*] Address Space Layout Randomization
 [*]   Randomize kernel stack base
 [*]   Randomize user stack base
 [*]   Randomize mmap() base
 [*]     Randomize ET_EXEC base
</pre>

<p>
Build this kernel as you normally would and install it to <path>/boot</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Building a PIE/SSP Enabled Userland</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Hardened Gentoo has added support for transparent PIE/SSP building via GCC's
specfile. This means that any users upgrading an older Hardened install should
remove any LDFLAGS or CFLAGS used to trigger PIE/SSP. Also, the 
<c>hardened-gcc</c> package is now deprecated and should be unmerged 
(version 5.0 is a dummy package). To get the current GCC, add 
<c>USE="hardened pic"</c> to <path>/etc/make.conf</path> if not using the hardened
profile.
</p>

<p>
To maintain a consistant toolchain, first <c>emerge binutils gcc virtual/libc</c>.
Next, rebuild the entire system with <c>emerge -e world</c>. All future packages
will be built with PIE/SSP.
</p>

<warn>
Both PIE and SSP are known to cause issues with some packages. If you come
across a package that fails to compile, please file a detailed bug report including 
a log of the failed compile and the output of <c>emerge info</c> to
<uri>http://bugs.gentoo.org/</uri>.
</warn>

<p>
You will probably also want to merge pax-utils.
Often if an ELF has executable relocations in the text segment these can cause problems for us.
scanelf -BRylptq
</p>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>When Things Misbehave (PaX Control)</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Some legitimate applications will attempt to generate code at run time which is
executed out of memory. Naturally, PaX does not allow this and it will promptly
kill the offending application.
</p>

<note>
The most notable of these applications are XFree/Xorg, mplayer and multimedia tools
based on xine-lib. The easiest way around these problems are to disable PaX
protections.
</note>

<p>
Luckily there is a utility to toggle protections on a per-executable basis,
<e>paxctl</e>. As with any other package in Gentoo, install paxctl with the
command <c>emerge paxctl</c>. Usage is show by <c>paxctl -h</c>.
</p>

<note>
If you have an older version of binutils, you will need to use <e>chpax</e>,
which edits the old-style PaX markings. Usage of chpax is largely the same as
paxctl. This also requires legacy marking support built into your kernel.
</note>

<pre caption="paxctl -h">
usage: paxctl &lt;options&gt; &lt;files&gt;

options:
        -p: disable PAGEEXEC            -P: enable PAGEEXEC
        -e: disable EMUTRMAP            -E: enable EMUTRMAP
        -m: disable MPROTECT            -M: enable MPROTECT
        -r: disable RANDMMAP            -R: enable RANDMMAP
        -x: disable RANDEXEC            -X: enable RANDEXEC
        -s: disable SEGMEXEC            -S: enable SEGMEXEC

        -v: view flags                  -z: restore default flags
        -q: suppress error messages     -Q: report flags in short format flags
</pre>

<p>
The first option we will note is <c>-v</c>, which can display flags set on a
particular binary.
</p>

<pre caption="paxctl -v">
shell user # paxctl -v /usr/bin/Xorg
PaX control v0.2
Copyright 2004 PaX Team &lt;pageexec@freemail.hu&gt;

- PaX flags: -p-sM--x-eR- [/usr/bin/Xorg]
        PAGEEXEC is disabled
        SEGMEXEC is disabled
        MPROTECT is enabled
        RANDEXEC is disabled
        EMUTRAMP is disabled
        RANDMMAP is enabled
</pre>

<p>
This shows an XFree binary with all protections disabled.
</p>

<p>
To set flags on a binary, the <c>-z</c> flag is useful as it restores the
default flags.
</p>

<p>
To disable protections on Xorg, run
<c>paxctl -zpeMRxs /usr/bin/Xorg</c>.
</p>

<p>
Play around with disabling/enabling protections to see what is the least needed
to run. Often we find that we need the -m -sp combos.
</p>

<p>
A default init/conf.d script gets installed when you merge the chpax package 
that setups some reasonable defaults on the well known misbehaviors.
You may want to enable the setting of these permissions at every boot.
Todo that you can run the following command
<c>emerge chpax ; rc-update add chpax default ; /etc/init.d/chpax start</c>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
