<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>hardened</name>
<longname>Hardened Gentoo</longname>
<description>
  Hardened Gentoo is an official project with the goal of bringing advanced
  security measures to the Gentoo linux distribution.
</description>

<longdescription>
  Hardened Gentoo is an umbrella project which oversees the research, implementation, and maintainence of
  security oriented projects for Gentoo Linux. We are a team of very competent individuals dedicated
  to bringing advanced security to Gentoo with a number of subprojects.
</longdescription>

<goals>
  Hardened Gentoo&#39;s purpose is to make Gentoo viable for high security,
  high stability production server environments. This project is not a 
  standalone project disjoined from Gentoo proper; it is intended
  to be a team of Gentoo developers which are focused on delivering solutions
  to Gentoo that provide strong security and stability. These solutions will be
  available in Gentoo once they&#39;ve been tested for security and stability
  by the Hardened team.
</goals>

<dev role="lead" description="Hardened Gentoo Team Leader">method</dev>
<dev description="SELinux lead">pebenito</dev>
<dev description="Propolice lead">frogger</dev>
<dev description="PaX/Grsecurity lead, Prelude, Network/Security">solar</dev>
<dev description="Hardened GCC/ET_DYN">pappy</dev>
<dev description="Stage Building, SAL">zhen</dev>
<dev description="Prelude">mboman</dev>
<dev description="SELinux">sindian</dev>

<extraproject name="SELinux" lead="pebenito">
  Adding SELinux support to Gentoo and Portage, this includes providing kernels
  with SELinux support, providing patches to userland utilities, writing good
  Gentoo specific default profiles, and deploying policies via Portage.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Propolice" lead="frogger">
  Propolice is GCC stack smashing protection written by IBM.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Hardened-Sources">
  A kernel which provides patches for hardened subprojects, and
  stability/security oriented patches.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Grsecurity" lead="solar">
  Grsecurity ACL policies and documentation outlining effective use of Grsecurity.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Hardened GCC/ET_DYN">
  Implementation of <uri link="http://pageexec.virtualave.net/docs/aslr.txt">PaX</uri>
  <i>A</i>ddress <i>S</i>pace <i>L</i>ayout <i>R</i>andomizations using ELF
  shared objects as executables.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Prelude">
  Prelude is a hybrid intrusion detection system that tracks both network 
  intrusions and host intrusions with an lml (log monitoring lackey). 
  Integrating this on a large scale, adding support to certain apps, and adding
  rules so that lml can monitor other projects like SELinux.
</extraproject>

<extrachapter position="subproject">
<title>Planned Subprojects</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
   The current planned subprojects in Hardened Gentoo are:
   <table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>Description:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>SAL</ti>
		<ti>Secure Auditing for Linux. This provides government level secure auditing which can be used to take legal action against attackers. This is a logging system that supports secure, encrypted, protected logs which cannot be modified easily.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Openwall</ti>
		<ti>Openwall provides patches to daemons which allow them to be chrooted and add privilege seperation.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Encryption</ti>
		<ti>Added algorithms to the unix crypt() function including blowfish and tcb.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Security Forum</ti>
		<ti>To provide a place for security oriented projects, like Kerberos, to be hosted, maintained and documented.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Security Documentation</ti>
		<ti>There are plans to maintain documentation about best practices, and general security measures such as process limiting, setting quotas, securing systems with kerberos, chrooting, tightening services, et al.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>CryptoAPI</ti>
		<ti>Cryptographic filesystem support, possibly using <uri link="http://www1.cs.columbia.edu/~ezk/research/">FiST</uri>.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Bastille</ti>
		<ti>Bastille is an interactive app which gives the user suggestions on securing their machine. It will be customized to make suggestions about other Hardened Gentoo subprojects.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>IPSec</ti>
		<ti>Documentation and ebuilds/patches for using FreeS/WAN with opportunistic encryption and tunneling between networks.</ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<resource link="http://selinux.dev.gentoo.org">SELinux Demonstration Machine</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/selinux-x86-install.xml">SELinux x86 Install Guide</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/selinux-quickstart.xml">SELinux QuickStart Guide for converting preexisting Gentoo installations</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/selinux-policy.xml">SELinux Policy Overview</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/grsecurity.xml">Grsecurity 1.9 Guide</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/prelude-ids.xml">Prelude Intrusion Detection Guide</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/etdyn-ssp.xml">Hardened GCC Guide</resource>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
  To participate in the Hardened Gentoo project first join the mailing list at 
  <i>gentoo-hardened@gentoo.org</i>. Then ask if there are plans to support 
  something that you are interested in, propose a new subproject that you are 
  interested in or choose one of the planned subprojects to work on. You may talk
  to the developers and users in the IRC channel <i>#gentoo-hardened</i> on
  <i>irc.freenode.net</i> for more information or just to chat about the project
  or any subprojects. If you don&#39;t have the ability to actively help by
  contributing work we will always need testers to maintain the security and
  stability of the overall product. All development, testing, and productive
  comments and feedback will be greatly appreciated.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
