<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Hardened Roadmap</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tocharian@gentoo.org">Adam Mondl</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="tigger@gentoo.org">Rob Holland</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="solar@gentoo.org">Ned Ludd</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="pebenito@gentoo.org">Chris PeBenito</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="method@gentoo.org">Joshua Brindle</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="kang@gentoo.org">Guillaume Destuynder</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="pappy@retired">Alexander Gabert</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="tseng@retired">Brandon Hale</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="klondike@xiscosoft.es">klondike</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="zorry@gentoo.org">Magnus Granberg</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="blueness@gentoo.org">Anthony G. Basile</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="swift" />
</author>

<abstract>
A roadmap that plots current needs and goals of the
Hardened Gentoo project.
</abstract>

<version>6</version>
<date>2012-05-26</date>

<chapter>
<title>Vision</title>
<section>
<body>

<!--
  What is the main vision that Gentoo Hardened strives towards?
  Why does Gentoo Hardened exist? In light of which vision do we
  take our decisions?
-->

<p>
Within Gentoo Linux, the Gentoo Hardened project wants to be a shepherd for all
security oriented projects. The project wants to make Gentoo viable for highly
secure, high stability production environments. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Strategy</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<!--
  Our strategy should reflect our high-level choices and focuses. It should
  describe what we aim for (in light of our vision) in a generic descriptive
  approach. The strategy of Gentoo Hardened should be what we envision to be the
  way to go forward to implement our vision. It should not change much in time.
-->

<p>
In order to succesfully strive towards our vision, Gentoo Hardened aims to
provide subprojects that test, develop, enhance, implement and integrate 
specific security measures in Gentoo Linux. Although each of these projects has
operational responsibilities (after all, the technologies that they support are
used by users all around) they continue to research and develop, making Gentoo
Linux even better than it is today.
</p>

<p>
The direction that each of these projects is heading towards is described in
their <e>roadmap</e>, a combination of strategic directions and shorter term
milestones. These roadmaps are combined in this very document, allowing users to
get a general overview of where Gentoo Hardened is evolving towards.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation</title>
<body>

<p>
Documentation is Gentoo Hardened's first asset that users come in contact with.
It is important that Gentoo Hardened's documentation is well structured, easily
accessible and correctly written. Although we currently focus on technically
educated users and system administrators, this focus should not lower our
responsibility of creating the necessary documents to guide new users in Gentoo
Hardened's realms.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Vulnerability Mitigation</title>
<body>

<p>
Users use a <e>toolchain</e>, a set of libraries and tools like compilers,
linkers and more, to build their systems with. To fight potential
vulnerabilities and future exploits, Gentoo Hardened maintains a toolchain that
supports additional security-enhancing features like SSP, PIE and PIC.
Our focus is to enhance and maintain this toolchain and help the integration of
these security-enhancing patchsets within the upstream communities so that the
benefits are available for all Linux users.
</p>

<p>
Yet toolchains are not the only method where risks can be reduced. Specific
patch sets that enhance Linux' security-related capabilities exist, such as
PAX, that help users mitigate the risk of succesful exploitation of
vulnerabilities. Gentoo Hardened positions and integrates these patches in the
distribution.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Access Control</title>
<body>

<p>
Although definitely not the only security component of a system, proper access
control is a prerequisite for a safer environment. Within Gentoo Hardened,
support of proper access control systems is important, and reflected in our
choices of enhanced development of SELinux, grSecurity RSBAC and more.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Architecture Support</title>
<body>

<p>
The current primary development activities take place within the popular and
commodity architectures x86 and amd64 (x86_64). Yet many other architectures
exist, especially within the server and embedded/mobile environments. These
architectures need to be properly supported as well.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Staffing</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to sustain or even grow our research and development pace and keep
supporting operational tasks and help out users, the Gentoo Hardened team is
always looking for fresh blood. Users who take a proactive approach to finding
places for improvement and filling in the holes should and will be noticed and
probably recruited. Yet recruitment is not mandatory to help out our project. 
The necessary resources are put in place to let contributors efficiently help 
out the project.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Documentation Goals and Milestones</title>
<section>
<title>Current State</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Hardened project is currently lagging behind a bit on documentation.
Recent upstaffing and contributions have helped this out, but we still need to
focus on the toolchain documentation (both toolchain-specific documentation
as wel as documents that relate to the toolchain) such as SSP, PIE and PIC
information.
</p>

<p>
Also, comparative documents should be written to explain the choices that Gentoo
Hardened has made, such as tool selection.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Goals and Milestones</title>
<body>

<!--
  TODO I just verbatimly copied it from the previous version. However, I think
  we should set goals (what to go for) and milestones (specific points that are
  benchmarkable and - most likely - be strengthened by the availability of bug
  reports)
-->

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>ETA</th>
  <th>Status</th>
  <th>Coordinator(s)</th>
  <th>Related Bugs</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Document the Hardened Toolchain</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti>In Progress</ti>
  <ti>Zorry</ti>
  <ti />
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Comparative analysis of security approaches taken by distributions</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti>Unassigned</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti />
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Rework grSecurity documentation</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti>Unassigned</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti />
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Update/rewrite propolice documentation</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti>Unassigned</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti />
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardened Toolchain Goals and Milestones</title>
<section>
<title>Current State</title>
<body>

<p>
Our toolchain so far has seen a tremendous evolution. Some of the integrated
patches have been accepted upstream (like SSP), but work can still improve.
To allow changes to be pushed upstream more easily, we might need improvements
on the ways to strengthen the current implementation, and work on the areas of
code that need clean-up.
</p>

<p>
Our next steps are to take a step backwards and examine the work that has been
done so far. We need to improve our existing documents, but also review the
packages available in the Portage tree and help out the package maintainers in
handling CFLAG filters for a hardened toolchain in a proper way.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Goals and Milestones</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>ETA</th>
  <th>Status</th>
  <th>Coordinator(s)</th>
  <th>Related Bugs</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th colspan="5">Enhance documentation</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Document the toolchain feature set</ti>
  <ti />
  <ti>In progress</ti>
  <ti />
  <ti />
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Describe the grSecurity RBAC system</ti>
  <ti />
  <ti>Unassigned</ti>
  <ti />
  <ti />
</tr>
<tr>
  <th colspan="5">Kernel development and maintenance</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Release hardened-sources-2.6.37</ti>
  <ti />
  <ti>Done</ti>
  <ti>blueness</ti>
  <ti />
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>grSecurity Goals and Milestones</title>
<section>
<title>Current State</title>
<body>

<p>
grSecurity is well integrated within Gentoo Hardened (patch- and software wise
as well as knowledge). However, the documentation is lagging behind a lot and
is in need for attention.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Goals and Milestones</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>ETA</th>
  <th>Status</th>
  <th>Coordinator(s)</th>
  <th>Related Bugs</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>
    the existing grSecurity2 document needs to be converted to Handbook XML
  </ti>
  <ti />
  <ti>Unassigned</ti>
  <ti />
  <ti />
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>
    the features of PAX and grSecurity need to be described and documented
  </ti>
  <ti />
  <ti>Unassigned</ti>
  <ti />
  <ti />
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>
    the RBAC system needs to be covered documentation-wise in much more detail
  </ti>
  <ti />
  <ti>Unassigned</ti>
  <ti />
  <ti />
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>SELinux Goals and Milestones</title>
<section>
<title>Current State</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Hardened SELinux state is up to date and fully supported (except
MLS which is considered experimental). The documentation is being updated as 
the state evolves, but can still improve. Primary focus now is on the quality
of the packages and standard policies.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Goals and Milestones</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>ETA</th>
  <th>Status</th>
  <th>Coordinator(s)</th>
  <th>Related Bugs</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Have SELinux-enabled stage3 available on the mirrors</ti>
  <ti>2012-06-31</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti></ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
