<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link = "roadmap.xml">
<title>Hardened Gentoo Roadmap</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tocharian@gentoo.org">Adam Mondl</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="tigger@gentoo.org">Rob Holland</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="solar@gentoo.org">Ned Ludd</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="pebenito@gentoo.org">Chris PeBenito</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="method@gentoo.org">Joshua Brindle</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="kang@gentoo.org">Guillaume Destuynder</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="pappy@retired">Alexander Gabert</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="tseng@retired">Brandon Hale</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
A roadmap that plots current needs and goals of the
Hardened Gentoo project.
</abstract>

<version>1.2</version>
<date>2005-11-09</date>

<chapter>
<title>Where the Hardened Gentoo Project Is Today</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Past Hardened Gentoo work has focused on developing the hardened toolchain into
the more mature, consistent approach that it currently takes.  It is
implemented as a patchset for gcc with rules that control object code creation
and linking scenarios. Since the spotlight of development is no longer on the
design aspect of the toolchain, the goals of the Hardened Gentoo Project must
shift accordingly.
</p>

<p>
Similarly, the access control systems offered by the Hardened Gentoo Project
have continued to mature, and both Grsecurity2 and the latest version of
SELinux are now offered. Recent work by Guillaume Destuynder (kang) has also
introduced RSBAC as another access control system available to Hardened Gentoo
users.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Short-Term Goals</title>
<section>
<title>Hardened Toolchain</title>
<body>

<p>
Now is the time to take a step back and examine the work that has been done so
far. A review of the current approach that the hardened toolchain takes is
needed. There may be ways to strengthen the current implementation or areas of
code that can be cleaned up to allow changes to be pushed upstream easier.
</p>

<p>
As a lingering effect of the previous hardened toolchain, many ebuilds
currently filter hardened CFLAGS such as -fPIC and -fstack-protector. Work can
now be devoted to reviewing those packages and seeking alternate solutions for
the filters. Also, the hardened code in flag-o-matic.eclass should be reviewed
and possibly rewritten.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Access Control Systems</title>
<body>

<p><b>Grsecurity</b></p>

<ul>
<li>
Documents regarding Grsecurity are currently a major need for Gentoo. The
existing Grsecurity2 document needs to be converted to Handbook XML. Also, a
document describing the RBAC system in more detail is needed.
</li>
</ul>

<p><b>SELinux</b></p>

<ul>
<li>
Strengthen and extend current policies.
</li>
<li>
Extend support to more architectures.
</li>
<li>
Policy module support.
</li>
<li>
Additional Daemon Policies.
</li>
</ul>

<p><b>RSBAC</b></p>

<ul>
<li>
Bring policy support tool to Gentoo packages.
</li>
<li>
Develop default Gentoo policies with policy support tool.
</li>
<li>
Enhance current documentation, and possibly add documentation about desktop
RSBAC.
</li> </ul>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Long-Term Goals</title>
<section>
<title>Documentation</title>
<body>

<p>
The Hardened Gentoo Project is currently very lacking in documentation. The
hardened toolchain needs to be documented fully, and older documents that have
a relationship to the toolchain need to be updated, such as the SSP, PIE, and PIC
documents. Also, comparative documents should be written to explain the choices
that Hardened Gentoo has made in deciding which security tools to support and
which not to support.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Support More Architectures</title>
<body>

<p>
A long-term goal of the Hardened Gentoo Project is to support all of the
architectures that are officially supported by Gentoo. The only strong support
that exists at the moment is for x86.
</p>

<p>
The hardened toolchain supports x86, amd64, and sparc64, and would like to extend
support to ppc, ppc64, s390, and similar architectures.  With access to different
kinds of hardware, hardened support can slowly be extended to those architectures
as well.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Expand the Hardened Team</title>
<body>

<p>
There will always be unfinished tasks for the Hardened Team. Users who take a
proactive approach to finding places for improvement and filling in the holes
will be noticed and probably recruited. Current Hardened Team members will be
responsible for training new developers to fill new roles. If you are
interested in helping out, stop by the IRC channel and let someone know what
you are interested in and what you will be doing about it. Input/peer review
should always be welcome as it helps everyone out in the long run.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Roadmap Tracking</title>
<section>
<title>Hardened Toolchain</title>
<body>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Description</th><th>Coordinator(s)</th><th>Status</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>x86 Support</ti><ti>solar</ti><ti>Complete</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>amd64 Support</ti><ti>solar,r2d2</ti><ti>In experimental</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>sparc32 Support</ti><ti></ti><ti>Unassigned</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>sparc64 Support</ti><ti></ti><ti>Stalled</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>ppc Support</ti><ti></ti><ti>In testing</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>ppc64 Support</ti><ti>solar,dostrow</ti><ti>seed stage built</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>s390 Support</ti><ti></ti><ti>Unassigned</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>hppa Support</ti><ti></ti><ti>Not supported</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>arm Support</ti><ti></ti><ti>Unassigned (uclibc only)</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>mips Support</ti><ti></ti><ti>Unassigned (uclibc only)</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SELinux</title>
<body>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Description</th><th>Coordinator(s)</th><th>Status</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Strengthen and extend the current policies</ti><ti>pebenito/kaiowas</ti><ti>In Progress</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Extend support to more architectures</ti><ti>pebenito</ti><ti>In Progress</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Policy module support</ti><ti>pebenito</ti><ti>In Progress</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Additional Daemon Policies</ti><ti>pebenito/kaiowas</ti><ti>In Progress</ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>RSBAC</title>
<body>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Description</th><th>Coordinator(s)</th><th>Status</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Bring policy support tool to Gentoo packages.</ti><ti>kang</ti><ti>In Progress</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Enhance RSBAC Documentation</ti><ti></ti><ti>Unassigned</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Documentation</title>
<body>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th>Description</th><th>Coordinator(s)</th><th>Status</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Comparative analysis of security approaches taken by distributions.</ti>
    <ti>Dave Monnier</ti><ti>In Progress</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Rework Grsecurity Documentation</ti><ti></ti><ti>Unassigned</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Update/Rewrite Propolice Documentation</ti><ti>Adam Mondl</ti><ti>In Progress</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Document the Hardened Toolchain</ti><ti></ti><ti>Unassigned</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
