<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/hardened/selinux-faq.xml,v 1.3 2011/06/07 19:57:25 klondike Exp $ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/hardened/selinux-faq.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Hardened SELinux Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="pebenito@gentoo.org">Chris PeBenito</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="sven.vermeulen@siphos.be">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Frequently Asked Questions on SELinux integration with Gentoo Hardened.
The FAQ is a collection of solutions found on IRC, mailinglist, forums or 
elsewhere
</abstract>

<version>9</version>
<date>2011-06-01</date>

<faqindex>
<title>Questions</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Using SELinux requires administrators a more thorough knowledge of their
system and a good idea on how processes should behave. Next to the <uri 
link="/proj/en/hardened/selinux/selinux-handbook.xml">Gentoo Hardened SELinux
handbook</uri>, a proper FAQ allows us to inform and help users in their 
day-to-day SELinux experience.
</p>

<p>
The FAQ is an aggregation of solutions found on IRC, mailinglists, forums
and elsewhere. It focuses on SELinux integration on Gentoo Hardened, but 
general SELinux questions that are popping up regularly will be incorporated
as well.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</faqindex>

<chapter>
<title>General SELinux Support Questions</title>
<section id="features">
<title>Does SELinux enforce resource limits?</title>
<body>

<p>
No, resource limits are outside the scope of an access control system. If you 
are looking for this type of support, take a look at technologies like
grsecurity, cgroups, pam and the like.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="grsecurity">
<title>Can I use SELinux with grsecurity (and PaX)?</title>
<body>

<p>
Definitely, we even recommend it. However, it is suggested that grsecurity's
ACL support is not used as it would be redundant to SELinux's access control.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="pie-ssp">
<title>Can I use SELinux and the hardened compiler (with PIE-SSP)?</title>
<body>

<p>
Definitely. We also suggest to use PaX to take full advantage of the PIE
features of the compiler.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="rsbac">
<title>Can I use SELinux and RSBAC?</title>
<body>

<p>
We don't know. If you try this combination, we would be very interested
in its results.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="filesystem">
<title>Can I use SELinux with any file system?</title>
<body>

<p>
SELinux requires access to a file's security context to operate properly.
To do so, SELinux uses <e>extended file attributes</e> which needs to be 
properly supported by the underlying file system. If the file system supports
extended file attributes and you have configured your kernel to enable this
support, then SELinux will work on those file systems.
</p>

<p>
General Linux file systems, such as ext2, ext3, ext4, jfs, xfs and btrfs
support extended attributes (but don't forget to enable it in the kernel
configuration) as well as tmpfs (for instance used by udev). If your file
system collection is limited to this set, then you should have no issues.
</p>

<p>
Ancillary file systems such as vfat and iso9660 are supported too, but with
an important caveat: all files in each file system will have the same SELinux
security context information since these file systems do not support extended
file attributes. 
</p>

<p>
Network file systems can be supported in the same manner as ancillary file
systems (all files share the same security context). However, some development
has been made in supported extended file attributes on the more popular file
systems such as NFS. Although this is far from production-ready, it does look
like we will eventually support these file systems on SELinux fully as well.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="nomultilib">
<title>Can I use SELinux with AMD64 no-multilib?</title>
<body>

<p>
Yes. However, for the time being, it is only supported through developer
profiles, meaning that the profiles should not be seen as very stable (their
content can still change swiftly). Try out
<c>hardened/linux/amd64/no-multilib/selinux</c> and tell us what you get.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="ubac">
<title>What is UBAC exactly?</title>
<body>

<p>
UBAC, or <e>User Based Access Control</e>, introduces additional constraints
when using SELinux policy. Participating domains / types that are <e>both</e>
marked as a <c>ubac_constrained_type</c> (which is an attribute) will only
have the allowed privileges in effect if they both run with the same SELinux
user context.
</p>

<pre caption="Domains and their SELinux user context">
<comment># The SELinux allow rule</comment>
allow foo_t bar_t:file { read };

<comment># This will succeed:</comment>
staff_u:staff_r:foo_t reads file with type staff_u:object_r:bar_t

<comment># This will be prohibited:</comment>
user_u:user_r:foo_t reads file with type staff_u:object_r:bar_t
</pre>

<p>
Of course, this is not always the case. Besides the earlier mentioned
requirement that both types are <c>ubac_constrained_type</c>, if the source
domain is <c>sysadm_t</c>, then the constraint will not be in effect (the 
<c>sysadm_t</c> domain is exempt from UBAC constraints). Also, if the source
or destination SELinux user is <c>system_u</c> then the constraint will also
not be in effect. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Using SELinux</title>
<section id="enable_selinux">
<title>How do I enable SELinux?</title>
<body>

<p>
This is explained in the <uri 
link="/proj/en/hardened/selinux/selinux-handbook.xml">SELinux Handbook</uri>
in the chapter on <e>Using Gentoo/Hardened SELinux</e>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="switch_status">
<title>How do I switch between permissive and enforcing?</title>
<body>

<p>
The easiest way is to use the <c>setenforce</c> command. With <c>setenforce 
0</c> you tell SELinux to run in permissive mode. Similarly, with 
<c>setenforce 1</c> you tell SELinux to run in enforcing mode.
</p>

<p>
You can also add a kernel option <c>enforcing=0</c> or <c>enforcing=1</c>
in the bootloader configuration (or during the startup routine of the system). 
This allows you to run SELinux in permissive or enforcing mode from the start 
of the system.
</p>

<p>
The default state of the system is kept in <path>/etc/selinux/config</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="disable_selinux">
<title>How do I disable SELinux completely?</title>
<body>

<p>
It might be possible that running SELinux in permissive mode is not sufficient
to properly fix any issue you have. To disable SELinux completely, you need to
edit <path>/etc/selinux/config</path> and set <c>SELINUX=disabled</c>. Next,
reboot your system.
</p>

<impo>
When you have been running your system with SELinux disabled, you must boot 
in permissive mode first and relabel your entire file system. Activities ran
while SELinux was disabled might have created new files or removed the labels
from existing files, causing these files to be available without security
context.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
<section id="matchcontext">
<title>
  How do I know which file context rule is used for a particular file?
</title>
<body>

<p>
If you use the <c>matchpathcon</c> command, it will tell you what the security
context for the given path (file or directory) should be, but it doesn't tell
you which rule it used to deduce this. To do that, you can use <c>findcon</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Using findcon">
~# <i>findcon /etc/selinux/strict/contexts/files/file_contexts -p /lib64/rc/init.d</i>
/.*                          system_u:object_r:default_t
/lib64/rc/init\.d(/.*)?   system_u:object_r:initrc_state_t
/lib64/.*                    system_u:object_r:lib_t
</pre>

<p>
When the SELinux utilities try to apply a context, they try to match the rule
that is the most specific, so in the above case, it is the one that leads to the
initrc_state_t context.
</p>

<p>
The most specific means, in order of tests:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    If line A has a regular expression, and line B doesn't, then line B is more
    specific.
  </li>
  <li>
    If the number of characters before the first regular expression in line A is
    less than the number of characters before the first regular expression in
    line B, then line B is more specific
  </li>
  <li>
    If the number of characters in line A is less than in line B, then line B is
    more specific
  </li>
  <li>
    If line A does not map to a specific SELinux type, and line B does, then
    line B is more specific
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>SELinux Kernel Error Messages</title>
<section id="register_security">
<title>I get a register_security error message when booting</title>
<body>

<p>
During boot-up, the following message pops up:
</p>

<pre caption="Kernel message on register_security">
There is already a security framework initialized, register_security failed.
Failure registering capabilities with the kernel
selinux_register_security: Registering secondary module capability
Capability LSM initialized
</pre>

<p>
This is nothing to worry about (and perfectly normal).
</p>

<p>
This means that the Capability LSM module couldn't register as the primary 
module, since SELinux is the primary module. The third message means that it
registers with SELinux as a secondary module.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>SELinux and Gentoo</title>
<section id="no_module">
<title>I get a missing SELinux module error when using emerge</title>
<body>

<p>
When trying to use <c>emerge</c>, the following error message is displayed:
</p>

<pre caption="Error message from emerge on the SELinux module">
!!! SELinux module not found. Please verify that it was installed.
</pre>

<p>
This indicates that the portage SELinux module is missing or damaged. Recent 
Portage versions provide this module out-of-the-box, but the security contexts
of the necessary files might be wrong on your system. Try relabelling the files
of the portage package:
</p>

<pre caption="Relabel all portage files">
~# <i>rlpkg portage</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section id="loadpolicy">
<title>I get 'FEATURES variable contains unknown value(s): loadpolicy'</title>
<body>

<p>
When running emerge, the following error is shown:
</p>

<pre caption="Emerge error on loadpolicy">
FEATURES variable contains unknown value(s): loadpolicy
</pre>

<p>
This is a remnant of the older SELinux policy module set where policy packages
might require this FEATURE to be available. Although the more recent packages
do not support this FEATURE value anymore, these are still in the ~arch phase 
so the current SELinux profile still offers this value. Portage however already
knows that this FEATURE is not supported anymore and complains.
</p>

<p>
We recommend you to use the ~arch versions of all packages in the sec-policy
category, and set <c>FEATURES="-loadpolicy"</c> to disable this (cosmetic)
error.
</p>

<p>
Once the newer policy modules are stabilized, the SELinux profile will be updated
to remove this setting.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="conflicting_types">
<title>During rlpkg I get 'conflicting specifications for ... and ..., using ...'</title>
<body>

<p>
When trying to relabel a package (<c>rlpkg packagename</c>) or system (<c>rlpkg
-a -r</c>) you get a message similar to the following:
</p>

<pre caption="rlpkg complaining about conflicting specifications">
filespec_add: conflicting specifications for /usr/bin/getconf and 
/usr/lib64/misc/glibc/getconf/XBS5_LP64_OFF64, using
system_u:object_r:lib_t
</pre>

<p>
This is most likely caused by hard linked files. Remember, SELinux uses the
extended attributes in the file system to store the security context of a file.
If two separate paths point to the same file using hard links (i.e. the files
share the same inode) then both files will have the same security context.
</p>

<p>
The solution depends on the particular case; in order of most likely to happen
and resolve:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    Although both files are the same, they are not used in the same context. 
    In such cases, it is recommended to remove one of the files and then copy
    the other file back to the first (<c>rm B; cp A B</c>). This way, both
    files have different inodes and can be labelled accordingly.
  </li>
  <li>
    Both files are used for the same purpose; in this case, it might be better
    to label the file which would not be labelled correctly (say a binary
    somewhere in a <path>/usr/lib64</path> location) using <c>semanage</c>
    (<c>semanage fcontext -a -t correct_domain_t /usr/lib64/path/to/file</c>)
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
It is also not a bad idea to report (after verifying if it hasn't been reported
first) this on <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo's bugzilla</uri> so 
that the default policies are updated accordingly.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="portage_libsandbox">
<title>
  During package installation, ld.so complains 'object 'libsandbox.so' from 
  LD_PRELOAD cannot be preloaded: ignored'
</title>
<body>

<p>
During installation of a package, you might see the following error message:
</p>

<pre caption="Error message during package installation">
&gt;&gt; Installing (1 of 1) net-dns/host-991529
&gt;&gt;&gt; Setting SELinux security labels
ERROR: ld.so: object 'libsandbox.so' from LD_PRELOAD cannot be preloaded: ignored.
</pre>

<p>
This message should <e>only</e> occur after the <e>Setting SELinux security
labels</e> message. It happens because SELinux tells glibc to disable 
<c>LD_PRELOAD</c> (and other environment variables that are considered 
potentially harmful) during domain transitions. Here, portage calls the
<c>setfiles</c> command (part of a SELinux installation) and as such 
transitions from portage_t to setfiles_t, which clears the environment
variable.
</p>

<p>
We believe that it is safer to trust the SELinux policy here (as setfiles runs
in its own confined domain anyhow) rather than updating the policy to allow
transitioning between portage_t to setfiles_t without clearing these 
environment variables. Note that <e>libsandbox.so is not disabled during builds
and merges</e>, only during the activity where Portage labels the files it 
just merged.
</p>

<p>
So the error is in our opinion cosmetic and can be ignored (but sadly not
hidden).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="emergefails">
<title>Emerge does not work, giving 'Permission denied: /etc/make.conf'</title>
<body>

<p>
This is to be expected if you are not using the <c>sysadm_r</c> role. Any
Portage related activity requires that you are in the <c>sysadm_r</c> role. To
transition to the role, first validate if you are currently known as
<c>staff_u</c> (or, if you added your own SELinux identities, a user that has
the permission to transition to the <c>sysadm_r</c> role). Then run <c>newrole
-r sysadm_r</c> to transition.
</p>

<pre caption="Transitioning to sysadm_r">
~$ <i>emerge --info</i>
Permission denied: '/etc/make.conf'
~$ <i>id -Z</i>
staff_u:staff_r:staff_t
~$ <i>newrole -r sysadm_r</i>
Password: <comment># Enter your users' password</comment>
</pre>

<p>
This is also necessary if you logged on to your system as root but through SSH.
The default behavior is that SSH sets the lowest role for the particular user
when logged on. And you shouldn't allow remote root logins anyhow.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="cronfails">
<title>
  Cron fails to load in root's crontab with message '(root) ENTRYPOINT
  FAILED (crontabs/root)'
</title>
<body>

<p>
When you hit the mentioned error with a root crontab or an administrative
users' crontab, but not with a regular users' crontab, then check the context of
the crontab file:
</p>

<pre caption="Check context of the crontab file">
~# <i>ls -Z /var/spool/cron/crontabs/root</i>
staff_u:object_r:user_cron_spool_t /var/spool/cron/crontabs/root
</pre>

<p>
Next, check what the default context is for the given user (in this case, root)
when originating from the <c>crond_t</c> domain:
</p>

<pre caption="Check default context for user root">
~# <i>getseuser root system_u:system_r:crond_t</i>
seuser:  root, level (null)
Context 0       root:sysadm_r:cronjob_t
Context 1       root:staff_r:cronjob_t
</pre>

<p>
As you can see, the default context is always for the <c>root</c> SELinux user.
However, the <path>/var/spool/cron/crontabs/root</path> file context in the
above example is for the SELinux user staff_u. Hence, cron will not be able to
read this file (the <c>user_cron_spool_t</c> type is a UBAC constrained one).
</p>

<p>
To fix this, change the user of the file to root:
</p>

<pre caption="Change the SELinux user of the root crontab file">
~# <i>chcon -u root /var/spool/cron/crontabs/root</i>
</pre>

<p>
Another fix would be to disable UBAC completely. This is accomplished with
<c>USE="-ubac"</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
