<?xml version='1.0' encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/security/en/index.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Security Project</title>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="solar@gentoo.org">solar</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<abstract>This document describes the overall Gentoo Linux Security Project</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>March 30, 2004</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Security</title>
	<section>
	<body>
		<p>
		Security is a primary focus of Gentoo Linux and ensuring the confidentiality and security of our users machines is of
		utmost importance to us.  The Gentoo Linux Security Response team is tasked with providing timely information about
		security vulnerabilities in Gentoo Linux, along with patches to secure those vulnerabilities.  We work directly with
		vendors, end users and other OSS programs to ensure all security incidents are responded to quickly and professionally.
		</p>
		<p>
			<uri link="glsa/index.xml">Gentoo Linux Security Announcements (GLSAs)</uri>
		</p>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Linux Security Announcements (GLSAs)</title>
	<section>
	<body>
		<p>
		Gentoo Linux Security Announcements are notifications that we send out to the community to inform them of security vulnerabilities related to Gentoo Linux or the packages contained in our portage repository.  For a full list of all recent GLSAs, please see our <uri link="glsa/index.xml">GLSA index page</uri>.
		</p>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Linux Security Team</title>
	<section>
	<body>
			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>Team Member</th>
					<th>Username</th>
					<th>Areas of Responsibilty</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Joshua Berry</ti>
					<ti>CondorDes</ti>
					<ti>GLSA Coordinator</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Thierry Carrez</ti>
					<ti>koon</ti>
					<ti>Security documentation</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Sune Kloppenborg Jeppesen</ti>
					<ti>jaervosz</ti>
					<ti>GLSA Coordinator</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Kurt Lieber</ti>
					<ti>klieber</ti>
					<ti>Project co-manager</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Ned Ludd</ti>
					<ti>solar</ti>
					<ti>Bug hunter, auditing</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Dan Margolis</ti>
					<ti>KrispyKringle</ti>
					<ti>GLSA Coordinator</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Rajiv Manglani</ti>
					<ti>rajiv</ti>
					<ti>Auditing</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Marius Mauch</ti>
					<ti>genone</ti>
					<ti>Portage integration</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti>Tim Yamin</ti>
					<ti>plasmaroo</ti>
					<ti>Systems development</ti>
				</tr>
			</table>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Contact Information</title>
	<section>
	<body>
		<p>
		Gentoo Linux takes security vulnerability reports very seriously.  Please send security related reports to security@gentoo.org
		and file a bug on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>. The Gentoo Linux Security team will ensure all
		security-related bug reports are responded to in a timely fashion.
		</p>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>Additional Gentoo Linux security-related links</title>
	<section>
	<body>
		<ul>
			<li><uri link="/proj/en/hardened/">Gentoo Hardened</uri> -- bringing advanced security to Gentoo Linux</li>
			<li><uri link="/proj/en/server/">Gentoo Server</uri> -- focusing on server-specific issues, such as security and stability</li>
		</ul>
	</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>I Want to Participate</title>
	<section>
<body>
<p>
  To participate in the Gentoo Security project first join the mailing list at
  <e>gentoo-security@gentoo.org</e> and sign yourself up a <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugzilla account</uri>.

  You may be able to talk to one of our security developers and or users in the IRC channel 
  <e>#gentoo-security</e> on <e>irc.freenode.net</e> for more information or just to chat about 
  the security state of existing projects.

  If you don&#39;t have the ability to actively help by
  contributing work we will always need testers to maintain the security and
  stability of the overall project. All development, testing, and productive
  comments and feedback will be greatly appreciated.
</p>
</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
