<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/proj/en/releng/catalyst/faq.xml">

<title>Catalyst FAQ</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">
John Davis</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">Daniel Robbins</author>

<abstract>
Frequently asked questions relating to the Catalyst tool.
</abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>3 October 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>

<section>
	<title>Catalyst FAQ</title>
	<body>
	<p><b>Q: How do I build a stage2 and stage3 tarball for a non-generic CPU type,
	such as <c>pentium4</c> or <c>g4</c>?</b></p>
	<p>A: First, make sure that your hardware is capable of building such a stage.
	If you want to build a <c>pentium4</c> stage,
	you will need to build on a Pentium 4 or AMD64/Opteron system. 
	You can't build a <c>pentium4</c> stage on an Athlon XP system,
	as Athlon XP CPUs do not support SSE2 instructions, and SSE2 instructions will be enabled for
	<c>pentium4</c> stages. Likewise,
	if you want to build a <c>g4</c> stage, you will need to do this on a PowerPC G4 or G5 system.</p>
	<p>Once you've made sure that you're building on the right hardware, simply follow the steps
	above, but for building the stage2,
	simply change the <c>subarch</c> setting to a valid 
	non-generic subarchitecture (ie. <c>pentium4</c>.) Then your stage2 will
	be built for the subarchitecture that you specify. Then, use this stage2 as the "seed" stage to
	build your stage3. Of course, you will also want to modify the <c>subarch</c> setting in your stage3
	spec to match what you used in your stage2 spec.</p>

	<p><b>Q: I want to build a bunch of stages for various subarches. How should I do this?</b></p>
	<p>A: First, build a generic stage1. Then use this stage1 to build a specialized stage2 and stage3. 
	Use the stage1 again to build another specialized stage2 and stage3. You do not need to re-build the 
	stage1 -- all your specialized stage2s and stage3s can use the same "seed" stage1.</p>

	<p><b>Q: Can I build a stage1 for a non-generic CPU type?</b></p>
	<p>A: This is a very bad idea, as users expect stage1's to work on any type of sub-architecture.
	This way, they can use
	the stage1 on any system without worries. You should be sure to not "pollute" your stage1 with 
	non-generic-CPU-specific code.
	Always use a "generic" stage2 or stage3 to build a new stage1.</p>

	<p><b>Q: I thought that catalyst was able to build stages "from scratch." If catalyst builds 
	stages from scratch, then why does it need a "seed stage"?</b></p>
	<p>A: Good question. As you know, a stage2 and stage3 are dependent on
	previous stages for building, which is expected
	and made clear by their name (ie. a "stage2" implies that there was a "stage1".)
	However, catalyst does need a seed stage for building a stage1, so in regards to building
	a stage1 it's worth looking into why this is necessary. When building
	a stage1, catalyst uses the seed (stage2 or stage3) to set up a chroot environment.
	Inside the chroot environment, the new stage1 is built by setting the <c>ROOT</c> environment
	variable to <path>/tmp/stage1root</path>. This instructs Portage
	to merge all new packages not to the current filesystem, but to the filesystem in
	<path>/tmp/stage1root</path>. <path>/tmp/stage1root</path>
	is then tarred up and becomes the target stage1. What this means is that when catalyst
	builds a stage1, the stage1 itself does not
	inherit any binaries or libraries from the seed that is used. The seed that is used <e>does</e>
	impact the target stage1 somewhat -- the Linux headers on the seed are used for building the stage1's
	glibc, and the compilers on the seed are used to compile all the
	programs on the stage1. The seed stage is used to isolate the stage1 build process from your local system,
	and also allows for x86 stage1s to be built on amd64 systems, for example.</p>

	<p><b>Q: Is there an official HOWTO for Catalyst?</b></p>
	<p>Currently, there is no official HOWTO. If you are interested in writing one though, please
	contact me via e-mail (zhen at gentoo dot org). The lack of an official HOWTO does not mean that
	Catalyst is completely undocumented though. If Catalyst is emerged with the <c>doc</c> USE flag set,
	well commented example specfiles are installed to <path>/usr/share/doc/catalyst-$version/examples</path>.
	</p>

	<p>If you still have questions after reading through the examples, feel free to jump onto IRC and ask
	in #gentoo-releng on irc.freenode.net. Additionally, the author of Catalyst does not mind if you mail
	him asking for help! </p>

	</body>
	</section>

</chapter>

</guide>
