<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/catalyst/index.xml,v 1.32 2006/03/24 17:56:22 wolf31o2 Exp $ -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>

<name>Catalyst</name>
<longname>Catalyst</longname>

<description>
This project develops the catalyst tool, which is used to build official Gentoo
stage tarballs, packages and install CDs.
</description>

<longdescription>
This project develops the catalyst tool, which is used to build official Gentoo
stage tarballs, packages and install CDs. It is also used in other Gentoo
projects, such as GNAP and the upcoming Gentoo GameCD project. This tool is
designed to be easy to use, customize, extend and maintain.
</longdescription>

<goals>
<p>The goal of the catalyst project is to provide a single multi-faceted tool
that can reliably build all aspects of a Gentoo Linux release: stage tarballs,
GRP package sets, and install CDs.</p>

<p>Our specific development goals for <c>catalyst</c> include the following:
ensuring it provides high-quality builds of Gentoo Linux, and for the tool to
be easy to use, customize, extend and maintain. The catalyst tool is intended
to be used by those who wish to create their own customized versions of Gentoo
Linux, or their own customized LiveCDs. Our goal is to make catalyst a powerful
tool that's a pleasure to use, and to ensure that the code we write is
maintainable and of high-quality.</p>
</goals>

<dev role="lead" description="Design lead">wolf31o2</dev>
<dev role="lead" description="Code monkey">rocket</dev>

<extrachapter position="top">
	<title>Documentation</title>
	<section>
		<body>
			<p>
			The catalyst <uri link="faq.xml">FAQ</uri> attempts to answer
			commonly asked questions related to catalyst
			</p>
			<p>
			Catalyst has branched into two versions.  The current 1.x branch
			will remain supported and will be used for bug-fix only until the
			2.0 branch is stabilized.  No new features will be added to
			catalyst 1.x after version 1.1.10.10.
			</p>
			<p>
			The catalyst Reference Manual is now available in two flavors, one
			for catalyst <uri link="1.x/reference.xml">1.x</uri> and one for
			catalyst <uri link="2.x/reference.xml">2.x</uri>.
			</p>
			<impo>
			Currently the 2.x version is under construction, so it is
			only partitally	correct.  Please do not use it until this note is
			no longer here.
			</impo>
			<p>
			The Reference Manual is the definitive guide to
			valid options for catalyst spec files and also for
			<c>catalyst.conf</c>.
			</p>
			<impo>
			The catalyst Reference Manual has not been updated in some time.
			The best documentation for each catalyst option comes from
			installing catalyst with <c>emerge catalyst</c> and looking through
			the actual spec files used to build the last release, along with
			the example templates.
			</impo>
		</body>
	</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
	<title>Supported Architectures</title>
	<section>
		<body>
			<p>
			Catalyst supports a number of architectures.  In catalyst-speak, an
			"architecture" is a general type of CPU platform. Here is a
			complete list of architectures supported by catalyst:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>Architecture</th>
					<th>Description</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>x86</c></ti>
					<ti>Intel-compatible PC, ranging from i386 to Pentium 4 and
					Athlon XP.</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>amd64</c></ti>
					<ti>AMD's 64-bit platform, also known as "Opteron" or
					"x86-64".  This also includes Intel EM64T machines.</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>alpha</c></ti>
					<ti>The Alpha processor (all flavors)</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>hppa</c></ti>
					<ti>HP's PA-RISC systems</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>ia64</c></ti>
					<ti>Intel's Itanium 64-bit platform (Itanium Classic and
					Itanium 2)</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>ppc</c></ti>
					<ti>Apple's PowerPC platform, including original PowerPC
					systems, G3, G4 and G5 in 32-bit mode</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>s390</c></ti>
					<ti>IBM's S/390 platform, including zSeries machines</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>sparc</c></ti>
					<ti>32-bit Sparc-based systems</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>sparc64</c></ti>
					<ti>64-bit Sparc-based systems</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>mips</c></ti>
					<ti>MIPS-based systems</ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>arm</c></ti>
					<ti>ARM-based processors</ti>
				</tr>
			</table>

			<p>
			For each architecture, catalyst supports a number of
			"sub-architectures."  A sub-architecture is a specific variant of
			the architecture.  For example, <c>pentium4</c> is a
			sub-architecture of the <c>x86</c> architecture.  Here is a list of
			all sub-architectures supported by catalyst:
			</p>

			<table>
				<tr>
					<th>Architecture</th>
					<th>Sub-architectures</th>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>x86</c></ti>
					<ti><c>x86 i386 i486 i586 i686 pentium-mmx athlon athlon-xp
					athlon-mp pentium3 pentium4</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>amd64</c></ti>
					<ti><c>amd64</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>alpha</c></ti>
					<ti><c>alpha ev4 ev45 ev5 ev56 pca56 ev6 ev67</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>hppa</c></ti>
					<ti><c>hppa</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>ia64</c></ti>
					<ti><c>ia64</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>ppc</c></ti>
					<ti><c>ppc power-ppc g3 g4</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>s390</c></ti>
					<ti><c>s390</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>sparc</c></ti>
					<ti><c>sparc</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>sparc64</c></ti>
					<ti><c>sparc64</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>mips</c></ti>
					<ti><c>mips mips1 mips2 mips3 mips4 mipsel mipsel1 mipsel2
					mipsel3 mipsel4 cobalt</c></ti>
				</tr>
				<tr>
					<ti><c>arm</c></ti>
					<ti><c>arm</c></ti>
				</tr>
			</table>
	
			<p>
			You'll notice that all architectures have a sub-architecture with
			the same name as the architecture.  This sub-architecture is meant
			to represent a "generic" build that should work on all systems in
			that architecture.	Each sub-architecture has an associated set of
			<c>CFLAGS</c>, <c>CXXFLAGS</c>, as well as a <c>CHOST</c> and set of
			<c>USE</c> variables that are enabled on that sub-architecture.  The
			<c>USE</c> settings are intended to enable any CPU-specific options,
			such as <c>mmx</c> or <c>altivec</c>.
			</p>

			<note>Catalyst currently also supports the ability to build
			<c>x86</c> architecture stages on <c>amd64</c> systems.
			</note>
		</body>
	</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
