<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
	<name>recruiters</name>
	<longname>Gentoo Developer Recruiters</longname>
	<author title="Author">
   		<mail link="avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail>
	</author>
	<description>
	The recruiters subproject provides a central location for information about developer recruitment and recruiter policy.
	</description>

	<date>17 January 2004</date>

	<longdescription>
	Gentoo's true strength is its impressive and constantly evolving developer base. It's the job of recruiters to manage the growth of the
	development team by locating, approving, and managing new developers to add further innovative talent to our already strong organization.
	</longdescription>

	<dev role="lead">seemant</dev>
	<dev role="lead">avenj</dev>
	<dev description="recruiter">spyderous</dev>
	<dev description="recruiter">coredumb</dev>
	<dev description="recruiter">cybersystem</dev>


	<extrachapter>
	<title>What does it take to be a recruiter?</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>First and foremost, a recruiter needs to be a good judge of character. While most new developer sponsors pick only the best candidates,
	there have been and will be occassional duds. Recruiters need to be able to analyze an individual's background, experience, and past
	contributions, then use that information to decide whether or not to accept a developer. Remember, recruiters always have the final say
	on new developers. Never be afraid to say no, but always offer a detailed explanation of why you made that decision.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>

	<extrachapter>
	<title>What does the recruitment process involve?</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>First, an existing developer sponsors a new developer. The sponsor must be willing to be a mentor to the new developer.
	Mentors are responsible for pointing mentees to developer-related documentation, answering questions, explaining the ins and outs of
	working for Gentoo as much as possible, and assisting/supporting the new developer even past the required two week training period.
	A new developer bug must be filed by the sponsor or a recruiter. An experienced recruiter can point out excellent examples of new
	developer bugs giving all the relevant information.
	</p>
	<p>A two week probationary period for training and review begins when the new developer bug is filed, assuming it is not rejected by
	recruiters. The mentor should be in regular contact with their mentee to regularly review their work and offer suggestions and constructive
	criticism. Please note that two weeks is the absolute required minimum, but definitely not the maximum. Mentors and recruiters should both be
	confident in the new developer before proceeding.
	</p>
	<p>At the end of the two week period, a <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~avenj/quiz">questionnaire</uri> should be filled out by the mentee.
	This is not a pass/fail examination by any means. The questionnaire is intended to make sure new developers carefully read both developer policy and technical documentation.
	This should be emailed to <mail link="recruiters@gentoo.org">recruiters@gentoo.org</mail> along with a scanned 
	<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/copyright-assignment.xml">copyright assignment</uri> agreement and a SSH DSA public key.
	When recruiters and the mentor both agree that a new developer is ready and all the relevant information has been received, access to Gentoo infrastructure is granted.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>

</project>
