<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/recruiters/index.xml,v 1.101 2014/01/03 21:59:25 hwoarang Exp $ -->

<project>
<name>recruiters</name>
<longname>Gentoo Developer Recruiters</longname>

<date>2013-07-15</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dmwaters@gentoo.org">Deedra M. Waters</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Joshua Saddler</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="calchan@gentoo.org">Denis Dupeyron</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="hwoarang@gentoo.org">Markos Chandras</mail>
</author>

<description>
The recruiters subproject provides a central location for information about
developer recruitment and recruiter policy.
</description>

<longdescription><p>
Gentoo's true strength is its impressive and constantly evolving developer base.
It's the job of recruiters to manage the growth of the development team by
locating, approving, and managing new developers to add further innovative
talent to our already strong organization.
</p></longdescription>

<extraproject name="Staffing Needs" lead="Gentoo Recruiters Team">
The <uri link="/proj/en/devrel/staffing-needs/index.xml">Staffing Needs</uri>
page lists openings for new and existing developers.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Mentoring Guide" lead="Gentoo Recruiters Team">
The <uri link="/proj/en/devrel/recruiters/mentor.xml">Mentoring Guide</uri>
gives information for mentors of new recruiters.
</extraproject>

<dev role="lead">hwoarang</dev>
<dev description="recruiter">tommy</dev>
<dev description="recruiter">jlec</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>What does it take to be a recruiter?</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Recruiters need to possess several talents in order to successfully oversee
additions to the development team.  First and foremost, a recruiter needs to be
a good judge of character. While most new developer sponsors pick only the best
candidates, there have been and will be occasional duds. Recruiters need to be
able to analyze an individual's background, experience, and past contributions,
then use that information to decide whether or not to accept a developer.
Recruiters also need to be aware of the big picture in order to recognize
weaknesses in the organization and accept developers who will shore up those
weaknesses.  Remember, recruiters always have the final say on new developers.
Never be afraid to say no, but always offer a detailed explanation of the
decision.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>What does the recruitment process involve?</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
All new developers must have a mentor. This mentor will be responsible for
guiding the new developer through the new developer process and offering help to
the developer futurely. Mentors should assist by pointing the new developer to
developer-related documentation, answering questions, and explaining the ins and
outs of working for Gentoo as much as possible.
</p>

<p>
A bug must be filed for each new developer. The bug summary should be 'New
Developer (real name) (nickname).' The bug must contain the new developer's real
name, email address, and reason for joining the project.  Real names must be
provided for all developers, including infrastructure and documentation. Any
exceptions to this for extenuating circumstances will be considered on a
case-by-case basis. No exceptions will be made for people doing copyrightable
work (ebuilds, software, scripts, documentation, etc.).  The bug should also
contain who the new developer's mentors will be and any other information the
mentor wishes to provide. Please do not attach quiz answers or encryption keys
to the bug -- these should be emailed to recruiters.  The new developer and all
mentors should be CCed on the bug to keep everybody in the loop.
</p>

<p>
A developer's bug tracks his progress throughout his lifetime at Gentoo.  If the
developer retires, the initial recruitment bug is used to track all the things
that must be done to retire a dev. If the developer later returns, the same
initial recruitment bug is used to track it.  Returning developers are subject
to the same criteria as a first-time developer and must go through the same
steps to rejoin Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
The new developer will have a mentoring and evaluation period of up to a month.
This will be determined by the recruiter based on feedback from the mentor.
During this mentoring period, the mentor is responsible for providing the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz">quiz</uri>.  <!--  <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/copyright">copyright</uri> document
to the new developer.  Copyright documents should be signed, scanned, and sent
to recruiters, or optionally GPG-signed. Hand signatures are preferred. See the
copyright information page linked above for more information.--> Additionally,
new developers should be responsive to questions from recruiters during this
waiting period. If the new developer will be absent for significant periods of
time during this period, the bug should be updated to reflect this. If a new
developer is unresponsive to pings, recruiters will close the bug. Bugs closed
under these circumstances may be reconsidered at a later time.
</p>

<p>
Developers taking the quiz (linked above) should consult technical and policy
documentation for answers. Mentors may provide as much assistance as needed.
Along with the quiz <!--and copyright document-->, an OpenSSH SSH2 DSA public
key for infrastructure access should be provided to recruiters.
</p>

<p>
Developers working strictly on infrastructure, documentation, or bug-wranglers
with no CVS access to the Portage tree typically do not need to take the ebuild
quiz. Instead, a staff quiz is provided. See the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz">quiz page</uri> for more
information.
</p>

<p>
Recruiters may reject new developers if they feel it's appropriate.
Additionally, for 30 days after joining, a new developer is considered to be in
a 'probationary period' in which their mentor is responsible for actions taken
by the new developer. This provides a certain level of accountability.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Stuff to remember</title>
<section>
<title>When adding yourself to a bug</title>
<body>

<p>
I will be your recruiter. Please send your quizzes to recruiters@gentoo.org
when approved by your mentor. Always add a comment to this bug when you send
something to that address. When the quizzes are sent please contact me by IRC
or email to schedule the first review session. If you think that recruiters
aren't paying attention to this bug at any later point in time, it's your job
to ping us on IRC if you don't want any delays.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>For review session</title>
<body>

<p>
I will go through your answers, find out errors and ask some extras related
and unrelated to the quiz questions. Take your time, it's supposed to be a
learning experience as much as a test of your skills. But just tell me if
you can't absolute find something so that you don't use too much time.
</p>

<p>
After the sessions you are asked to submit a fixed versions of the quizzes so
logging the session might be prudent.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>For setting up</title>
<body>
<pre caption="Bugzilla setup comment">
What we did:
- LDAP
- bugzilla
- cvs/svn/git groups on cvs.gentoo.org
- IRC cloak
- sent you your LDAP/mail password via encrypted mail
- announcement

Automatic:
- gentoo-core
- gentoo-dev-announcement

What you need to do:
- subscribe to mailing lists with your @gentoo.org address
- request forum status bump in #gentoo-forums or by mail to
  forum-mods@gentoo.org (if you have a forums account)
- send yourself mail to check if it works
- add yourself to mail aliases ( like java@gentoo.org )
  see /var/mail/alias on dev.gentoo.org
- ask team leads to add yourself to herds.xml for the herds you want to
  join or do it yourself if you have the permission to do so
- Register to wiki.gentoo.org with your @gentoo.org e-mail address using
  the following instructions: https://wiki.gentoo.org/getting-started
- set lat and lon attributes in LDAP if you want others to know where
  exactly you are located
- set gentooIM if you want people to be able to contact you via other
  means than email
- If you want your blog to be syndicated to planet.gentoo.org, check
  http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/userrel/planet/index.xml
- contact trustees@gentoo.org for Foundation membership (optional)

For the mentor:
- You are also responsible for the commits of your recruit during the first
  month so you should watch the commits of your recruit via gentoo-commits
  mailing list.
</pre>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Steps for adding a new developer</title>
<section>
<title>1. Adding the new developer to LDAP</title>
<body>

<p>
At first, start adding the new developer to LDAP. This requires you to
<c>ssh</c> to <c>dev.gentoo.org</c> and use the <c>newdev-fill.sh</c> 
script to create the new account. This script will ask you for all 
needed information and will set the ldap attributes. You should have 
your LDAP password by hand, you will be asked for it for every LDAP 
change.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the initial UID in LDAP">
# <i>ssh dev.gentoo.org</i>
# <i>newdev-fill.sh hyakuhei</i>
</pre>
<p>
Please be aware, that as of <b>17. December 2007</b>, all dates
in LDAP should be spelled in ISO8601, meaning like this: YYYY/MM/DD
(ie. 2007/12/18).
</p>

<p>
Afterwards it should look like this:
</p>

<pre caption="Completely filled informations">
# <i>perl_ldap -b user -s hyakuhei</i>
Searching...
------------------------------------------------------------------------
dn:uid=hyakuhei,ou=devs,dc=gentoo,dc=org

             uid: hyakuhei
              cn: Robert Clark
       givenName: Robert
              sn: Clark
    userPassword: {crypt}$1$HP/3wW0V$XUMrrFeQDHiMSGDOIUAbi/
shadowLastChange: 13520
       shadowMax: 99999
   shadowWarning: 15
      loginShell: /bin/bash
   homeDirectory: /home/hyakuhei
            mail: hyakuhei@gentoo.org
                  joe.dev@mydomain.com
           gecos: Robert Clark
  shadowInactive: 15
    shadowExpire: 14883
       gidNumber: 100
       uidNumber: 2159
      gentooJoin: 2007/01/07
            herd: undefined
    gentooStatus: active
     objectClass: top
                  person
                  organizationalPerson
                  gentooDev
                  inetOrgPerson
                  posixAccount
                  shadowAccount
                  ldapPublicKey
  gentooLocation: Wales, UK
        birthday: 1984/06/29
     gentooRoles: Security/log monitoring apps, Auditing
          gpgkey: 0x2217D168
  gpgfingerprint: 4C01 D375 8AEF CB2D 3AED  3B2D 119C 7E35 2217 D168
    gentooMentor: his-mentor
    gentooDevBug: 012345
    sshPublicKey: ssh-dss AAAAB3NzaC1kc3MAAACBAKmRjZ21SqPHwRXgkWDVuLfSZ5FOSV26x\
		  aV3Fnsc68r9caDWMZyD8PAJfXUeDXYOcUt4F3ZB+VL3DQSGg4ZEf4XVoNIOVn\
		  u87QaQyMJYT+u2EPsTJv99HZJM+tGT/ng6JfnRMWYdEDAUJ6iKZLNPKt+KWH7\
		  KprlHxRUJzd1MpbsVAAAAFQD9i0iTAesG4A1PJwT232+6IxtDlwAAAIEAoVtc\
		  O/ef4pd5WdJaeneOlmaFEF+P3lBbkaomT5oFv4GI+0BS3b+C9gOV+akDpu3Fn\
		  5JREwN665P+Cnid2y3FVZY77CazbfHBpVX6elTndo1wxRYE02GxMkhqWpuMkc\
		  MChdRjhRrcLHzAh6wO64r/wd5ofciBxuP2+ilWT151frgAAACAda4optpsYWm\
		  oSwIiLqfjr+Akxvzn9LWDcJ4LI4U8wakiHgBEGlhiIE7zrmS4ZEp8vGKv/Rhk\
		  3fOU96eUsoWFyMYtYFtCv5hQBJrqhC5Ur3dvjVzbracSZytn2xrTc+AEngPXu\
		  55WN2ebq/LMMTQV0Sq2wbDc7g9Jkxr4apAGDIM= hyakuhei@gentoo.org"
    gentooAccess: dev.gentoo.org
                  cvs.gentoo.org
             lat: 3.43521
             lon: -4.2333
</pre>
<p>
The sshPublicKey has been splitted in many lines for this website, it is just one line.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>2. Granting svn/cvs/git access</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to grant access to cvs/svn/git to the newly added developer, you will need
to <c>ssh</c> to <c>cvs.gentoo.org</c> and add the username to the appropriate
groups.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding a developer to the groups cvs, svn and git">
# <i>ssh cvs.gentoo.org</i>
# <i>gpasswd -a hyakuhei cvs</i>
Adding user hyakuhei to group cvs
# <i>gpasswd -a hyakuhei svn</i>
Adding user hyakuhei to group svn
# <i>gpasswd -a hyakuhei git</i>
Adding user hyakuhei to group git
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>3. Creating the developer's account on dev.gentoo.org</title>
<body>

<p>
Now get the developer to <c>ssh</c> to <c>dev.gentoo.org</c> as the first login
will trigger the creation of his account.
</p>

<note>
Try handing the dev-to-be the full commandline like
<c>ssh hyakuhei@dev.gentoo.org</c>, in order to minimize mistakes and/or
misconfigurations. Also point developer to <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/ldap.xml">LDAP guide</uri>
 so they know how to check and change their attributes if needed.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>4. Changing the developer's bugzilla login</title>
<body>

<note>Before chaning the developer's bugzilla login email, let them decide wether
she/he wants to setup email forwarding for his Gentoo e-mail account.</note>

<p>
After the developer logged in successfully, you can proceed with the recruiter
process. Login to bugzilla, choose <c>Users</c> in the Row <b>Edit</b>.
Supplement the developer's current email adress (the one he used for bugzilla).
</p>

<p>
Change his current <c>Login name</c> to read <b>handle-name@gentoo.org</b> (in
the present case that is <b>hyakuhei@gentoo.org</b>). Hit <c>Update</c> once
you're finished with the modifications.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>5. Setting the developer cloak to gentoo/developer/account</title>
<body>

<p>
	Every developer should get a cloak in the form @gentoo/developer/account,
	where in most cases the account is the same as the nickname he uses.
</p>
<p>
	You need to ping our group contacts (mentioned in the topic) on <c>#gentoo-groupcontacts</c>
	and ask for a gentoo/developer cloak for the new dev. One of them will have to acc the
	request. After this, someone from freenode staff will change the cloak.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>6. Developer operator status in #gentoo-dev</title>
<body>

<p>
After freenode staff has changed the cloak for our new dev, he should get
+o when joining <c>#gentoo-dev</c>.
In order to make sure, the <c>AUTOOP</c> is working, kick the new developer 
from <c>#gentoo-dev</c> and wait till he rejoins. If everything is working
as it should, he will get the <b>+o</b> on join by ChanServ.
</p>

<p>
If you want to automatically give voice status (+v) in <c>#gentoo-dev</c> to a
recruit, e.g. during his/her mentoring period, use the following command:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding the developer to ChanServ's access list">
[(status)] <i>/msg ChanServ access #gentoo-dev add hyakuhei +ViA</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>7. Introducing the developer on mailing lists</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to announce the new developer, you as recruiter have the honour to
introduce him to the developer community. Write a brief introduction containing
some details about your recruitee to gentoo-dev-announce and gentoo-project.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Remaining tasks</title>
<body>

<p>
Please follow up with the developer during their first month to make sure they
are adapting well and to address any concerns.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<extrachapter>
<title>Reinstating developers</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
	For returning developers <c>gentooJoin</c> needs to have an entry for everytime they
	come back and <c>gentooAccess</c> needs to be set to <c>"active"</c>. You also need to make sure that the <c>gentooAccess</c> attribute contains at least the following two values: <c>cvs.gentoo.org</c> and <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Updating gentooJoin">
# <i>perl_ldap -b user -C gentooJoin "YYYY/MM/DD" nick</i>
</pre>
<pre caption="Updating gentooStatus">
# <i>perl_ldap -b user -M gentooStatus "active" nick</i>
</pre>
<pre caption="Updating gentooAccess">
# <i>perl_ldap -b user -C gentooAccess "dev.gentoo.org" nick</i>
# <i>perl_ldap -b user -C gentooAccess "cvs.gentoo.org" nick</i>
</pre>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Permissions needed for recruiters</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
	<li>useradmin group on cvs.gentoo.org</li>
	<li>recruiters group on dev.gentoo.org for newpasswd</li>
	<li>recruiters.group in LDAP</li>
	<li>editusers in bugzilla</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
