<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
	<name>recruiters</name>
	<longname>Gentoo Developer Recruiters</longname>
	<date>1 May 2004</date>

	<author title="Author">
   		<mail link="avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail>
	</author>
	<author title="Author">
		<mail link="dmwaters@gentoo.org">Deedra M. Waters</mail>
	</author>
	<author title="Author">
		<mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>
	</author>
	<description>
	The recruiters subproject provides a central location for information about developer recruitment and recruiter policy.
	</description>


	<longdescription>
	Gentoo's true strength is its impressive and constantly evolving
	developer base. It's the job of recruiters to manage the growth of the
	development team by locating, approving, and managing new developers
	to add further innovative talent to our already strong organization.
	</longdescription>

	<dev role="lead">dmwaters</dev>
	<dev role="lead">avenj</dev>
	<dev description="recruiter">spyderous</dev>
	<dev description="recruiter">cybersystem</dev>
	<dev description="recruiter">jhuebel</dev>


	<extrachapter>
	<title>What does it take to be a recruiter?</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>Recruiters need to possess several talents in order to successfully
	oversee additions to the development team.  First and foremost, a
	recruiter needs to be a good judge of character. While most new
	developer sponsors pick only the best candidates, there have been and
	will be occasional duds. Recruiters need to be able to analyze an
	individual's background, experience, and past contributions, then use
	that information to decide whether or not to accept a developer.
	Recruiters also need to be aware of the big picture in order to recognize
	weaknesses in the organization and accept developers who will shore up
	those weaknesses.  Remember, recruiters always have the final say on new
	developers. Never be afraid to say no, but always offer a detailed
	explanation of the decision.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>

	<extrachapter>
	<title>What does the recruitment process involve?</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>All new developers must have a mentor. This mentor will be responsible for guiding the new developer through the
	new developer process and offering help to the developer futurely. Mentors should assist by pointing the new developer
	to developer-related documentation, answering questions, and explaining the ins and outs of working for Gentoo as much
	as possible.
	</p>
	<p>A bug must be filed for each new developer. The bug summary should be 'New Developer (real name) (nickname).'
	The bug must contain the new developer's real name, email address, and reason for joining the project.
	Real names must be provided for all developers, including infrastructure
	and documentation. Any exceptions to this for extenuating circumstances
	will be considered on a case-by-case basis. No exceptions will be made for
	people doing copyrightable work (ebuilds, software, scripts, etc.).
	The bug should also contain who the new developer's mentors will be and any other information the mentor wishes
	to provide. Please do not attach quiz answers or encryption keys to the bug -- these should be emailed to recruiters.
	The new developer and all mentors should be CC'd on the bug to keep everybody in the loop.
	</p>
	<p>
	A developer's bug tracks his progress throughout his lifetime at Gentoo.
	If the developer retires, the initial recruitment bug is used to track
	all the things that must be done to retire a dev. If the developer later
	returns, the same initial recruitment bug is used to track it. Returning
	developers are subject to the same criteria as a first-time developer and
	must go through the same steps to rejoin Gentoo.
	</p>
	<p>The new developer will have a waiting period of 1 to 2 weeks. This will be determined by the recruiter based on
	feedback from the mentor. During this waiting period, the mentor is responsible for providing the 
	<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz">quiz</uri> and
	<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/copyright">copyright</uri> document to the new developer.
	Copyright documents should be signed, scanned, and sent to recruiters, or optionally GPG-signed. Hand signatures
	are preferred. See the copyright information page linked above for more information. Additionally, new developers should
	be responsive to questions from recruiters during this waiting period. If the new developer will be absent for significant
	periods of time during this period, the bug should be updated to reflect this. If a new developer is unresponsive to
	pings, recruiters will close the bug. Bugs closed under these circumstances may be reconsidered at a later time.
	</p>
	<p>Developers taking the quiz (linked above) should consult technical and policy documentation for answers. Mentors
	may provide as much assistance as needed. Along with the quiz and copyright document, an OpenSSH SSH2 DSA public key for
	infrastructure access should be provided to recruiters.
	</p>
	<p>Developers working strictly on infrastructure, documentation, or bug-wranglers with no CVS access to the Portage tree
	typically do not need to take the quiz. Some developers working on software external to the tree may need to take the quiz for
	a general sense of how Gentoo development works. This will be decided on a case by case basis by recruiters.
	</p>
	<p>Recruiters may reject new developers if they feel it's appropriate. Additionally, for 30 days after joining, a
	new developer is considered to be in a 'probationary period' in which their mentor is responsible for actions taken by
	the new developer. This provides a certain level of accountability.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>

	<extrachapter>
	<title>Steps for adding a new developer</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>Make sure that the new developer has operator status in #gentoo-dev.
	dmwaters, avenj, seemant, rac, cybersystem, and spyderous currently have
	access to add operators.</p>
	<p>Add the developer's account to dev.gentoo.org
	(emu.gentoo.org).  Check <c>/etc/passwd</c> for the last
	<b>developer</b> account.  Please note that other types of accounts
	exist and they have UIDs in different ranges.  Run
	<c>sudo /usr/sbin/superadduser</c>.  The UID should be the most recent
	incremented by one (760 if the last was 759).  The rest of the fields
	can be just defaults, other than the real name.  Set a password so that
	the user can login and change it for mail purposes.  Run
	<c>sudo /usr/bin/vim /home/(new developer name)/.ssh/authorized_keys</c>
	and paste their SSH public key there. Have them confirm that they can
	login via SSH.  If there are problems, doublecheck the SSH key.
	The developer should be told to change their password from the one you
	assigned, and then pointed to the
	<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/dev-email.xml">
	developer email how-to</uri> to set up email.</p>

	<p>If they need CVS access to the Portage tree, contact avenj,
	dmwaters or
	spyderous.  If you have the permissions to do so, login to the CVS box
	and run: <c>sudo /usr/sbin/superadduser</c> and give them the same UID
	as on the dev box.  Also make sure to add them to the <c>cvs</c> group
	(and leave them in the default users group). If you do not have access
	to the CVS server, contact avenj.</p>
	
	<p>Contact dmwaters to subscribe them to
	the gentoo-core developer-only mailing list. Additionally, if they are
	presently subscribed to any Gentoo mailing lists, they should unsubscribe
	and resubscribe with their Gentoo address.</p>

	<p>Edit their current Bugzilla login and change it to their gentoo
	account.  While you're in there, make sure their real
	name is in the Name field.  <b>Do not change their Bugzilla
	password.</b> If you do not have access to edit users in Bugzilla,
	contact avenj.</p>

	<p>Ping rac, klieber, or one of the other forums administrators to
	update their status on the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo
	Forums,</uri> if applicable. Forums accounts are not required.</p>
	<p>Finally, send an email to the
	<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml">gentoo-dev mailing list</uri>
	to introduce them to the developer and user community.  In your
	introduction, feel free to be funny, but please explicitly state their
	reason for being a developer (primary herds, other gentoo related
	projects, etc).
	</p>

	<p>Please follow up with the developer during their first month to
	make sure they are adapting well and to address any concerns.</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>
</project>
