<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide lang="en">
  <title>Why We Still Need Java 1.4</title>

  <author title="Author">
    <mail link="nichoj@gentoo.org">Joshua Nichols</mail>
  </author>
  <author title="Editor">
    <mail link="wltjr@gentoo.org">William L. Thomson Jr.</mail>
  </author>
  <abstract>
    This document provides information on why we still need Java 1.4 on 
    Gentoo
  </abstract>

  <!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
  <!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
  <license/>

  <version>1.0</version>
  <date>2006-12-08</date>

  <chapter>
    <title>Primary Reasons</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
	  There are two primary reasons for requiring Java 1.4, with regards
	  to Gentoo and building packages.
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dd>
            <ol>
              <li>
		There are still packages which don't compile when built with
		Java 1.5. In these cases, the new Java build system switches to
		a 1.4 JDK for building
              </li>
              <li>
		It is needed for packages that haven't been migrated to use
		the new Java system. This is necessary, otherwise we encounter
		the same exact problems that prompted the initial package.mask
		of Java 1.5.
              </li>
            </ol>
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>1.5 package.mask recap</title>
    <section>
      <title>Unable to build/compile</title>
      <body>
        <p>
	  Just to recap why Java 1.5 was package was package.mask'd.... It
	  really comes down to backwards compatibility, and that Java 1.5 isn't
	  100% backwards compatible with Java 1.4. Things that ran with Java
	  1.4 should still run with Java 1.5... but some things that once
	  built with Java 1.4 no longer compile with Java 1.5.
        </p>
        <dl>
          <dd>
            <ol>
              <li>
		There's a new reserved keyword with Java 1.5, enum. So where
		you used to be able to use enum as a variable name, you no
		longer can in 1.5.
              </li>
              <li>
		A number of new methods have been introduced to some abstract
		classes and interfaces. If a particular implementation doesn't
		implement the new methods, then it won't compile against Java
		1.5.
              </li>
            </ol>
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>UnsupportedClassVersionError</title>
      <body>
        <p>
	  Now, say you're using Java 1.5 to build all your packages, and then
	  you come up to a package that can't compile for one of these reasons?
	  It'd fail for one. But then you may try with Java 1.4... and all is
	  well until you see a compile error: UnsupportedClassVersionError.
	  What does this mean though?
        </p>
        <p>
	  Well, each major release of Java has it's own version of bytecode.
	  Bytecode is forward compatible, ie run 1.4 bytecode in 1.5, but not
	  backwards compatible. If you try to use 1.5 bytecode in 1.4, you will
	  see the infernal UnsupportedClassVersionError. This happens because,
	  since you were using Java 1.5, the dependencies of the package you
	  were just trying to compile with 1.4 were built with 1.5, and the
	  default behavior is to build the highest possible bytecode.
        </p>
        <p>
	  So, these are the reasons Java 1.5 was package.mask'd, and why we
	  need to use Java 1.4 for building unmigrated packages.
        </p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>


  <chapter>
    <title>How the new system helps</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
	  Here is a few reasons how the new java system helps correct the
	  situation.
	</p>
        <dl>
          <dd>
            <ul>
              <li>
		We get around the problem of enum by specifically telling the
		compiler to use source="1.4", where enum is a valid variable 
		name.
              </li>
              <li>
		We get around the changes in API by switching to a version
		where it can be compiled, until such time as the package can be 
		properly patched.
              </li>
              <li>
		Additionally, we make javac compile the lowest possible
		bytecode. So it can be used by as many other packages as
		possible.
              </li>
            </ul>
          </dd>
        </dl>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter>
    <title>I still don't want 1.4</title>
    <section>
      <body>
        <p>
	  For now you pretty much have to have a 1.4 jdk installed. Work is
	  being done to get all packages migrated to the new java system.
	  Along with testing them under 1.5, both compile and running. 
	  Which is a pretty large task, considering we still have to maintain 
	  other packages in the mean time. 
	</p>
	<p>
	  There is no time frame for when Java 1.4 will no longer be required.
	  We do welcome any help with migrating the remaining packages causing
	  the 1.4 dependency. Then testing the packages under a 1.5 jdk and jre.
	</p>
      </body>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</guide>
