<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
	<name>kde</name>
	<longname>Gentoo KDE Project</longname>
	<date>05 May 2004</date>
	<author title="Author">Caleb Tennis</author>

	<description>
		The KDE project manages the qt and kde ebuilds in gentoo
	</description>

	<longdescription>
<p>The kde project manages the qt ebuilds and kde ebuilds within gentoo. 
Currently this includes all kde applications. However, the kde 
applications will be put into function specific herds as the kde project  
can not maintain them properly as there are too many. Further many of 
the applications are not used by the kde maintainers. The project does 
however still support the teams that do manage these applications, and 
will ensure that they use the kde eclass where appropriate.
</p>
	</longdescription>
<goals>
	<p>The goal of the Gentoo KDE team is to provide working support for all
	packages supported by the KDE Project.  We also support as many underlying
	packages as necessary in order to have a properly working KDE environment.
	</p>
</goals>

	<dev role="lead">caleb</dev>
	<dev role="inactive" description="Currently unavailable">danarmak</dev>
	<dev role="member">centic</dev>
	<herd name="qt"/>
	<herd name="kde-core"/>
	<herd name="kde-other"/>

<extraproject name="Bleeding edge KDE">
	<p>We attempt to support running KDE directly from the CVS source utilizing
	a special set of ebuilds.  They are available for download from 
    <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/desktop/kde/kde-cvs.xml">here</uri>.</p>
</extraproject>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>How KDE works in portage</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>KDE 3.0.x installs into /usr/kde/3</p>
<p>KDE 3.1.x installs into /usr/kde/3.1</p>
<p>KDE 3.2.x installs into /usr/kde/3.2</p>
<p>KDE cvs installs into /usr/kde/cvs</p>
<p>3rd party applications install into /usr, NOT /usr/kde.  This
behavior can be changed by setting the KDEPREFIX variable to a different
destination directory.</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Why?</title>
<body>
<p>
This allows different minor versions of KDE as well as the cvs version to
be installed side by side in portage, and share applications.  No two KDE
versions should be aware of each other.  You can safely merge in a new
version of KDE without it unmerging an old version.  Simply change which
version you want to start in /etc/rc.conf, and the proper version of KDE
should start.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Need help?</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
The best way to get support with KDE related issues is to address your concerns
in the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">forums</uri>.  You may also submit a
bug report to the KDE team at <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo's Bugzilla
</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>

