<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>

<name>KDE</name>
<longname>Gentoo KDE Project</longname>

<date>2008-11-22</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="caleb@gentoo.org">Caleb Tennis</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="deathwing00@gentoo.org">Ioannis Aslanidis</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="philantrop@gentoo.org">Wulf Krueger</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="masterdriverz@gentoo.org">Charlie Shepherd</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="jmbsvicetto@gentoo.org">Jorge Manuel B S Vicetto</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="keytoaster@gentoo.org">Tobias Heinlein</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="gentoofan23@gmail.com">Thomas Anderson</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="scarabeus@gentoo.org">Tomáš Chvátal</mail>
</author>

<description>
The KDE project manages the KDE and Qt ebuilds within Gentoo.
</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
The KDE project consists of two teams that manage the KDE and Qt ebuilds
within Gentoo, which include all KDE applications. However, some KDE
applications might belong to function specific herds due to the fact that the
KDE project cannot maintain all of them properly, as there are too many
applications and many of them are not used by the KDE maintainers.
Nevertheless, the project does support the teams that do manage these
applications, and will ensure that they use the KDE eclasses appropriately.
</p>

</longdescription>

<goals>

<p>
The goal of the Gentoo KDE team is to provide working support for all packages
supported by the KDE Project. We also support as many underlying packages as
necessary in order to have a properly working KDE environment.
</p>

</goals>

<dev role="member">caleb</dev>
<dev role="member">carlo</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Tester: PPC64">corsair</dev>
<dev role="member">cryos</dev>
<dev role="member">deathwing00</dev>
<dev role="member">genstef</dev>
<dev role="member">jmbsvicetto</dev>
<dev role="member">keytoaster</dev>
<dev role="member">mattepiu</dev>
<dev role="member">tgurr</dev>
<dev role="member">patrick</dev>
<dev role="member">yngwin</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Herd Testers Lead">scarabeus</dev>

<extraproject name="KDE Herd Testers" link="/proj/en/desktop/kde/at/"
lead="scarabeus">
The KDE HT Project is devoted to help the developers with testing packages,
identifying issues and finding fixes.
</extraproject>

<herd name="kde" />
<herd name="qt" />

<extrachapter position="goals">
<title>Current situation</title>
<section>
<title>KDE-3.5</title>
<body>

<p>
The latest stable version of KDE in the official Portage Tree is
<b>3.5.9</b>. It has been marked stable on all stable-supporting architectures:
<b>alpha</b>, <b>amd64</b>, <b>hppa</b>, <b>ia64</b>, <b>ppc</b>,
<b>ppc64</b>, <b>sparc</b>, <b>x86</b>.
</p>

<note>
x86-fbsd currently has no stable packages and will therefore remain marked
testing/unstable. As of 2008.0 mips will only support ~arch so mips will not have
any stable KDE packages.
</note>

<p>
The latest testing version of KDE 3 in the official Portage Tree is
<b>3.5.10</b>. This version only includes split ebuilds.
</p>

<p>
If you're having problems updating to a KDE version >3.5.7, please read this <uri
link="kde-expat-upgrading.xml">FAQ</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>KDE-4.1</title>
<body>

<p>
The latest version of KDE 4 in the official Portage Tree is <b>4.1.3</b>. This
version is also only availible via split ebuilds. We're currently in the process
of requesting arch teams to keyword the ebuilds for other arches as we only tested
the ebuilds in the <b>amd64</b> and <b>x86</b> arches.
</p>

<p>
KDE 4 is not yet marked stable as we feel it isn't sufficiently stable and feature
complete - in particular when compared to KDE 3.5. At this time we estimate that
won't happen before the release of KDE 4.2 which is planned for <uri
link="http://techbase.kde.org/Schedules/KDE4/4.2_Release_Schedule">27/01/2009</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="goals">
<title>KDE4 Overlays</title>
<section>
<title>Official Gentoo KDE overlays</title>

<body>
<p>
Some additional applications are located in <e>kde-testing</e>
overlay via layman. Things in there are considered somehow stable but not yet in
the tree. Please see the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/overlays/userguide.xml">
Gentoo Overlays Users's Guide</uri> to get all information about how to use it.
</p>

<p>
If you are a bold and daring Gentoo user, you might want to try snapshot or live
versions of KDE 4 which are not in the main Portage tree.
The KDE team (mostly its Herd Testers) maintains an official KDE overlay for 
experimental releases and ebuilds, which is called <e>kde-crazy</e> in layman.
</p>
<p>
You can get support for these overlays in <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-kde">#gentoo-kde</uri> and you can help us
testing it before we move it to the tree.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>genkdesvn overlay</title>
<body>

<p>
For those beyond bold and daring but rather suicidal, live SVN ebuilds are
provided in the genkdesvn overlay, called <e>kde</e> in layman, which you'll
recognise by the version scm.
</p>

<p>
You can get all information about the overlay at the official website which
is located at <uri>http://genkdesvn.mailstation.de</uri>. You can get support
for this overlay in <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/genkdesvn">#genkdesvn</uri>.
</p>

<impo>
Although the genkdesvn overlay is called <e>kde</e> in layman, it's in no way
supported by the Gentoo KDE team. The overlay still uses this name because it
was using it in the past when the Gentoo KDE team still supported it, but today
the circumstances changed.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="goals">
<title>Meeting logs and summaries</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The KDE team used to hold regular meetings in <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-kde">#gentoo-kde</uri> on the first
Wednesday/Thursday of every month at 19:00 UTC. Whenever there is a
meeting, it will be announced together with the agenda in the topic of <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-kde">#gentoo-kde</uri>. Summaries of each
meeting will be available here, along with raw logs for public viewing.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Date</th>
  <th>Participants</th>
  <th>Log</th>
  <th>Summary</th>
</tr>
<!--<tr>
  <ti>January 04, 2009</ti>
  <ti></ti>
  <ti><uri link="meeting-logs/kde-herd-meeting-log-200.txt">200</uri></ti>
  <ti><uri link="meeting-logs/kde-herd-meeting-log-200.txt">200</uri></ti>
</tr>-->
<tr>
  <ti>December 04, 2008</ti>
  <ti>cryos, jmbsvicetto, keytoaster, patrick, scarabeus, most of the HTs</ti>
  <ti><uri link="meeting-logs/kde-herd-meeting-log-20081204.txt">20081204</uri></ti>
  <ti><uri link="meeting-logs/kde-herd-meeting-log-20081204.txt">20081204</uri></ti>
</tr> 
<tr>
  <ti>March 06, 2008</ti>
  <ti>caleb, cryos, deathwing00, genstef, ingmar, jmbsvicetto, keytoaster, philantrop, tgurr, zlin</ti>
  <ti><uri link="meeting-logs/kde-herd-meeting-log-20080306.txt">20080306</uri></ti>
  <ti><uri link="meeting-logs/kde-herd-meeting-summary-20080306.txt">20080306</uri></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>October 13, 2007</ti>
  <ti>cryos, genstef, jmbsvicetto, keytoaster, philantrop, tgurr</ti>
  <ti><uri link="meeting-logs/kde-herd-meeting-log-20071013.txt">20071013</uri></ti>
  <ti><uri link="meeting-logs/kde-herd-meeting-summary-20071013.txt">20071013</uri></ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="goals">
<title>Support and assistance</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
There are several ways to get support with KDE related issues. You can:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    Join <uri link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-kde">#gentoo-kde</uri> on the
    Freenode IRC network. You'll find some of the team members there most of
    the time.
  </li>
  <li>
    Address your concerns in the Gentoo Forums. Not all of us are avid forums
    users but many experienced users and some developers are likely to be able
    to help you.
  </li>
  <li>
    Of course, you can also file a bug report at Gentoo's Bugzilla (do not
    forget to add your <c>emerge --info</c> and the output of <c>emerge -pv
    &lt;package&gt;</c>).
  </li>
  <li>
    For your convenience, we provide a few documents about how to install KDE
    on Gentoo:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <uri link="kde-split-ebuilds.xml">The KDE Split Ebuilds HOWTO</uri>
      </li>
      <li>
        <uri link="kde-config.xml">The KDE Configuration HOWTO</uri>
      </li>
      <li>
        <uri link="kde-expat-upgrading.xml">Upgrading to KDE 3.5.7/8: Frequently
        Asked Questions</uri>
      </li>
      <li><uri link="kde4-guide.xml">KDE 4.X Guide</uri></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="goals">
<title>How *you* can help</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The main thing that needs doing is trawling through the current open bugs and
finding those that are stale, or those that have an equivalent on <uri
link="https://bugs.kde.org">KDE's Bugzilla</uri>.
</p>

<p>
You'll find a current list of open bugs here:
<uri>http://tinyurl.com/3bpdlv</uri>.
</p>

<p>
For those that are stale, you should ask if on the bug if the problem remains in
the latest version. If someone has already done this and the reporter (or
someone else experiencing the same problem) has not replied it should be marked
NEEDINFO.
</p>

<p>
Also, some bugs have been filed from people using the sabayon overlay or others.
These need to be reproduced by someone using vanilla ebuilds (i.e.,
not from an unstable overlay). Pointing this out on the bug is likely to prompt
one of us to close it as INVALID until someone can reproduce it. It would also
be nice if you could ask the reporter to report it to that overlay's bug
tracker. For Sabayon it's <uri>http://bugs.sabayonlinux.org</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Speaking of bugs - now you can become a Herd Tester, too! You'll find all the
necessary information about what a Herd Tester is and does on the <uri
link="/proj/en/desktop/kde/at/">KDE Herd Testers Project Page</uri>.
</p>

<note>
To become an HT, please read the <uri
link="/proj/en/desktop/kde/at/">document</uri> and contact the current KDE HT
lead, <mail link="scarabeus@gentoo.org">scarabeus</mail>.
</note>

<p>
Finally, it would be great to chat to you on IRC, too - this is how we normally
get to know each other. Please drop into <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-kde">#gentoo-kde</uri> and chat with us. If
you have any problems or questions, feel free to /query individual team members
or ask in <uri link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-kde">#gentoo-kde</uri>, <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-desktop">#gentoo-desktop</uri> or <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo">#gentoo</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
