<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
	<name>kde-cvs</name>
	<longname>Gentoo KDE-CVS Project</longname>
	<date>06 Aug 2004</date>
	<author title="Author">Caleb Tennis</author>

	<description>
		Live KDE cvs ebuilds - UNMAINTAINED!!!!!
	</description>

<longdescription>
<p>These are live cvs ebuilds for KDE's current CVS.  They are not present in
portage itself mostly because emerge doesn't have proper support for live cvs
ebuilds.</p>
<p>These ebuilds are released on a works-for-me basis, with minimal testing.
Please report any bugs with the ebuilds to <uri link="mailto:caleb@gentoo.org">
caleb@gentoo.org</uri>.
</p>
<p>Finally, please understand that these ebuilds are only shortcuts to compiling
KDE from cvs.  Don't use them if you wouldn't otherwise do this manually.  Because
bug reports about cvs source will inevitably make their way to the KDE devs, you
should realize that you're on the same footing as anyone using the cvs sources
directory, and <i>not</i> in the position of one whose distribution offered
packages that weren't working</p>
</longdescription>

<goals>
<p>Provide a nice interface for KDE cvs source through portage.</p>
</goals>

	<dev role="lead">caleb</dev>
	<dev role="inactive" description="Currently unavailable">danarmak</dev>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>About these ebuilds</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
A live cvs ebuild, using cvs.eclass, runs cvs to fetch the latest sources
at the unpacking stage instead of downloading a tarball like a cvs snapshot
ebuild would. Live ebuilds are simply a shortcut to fetching and building cvs
sources yourself, plus it lets portage's installed stuff database know about
the package.  There are several variables you can set in your environment or
make.conf to control the fetching process - see the cvs eclass for more information.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing</title>
<body>

<ol>
<li>Make sure you have the latest eclasses (via emerge sync)</li>
<li>Download the latest kde-cvs tarball and install the files in your
PORTDIR_OVERLAY directory.  Don't install them directory in your portage
tree as they will be overwritten with your next emerge sync.</li>
<li>If you plan to do this compiling often, make sure you are using ccache and
distcc, and have them set up in your make.conf.</li>
<li>Try an emerge.</li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Important Notes</title>
<body>

<ul>
<li>You can set your cvs server by using the ECVS_SERVER environment variable.
See the cvs.eclass for more information.</li>
<li>If you run into a compilation problem, you may need to just wait a while
and try emerging again.  KDE's cvs source breaks rather frequently.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Get the ebuilds</title>
<section>
<body><p>
The latest tarball is available 
<uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~caleb/kde-cvs-20040806.tar.gz">here</uri>.
</p>
<p>Note that I currently don't have the time to keep up with the changes to these ebuilds.
If you want to submit revised builds I can try and keep them here for people to download, but at the
moment these builds are going to stay dormant.</p>
</body></section>
<section>
<title>ChangeLog</title>
<body>

<ul>
<li>08-06-04 - Fix typo in kdelibs ebuild</li>
<li>08-03-04 - Fix startkde script; do some dep changes in kde ebuilds</li>
<li>06-09-04 - Fix k3b typo that caused borked dependency</li>
<li>05-25-04 - Fix startkde script for 3.3 and k3b dependency on mad -> madplay</li>
<li>05-05-04 - Add some new dependencies for kdenetwork, and bump Qt to version 3.3.2</li>
<li>03-03-04 - Modify Qt ebuild to update new version + incorporate changes from regular portage ebuild</li>
<li>03-03-04 - Change virtual/motif deps to x11-libs/openmotif</li>
<li>First update for this new web page.  Replaces the old one.</li>
<li>02-18-04 - Remove app-editors/quanta, replaced with kde-base/kdewebdev</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>
