<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings/summaries/2003/20031215.xml">
<title>Gentoo Managers' Meeting Summary</title>
<subtitle>9 Feb. 2004</subtitle>
<date>9 Feb. 2004</date>
<author title="Author">Grant Goodyear</author>

<abstract>This meeting began at 1800 UTC, and the guest chair was Grant
	Goodyear. The agenda items included a discussion of the proper use of -fPIC
	across the various architectures and a proposal of how to limit the
	use of suid/sgid binaries. 
	The raw 
	<uri link="/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings/logs/2004/20040209.txt">
		log</uri> is available.
</abstract>


<chapter>
	<title>The proper role of -fPIC in CFLAGS</title>
<section><body><p>
			On systems that provide shared libraries a cardinal rule is that
			code which ends up in a shared library should be compiled as
			position-independent code (PIC), while code which ends up 
			in an executable should definitely not be compiled as PIC.  The
			resolution of this problem seems simple enough: if a package 
			provides a shared library then CFLAGS should contain -fPIC, while
			if a package provides only executables then CFLAGS should not
			contain -fPIC.  The problem, of course, occurs when a program
			provides both shared libraries and executables.  In that case
			the package's build process should be smart enough to know
			what do when.  This issue has arisen because on some 
			non-x86 architectures the <e>apparent</e> fix to various
			obscure compiler errors
			has been to add -fPIC to the global CFLAGS.  The true fix,
			of course, is to fix the makefiles.
</p></body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Should suid/sgid files be (nearly) verboten in Gentoo?</title>
<section><body><p>
			Suid and guid files allow ordinary users to run programs
			with elevated permissions.  As such, these files invariably
			are potential security holes.  Unfortunately, on *nix systems
			they are also quite necessary, with the <c>passwd</c> executable
			being a prime example of a command that 
			users run that itself requires root permissions
			to do its job.  Portage already contains code to flag suid/
			sgid files, and solar has proposed that before a package is
			allowed to merge suid/sgid files into the filesystem those
			files should first be reviewed by a group of Gentoo security
			wonks.  Additional proposals include creating a list of Gentoo-
			allowed s[gu]id files, and having portage strip the s[gu]id
			flags from files unless an ebuild has RESTRICT='setid' set.
</p></body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Open Floor</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
	The issue of ebuild signing was raised, and it seems that signing-
	support is mostly in portage at the moment.  An additional discussion
	involved how to make the gcc ebuild more adaptable for people working
	on hardened-gcc.  The meeting officially adjourned at 1930 UTC, but 
	informal discussions continued until 2013 UTC.
</p>
</body></section>
</chapter>
</guide>
