<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings/summaries/2003/20031215.xml">
<title>Gentoo Managers' Meeting Summary</title>
<subtitle>26 Jan. 2004</subtitle>
<date>29 Jan. 2004</date>
<author title="Author">Grant Goodyear</author>

<abstract>This meeting began at 1900 UTC, and the guest chair was Grant
	Goodyear. The principal agenda item was the Gentoo Server effort. 
	The raw log is available 
	<uri link="/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings/logs/2004/20040126.txt">
		here</uri>.
</abstract>


<chapter>
	<title>Gentoo Server/Enterprise</title>
<section><body><p>
	Kurt Lieber announced a plan to develop an enterprise-friendly
	version of Gentoo.  The basic idea is that Gentoo Enterprise would
	be extremely stable, with quarterly sets of release ebuilds guaranteed to
	persist for at least a year.  Discussion mainly focussed on
	whether there should be a separate server portage tree, or 
	whether a server keyword would suffice as an indication of which
	ebuilds should be "cut" to form a new release.  Kurt Lieber will
	be releasing a GLEP to further develop these ideas.
</p></body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Open Floor</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
	Two developer issues were raised once the floor was opened.  The
	first was the idea of "server metapackages", proposed by iggy.
	Just as KDE and GNOME have metapackages, perhaps there should also
	be special server metapackages so that one could, for example,
	"emerge vmail" to create an already-configured virtual mail
	system.  This notion seemed to have some traction, but more work is
	clearly needed.
</p>
<p>
	Next up was additional discussion about the separate tree for 
	Gentoo Server.  Ideas tossed around included using webrsync to get
	around paranoid corporate firewalls, perhaps incorporating xdelta,
	and a kickstart-like installation tool for Gentoo.
</p>
<p>
	Weeve made (yet another) impassioned plea for devs to stop breaking
	packages on architectures not their own.  The 2.0.50_pre series 
	repoman now reports how changes will affect all architectures, so
	there really is no excuse for devs to be breaking the non-x86 trees
	anymore.
</p>
<p>
	Finally, spyderous noted that the Gentoo Installer subproject is
	now underway.  People who are interested should visit #gentoo-installer.
</p>
<p>Meeting adjourned at 2000 UTC</p>
</body></section>
</chapter>
</guide>
