<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings/summaries/2003/20031215.xml">
<title>Gentoo Managers' Meeting Summary</title>
<subtitle>12 Jan. 2004</subtitle>
<date>29 Jan. 2004</date>
<author title="Author">Alexander Gabert</author>
<author title="Editor">Grant Goodyear</author>

<abstract>This meeting began at 1900 UTC, and the guest chair was Alexander
	Gabert. Although there ended up being essentially no agenda, the
	meeting was nonetheless informative, wandering from portage issues
	to hardware. The raw log is available 
	<uri link="/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings/logs/2004/20040112.txt">
		here</uri>.
</abstract>


<chapter>
<title>Pronouncements from Carpaski</title>
<section><body><p>
	Nick Carpaski made an impassioned plea for all Gentoo developers to use our
	quality management utility "repoman" in order to
	ensure the high standard of our cvs tree.  He also announced that
	the 2.0.50_pre series of portage trees is under active development
	and needs testing.
</p></body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Need for hardware?</title>
<section><body>
<p>
	Pappy introduced this issue by asking if "...developers and
	managers feel we are in need of more bare metal to test releases
	and software more comfortably?"  The simple answer was that yes,
	we could use more hardware, especially non-x86 hardware.  That said,
	hardware is not the only bottleneck, as it is also often because
	of a lack of manpower that ebuilds linger in ~arch.  It was also
	pointed out that if portage could handle cross-compiling then
	life would be much simpler.  Right now cross-compiling is not
	a priority for the portage developers, but if anybody wants to
	work on it then the portage team would be quite welcoming.
</p>
<p>
	Discussion then turned to what should be done if Gentoo did have
	more hardware.  A reasonable first step would be a compiler farm.
	The technical details of how to use such a farm, given that root
	access would probably be needed on those machines (especially for
	kernel testing), are still rather fuzzy.  Pappy will be generating
	a GLEP to describe how remote access and authentication, perhaps
	via VPN, can be
	performed.
</p>
</body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Open Floor</title>
<section><body><p>
	No developer issues were raised.
</p>
<p>Meeting adjourned at 2056 UTC</p>
</body></section>
</chapter>
</guide>
