<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>accessibility</name>
<longname>Gentoo Accessibility Project</longname>
<date>2009-05-06</date>

<description>
  The Gentoo Accessibility Project provides a way for Gentoo developers in
  various teams to coordinate efforts to make Gentoo more accessible to
  users who have disabilities.
</description> 
 
<longdescription>
  <p>
  This project will help to make gentoo more accessible to disabled users,
  and support them as well. We intend to work closely with 
  <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/desktop">the Desktop</uri> (and
  in particular <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/desktop/gnome">the GNOME
  team</uri>), <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/kernel">the Kernel</uri>, and
  <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/base">the Base System</uri>
  teams to help resolve accessibility issues that come up with <uri
  link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/app-accessibility/orca">orca</uri> and other gnome-accessibility applications. We do not
  intend to make the applications themselves accessible. Rather, we leave that
  to the upstream authors. However, we can suggest default settings that may
  help make an application more usable to a disabled user.
  </p>
</longdescription>

<goals>
 <p>
  We can not currently support other desktop environments, because we have not
  found any others that offer usable accessibility features. <uri
  link="http://www.kde.org">KDE</uri> and others have tried, but currently
  <uri link="http://www.gnome.org">GNOME</uri> has been the most successful.
 </p>

 <p>
  We intend to help see that <uri
  link="http://www.linux-speakup.org">speakup</uri> is included and
  supported in Gentoo.
 </p>

 <p>
  We also intend to add other accessibility applications to
  portage.
 </p>

 <p>
  We aim to make the Gentoo installation process accessibility friendly as
  well.  This means that we would like to have speakup and brltty
  included on the Gentoo live cd.
 </p>

 <p>
  Currently, speakup is included on the 2007.0 x86 release of Gentoo's
  live cd, and we are working closely with the <uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng">Release
		  Engineering</uri> team to be sure that speakup and brltty are
  included on all future Gentoo live cds.
 </p>
</goals>

<dev role="lead" description="Gentoo Accessibility Project Lead">WilliamH</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="ebuild maintainer">neurogeek</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="ebuild maintainer">teiresias</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="GNOME Team Lead">leio</dev>
<dev role="Member" description="GNOME Accessibility Maintainer">dang</dev>

<herd name="accessibility"/>
<herd name="gnome-accessibility"/>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
  <title>Contacting Us</title>
  <section>
    <title>Mailing List</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        We recommend that you subscribe to the gentoo-accessibility
        mailing list; this is where accessibility-related discussions
        will take place.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>IRC</title>
    <body>
      <p>
        If you are on irc, please join us on #gentoo-accessibility on
        freenode.
      </p>
    </body>
  </section>
</extrachapter>
</project>
