<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="local-email.xml">
<title>Setting up an integrated local email delivery system</title>
<author title="Senior Developer Manager">
    <mail link="spider@gentoo.org">Spider (D.M.D. Ljungmark)</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This is a guide to setup an integrated email system for a normal 
desktop setup. It will cover Local delivery, incoming email, email 
retrieval through IMAP and spam filtering using standard unix tools.
</abstract>

<version>0.3.1</version>
<date>10 Sep 2003</date>


<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>Assumptions</title>
<body>
<p>
For this guide I will assume a lot  about your system, and simplify even more about
 the  how things work. The guide assumes that you are not running email services
for a domain, but have a normal connection to the internet where your provider 
hosts email accounts. 
</p>
</body>
</section>


<section>
<title>Tools</title>
<body>
<p> I will use some fairly standard and popular tools for this, namely 
"postfix" "procmail" "SpamAssassin" "fetchmail" and "courier-imapd"  </p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Overview</title>
<body>
<p>The configuration documented in this guide is might seem complex, but have
 been tested and has been found to be solid and flexible.</p>

<p>For locally generated email, it first goes to the smtp server, which 
delivers email to a users home directory via procmail. To gain access 
to your email, we'll setup an imap server that simply serves the same directory 
back to the user. This makes for a good solution since your email is not 
tied to a single application, and you can at your leisure try out several 
different applications. </p>

<p>Remote email is fetched with the program <c>fetchmail</c>. Fetchmail 
delivers the email to the local smtp daemon <c>postfix</c> for processing. 
Once in the smtp queue, the message is handled as an ordinary email.</p>

<p>Spam filtering is done inside procmail, and thus integrates
seamlessly into the setup.</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Preparations</title>
<body>

<p>To start with, we need to set a few USE flags. Edit 
<c>/etc/make.conf</c>  or use <c>ufed</c> to set the flags: <c>imap</c>
 and <c>maildir</c>.</p> 

<note> Since we are only installing for local delivery and configuration there 
is no need to use <c>ssl</c> or <c>smtp-before-pop</c> authentications.</note>

<p>The reader will need to know the following data:</p>
<p>I call the system <e>testhost</e>, the domain is called  <e>testdomain</e> and the user whom I normally login as <e>testuser</e>.</p>

<note>You should make sure that you give the exact names that the system reports, using the commands <c>hostname</c> and <c>domainname</c>.</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>




<chapter>
<title>Procmail</title>
<section>
<title>Installing procmail</title>
<body>
<p>Installing procmail is a simple task:</p>

<pre caption="emerge procmail">
#<i>emerge procmail</i>
</pre>
</body>
</section>


<section>
<title>Configuring procmail</title>
<body>
<p>We want to configure procmail to do the actual delivery of email into a
users home directory. Simply make sure the following exists in 
the file <path>/etc/procmailrc</path></p>

<pre caption="/etc/procmailrc">
# Use maildir-style mailbox in user's home directory
DEFAULT=$HOME/.maildir/
SHELL=/bin/sh

</pre>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>



<chapter>
<title>Postfix</title>
<section>
<title>Installing postfix</title>
<body>
<p>If at this point you get a block from the default package <c>ssmtp</c>,  
unmerge that and try again with the installation of postfix.</p>
<pre caption="installing postfix">
# <i>emerge postfix</i>
</pre>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Configuring postfix</title>
<body>
<p>Now it is time to fire up your favorite editor and find  and edit the file
<path>/etc/postfix/main.cf</path>. Please note that you should just set the following 
variables in-place, (make sure they are only set once, comment out the others) 
or things may break.</p>


<pre caption="/etc/postfix/main.cf">
myhostname = testhost.testdomain
mydomain = testdomain
inet_interfaces = localhost
home_mailbox = .maildir/
mailbox_command = /usr/bin/procmail
relayhost = smtp.myisp.com
</pre>

<note>These are the variables that are of importance. Make sure you set them, 
and do not define them more than once. </note>

<note>smtp.myisp.com is supposed to be your ISP assigned mailserver. If you have none, it should be ok to leave this empty.</note>

<p>Now it is time to configure a user to receive root's email (you don't 
read email as root, do you?). Open up <path>/etc/mail/aliases</path> and 
at the end, add the following</p>

 <pre caption="/etc/mail/aliases">
 root:                testuser
# trap decode to catch security attacks
# decode:           /dev/null
</pre>

<p>After this, it's time to run <c>/usr/bin/newaliases</c> and then we are 
ready to start.</p>

<pre caption="finishing touches">
# <i>/usr/bin/newaliases </i>
# <i>rc-update add postfix default</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/postfix start</i>
</pre>

<p>Now we can test the setup by doing:</p>

<pre caption="Using sendmail to test email delivery">
# <i>echo "Email test"  | sendmail  root@localhost</i>
# <i>ls -l /home/testuser/.maildir/new</i>
</pre>

<p>if all worked ok, there should be a file listed there. If things go
 wrong it is time to dig out <c>netstat -la</c> , <path>/var/log/mail*</path> 
and see if there are errors reported. </p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
 

<chapter>
<title>Courier-imap</title>
<section>
<title>Installing courier-imap</title>
<body>

<p>The installation here is also simple.</p> 

<pre caption="installing courier-imap">
# <i>emerge net-mail/courier-imap</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Configuring courier-imap</title>
<body>
<p>There is not much that needs to be configured with <c>courier-imap</c>. 
We want to restrict access a bit further, thus we'll bind the server to 
localhost. To do this, open <path>/etc/courier-imap/imapd</path> in editor 
of choice and change the value of <c>ADDRESS</c> to localhost, see the 
code-listing below for an example.</p>
 
<pre caption="/etc/courier-imap/imapd">
ADDRESS=127.0.0.1
</pre>

<p>Now we add courier to the default runlevel and start it</p>

<pre caption="starting the imap server">
# <i>rc-update add courier-imapd default</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/courier-imapd start</i>
</pre>

<p>To test this, open your favourite email client (If you do not have a 
favourite,  may I suggest <c>sylpheed</c>?)  and add an imap server (also 
known as an IMAP4 server). Where it specifies "hostname" simply enter 
"localhost" or "127.0.0.1". If things do not work at this point, reading 
the log files should be a good place to start.
</p>
 
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>SpamAssassin</title>
<section>
<title>Installing SpamAssassin</title>
<body>
<p>This chapter deals with how to install SpamAssassin into your system. This
 is a very flexible spam filter that will integrate smoothly into the setup we have 
in place. Its a completely optional step, but one I suggest nonetheless.</p>

<p> Lets start the installation. This will install SpamAssassin on your system, 
and configure it to run in daemon mode (which is more efficient since it will not
 try and load perl with each received email.)
<pre caption="Mail-SpamAssassin"> 
# <i>emerge Mail-SpamAssassin</i>
# <i>rc-update add spamd default</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/spamd start</i>
</pre></p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Configuring SpamAssassin</title>
<body>

<p>This title is a bit misleading, since in this case we will not change
 SpamAssassins configuration, but will only "merge" SpamAssassin into your 
system. If you wish to change the filtering behavior, you will have to look in 
<c>man spamassassin</c></p>

<p> Now open up <path>/etc/procmailrc</path> in your favourite editor and modify
 it to look as the following:</p>

<pre caption="/etc/procmailrc">
# Use maildir-style mailbox in user's home directory
DEFAULT=$HOME/.maildir/
SHELL=/bin/sh
MAILDIR=$HOME/.maildir

:0fw
* &lt; 256000
| /usr/bin/spamc -f
 
</pre>


<note> Previous versions of this document had a bad INCLUDERC that is not necessary and could actually prove harmful.</note>

<note>Also note that messages above the size of 256k are not filtered to reduce CPU overhead</note>

<p>Now its time to test the setup</p>

<pre caption="Sending a message to root to test">
# <i>echo "TEST"  | sendmail root@localhost</i>
# <i>grep X-Spam /home/testuser/.maildir/new/*</i>
X-Spam-Status: No, hits=1.0 required=5.0
X-Spam-Level: *
X-Spam-Checker-Version: SpamAssassin 2.55 (1.174.2.19-2003-05-19-exp)
</pre>
<p>Yey! It worked. </p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>





<chapter>
<title>Fetchmail</title>
<section>
<title>Installing fetchmail</title>
<body><p>Fetchmail is a program to pull email off a remote server (IMAP or
 POP3) and  the reinsert it locally for delivery. This makes all email go into
 the same place, and through the same filtering rules, which makes for easier 
 adaptation. To install :</p>
 <pre caption="install fetchmail">
# <i>emerge fetchmail</i>
 </pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuring fetchmail</title>
<body>
<p>As the user who's mail we wish to fetch, open and edit 
<path>$HOME/.fetchmailrc</path> as following:</p>
<pre caption="~/.fetchmailrc">
set postmaster "testuser"
set bouncemail
set no spambounce
set properties ""
# set daemon 300
poll ISP.MAILSERVER with proto POP3
       user 'ISP-MAILLOGIN' there with password 'MAIL-PASS' is 'testuser' here options stripcr
</pre>

<note>You have to change the following items: "testuser" into your local user. 
ISP.MAILSERVER to your remote mailserver. ISP-MAILLOGIN with the
 username you have there, and MAIL-PASS with the accounts password.
</note>

<note> Please refer to <uri link="http://www.catb.org/~esr/fetchmail/fetchmail-man.html">
 the fetchmail manual</uri> for more information</note>



<p>Now we shall test this setup in order to make sure things work as supposed.</p>
<pre caption="testing fetchmail">
# <i> fetchmail -v</i>
</pre>
<note> You have to inspect the output for eventual errors.</note>

<p>If the fetchmail configuration is working the way you want it, enable
daemon mode by removing the # in front of <e>"set daemon 300"</e></p>
<pre caption="fetchmailrc reviewed">
set no spambounce
set properties ""
set daemon 300
</pre>

<p> Now your email will automatically be retrieved and delivered to your
 local directory for reading at your leisure. To automatically start
 fetchmail when you login, add the following to your <path>$HOME/.bash_login</path>
</p>
<pre caption="~/.bash_login">
fetchmail  &gt;/dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1 
</pre>

<p>Or you can run fetchmail as a cron-job:</p>
<pre caption="crontab -e">
0 6 * * * fetchmail &gt;/dev/null 2&gt;&amp;1
</pre>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Conclusion</title>
<section>
<title> Hints and tips </title>
<body>
<p>There are many more things you can do with the tools described here
 and others. One example is the program <c>gotmail</c> which can download email
 from hotmail accounts and inject locally.  Or you can do massive email 
 filtering in your local procmail rules. You can also integrate 
 <c>bogofilter</c> into the system, or do even more filtering with specialized
 <c>procmail</c> rules.</p>

<p>The following recipe will filter out spam, then automatically sort
 the Gentoo.org mailing-lists into different folders as mail is delivered.
 Simply add it to <path>$HOME/.procmailrc</path></p>

<pre caption="example procmail recipe for Gentoo.org mailing-list">
:0:
* ^X-Spam-Status: Yes
.SPAM/

:0
* ^List-Id.*gentoo-user\.gentoo\.org
.Gentoo-User/

:0
* ^List-Id.*gentoo-dev\.gentoo\.org
.Gentoo-Devel/

 :0
* ^List-Id.*gentoo-announce\.gentoo\.org
.Gentoo-Announce/
</pre>

<p>Even more information can be found in the manuals, or on the web. </p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Training SpamAssassin</title>
<body>
<p>SpamAssassin has a built-in bayesian filter that can be trained. Since 
the spam-check is launched as the user in question, this will behave 
differently for each user, and that is one of the strenghts of bayesian filtering.
 To "teach" the filter to behave better, move all recieved spam that the
 filter -doesnt- catch into a directory called <path>uncaught</path>. The 
following snippet is an example cron-job to teach SpamAssassin about spam 
in a daily basis.</p>

<pre caption="cron-job to teach SpamAssassin">
0 0 * * * /usr/bin/sa-learn --dir --spam $HOME/.maildir/.uncaught/cur &gt;/dev/null
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Final Words</title>
<section>
<title>Final Words</title>
<body>
<note>If you have any questions or additions, please 
<mail link="spider@gentoo.org">contact me</mail> with additions or comments.</note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>


