<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/elections/trustees/index.xml,v 1.9 2013/07/16 01:13:00 jmbsvicetto Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Trustee Elections Archives</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="jmbsvicetto"/>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dabbott"/>
</author>


<abstract>
This page lists a summary of the Gentoo Trustee Elections, including the
Results for previous elections and links for each election.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>4</version>
<date>2011-11-08</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Trustee Elections</title>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Trustee Election Rules</title>
<body>

<p>
Election rules, based on <uri link="/foundation/en/">Gentoo Foundation
Bylaws</uri>:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Gentoo Board of Trustees is composed of five elected members</li>
  <li>Elections happen every year starting in February</li>
  <li>
    There should be at least three election officials plus at least one person
    assigned from Gentoo Infrastructure project to handle their side of the
    election. Officials are allowed to vote in the election but they aren't
    allowed to run in it. They are selected by the current Board of Trustees.
  </li>
  <li>
    There's one month for nominations and one month for voting. In special cases
    current Board of Trustees may decide to shorten that period. Anyone can
    nominate.
  </li>
  <li>
    All Gentoo Foundation members may vote but only members of age above 18 are
    allowed to run (legal requirement). To run in the election, a person has to
    be nominated on the <c>gentoo-nfp</c> mailing list and personally accept
    that nomination on the same list.
  </li>
  <li>
    Members who are active Gentoo developers vote using <c>votify</c> script on
    <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Members who aren't active Gentoo developers should mail their GPG-signed
    ballot files to election officials who will verify authenticity of those and
    pass them to infra so they are taken into account while counting votes.
    Special care should be taken to ensure the ballot is signed by the gpg key
    in the Foundation records.
  </li>
  <li>
    After voting period is over, all election officials verify results provided
    by Infrastructure project member assigned to the election and then post them
    to the <c>gentoo-nfp</c> mailing list.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Condorcet method of voting</title>
<body>

<p>
For both Foundation and Council elections, <uri
link="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Condorcet_method">Condorcet method of
voting</uri> is used to count votes.
</p>

<p>
To cast votes in the Trustee elections we use the program named <c>votify</c>
which is installed on <c>dev.gentoo.org</c>.
</p>

<p>
Instructions on how to use <c>votify</c> to cast a vote:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>If you're eligible to vote in that election, log in to <c>dev.gentoo.org</c></li>
  <li>Type <c>votify --new election-name</c> to create a new ballot file</li>
  <li>
    Edit <path>.ballot-election-name</path> file in your home directory and rank
    the candidates
  </li>
  <li>
    Once you're finished, use <c>votify --verify election-name</c> command to
    verify the validity of your ballot file
  </li>
  <li>
    If everything is okay, use <c>votify --submit election-name</c> to submit
    your vote for the election. Don't forget your vote doesn't count until
    you submit it.
  </li>
  <li>
    If you run into problems, you can either work them out yourself using
    <c>votify --help</c> or contact election officials and ask them for help
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Trustee Election Results</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Election</th>
  <th>Results</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>2013</ti>
  <ti><uri link="2013/foundation-2013.xml">Trustees Results</uri></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>2012</ti>
  <ti><uri link="2012/foundation-2012.xml">Trustees Results</uri></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>2011</ti>
  <ti><uri link="2011/foundation-2011.xml">Trustees Results</uri></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>2010</ti>
  <ti><uri link="2010/foundation-2010.xml">Trustees Results</uri></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>2009</ti>
  <ti><uri link="2009/foundation-2009.xml">Trustees Results</uri></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>2008</ti>
  <ti><uri link="2008/foundation-200802.xml">Trustees Results</uri></ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
