<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/gdp/index.xml">
<title>Gentoo Documentation Project</title>
<subtitle>Main Page</subtitle>
<author title="Author">
    <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
    <mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
The Gentoo Documentation Project is an official Gentoo project 
devoted to the complete and concise documentation of the Gentoo Project.
</abstract>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>21th of July 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>General Project Information</title>

<section>
<title>What we do, and who we are</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project (GDP) is an official project of the
Gentoo project responsible for the creation and maintenance of all
official Gentoo documentation. The GDP is not a closed team of any
sorts, but instead an open community commited to critiqing, and possibly
integrating, viable user documentation.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mission Statement</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project was formed to address the need of
complete documentation for Gentoo. In doing so, the GDP team
is commited to the creation and maintenance of clear, concise, and
original documentation. We will protect our users and developers by the
use of free and open licensing on all documentation. The GDP is commited
to remaining a free and open project, and will abide by the Social
Contract set forth by the Gentoo Project.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Overview</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
 <th>Section</th>
 <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="#doc_chap2">Subprojects</uri></ti>
 <ti>A listing of the Subpojects the Gentoo Documentation Project hosts</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="#doc_chap3">Project Team</uri></ti>
 <ti>An overview of the project members.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="#doc_chap4">Mailing lists</uri></ti>
 <ti>Subscription and archive information for this project's mailing lists.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="roadmap.xml">Roadmap</uri></ti>
 <ti>A listing of our current and planned projects.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Issue Tracking</uri></ti>
 <ti>Create and query bugs/features/change requests/... for the Gentoo
 Project</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>GDP Documentation</ti>
 <ti>An overview of the GDP-specific documentation</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>GDP Subprojects</title>

<section>
<title>Active Subprojects</title>
<body>

<p>
The current active subprojects in the Gentoo Documentation Project are:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
 <th>Project</th>
 <th>Project Lead</th>
 <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="core.xml">Gentoo Core Documentation</uri></ti>
 <ti><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></ti>
 <ti>Core documentation, such as the arch specific installation guides,
 and the Desktop Guide, are maintained in this project. Project members
 will work closely with many other teams in the Gentoo project hierarchy
 to make absolutely positive that our most important documentation is
 one-hundred percent correct and up to date.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="user.xml">User Application Documentation</uri></ti>
 <ti><mail link="antifa@gentoo.org">Ken Nowack</mail></ti>
 <ti>The core of the GDP team, most of the work in this subproject
 relates to the maintenance and incorportation of application centric
 documentation.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="system.xml">System Documentation</uri></ti>
 <ti><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></ti>
 <ti>The Portage documentation, rc-scripts guide, and other Gentoo
 specific documentation is covered under this subproject. The goal of
 this subproject is to completely document what makes Gentoo,
 Gentoo.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="international.xml">International Documentation</uri></ti>
 <ti><mail link="sergey@gentoo.org">Sergey Kuleshov</mail></ti>
 <ti>As Gentoo continues to grow, international documentation will be
 key to communicating with our diverse user base. The translators will
 make sure that all Gentoo documentation is translated in a timely
 fashion.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti><uri link="gdp.xml">GDP Documentation</uri></ti>
 <ti><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></ti>
 <ti>The goal of this subproject is to document everything concerning
 the GDP Project itself. This includes the GDP Policy, XML Guide,
 ...</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
The reason for this seemingly artificial division of documents is
twofold. First, the individual subprojects have seperate priorities. The
Core Documentation is the most important as most, if not all users come
in contact with it. System Documentation is a close second as it is what
makes Gentoo Gentoo, and must be documented clearly. The User
Documentation is the subproject in which most of the documentation
development will be done, but has a lower priority than the previous 2. 
</p>

<p>
The GDP Documentation should stay rather static as it describes how
documents should be make, what GuideXML is, etc. 
</p>

<p>
The International Documentation is a seperate subproject which holds all
translations. It should try to stay up to date with the previously
mentioned subprojects in the given priority.
</p>

<p>
Another reason for this division is so that some members can actually
restrict themselves to editing and reviewing documents of a certain
subproject (which means their role is restricted to that subproject).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Planned Subprojects</title>
<body>

<p>
The current planned subprojects in the Gentoo Documentation Project are:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
 <th>Project</th>
 <th>Project Promotor</th>
 <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Printable Documentation</ti>
 <ti><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail></ti>
 <ti>GDP documentation needs to be printer compatible. This subproject
 will completely oversee the planning and implementation of making GDP
 documentation printer friendly.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Documentation WiKi</ti>
 <ti><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail></ti>
 <ti>In order for developers to easily write documentation concerning
 their project, the Gentoo Documentation Project provides them with a
 WiKi site on which they can develop the documentation. When that
 document is finished, the GDP Team can start converting the document
 into GuideXML</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Man Page Creation</ti>
 <ti><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail></ti>
 <ti>There are many packages in the Portage tree that need man
 pages.</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Whenever a Gentoo Documentation Team Member thinks he's up to it (and it
doesn't harm his other responsibilities), the subprojects can become
active.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Documentation Project Team</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
In order for the GDP to become a succesfull project, we need many people
playing many roles in a coherent way. This includes documentation
writers, reviewers, translators, editors, contributors, etc.
</p>

<p>
The team is compromised of Members and Contributors. Members can have
direct access to the source of a subproject and actively participate in
the development of documentation. Contributors improve the project
through submission of documents, etc to the Members. The
number of Contributors is unbounded. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Members</title>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
 <th>Member Name</th>
 <th>Nickname</th>
 <th>Roles</th>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Ken Nowack</ti>
 <ti><mail link="antifa@gentoo.org">antifa</mail></ti>
 <ti>User Application Documentation Subproject: Project Leader</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Guillaume Morin</ti>
 <ti><mail link="arachne@gentoo.org">arachne</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: French</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Jose Alberto Suarez Lopez</ti>
 <ti><mail link="bass@gentoo.org">bass</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Spanish</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Joe Kallar</ti>
 <ti><mail link="blademan@gentoo.org">blademan</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Carl Anderson</ti>
 <ti><mail link="carl@gentoo.org">carl</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>John Christian Stoddart</ti>
 <ti><mail link="chiguire@gentoo.org">chiguire</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Spanish</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Erwin</ti>
 <ti><mail link="erwin@gentoo.org">Erwin`</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Indonesian</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>George Shapovalov</ti>
 <ti><mail link="george@gentoo.org">george</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Russian</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Jared H. Hudson</ti>
 <ti><mail link="jhhudso@gentoo.org">jhhudso</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Joshua Brindle</ti>
 <ti><mail link="method@gentoo.org">method</mail></ti>
 <ti>Strategic Manager</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Marco Mascherpa</ti>
 <ti><mail link="m.mascherpa@gentoo.org">m.mascherpa</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Italian</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Masatomo Nakano</ti>
 <ti><mail link="nakano@gentoo.org">nakano</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Japanese</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Colin Morey</ti>
 <ti><mail link="peitolm@gentoo.org">peitolm</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Egor Tashilin</ti>
 <ti><mail link="pihta@gentoo.org">pihta</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Russian</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Lars Weiler</ti>
 <ti><mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">pylon</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: German</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Robert Coie</ti>
 <ti><mail link="rac@gentoo.org">rac</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Rajiv Manglani</ti>
 <ti><mail link="rajiv@gentoo.org">rajiv</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Jungmin Seo</ti>
 <ti><mail link="seo@gentoo.org">seo</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Korean</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Sergey Kuleshov</ti>
 <ti><mail link="sergey@gentoo.org">svyatogor</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Project Leader</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Sven Vermeulen</ti>
 <ti><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">swift</mail></ti>
 <ti>Operational Manager<br />
 International Documentation Subproject: Dutch</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Tavis Ormandy</ti>
 <ti><mail link="taviso@gentoo.org">taviso</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Mike Frysinger</ti>
 <ti><mail link="vapier@gentoo.org">vapier</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>Ivan Zenkov</ti>
 <ti><mail link="zenkov@gentoo.org">zenkov</mail></ti>
 <ti>International Documentation Subproject: Russian</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>John Davis</ti>
 <ti><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">zhen</mail></ti>
 <ti></ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Contributors</title>
<body>

<p>
Listing the enormous amount of contributors to the Gentoo Documentation
Project would require one very huge page. We thank all contributors
(both retired and active) for their enormous help to the project. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Mailing Lists</title>

<section>
<title>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project makes intensive use of the
<c>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</c> mailinglist. On this mailinglist
discussions about documentation, subprojects, translations and more pass
by.
</p>

<p>
To subscribe to this mailinglist, send an empty e-mail to <mail
link="gentoo-doc-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc-subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
Once subscribed you can post to it by sending an e-mail to
<c>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</c>. To unsubscribe from the list, send an
empty e-mail to <mail
link="gentoo-doc-unsubscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc-unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
There is also an online archive on <uri
link="http://news.gmane.org/thread.php?group=gmane.linux.gentoo.documentation">news.gmane.org</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Participating</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
To participate in the Gentoo Documentation Project first join the
mailing list at <c>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</c>. Then ask if there are plans to
support something that you are interested in, propose a new subproject
that you are interested in, or choose one of the planned subprojects to
work on. You may talk to the developers and users in the IRC channel
<c>#gentoo-doc</c> on <c>irc.freenode.net</c> for more information or just 
to chat about the project or any subprojects. If you don't have the ability to
actively help by contributing work we will always need editors to
maintain the quality and accuracy of the overall product. All
development, editing, and productive comments and feedback will be
greatly appreciated.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
