<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/gdp/index.xml">
<title>Gentoo Documentation Project</title>
<subtitle>Main Page</subtitle>
<author title="Author">
   <mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John Davis</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
	The Gentoo Documentation Project is an official Gentoo Linux project devoted to the
	complete and concise documentation of Gentoo Linux.
</abstract>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>8 July 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is the Gentoo Documentation Project?</title>
	<section>
	<title>What we do, and who we are</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The Gentoo Documentation Project (GDP) is an official sub-project of the Gentoo Linux project
		responsible for the creation and maintenance of all official Gentoo Linux documentation.
		The GDP is not a closed team of any sorts, but instead an open community commited to critiqing,
		and possibly integrating, viable user documentation.
		</p>
		
		<p>
		The purpose of the Gentoo Documentation Project is to create complete and concise Gentoo centric
		documentation. Creation of Gentoo documentation can happen in many fashions. With the consent and
		assistance of the original author, documentation can be created from the
		<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri>, the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org">GDP wiki</uri>,
		(under development) or documentation from the <i>gentoo-doc</i> mailing list.
		</p>
		
		<p>
		The GDP team upholds a strict policy against plagarism. We <i>will not</i> use documentation that cannot be
		verified to an original author, as well as documentation that does not have specific consent from the
		original author.
		</p>

		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Where is the documentation?</title>
		<body>
		<p>Official Gentoo Linux documentation can be found on the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org">gentoo.org</uri>
		website, indexed at the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/docs.xml">documentation index</uri>.
		</p>

		<p>Offical GDP documentation, such as developer HOWTOs and translator HOWTOs, can be found
		at the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/doc/index.xml">GDP documentation index</uri>.
		</p>

		<p>Documentation that is in development, can be found at the
		<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org">GDP wiki</uri>, which is still under development itself.
		</p>

		<p>If you are having a problem accessing either of the aforementioned documentation, please
		post a bug on the <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo Bugtraqing system</uri>.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>GDP Subprojects</title>

<section>
<title>Active Subprojects</title>
<body>
<p>
   The current active subprojects in the Gentoo Documentation Project are:
<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>Description:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Gentoo Core documentation</ti>
		<ti>Core documentation, such as the arch specific installation guides, and the Desktop Guide,
		are maintained in this project. Project members will work closely with many other teams in the
		Gentoo Linux hierarchy to make absolutely positive that our most important documentation is
		one-hundred percent correct and up to date.
		</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>User Application documentation</ti>
		<ti>The core of the GDP team, most of the work in this subproject relates to the maintenance
		and incorportation of application centric documentation.
		</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>System documentation</ti>
		<ti>The Portage documentation, rc-scripts guide, and other Gentoo specific documentation is covered
		under this subproject. The goal of this subproject is to completely document what makes Gentoo, Gentoo.
		</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>International documentation</ti>
		<ti>As Gentoo continues to grow, international documentation will be key to communicating with
		our diverse user base. The translators will make sure that all Gentoo documentation is translated
		in a timely fashion.
		</ti>
	</tr>
</table>

</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Planned Subprojects</title>
<body>
<p>
   The current planned subprojects in the Gentoo Documentation Project are:
   <table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>Description:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Documentation submission engine</ti>
		<ti>Since most documentation is submitted by Gentoo users, there needs to be an easier way
		for the GDP team to track and edit new user documentation. This subproject will focus on
		the creation of an offical submission system and offical submission policy.
		</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Printable documentation</ti>
		<ti>GDP documentation needs to be printer compatible. This subproject will completely oversee
		the planning and implementation of making GDP documentation printer friendly. </ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Man page creation</ti>
		<ti>There are many packages in the Portage tree that need man pages.
		</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Translations</ti>
		<ti>There is a need for full time translators in all languages.
		</ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Documentation Project Developers</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Each GDP developer is listed here, along with their respective responsibilities. </p>
<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Developer Name</th>
		<th>Username</th>
		<th>Full/ Part Time</th>
		<th>Areas of Responsibilty</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>John Davis</ti>
		<ti>zhen</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Project lead</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Sven Vermuelen</ti>
		<ti>swift</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Editor/ Dutch Translator</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Jorge Paulo</ti>
		<ti>peesh</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Editor</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Ken Nowack</ti>
		<ti>antifa</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Bug Wrangler/ Editor</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Lars Weiler</ti>
		<ti>pylon</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Lead German Translator</ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To participate in the Gentoo Documentation Project first join the mailing list at <i>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</i>.
Then ask if there are plans to support something that you are interested in, propose a new subproject that you
are interested in, or choose one of the planned subprojects to work on. You may talk to the developers and users
in the IRC channel <i>#gentoo-doc</i> on <i>irc.freenode.net</i> for more information or just to chat about the
project or any subprojects. If you don't have the ability to actively help by contributing work we will always
need editors to maintain the quality and accuracy of the overall product. All development, editing, and productive
comments and feedback will be greatly appreciated.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
