<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/gdp/roadmap.xml">
<title>Gentoo Documentation Project Roadmap</title>

<author title = "Author">
    <mail link = "swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<license/>

<version>3.3</version>
<date>February 21, 2004</date>

<abstract>
A TODO list for the Gentoo Documentation Project
</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>TODO List</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The first and foremost task of the GDP is to fix bugs in documentation and make
sure that the online documentation is available and at all times current
(including translations). However, there are other tasks in which the GDP is 
involved. Most tasks are of temporary nature - you will find information on the 
progress made on these tasks in the status updates. Unfinished tasks will be 
mentioned next.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Printable Documentation</title>
<body>

<p>
The main objective of the GDP is to have the online documentation be in perfect
shape. Lots of users want to have offsite documentation too and even today most
of them are left in the cold. The GDP should work on printable documentation
(preferrably PDF), but albeit creating PDFs of its documentation isn't
difficult, the main issues are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The online available PDFs should be fully in sync with the online HTML
    documentation. This requirement translates into the fact that the
    webserver(s) should be able to generate the PDFs on-the-fly from the sources
    provided.
  </li>
  <li>
    The online available PDFs should be professionally-looking. This doesn't
    rhyme well with on-the-fly creation and more importantly, we currently don't
    have the resources to create professionally-looking PDFs.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
<mail link="plasmaroo@gentoo.org">Tim Yamin</mail> has written up a XSL-FO
stylesheet to transform the Gentoo Handbook into PDF format. Example runs can be
found online at <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~plasmaroo/handbook-test">his
dev-page</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Right now we need to fix the <c>dev-java/fop-bin</c> program so it doesn't
compile-in XFree support as we don't need it (and definitely don't want it on
our servers). When this is finished, we should be able to run a script on an
online server to regenerate the PDFs every time the Gentoo Handbook is altered.
</p>

<p>
<mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">Xavier Neys</mail> has written up XSL stylesheets
to be able to view the Gentoo Handbook in a single page, suitable for quick
printing. Regression tests are currently done to check if these stylesheets can
be used on our main Gentoo webnodes.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Moving User-Specific Documentation</title>
<body>

<p>
Many projects host documentation that can be of use for the Gentoo users. To
centralise the documentation development efforts, those documentation should be
placed under control of the GDP project. A listing of these documents is
available under the resources.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation Updates</title>
<body>

<p>
One of the most important goals of the GDP is to develop high-quality
documentation. The following is a listing of updates and rewrites we need to do
in order to keep up with the high-pace development. If a developer's name is
listed, it means that (s)he has taken the challenge :)
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Improving Desktop-related Documentation</li>
  <li>Gentoo and uDev (<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>)</li>
  <li>E-mail for SOHO</li>
  <li>Gentoo Utilities</li>
  <li>Architecture-specific Tips 'n Tricks</li>
  <li>A Troubleshooting Guide (<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>)</li>
  <li>EVMS Guide</li>
  <li>Update on Gentoo FAQ (<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>)</li>
  <li>Update on the various <path>/etc/portage</path> possibilities (<mail
  link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike Frysinger</mail>)</li>
  <li>Update on alsa-guide for 2.6 kernels</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Have documentation-related news online</title>
<body>

<p>
<mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">Xavier Neys</mail> proposed to add
documentation-related news to the website (either the documentation index or the
GDP website) on which we add items such as when documents are heavily updated
(not just fixups), new documentation written, new projects started, decisions
made, etc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
