<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>


<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/gdp/roadmap.xml">
<title>Gentoo Documentation Project Roadmap</title>

<author title = "Author">
    <mail link = "swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<license/>

<version>3.1</version>
<date>February 15, 2004</date>

<abstract>
A TODO list for the Gentoo Documentation Project
</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>TODO List</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The first and foremost task of the GDP is to fix bugs in documentation and make
sure that the online documentation is available and at all times current
(including translations). However, there are other tasks in which the GDP is 
involved. Most tasks are of temporary nature - you will find information on the 
progress made on these tasks in the status updates. Unfinished tasks will be 
mentioned next.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Printable Documentation</title>
<body>

<p>
The main objective of the GDP is to have the online documentation be in perfect
shape. Lots of users want to have offsite documentation too and even today most
of them are left in the cold. The GDP should work on printable documentation
(preferrably PDF), but albeit creating PDFs of its documentation isn't
difficult, the main issues are:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The online available PDFs should be fully in sync with the online HTML
    documentation. This requirement translates into the fact that the
    webserver(s) should be able to generate the PDFs on-the-fly from the sources
    provided.
  </li>
  <li>
    The online available PDFs should be professionally-looking. This doesn't
    rhyme well with on-the-fly creation and more importantly, we currently don't
    have the resources to create professionally-looking PDFs.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
If you are interested in helping out in this issue, don't hesitate to contact
us. At this time, we believe that FOP is the best way to go as it allows us to
process the GuideXML into XML-FO, which can then be parsed to PDF. Other options
are of course also welcomed.
</p>

<p>
A second frequently-requested feature regarding the printable documentation is
to have a one-page, show all Handbook which allows for easy printing of the
Handbook. If we cannot provide a PDF as previously mentioned this option will be
introduced. However, at this point most efforts are going to the PDF creation.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Moving User-Specific Documentation</title>
<body>

<p>
Many projects host documentation that can be of use for the Gentoo users. To
centralise the documentation development efforts, those documentation should be
placed under control of the GDP project. A listing of these documents is
available under the resources.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation Updates</title>
<body>

<p>
One of the most important goals of the GDP is to develop high-quality
documentation. The following is a listing of updates and rewrites we need to do
in order to keep up with the high-pace development. If a developer's name is
listed, it means that (s)he has taken the challenge :)
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Improving Desktop-related Documentation</li>
  <li>Gentoo and uDev</li>
  <li>E-mail for SOHO</li>
  <li>Gentoo Utilities</li>
  <li>Architecture-specific Tips 'n Tricks</li>
  <li>A Troubleshooting Guide (<mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>)</li>
  <li>EVMS Guide</li>
  <li>Update on Gentoo FAQ (<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Scherbaum</mail>)</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Fixing DTDs</title>
<body>

<p>
The current GuideXML DTDs and Handbook DTDs don't match up with what we have in
mind for GuideXML and Handbook XML usage. Even though it isn't right to fix DTDs
to go with XMLs, in this case the DTDs really are flawed. 
</p>

<p>
The DTDs need to be fixed to deal with correct GuideXML usage so we can enforce
total DTD-validity across documents.
</p>

<p>
<mail link="dertobi123@gentoo.org">Tobias Sherbaum</mail> has added this to his
TODO list.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Have documentation-related news online</title>
<body>

<p>
<mail link="neysx@gentoo.org">Xavier Neys</mail> proposed to add
documentation-related news to the website (either the documentation index or the
GDP website) on which we add items such as when documents are heavily updated
(not just fixups), new documentation written, new projects started, decisions
made, etc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
