<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>Configuration Tools Requirements</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="blubber@gentoo.org">Tiemo Kieft</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document specifies the requirements for the config tools subproject.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>March 5, 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
This document specifies the requirements for the Configuration Tools subproject.
Individual requirements are specified for every tool, describing the function
of that specific tool. Some overall requirements are specified which are met
by all tools.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Overall Requirements</title>

<section>
<title>Initial version</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
  <li>The tools can have more then one userinteface</li>
  <li>The user can select a userinterface by specifing some commandline 
    option (for example -g for a GUI)</li>
  <li>If no commandline option is specified the GUI is tried</li>
  <li>All tools can ask for the root password when necesary</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Runlevel editor</title>
<section>
<title>Initial Version</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
  <li>The runlevel editor can start services</li>
  <li>The runlevel editor can stop services</li>
  <li>The runlevel editor can restart services</li>
  <li>The runlevel editor can remove any service from any runlevel</li>
  <li>The runlevel editor can display a description for every service 
   in the list</li>
  <li>The runlevel editor can display the status for any service in 
    the list</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Network Configuration editor</title>
<section>
<title>Initial Version</title>
<body>
<p>
<ul>
  <li>The Network Configuration editor can display an overview of available
    ethernet interfaces</li>
  <li>The Network Configuration editor can add ethernet interfaces
    <ul>
      <li>Add net.* links to /etc/init.d/</li>
      <li>Edit /etc/conf.d/net</li>
      <li>Autoload the appropriate module</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>The Network Configuration editor can remove ethernet interfaces (See 
    the above)</li>
  <li>The Network Configuration editor can configure a gateway</li> 
  <li>The Network Configuration editor can edit dns settings</li>
</ul>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
