<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>Foundation Activity - Initiate Trustee Election</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail>rich0</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail>dabbott</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The Foundation Secretary initaties the annual election of trustees, and the
Trustees approve key elements of the election process.  The execution of the
election and documentation of its results are performed by the Election Team.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->
<license/>

<version>6</version>
<date>2014-06-12</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>Foundation Activity - Initiate Trustee Election</title>
<body>
<p>
The Foundation is responsible for initiating annual elections and has some
roles in the process.  The election team is responsible for carrying out the
election.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Relevant Standards and Regulatory Repositories</title>
<section>
<body>
	
<p>
The details of the Trustee Election is governed by the <uri
	link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/BylawsAdopted.xml">Bylaws</uri>.
The operation of the Election Team is documented on <uri
	link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/elections/trustees/">their page.</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Tools and Templates</title>
<section>
<body>
<ul>
<li><uri
		link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/20110202_members_list.xml">Member
		List Template.</uri></li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Roles and Responsibilities</title>
<section>
<body>
	
<p>
The Secretary is responsible for initiating the elction process, and is
reponsible for assembling the official list of members.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Official Gentoo Repository</title>
<section>
<body>
	
<p>
The Election Team maintains the official <uri
	link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/elections/trustees/">repository</uri> of
past elections.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Procedure</title>
<section>
<body>
<ol>
<li>The Secretary adds the annual election to a regular meeting of the Trustees.</li>
<li>The Trustees agree upon a recording date for membership, nomination period, and election period.  The nomination period and election period are one month, and follow the recording date.</li>
<li>The Secretary sends out the <uri link="recording_date.txt">recording date email</uri> to gentoo-project@g.o and gentoo-dev-announce@g.o.</li>
<li>The Secretary sends out the <uri link="trustee_election_nomination_email.txt">nomination email</uri> to gentoo-nfp@lists.gentoo.org, gentoo-project@g.o and gentoo-dev-announce@g.o. and gentoo-elections@g.o</li>
<li>The Secretary sends the <uri link="election_email.txt">announcement email</uri> to gentoo-foundation-announce@g.o and gentoo-nfp@g.o.</li>
<li>The Secretary notifies the election team lead of the need to hold the election.</li>
<li>During the nomination period, the Secretary publishes list of members as of the recording date, linked to the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/">foundation page</uri>.  This <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/20110202_members_list.xml">list</uri> may be used as a template.</li>
<li>Approve list of election officials.</li>
<li>Election officials execute election.  Results are considered official upon certification by the Election Team, and new Trustees take office at that time.</li>
<li>Election team updates the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/elections/trustees/">archive of election results.</uri></li>
</ol>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Contact</title>
<section>
<title>Trustees</title>
<body>
<ul>
	<li>Trustees - email, trustees at gentoo.org</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
