<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/base/amd64/status/status_20060110.xml">
<title>AMD64 Status Report</title>

<author>
  <mail link="blubb@gentoo.org">Simon Stelling</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This is the status of the Gentoo/AMD64 Project. It will be posted regularly,
but not with a static frequency.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-01-10</date>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo/AMD64 Project. It will be posted regularly,
but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail>amd64@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>

<p>
This status report is mainly concerned about the progress made between Jan 1,
2005 and Dec 31, 2005.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Status Report in Figures</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    1486 bugs assigned to <mail>amd64@gentoo.org</mail> and
    <mail>amd64-test@gentoo.org</mail> were fixed.
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/#Developers">The Gentoo/AMD64 team</uri> has
    grown from 9 developers to 32 developers. Also, we have our own <uri
    link="/proj/en/base/amd64/tests/index.xml?part=1&amp;chap=1#doc_chap1">arch
    testers team</uri> which counts 16 active volunteers. Two full releases and
    one media refresh release were made.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Release Engineering</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
In March 2005, a major step towards true multilib support was made when
releasing 2005.0. Starting from this release, the <c>multilib</c> USE flag,
mainly used by the toolchain packages, was deprecated and instead, subprofiles
should be used to control the behaviour regarding multilib-support. As a
consequence of this change, the <c>sys-libs/glibc</c> package now builds
natively both 64bit and 32bit version and the precompiled
<c>app-emulation/emul-linux-x86-glibc</c> package is no longer needed.
</p>

<p>
The change also enabled a far easier way to track dependencies for 32bit
packages through <c>multilib.eclass</c> that was written.
</p>

<p>
With 2005.0 and the profile change, a new feature called <c>multilib-strict</c>
was introduced. It is a QA tool to assure that all packages install their
libraries into the correct directories, which is essential for multilib
systems.
</p>

<p>
To make the complicated upgrade process easier for users, automated scripts and
detailed documentation were provided.
</p>

<p>
In August 2005, Gentoo 2005.1 was released. New stages and CDs were made and
the default USE flags were reviewed and cut down to a minimum.
</p>

<p>
In November, a media refresh release called 2005.1-r1 was made. It was mainly
a bugfix release to fix a few bugs in the stages and CDs, the 2005.1 profile
was kept.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Stable-profile</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
As AMD64 processors became a lot cheaper, its popularity grew enormously.
Thanks to the stable-profile- and AT-project we could ensure that the AMD64
stable profile was always up to date and almost as recent as the x86 one.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Documentation</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The documentation subproject has written multiple new documents:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-amd64-faq.xml">The Gentoo/AMD64 FAQ</uri></li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/howtos/index.xml?part=1&amp;chap=1">The
    2005.0 Upgrade Guide</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/howtos/index.xml?part=1&amp;chap=2">Howto
    file bugs</uri>
  </li> 
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/howtos/index.xml?part=1&amp;chap=3">32bit
    Chroot Guide for Gentoo/AMD64</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/tests/index.xml">The Gentoo/AMD64 Testing
    Docs</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~plasmaroo/devmanual/archs/amd64/">Arch
    Specific Notes -- AMD64/EM64T</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Since these documents cover almost all aspects of a amd64 system, the old <uri
link="/proj/en/base/amd64/technotes/index.xml">technotes</uri> could be
deprecated.
</p>

<p>
Further, a <uri link="/proj/en/base/amd64/emul/emul-content.txt">list</uri> was
put together to document the emulation packages, mainly to assure that
vulnerabilities also get fixed in the pre-compiled <c>emul-linux-x86-*</c>
packages.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo/AMD64 Arch Testers</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo/AMD64 Arch Testers subproject was founded to recruit more developers
and power-users which could help to reduce the workload significantly. The idea
turned out to be a great success: Over 25 <uri
link="/proj/en/base/amd64/tests/index.xml?part=1&amp;chap=1#doc_chap1">ATs</uri>
were recruited of which 6 became developers. To make the testing and keywording
even more efficient, <uri link="/proj/en/glep/glep-0041.html">GLEP 41</uri> was
brought up.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Donations</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
We got multiple boxes donated by AMD, which are now mainly used to offer
shell accounts to other Gentoo developers that want to test their patches
before committing them. They're also used as distcc nodes to speed up the
release engineering tasks.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
