<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Alpha/Status_Reports/20070721">
<title>Gentoo/Alpha Status Report</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="alpha@gentoo.org">Gentoo/Alpha</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo/Alpha Status Report
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2007-07-21</date>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo/Alpha porting team. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-alpha@gentoo.org">gentoo-alpha@gentoo.org</mail>.
The Gentoo/Alpha porting team, has its own project page (just like 
almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://alpha.gentoo.org/</uri>. Also you can contact us
via IRC at #gentoo-alpha on irc.freenode.net. The latest status report
can always be found on the <uri
link="/proj/en/base/alpha/status/index.xml">Gentoo Linux Alpha Status
Reports</uri> subproject page.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Index</title>
<body>

<p>
This status report will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives, 
and/or projects related to the Gentoo/Alpha porting team:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect1">Developers</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">Toolchain status</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3">New revision of aboot</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect4">Keywording and Security</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect5">Firefox and Thunderbird fixed</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect6">Alpha Arch Testers Project</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect7">Donations</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Content</title>
<section>
<title>Developers</title>
<body>

<p>
Since the last status report, some of our developers have gone and some others
have joined the Gentoo/Alpha porting project.
</p>

<p>
Developers who left the Alpha Team:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <b>Bryan Østergaard</b> (<mail
      link="kloeri@gentoo.org">kloeri</mail>)<br/>
  	  Our leader left Gentoo some time ago. He was one of the oldest alpha
	  Gentoo developers and one of the main contributors to the port. We 
	  wish him the best.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Thomas Cort</b> (<mail link="tcort@gentoo.org">tcort</mail>)<br/>
    Thomas was one of our most active developers but, had to stop his 
	contributions due to lack of time. We hope to have him with us
	again some time in the future.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
New developers, arch testers and contributors:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <b>Raúl Porcel</b> (<mail
      link="armin76@gentoo.org">armin76</mail>)<br/>
	  Raúl joined the Gentoo/Alpha porting team to help with keywording
	  and security bugs.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Brian Evans</b> (Gentoo/Alpha arch tester)<br/>
    Brian joined our arch tester program in May. He is helping with 
	keywording and bug fixing.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Tobias Klausmann</b> (Gentoo/Alpha arch tester)<br/>
	Tobias is our last addition to the team. He is also the admin
	of our main dev box.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Toolchain and Kernel development</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    <b>GCC</b><br/>
    GCC 4.1.2 is our stable version which seems to not have any problem.
	Testing with gcc-4.2 is going fine so probably will enter into 
	~alpha some time soon.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Kernel</b><br/>
    Gentoo/Alpha changed the supported sources and now, we are happy to 
	announce that <c>gentoo-sources</c> are our default kernel sources.
	Gentoo/Alpha current stable version is 2.6.21.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>C libraries</b><br/>
    glibc-2.5 is the stable version since February. There was a known 
	compiling error related to CFI in sigsuspend files. The error was fixed
	by bumping binutils version during these last weeks. The testing with
	glibc-2.6 goes just fine and it will enter in ~alpha sometime soon. 
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Binutils</b><br/>
	Gentoo/Alpha is now using an advanced version of binutils due to 
	fails with stable glibc and a bug which makes ld takes too much 
	time with some packages. 2.17.50.0.16 is the stable version after
	a heavy testing process.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New revision of aboot</title>
<body>

<p>
Due to some changes in the way the kernel headers allow to use the 
types declaration (knowing by "sanitized headers") aboot was not able
to compile against kernel headers >=2.6.19.
</p>

<p>
Aboot uses a lot of kernel structure definitions so the only quick fix 
available was to use the old headers during the building process. Mike 
Frysinger was kindly enough to provide a revision of the latest aboot
version and now we have a shiny: <c>aboot-1.0_pre20040408-r1</c> marked as 
~alpha.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Keywording and Security</title>
<body>

<p>
The keywording process has suffer a major improvement thanks mainly
to the work of armin76 and our arch testers. xorg-7.2, gnome-2.16 
and kde-3.5 are stables on alpha as well as latest versions for 
all desktop packages.
</p>

<p>
We also keep the status of security supporting arch attending all
the security bugs managed by the Gentoo Security team with a very
good response time.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Firefox and Thunderbird fixed</title>
<body>

<p>
In the previous status report, firefox and thunderbird 1.5 series were broken 
on alpha. Currently, the situation has changed and now, the latest versions
of these mozilla products are keyworded for alpha.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Alpha Arch Testers Project</title>
<body>

<p>
The Alpha Arch Testers Project was created by Fernando J. 
Pereda (<mail link="ferdy@gentoo.org">ferdy</mail>). The project is 
meant to help the Alpha Arch Team provide a stable, secure and up to 
date Gentoo Linux port by allowing users to participate in the testing 
and stabilization process. If you want to learn more about this 
excellent opportunity to give back to Gentoo, please check out the <uri
link="/proj/en/base/alpha/AT/index.xml">Alpha Arch Testers Project
Page</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Donations</title>
<body>

<p>
Hardware donations are always welcome. We will gladly accept spare alpha 
hardware. We are specially looking for desktops systems which aren't too
big to keep them in a house. That's because we lack the resources to 
test some software which needs to have physical contact with the box
(cd-writers, sound, bootloaders, kernels, etc.).
</p>

<p>
More powerful systems could be used to assist in testing packages, to provide
developers with access to alpha hardware to port applications, or to assist in
building releases. Alpha computers aren't the only hardware that we could
benifit from, other hardware components are also quite useful to improve our
developers machines.  If you would like to make a donation, please drop by
#gentoo-alpha on irc.freenode.net or send an e-mail to <mail
link="alpha@gentoo.org">alpha@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
