<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide lang="en" disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="https://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Alpha/Status_Reports/20060621">
<title>Gentoo/Alpha Status Report</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="alpha@gentoo.org">Gentoo/Alpha</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo/Alpha Status Report
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-06-21</date>

<chapter>
<title>Status Reports</title>
<section>
<title>Preliminaries</title>
<body>

<p>
This is the status of the Gentoo/Alpha porting team. It will be posted
regularly, but not with a static frequency. All questions can be posted to
<mail link="gentoo-alpha@gentoo.org">gentoo-alpha@gentoo.org</mail>.
The Gentoo/Alpha porting team, has its own project page (just like 
almost all other Gentoo projects). You can find it at
<uri>http://alpha.gentoo.org/</uri>. Also you can contact us
via IRC at #gentoo-alpha on irc.freenode.net. The latest status report
can always be found on the <uri
link="/proj/en/base/alpha/status/index.xml">Gentoo Linux Alpha Status
Reports</uri> subproject page.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Index</title>
<body>

<p>
This status report will briefly discuss the following tasks, objectives, 
and/or projects related to the Gentoo/Alpha porting team:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect1">New Developers</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">Keywording and Stabilization</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect3">Firefox and Thunderbird are Broken</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect4">Documentation Project</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect5">Alpha Arch Testers Project</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect6">New Alpha project page</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect7">Donations</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="#doc_chap2_sect8">2.6 SMP Kernels</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Content</title>
<section>
<title>New Developers</title>
<body>

<p>
Since the last status report, the following developers have joined the
Gentoo/Alpha porting project:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <b>Christel Dahlskjaer</b> (<mail
      link="christel@gentoo.org">christel</mail>)<br/>
    Christel joined the Gentoo/Alpha porting team recently to help with 
    testing kernels on SMP hardware.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Thomas Cort</b> (<mail link="tcort@gentoo.org">tcort</mail>)<br/>
    Thomas joined the Gentoo/Alpha porting team in early April to help 
    with bug fixing, keywording, documentation, and security bugs.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Chris Gianelloni</b> (<mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">wolf31o2</mail>)
    <br/>Chris joined the Gentoo/Alpha porting team recently to help 
    with testing kernels on SMP hardware.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Keywording and Stabilization</title>
<body>

<p>
Stephen Bennett (<mail link="spb@gentoo.org">spb</mail>) has continued
his work with SELinux on alpha. hardened-sources is now keyworded for
alpha. Thanks to the work of Stefaan De Roeck (<mail
link="stefaan@gentoo.org">stefaan</mail>) and others, modular X has been
keyworded and is working well on alpha. The Alpha arch team is also 
pleased to announce that we have stabilized gnome-2.12.3 and kde-3.5.2 
since the last status report.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Firefox and Thunderbird are Broken</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://mozilla.org">mozilla project</uri> has chosen to 
discontinue the development of the 1.0.x versions of firefox and thunderbird.
Since that decision, multiple security holes have been uncovered. As a 
result, we had to mask the 1.0.x versions of firefox and thunderbird 
to keep our users secure since there are no plans to fix the security 
holes.
</p>

<p>
No one on the Gentoo/Alpha team has been successful at getting the 
1.5.x versions of firefox and thunderbird to run correctly, see Bug #<uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/113944">113944</uri> and Bug #<uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/113944">131359</uri>. If you can help get 
these packages working on alpha, it would be very much appreciated.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation Project</title>
<body>

<p>
The documentation subproject has written multiple new documents:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-alpha-faq.xml">The Gentoo/Alpha FAQ</uri> -
    an FAQ intended to answer some of the most frequently asked 
    questions relating to Gentoo/Alpha and Linux/Alpha in general.
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="/proj/en/base/alpha/doc/alpha-porting-guide.xml">Alpha 
    Porting Guide</uri> - a guide intended to show C programmers how to 
    port programs written on other architectures to the Alpha architecture.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Thomas Cort (<mail link="tcort@gentoo.org">tcort</mail>) has begun work 
on an SRM console guide. It will be published in the <uri
link="/proj/en/base/alpha/doc/index.xml">documentation subproject</uri>
section of the Gentoo/Alpha project page.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Alpha Arch Testers Project</title>
<body>

<p>
The Alpha Arch Testers Project was recently created by Fernando J. 
Pereda (<mail link="ferdy@gentoo.org">ferdy</mail>). The project is 
meant to help the Alpha Arch Team provide a stable, secure and up to 
date Gentoo Linux port by allowing users to participate in the testing 
and stabilization process. If you want to learn more about this 
excellent opportunity to give back to Gentoo, please check out the <uri
link="/proj/en/base/alpha/AT/index.xml">Alpha Arch Testers Project
Page</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>New Alpha Project Page</title>
<body>

<p>
Our project page was significantly revamped by Jose Luis Rivero (<mail 
link="yoswink@gentoo.org">yoswink</mail>) and Fernando J.
Pereda (<mail link="ferdy@gentoo.org">ferdy</mail>) with the help of 
the rest of the Gentoo/Alpha team. The developer list has been 
refreshed to reflect the current team membership. We now have 
information about our subprojects too. Most subprojects now have their 
own project pages.
</p>

<ul>
  <li> 
    <uri link="http://alpha.gentoo.org/">Gentoo/Alpha Project Page</uri> 
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Donations</title>
<body>

<p>
Hardware donations are always welcome. We will gladly accept spare alpha 
hardware. Even an old AlphaServer 1000 is useful for testing installation
media and kernels. More powerful systems could be used to assist in 
testing packages, to provide developers with access to alpha hardware 
to port applications, or to assist in building releases. Alpha computers 
aren't the only hardware that we could benifit from; a SCSI or IDE DVD 
burner would allow us to test dvdrtools, PCI 802.11 NICs would allow 
us to do more extensive testing and unmask the wifi USE flag (currently 
only 1 dev has an alpha with wireless), PDAs would allow us to 
test PDA applications and unmask the pda USE flag. If you would like to 
make a donation, please drop by #gentoo-alpha on irc.freenode.net or 
send an e-mail to <mail link="alpha@gentoo.org">alpha@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>2.6 SMP Kernels</title>
<body>

<p>
The Linux kernel developers have been working hard on the Alpha port. 
SMP is functional again and has been tested by a number of developers 
and users in #gentoo-alpha. 2.6.15.1 and 2.6.16.19 have both been 
tested on SMP hardware with good results.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
