<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/proj/en/portage/glsa-integration.xml">
<title>Portage GLSA integration</title>
<author>
  <mail link="genone@gentoo.org">Marius Mauch</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document attempts to collect all information regarding the upcoming 
integration of Gentoo Linux Security Advisories into portage.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>13 Mar 2004</date>


<chapter>
<title>Overview</title>

<section>
<title>General information</title>
<body>
<p></p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Roadmap</title>
<body>
<p>The implementation will take place in the following order:</p>
<ol>
	<li>release a beta version of the GLSA handling code in gentoolkit</li>
	<li>move dependency handling code from emerge to portage.py</li>
	<li>add glsa.py to portage</li>
	<li>integrate functions from glsa-check in emerge and equery</li>
</ol>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>Current status</title>

<section>
<body>
<p>Currently we have a testing version of the proposed implementation released
in <e>gentoolkit</e> (versions 0.2.0_pre7 and higher). This implementation consists of
the general handling code (in <c>glsa.py</c>) and an interface script <c>glsa-check</c>.
While <c>glsa.py</c> will later be included in portage the interface script is only
temporary, its functionality will later be included in <c>emerge</c> and/or <c>equery</c>.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Known problems</title>
<body>
<p>Currently the following problems are known in the GLSA handling code:</p>
<ul>
	<li>The 200402-02 GLSA regarding xfree requires some functionality not
		present in portage. Because of that many systems will be shown as affected
		when they are not. As a workaround inject this GLSA.</li>
	<li>GLSAs that were released in 2003 don't follow the current DTD which is 
		required for the portage integration. Until they are converted to the new 
		DTD they will be ignored by <c>glsa-check</c>.</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>glsa-check</title>
<body>
<p><c>glsa-check</c> is included in <e>gentoolkit</e> from version 0.2.0_pre7 on.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>emerge</title>
<body>
<p>The integration into <c>emerge</c> is depending on positive test results from 
<c>glsa-check</c> and a code reorganization in <c>emerge</c> itself. This reorganization is
mandatory to avoid redundant and wasted work and to reduce complexity.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>equery</title>
<body>
<p>The <c>equery</c> implementation depends on including <c>glsa.py</c> in portage
and has therefore not been started yet.</p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>


</guide>
