<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/ati-faq.xml,v 1.48 2010/07/13 20:08:03 nightmorph Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Linux ATI FAQ</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="lu_zero@gentoo.org">Luca Barbato</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="peesh@gentoo.org">Jorge Paulo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="blubber@gentoo.org">Tiemo Kieft</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Joshua Saddler</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This FAQ should help users avoid some common installation and configuration
issues related to DRI and X11 for ATI boards.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>2</version>
<date>2010-07-13</date>

<chapter>
<title>Hardware Support</title>
<section>
<title>Is my ATI board supported?</title>
<body>

<p>
Many ATI boards (but not all) are supported by <uri
link="http://www.freedesktop.org/Software/xorg">xorg-x11</uri>, at least for the
2D accelerated features. The 3D support is provided either by xorg-x11, or by
ATI's <uri
link="http://mirror.ati.com/support/drivers/linux/radeon-linux.html">closed
source drivers</uri>. ATI's closed source driver only supports R600 and newer
GPUs. Older GPUs will use the mature open source xorg-x11 driver.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>GPU</th>
  <th>Common Name</th>
  <th>Support</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Rage128</ti>
  <ti>Rage128</ti>
  <ti>xorg</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>R100</ti>
  <ti>Radeon7xxx, Radeon64</ti>
  <ti>xorg</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>R200, R250, R280</ti>
  <ti>Radeon8500, Radeon9000, Radeon9200</ti>
  <ti>xorg</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>R300, R400</ti>
  <ti>Radeon 9500 - x850</ti>
  <ti>xorg</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>R500</ti>
  <ti>Radeon X1300 and higher</ti>
  <ti>xorg</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>R600</ti>
  <ti>RadeonHD 2000 series</ti>
  <ti>ATI DRI, xorg</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>RV670</ti>
  <ti>RadeonHD 3000 series</ti>
  <ti>ATI DRI, xorg</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>RV770</ti>
  <ti>RadeonHD 4000 series</ti>
  <ti>ATI DRI, xorg</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>R800</ti>
  <ti>RadeonHD 5000 series, "Evergreen"</ti>
  <ti>ATI DRI, xorg</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>
  I have an All-In-Wonder/Vivo board.  Are the multimedia features supported?
</title>
<body>

<p>
You don't need to use anything special for the board's multimedia features;
<c>x11-drivers/xf86-video-ati</c> will work just fine.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I'm not using an x86-based architecture.  What are my options?</title>
<body>

<p>
X11 support on the PPC or Alpha platforms is quite similar to x86 X11 support.
However, ATI's closed source Catalyst drivers are not supported on the PPC or
Alpha, so you will have to use the open source drivers. The Catalyst drivers are
only available for x86 and AMD64. The open source xorg-x11 drivers should work
well on all architectures.
</p>

<impo>
To enable agpgart support for certain old AMD64 chipsets, you have to disable
support for the K8 IOMMU.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I have a laptop. Is my ATI Mobility model supported?</title>
<body>

<p>
It should be, but you may have a configuration issue due to the OEM PCI id that
such chips may have. In such cases, you may have to write the configuration
file yourself.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Installation</title>
<section>
<title>Packages</title>
<body>

<p>
There are two ways of getting drivers for your ATI card:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>The <c>xorg-x11</c> ebuild provides the X11 implementation</li>
    <li>
    The <c>ati-drivers</c> ebuild provides the ATI closed source X drivers and
    kernel modules
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
If you want to use ATI's <e>internal</e> agpgart support instead of the Linux
kernel one, the agpgart driver and the chip set specific driver (in your kernel
configuration) must be built as modules or not at all.
</p>

<note>
Please read the <uri link="/doc/en/dri-howto.xml">Hardware Acceleration
Guide</uri> for more information on installing drivers for your ATI graphics
card.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
You may not need to manually create <path>xorg.conf</path> or modify it. Try
running without it first. You can also use the Xorg auto configuration option:
</p>

<pre caption="Autoconfiguring X">
# <i>X -configure</i>
</pre>

<p>
For more information on how to get a basic <c>xorg.conf</c> configuration file,
please refer to the <uri link="/doc/en/xorg-config.xml">Gentoo X Server
HowTo</uri>.
</p>

<note>
You can use <c>aticonfig</c> if you have installed the <c>ati-drivers</c>
package.
</note>

<note>
PPC users could use the <c>Xorgautoconfig</c> stand-alone configuration tool by
emerging the <c>Xorgautoconfig</c> ebuild, but isn't required.
</note>

<impo>
If you're using <c>ati-drivers</c>, then you'll need to disable <c>radeonfb</c>
(and probably any other framebuffer drivers) in your kernel config, as it
conflicts with the built-in framebuffer in <c>ati-drivers</c>.
</impo>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Switching to OpenGL</title>
<body>

<p>
Once X is installed, configured, and running, it can use the ATI OpenGL
libraries:
</p>

<pre caption="Running eselect">
# <i>eselect opengl set ati</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>More Resources</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Please read the <uri link="/doc/en/dri-howto.xml">Hardware Acceleration
Guide</uri> for more information on configuring your ATI graphics card.
</p>

<p>
More information on Gentoo Linux and the ATI Radeon binary drivers can be found
on the <uri
link="http://odin.prohosting.com/wedge01/gentoo-radeon-faq.html">Wedge
Unofficial Gentoo ATI Radeon FAQ</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
