<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/gdp/doc/doc-policy.xml">

<title>Gentoo Linux Documentation Policy</title>
<author title="Author">
    <mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John P. Davis</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
    <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
    <mail link="spyderous@gentoo.org">Donnie Berkholz</mail>
</author>

<license/>

<abstract>
This document contains the Gentoo Documentation Policy, which is the
base document which all Gentoo Documentation developers and
Contributers should know and exercise.
</abstract>

<version>2.1.9</version>
<date>4th of August 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Linux Documentation team aspires to create exceptionally 
professional documentation that is immediately clear and concise to the 
end user. In order to fulfill this goal, we have very specific rules and 
guidelines that <e>all</e> documentation must go through before it is 
published on our website, or otherwise.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Covered Topics</title>
<body>

<p>
This policy will cover these topics: 
</p>

<ul>
<li>Documentation Project Team Organization</li>
<li>Documentation Guidelines</li>
<li>Documentation Team Recruitement</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Documentation Project Team Organization</title>

<section>
<title>Organization</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project Team is split into several smaller teams
that operate in complete cooperation with each other. Each smaller team
represents an active development team of a Gentoo Documentation
Subproject.
</p>

<p>
The Gentoo Documentation Project is strategically lead by a top-level 
manager as required by the 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/management-structure.xml">Gentoo Management Structure</uri>. 
This document also describes the responsibilities of the strategic manager with
respect to Gentoo Linux.
</p>

<p>
For day-to-day managerial tasks the Gentoo Documentation Project has an
operational manager. This person keeps track of all
documentation-related tasks that are more short-term. The operational
manager and strategic manager can be one and the same if the strategic
manager wishes so.
</p>

<p>
Currently these positions are taken by the following people:
</p>

<table>
 <tr><th>Position</th><th>Developer Name</th><th>Developer Nick</th></tr>
 <tr><ti>Strategic Manager</ti><ti>Joshua Brindle</ti><ti><mail
 link="method@gentoo.org">method</mail></ti></tr>
 <tr><ti>Operational Manager</ti><ti>Sven Vermeulen</ti><ti><mail
 link="swift@gentoo.org">swift</mail></ti></tr>
</table>

<p>
Every subproject has a strategic manager of its own. He or she can
have an operational manager if he or she deems appropriate. His
responsibilities to the Gentoo Documentation Project are the same as are
listed on the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/management-structure.xml#doc_chap1_sect6">Gentoo Management Structure</uri>.
</p>

<p>
The subprojects of the Gentoo Documentation Team together with their
respective strategic managers are listed on the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp">GDP Website</uri>. 
</p>

<p>
The decision on adding subprojects is in hands of the strategic manager. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation Project Team Members</title>
<body>

<p>
Every member of the Gentoo Documentation Project must be subscribed to
the <mail link="gentoo-doc-subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</mail>
mailing list. This mailing list will be used to discuss all
documentation-related issues. This mailing list is open to all interested
parties, developer or not.
</p>

<p>
Every member of the Gentoo Documentation Project must be subscribed to
the <mail link="docs-team@gentoo.org">docs-team@gentoo.org</mail> alias.
This alias is <e>only</e> used by <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>
to inform the documentation team about bugs regarding the Gentoo
Documentation.
</p>

<p>
Every member of the Gentoo Documentation Team should be available at
<c>#gentoo-doc</c> on <uri link="http://www.freenode.net">irc.freenode.net</uri>
whenever he or she is online. He or she should inform <c>#gentoo-doc</c> about
changes made to the CVS he or she made.
</p>

<p>
Depending on her/his responsibilities, he or she can have limited CVS 
access to <c>cvs.gentoo.org</c>. CVS access can only be given to Gentoo
developers. A listing of who has CVS access to what is available at the
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/">GDP Website</uri>.
</p>


</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Documentation Translation Teams</title>
<body>

<p>
Every language should be backed up by an official translation team. This
team is lead by a lead translator and perhaps a follow-up lead translator, who 
both have CVS commit access. If for any reason the lead translator cannot
perform his or her duties, the follow-up lead translator is in charge. If
even this person is unavailable, the mentor(s) is/are in charge of the language.
</p>

<p>
If a translated document is contributed, but the language in itself is
not supported, the Gentoo Documentation Team will not publish it
officially. In this case the document will stay on <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri> until an official
translation team of that language is formed.
</p>

<p>
When a language is officially supported, but the team doesn't have any
members or no one wants to take on the responsibilities of the lead
translator, all links to the documents will be removed from the site.
However, the documents will stay available in case the language becomes
officially supported again.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Documentation Guidelines</title>

<section>
<title>Legal Issues</title>
<body>

<p>
Every document published by the Gentoo Documentation Project must be
licensed by the <uri link="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License</uri>. 
</p>

<p>
Every document must have the following tag inside its GuideXML
sourcecode before starting with <c>&lt;chapter&gt;</c>:
</p>

<pre caption = "Licensing notice for the Gentoo Documentation">
&lt;license/&gt;
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Bugs and Updates</title>
<body>

<p>
Every bug reported on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>
should be handled as fast as possible. If a bug cannot be handled 
in a timely fashion, the reporter of that bug should be informed about
this using a comment on the bug. The tactical or operational manager can 
decide that a bug has a higher priority and should be handled first before any 
other task the assingee is responsible of.
</p>

<p>
Whenever a Gentoo Documentation Team member takes care of a bug, he or
she should assign the bug to herself/himself, but make sure that
<c>docs-team@gentoo.org</c> is on the Cc-list. Unless with the consent
of the operational manager, a bug may not be taken away from another
Gentoo Documentation Team member without his/her approval.
</p>

<p>
Whenever a translation is started, a bug must be filled in on <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri> describing what
guide is going to be translated in what language. The subject of the bug
must contain the language and document filename. It should be filed
against <c>Docs-developer</c> or <c>Docs-user</c> with <e>Translated
Documentation</e> as component. When the translation is finished, the
document itself must be available as an attachment to the bug.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Document Development</title>
<body>

<p>
Every document the Gentoo Documentation Team develops can be developed
as the related parties see fit. However, when the document is finished,
it should be transformed into <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">GuideXML</uri>.
</p>

<p>
When a new document is started or a change is needed, a bug should be filed 
at <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>
concerning the development of this document. If there is already a bug
in the database that requests a change to the documentation, a new bug
does not have to be filed. However, grammatical or syntactical changes
do not require a bug to be filed on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reviewing and Committing</title>
<body>

<p>
When a change to the document is technical or intrusive in nature, or is
a translation of an existing document, the revised document, along with the
associated bug number must be posted to the <c>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</c> 
mailing list for review. This step is incredibly important, as it ensures the
technical accuracy of our documentation. The document in question 
<e>cannot</e> be committed to CVS unless it is submitted for review and
approved.
</p>

<p>
The person(s) reviewing the document must place a comment on the
bugreport stating that they are now reviewing the document. This comment
plays the role of a "lock", meaning that other reviewers should not
start reviewing before the current reviewer has done its task (otherwise
clashes could occur). After finishing the review, the reviewers should state 
their name and Gentoo e-mail on the reviewed document using the following code:
</p>

<pre caption = "Reviewed mark">
&lt;author title = "Reviewer"&gt;
    &lt;mail link = "your.email@gentoo.org"&gt;Your Name&lt;/mail&gt;
&lt;/author&gt;
</pre>

<p>
The reviewed document should be attached to the bug on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>.
It is <e>this</e> document that should be committed to CVS.
</p>

<p>
If the change/ bugfix is grammatical or syntactical in nature, all that
is needed is a short note to <c>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</c> stating the
bug number if applicable, and the fix. No reviewing is needed in this
case. However, the person in charge of committing the document to CVS is
responsible for its syntactical correctness.
</p>

<p>
If you do not have CVS access, check the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp">GDP Website</uri> to find out
who does, and ask him to commit the document for you. 
</p>

<p>
If you have CVS access, be sure to wait until the document has been
reviewed (if appropriate). 
</p>

<p>
In case of a translation, the lead translator of the language is
responsible for the document. Only he or she may commit the document to CVS
unless he or she is currently "in training," in which case his or her
mentor should commit it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Documentation Team Recruitement</title>

<section>
<title>Contributors, Authors, Translators</title>
<body>

<p>
Everyone interested in contributing documentation, editing existing
documentation, writing new documentation or translating documentation is
welcome to join the team. There are no rules or strings attached to
this. Just make sure you are subscribed to <c>gentoo-doc@gentoo.org</c>
and you have fully read this policy and understand it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Documentation Developer</title>
<body>

<p>
As a Gentoo documentation developer should know everything in the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/policy.xml">Gentoo Policy</uri>
even though you're not submitting ebuilds. You should also have read the
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-release-policy.xml">Gentoo Release Policy</uri>
and <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/management-structure.xml">Gentoo Management Structure</uri>.
This is all needed to ensure our userbase that no Gentoo developer gives
wrong information about critical things.
</p>

<p>
Contact the operational manager of the Gentoo Documentation Project. He
will ask you for your coordinates and other information and then arrange 
a mentor for you who will guide you through the first days or weeks as
developer.
</p>

<p>
You will be given a Gentoo e-mail address and be appointed to one or
more subprojects. During the initial days or weeks, you should ask your
mentor as much as possible, preferably have him double-check everything
you do. If your function requires CVS access, you will only receive it
when your mentor deems it appropriate. Until then, your mentor is in
charge of the CVS commits.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reviewers and Editors</title>
<body>

<p>
Reviewing documents should not be held lightly. You are responsible for
reviewing a final document and make sure that it has no errors in it. We
know that no one is perfect, but we do require a Best Effort. You should
also already be known to the Gentoo Documentation Project as an
active contributor.
</p>

<p>
In order to become a Gentoo reviewer or editor you must be a Gentoo
developer.
</p>

<p>
During your "training" period you are a reviewer and should act upon it.
All guidelines regarding reviewing apply.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>(Follow-Up) Lead Translator</title>
<body>

<p>
Becoming a (follow-up) lead translator shouldn't be held lightly. You are
responsible for every translated document and final reviewing. The lead
translator will make certain that the translated documents are
grammatically and syntactically perfect. 
</p>

<p>
In order to become a Gentoo (follow-up) lead translator you must be a Gentoo
developer.
</p>

<p>
During your "training" period you are a (follow-up) lead translator and 
should act upon it. All guidelines regarding (follow-up) lead translators 
apply.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
