<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/en/doc-developer-guide.xml">

<title>Gentoo Linux Documentation Developer Policy</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John P. Davis</mail></author>
<abstract>
	This guide is a HOWTO for the Gentoo Linux Documentation Team.
	This guide will cover all of the basics of writing documentation
	for the Gentoo Linux Project, and it will be a contact point
	for new developers.
</abstract>

<version>1.0.1</version>
<date>6 January 2002</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Overview</title>
		<section>
			<title>Introduction</title>
			<body>

			<p>If you are reading this guide, then you are either a new documentation developer, or someone that wishes
			to contribute to the project. First, I would like to thank you for contributing to the Gentoo Linux project.
			Part of our goal is to create documentation that is easily accesible to the public. Our format is easily
			learned, so you will not have a hard time with the XML language. For more information on our XML format,
			please go <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">here</uri>.
			</p>
		
		</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>What This Guide Will Cover</title>
			<body>

			<p>This guide will cover these items: </p>
			<li>Developer Responsibilities </li>
			<li>Formatting Conventions </li>
			<li>Document Encoding </li>
			<li><c>xmllint</c> and <c>xsltproc</c> Tutorials </li>
			<li>Gentoo.org website overview </li>
			<li>CVS commits </li>
			<li>Contact Lists </li>
			

			</body>
		</section>
	
	</chapter>
			
<chapter>
	<title>Developer Responsibilities</title>
		<section>
			<title>Responsibilities and Ethics</title>
			<body>

			<p>Even if you are not a developer, these guidelines still apply to you. If you are
			a developer, these guidelines should be your Gentoo Bible. There was much consideration
			put into these policies, and you are urged to follow them, and, if necessary contest them.
			</p>

			<p>The first thing that <i>every</i> developer should do is read the
			<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/policy.xml">Official Gentoo Linux Policy</uri>.
			This document is the collaboration of all of the developers, and it contains some
			extremely important information.
			</p>

			<p>As a documentation developer, you should <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml">subscribe
			</uri> to the <c>gentoo-doc</c> mailing list.
			There is a lot of information that is contained on this list, and it is a good idea to keep
			updated what is going on.
			</p>

			<p>When you commit something to CVS, it is <e>EXTREMELY</e> important that what you commit is fully 
			functional and correctly proofread. I cannot stress how important it is that your documents
			are correct in every way. If you fail to proofread your documents, and consistently commit
			broken XML, there will be repercussions, such as revocation of CVS access.
			</p>

			<p>It is your duty as a developer to check and complete your bugs on the buglist.
			Everyone pulls their own weight on the Gentoo Project. If you have a question, ask
			another developer, more often then not, they will be more than happy to assist you.
			Not addressing your bugs is a serious offense, and can lead to revocation of developer status.
			</p>

			<p>Most importantly, respect your other developer colleagues.
			</p>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
	<title>Formatting Conventions</title>
		<section>
			<title>Formatting</title>
			<body>

			<p>Just like any well written program, it is very important that some formatting conventions are
			followed while writing Gentoo Linux Documentation. Let's start at the beginning of the document.
			<e>Every</e> document that is written for the Gentoo Linux project must have these headers at the
			top.
			</p>

				<pre caption = "Required Headers">
&lt;?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd"&gt;
				</pre>

			<p>The first line ensures that the interpreter knows what version of XML it has to translate and what
			character encoding scheme it has to use. I will discuss character encoding later in this guide, but 
			as of November 2002, <e>all</e> Gentoo Linux documentation is to adopt the UTF-8 (Unicode) encoding
			scheme. </p>

			<p>The second line specifies the path where the DTD conversion sheet is. An explanation of the definition
			of a DTD Guide is out of the scope of this document, but if you are inquiring, you can
			definately do some <uri link="http://www.google.com">research</uri> and get back to the rest of us.
			</p>

			<p>The next line is very important. This sets the location of the document, and it must be set.
			</p>

			<note>This is the opening guide tag, check the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">
				XML guide</uri> for more information. 
			</note>
			
			<pre caption = "Guide Link">
<comment>Replace x with the name of your document. </comment>
&lt;guide link = "/doc/your_country_code/x.xml"&gt;
			</pre>

			<p>All "&lt;pre&gt;" tags are to have captions that adequately describe their contents.
			</p>

			<pre caption = "Examples">
&lt;pre caption = "This is what my pre contains"&gt;
			</pre>

			<p>Like any well-written programming code, it is expected of documentation developers to properly
			indent their XML code with tabs. This has not been done much in the past,
			but it needs to be done in the future. This increases readability, and it is
			Just Good Programming (tm) practice.
			</p>

			<p>You are required to write your name into the doc if you have made many changes to it.
			The "&lt;author&gt;" tags are to be used as follows: 
			</p>
				
				<li>If you are the original author, your title is "Author". </li>
				<li>If the original author is no longer present, and you have assumed his/her position,
					your title is "Contributor". If you get prior permission to assume author status,
					you may do so, keeping the original author listed as "Original Author".
				</li>
					
				<li>If you have made substansive changes to the document, your title is "Editor". </li>
				<li>If you have made grammatical changes to the document, your title is "Copyeditor". </li>
				
			<p>Organize your document. Coordinate your main points and sub points. Documentation that comes
			from Gentoo is to be professionaly laid out. Not only does this look good, it helps overall 
			readability. Make good use of Chapter/Section delineation, it makes navigation by the drop down
			box very easy.
			</p>

			<p>Use proper capitalization to recognize significance. i.e. gentoo linux == Gentoo Linux, kde = KDE, gnome	= GNOME, etc.
			</p>

			<p><e>MOST IMPORTANTLY</e>, read the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/xml-guide.xml">
			Gentoo XML Guide</uri>. There is a lot of important information contained within, and it should
			be read by <i>anybody</i> writing Gentoo Linux Documentation.
			</p>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Document Encoding</title>
		<section>
			<title>Unicode (UTF-8)</title>
			<body>

				<p>As of mid-November 2002, all of the new Gentoo Linux documentation is to be encoded in
				UTF-8. I will not go into the wonderful world of character encoding, but UTF-8 is an international
				standard that is recognized by any good browser. We are working on upgrading the old docs to
				UTF-8, and hopefully, sometime next year (2003), all documentation will be UTF-8 compliant.
				</p>

			</body>
		</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>XMLLINT and XSLTPROC quickie Tutorials</title>
		<section>
			<title>Using XMLLINT and XSLTPROC</title>
			
			<body>

			<p>Before commiting anything dealing with documentation,
			your documents <e>must</e> be checked/verified with <c>xmllint</c> and <c>xsltproc</c>. 
			<c>xmllint</c> is more or less a syntax checker, and <c>xsltproc</c> is a full fledged
			XML-->HTML conversion engine.
			</p>

			<p>Using <c>xmllint</c> is simple:
			</p>

			<pre caption = "Using xmllint">
# <c>xmllint doc.xml</c>
<comment>It may be nice to use the --format switch, as it makes the output nicer. </comment>
			</pre>

			<p>Basically, if there are errors in your doc, <c>xmllint</c> will catch them and report them to
			you.
			</p>

			<p><c>xsltproc</c> is a bit harder to use, but it is not that hard. <c>xsltproc</c> is used in the
			following fashion:
			</p>

			<pre caption = "Using xsltproc">
# <c>xsltproc /path/to/the/xsl/guide/guide.xsl your_doc.xml > output.html </c>
			</pre>

			<p>Of course, there are more options that can be used with both of these tools, and I urge
			you to explore those. The instances that I gave are just the basic ones that will check your 
			documents for you.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>The Gentoo.org Website</title>
		<section>
			<title>Overview</title>

			<body>

			<p>The Gentoo.org website is a constantly dynamic and evolving webpage. Our website is based on a XML/XSL
			conversion system. If you have not noticed (eek), our whole website is coded in XML. Our XML
			code is transformed on the fly by a nice server-side kit named Axkit. In other words, every time 
			that a XML document is requested, it is transformed on the fly into HTML. Now you can see why
			document accuracy is so important. If there is an error in the page's XML, it will simply
			not display. Again, make absolutely sure that your XML is flawless.
			</p>
		
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Organization</title>

			<body>

			<p>The Gentoo.org website can be found in the <c>gentoo-src</c> tree, under the <c>gentoo-xml</c>
			branch. All commits to documents are made in <path>gentoo-xml/doc/your_lang/</path>. Follow
			the naming convention of the files that are in the directory. If you are commiting in a new
			language that we do not yet have, contact a Senior Developer, and they will assist you in 
			setting it up.
			</p>

			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Bugzilla Commits (Non-CVS)</title>
		<section>
		<title>Commiting Documents via Bugzilla</title>

		<body>

		<p>If you do not have CVS access, you must commit your docs using <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Bugzilla</uri>.
		Create a bug, and assign it to <i>docs-team@gentoo.org</i>. Please attach your guide in XML format to the bug.
		</p>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>CVS Commits</title>
		<section>
		<title>Commiting Documents via CVS</title>

		<body>

		<p>For our documentation commits, we use plain old <c>cvs commit</c>. It is required of you to
		make a relevant good commit comment. We do not keep changelogs of the documents
		(that may change in the future), so we rely on the CVS commit comments. Remember that you
		are liable for what you commit to CVS. In other words, don't commit broken XML! You will face the
		wrath of Seemant and myself (not to mention the rest of the doc team).
		</p>

		<p>If you have any questions on CVS, please consult the 
		<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/cvs-tutorial.xml">CVS Tutorial</uri>.
		</p>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Documentation Contact List</title>
		<section>
		<title>Contact List</title>

		<body>

		<p>If you have any questions, please consult the people below:
		</p>

		<table>
		<tr><th>IRC Nick</th><th>Real Name</th><th>Duties</th></tr>
		<tr><ti>ZhEN</ti><ti><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John P. Davis</mail></ti><ti>Documentation Coordinator, Bug squasher, most everything
		(tm)</ti></tr>
		<tr><ti>stocke2</ti><ti><mail link="stocke2@gentoo.org">Eric Stockbridge</mail></ti><ti>Website, Vi expert, website coordination</ti></tr>
		<tr><ti>nakano</ti><ti><mail link="nakano@gentoo.org">Masatomo Nakano</mail></ti><ti>Japanese Documentation</ti></tr>
		<tr><ti>Seo</ti><ti><mail link="seo@gentoo.org">Seo</mail></ti><ti>Korean Documentation</ti></tr>
		<tr><ti>rajiv</ti><ti><mail link="rajiv@gentoo.org">Rajiv</mail></ti><ti>Gentoo-PPC Documentation</ti></tr>
		</table>

		<p>If I have forgotten anyone, I am sincerely sorry! I have included all of the major developers at this
		time. Do not hesitate to contact us if you have any questions. 
		</p>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
