<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>


<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link = "/doc/en/gentoo-security.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Security Guide</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="kn@insecurity.dk">Kim Nielsen</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor"><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John P. Davis</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor"><mail link="stocke2@gentoo.org">Eric R. Stockbridge</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor"><mail link="carl@gentoo.org">Carl Anderson</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor"><mail link="peesh@gentoo.org">Jorge Paulo</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor"><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<license/>

<abstract>
This guide is step-by-step guide for hardening Gentoo Linux.
</abstract>

<version>0.4.1</version>
<date>August 20th, 2003</date>

-- Introduction start --

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>Who should read this guide?</title>
<body>

<p>
People who are using Gentoo Linux in a server based environment and/or feel the need for more or paranoid security.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Credits</title>
<body>

<p>
Kim Nielsen
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Special thanks</title>
<body>

<p>
A special thanks goes to the following people for finding various bugs, spelling mistakes and sentence structure.
</p>

<p>
Bjarke Sørensen, Justin Lambert, Andreas Waschbuesch, Duncan Lissett, Sherman Boyd, Sami Dalouche and Väinö Järvelä.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Enhancements for Next Release of this Guide:</title>
<body>

<p>
In version 0.6 (Backup)
</p>
<ul>
<li>Arpwatch</li>
<li>Full system backup using Systemimager</li>
<li>Partial backup using tar</li>
<li>Backing up postgres</li>
</ul>


<p>
In version 0.8 (Penetration testing)
</p>
<ul>
<li>Remote audits</li>
<li>Network audits</li>
<li>Host audits</li>
<li>Software audits</li>
</ul>

<p>
In version 1.0 (After a compromise)
</p>
<ul>
<li>How to report an incident</li>
<li>Forensics analysis</li>
<li>Creating an image of the system without destroying evidence (Using dd)</li>
<li>Trap and trace (Using tcpdump)</li>
<li>.. More to come ..</li>
<li>Restoring system</li>
</ul>

<note>
Please note that each version concentrates on one subject at a time.  This is for
quality assurance purposes.
</note>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

-- Introduction end --

-- Considerations before installation start --

<chapter>
<title>Pre-Installation Concerns</title>
<section>
<title>Physical Security</title>
<body>

<p>
No matter how many safeguards you implement, it can all be easily circumvented if
the attacker can gain physical access to your box.  Make sure your hardware is not
casually accessible. For example, you may want to place your box
in a locked server closet.  Locking cases is a good idea too.  For the highest level
of security set your BIOS to restrict booting to your hard drive only.
Disable booting from the floppy and CD-ROM drive.  For the paranoid, enabling the
BIOS password is a good idea.  BIOS passwords are also a good idea for laptop users.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Daemon/Service Planning</title>
<body>

<p>
Document what services the machine should run or is supposed to run. This will help
you compose a better partition scheme for the system.  It can also make your
intrusion detection strategy much easier.
</p>

<p>
Of course you should not document this if you only have one or a few computers and
you are the only one using them.
</p>

<p>
Example:
</p>

<p>
The Computer is supposed to act as a firewall. What services should it run?
</p>

<p>
<e>none</e>, except maybe ssh.
</p>

<p>
Document this and the current version of SSH - it will help you keep track of which system to upgrade in case someone finds a security hole in sshd. This will also aid in determining who should have access to the system.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Partitioning Schemes</title>
<body>

<p>
Golden rules:
</p>

<ul>

<li>
Any directory tree a user should be able to write to (/home and /tmp /var), should be on a separate partition and use disk quotas. Portage uses /var/tmp to compile files so that partition should be large. This reduces the risk of a user filling up your "/" mount point.
</li>

<li>
Any directory tree where you want to install non-distribution software should be on a separate partition. According to the <uri link="http://www.pathname.com/fhs/">File Hierarchy Standard</uri>, this is <path>/opt</path> or /usr/local. If these are separate partitions, they will not be erased if you have to reinstall the system.
</li>

<li>
Try to move static data to its own partition, and mount that partition in read-only mode. If you're really paranoid you could try storing static data on read-only media like CDROMs.
</li>

</ul>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>The root user</title>
<body>
<p>
The user 'root' is the most vital user on the system and should not be used for anything except if it's necessary. If an attacker gains root access you can no longer trust your system, so reinstall.
</p>

<p>
Golden rules about 'root'
</p>

<ul>

<li>
Always create a user for everyday use and if this user needs to have root access, add the user to the group wheel. This makes it possible for a normal user to su to root.
</li>

<li>
Never run X or any other user application as root.
</li>

<li>
Always use absolute paths when logged in as root. It's possible to trick root into running a different application than he thinks he is using. For example if someone tampered with the PATH and root su's without using <c>su -</c>. Then root will use the path of the user.
</li>

<li>
If a user only needs a few commands instead of everything that root normally can do, consider using sudo, but be careful with this!
</li>

<li>
Never leave the terminal when you are logged in as root.
</li>

</ul>

<p>
Gentoo has general protection against normal users, trying to su. The default PAM setting states that a users has to be a member of wheel in order to be able to su.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Policies</title>
<body>
<section>
<title>Why policies are needed</title>
<body>

<p>There are several reasons why policies are needed.</p> 

<ul>

<li>
You cannot claim to have a secure network without a definition of what you think is secure.
</li>

<li>
It's almost impossible to catch potential attackers, resolve network problems, or conduct audits, without spying on network traffic or looking in private home directories. And spying without the users agreement is illegal in most countries. And since about 60% of all attacks currently come from inside the organization, it's important that you keep an open eye.
</li>

<li>
You cannot expect your users to think about security, if you never explained why it was important or how they should protect themselves and their colleagues.
</li>

<li>
Good guidelines and network documentation always pays off, no matter what.
</li>

<li>
Police or federal law enforcement can't help you catch the attacker, if they don't know your network configuration or the services that you provide.
</li>

<li>
What will you do when there has been an attack? You need to define what you are going to do and who you are going to tell about it. Are you just going to call the police/a CERT team on every occasion? They won't take you serious!
</li>

</ul>

<p>
This should clearly state why it is important to create policies on systems with more than one user and why it's important to educate users.
</p>

<p>
A policy is a document (or several documents) with answers to questions like who, where, why and what.
Every user on your system/network should read, understand and sign it. It is important that you take the time to help the users understand the policy and why the policy needs to be signed or what will happens if they act directly against the policy (the policy should also state this). This should be repeated at least once a year since the policy can change but also as a reminder to the user.
</p>
<note>Create policies that are easy to read and be very clear/specific on every subject.</note>

<p>
Most parts of a policy can be enforced directly in the operating system or through firewalls and others cannot.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Security policies</title>
<body>

<p>
A security policy is basically a set of rules that will insure your network/host security. It is basically a document containing information on how computer, network, password, email and even how users should or should not behave, how to act then attacked, how machines (workstation/servers) are installed, infrastructure etc.
</p>

<p>
A security policy should at least contain the following subjects:
</p>

<ul>

<li>Acceptable use.</li>
<ul>
  <li>Screen savers.</li>
  <li>Password handling.</li>
  <li>Download of software.</li>
  <li>Knowledge of if they are being monitored.</li>
  <li>Use of anti-virus software.</li>
  <li>etc.</li>
</ul>

<li>Handling of sensitive information (any written form, paper or digital).</li>
<ul>
  <li>Clean desk and locked up classified information.</li>
  <li>PC shutdown before leaving.</li>
  <li>Use of encryption.</li>
  <li>Handling of keys to trusted co-workers.</li>
  <li>Handling of classified material when traveling.</li>
</ul>

<li>Handling of computer equipment when traveling.</li>
<ul>
    <li>Laptop handling during travels and hotel stays.</li>
</ul>

</ul>

<p>
The policy for the IT-staff might be a bit different then the normal users.
</p>

<p>
The security policy can become huge, and vital information can easily be forgotten. The IT-staff's policy could contain information that is classified for the ordinary user, so it is wise to split it up into small policies; i.e. Acceptable Use Policy, Password policy, Email policy and Remote Access policy.
</p>

<p>
Examples of policies can be found at the <uri link="http://www.sans.org/newlook/resources/policies/policies.htm">The SANS Security Policy Project</uri>. If you have a small network and think these policies is to much you should look at <uri link="http://www.cis.ohio-state.edu/cgi-bin/rfc/rfc2196.html">RFC2196</uri> which is a site security handbook.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

-- Considerations before installation end --

-- Tightening the security after/during installation start --

<chapter>
<title>Tightening the security after/during installation</title>
<section>
<title>/etc/make.conf</title>
<body>

<p>
The make.conf file contains all the options and extra libraries that you want to have support for when building ebuilds. In this file you must make sure that if the ebuild supports any security library like PAM (Pluggable Authentication Modules), tcp wrappers or SSL (Secure Socket Layer) it will add support for it. Your global USE variable should contain pam, tcpd and ssl.
</p>

<p>
So add something like this:
</p>

<pre caption="USE settings to be added">
USE="tcpd pam ssl"
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>GRUB/LILO password</title>
<body>
<section>
<title>GRUB</title>
<body>

<p>
Grub supports 2 different ways of adding password restriction to its configuration file (<path>/boot/grub/grub.conf</path>). One with plain text password and one with md5+salt encryption.
</p>

<pre caption="/boot/grub/grub.conf">
timeout 5
password changeme
</pre>

<p>
This will add the password <e>changeme</e> and if no password is entered simply use the default boot setting.
</p>

<p>
When adding a md5 password, you need to convert the password into crypt format (man crypt) which is the same format as the shadow file. For example could the encrypted password <e>changeme</e> look like this <e>$1$T7/dgdIJ$dJM.n2wZ8RG.oEiIOwJUs.</e>
</p>

<p>
Or this:
</p>

<pre caption="/boot/grub/grub.conf">
timeout 5
password --md5 $1$T7/dgdIJ$dJM.n2wZ8RG.oEiIOwJUs.
</pre>

<warn>
When testing this, remember to insert the timeout. Otherwise you will not be able to boot the system, if your password is incorrect.
</warn>

<p>
The timeout on 5 seconds becomes very handy if the system is remote and should be able to reboot without any keyboard interaction. More on Grub passwords can be found by executing <path>info grub</path>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>LILO</title>
<body>

<p>
LILO also supports two ways of handling passwords: global and per-image, both in clear text.
</p>

<p>
The global one is set in the top of the configuration file:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/lilo.conf">
password=changeme
restricted
delay=3
</pre>

<p>
Otherwise simply add it to an image.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/lilo.conf">
image=/boot/bzImage
      read-only
      password=changeme
      restricted
</pre>

<p>
If the <e>restricted</e> option is not entered, it will prompt for password, every time.
</p>

<p>
In order to store the new information in lilo.conf you need to run <c>/sbin/lilo</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Restricting Console Usage</title>
<body>
<p>
<path>/etc/securetty</path> contains terminal types that enables/allows you to specify which TTY devices root is allowed to login in from.
</p>

<p>
We suggest that you comment out all lines except vc/1. This will ensure that root only can login once and only on one terminal.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/securetty">
vc/1
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>More logging</title>
<body>

<p>
Extra logging should be added to catch warnings or errors that might warn of an attack in progress or an already deployed attack. Attackers often scan or probe networks before attacking.
</p>

<p>
Its also vital that the log files are easy readable and manageable.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo Linux lets you choose between 3 different loggers when installing.
</p>

<section>
<title>Syslogd</title>
<body>

<p>
Syslogd is the most common logger for Linux and Unix in general. It does not come with log rotation. This feature is handled by running <path>/usr/sbin/logrotate</path> in a cron job and properly configured settings in <path>/etc/logrotate.conf</path>. How often log rotation should be done depends on the system load.
</p>

<p>
Here is an example of how you can configure syslog
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/syslog.conf">
*.=debug                   /var/log/debug
*.err                      /var/log/syslog

#Users who should the see message if they are logged in.
*.=alert                   root,<c>your user name here</c>
*.=emerg                   root,<c>your user name here</c>

mail.info,mail.notice      /var/log/maillog
kern.*                     /var/log/kern.log
daemon.info;daemon.notice  /var/log/daemon.log
cron.*                     /var/log/cron.log
mail.*                     /var/log/mail.log
user.*                     /var/log/user.log
uucp.*                     /var/log/uucp.log
*.*;auth,authpriv.none     /var/log/syslog

#Place the log file in 2 places
authpriv.*;auth.*          /admin/auth.log
authpriv.*;auth.*          /var/log/secure

#Write everything on the console
*.*                        /dev/tty12

#Or setup a remote logging server
*.*                        @logserver
</pre>

<p>
The attacker will most likely try to erase their tracks by editing or deleting the log files. You can make it harder for the attacker by sending the log to one or more logging servers on different machines.
</p>

<p>
More info about syslogd can be found in the man page (<path>man syslog</path>)
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Metalog</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://metalog.sourceforge.net">Metalog</uri> by Frank Dennis is not able to log to a remote server, but it does have advantages when it comes to performance and logging flexibility.
</p>

<p>
It can log by program name or by facility (like syslogd) and comes with regular expression matching and execution of commands. Very good for taking action when needed.
</p> 

<pre caption="/etc/metalog.conf">
maxsize  = 1000000
maxtime  = 86400
maxfiles = 7
minimum  = 7

Kernel messages :

  facility = "kern"
  logdir   = "/var/log/kernel"

Auth messages :
  facility = "auth"
  logdir   = "/var/log/auth"

Critical :
  facility = "critical"
  command  = "/usr/local/sbin/pwdfail.sh"  

Crond :

  program  = "crond"
  logdir   = "/var/log/crond"
  
Password failures :

  regex    = "(password|login|authentication)\s+(fail|invalid)"
  regex    = "(failed|invalid)\s+(password|login|authentication)"
  regex    = "ILLEGAL ROOT LOGIN"
  logdir   = "/var/log/pwdfail"
  command  = "/usr/local/sbin/pwdfail.sh"

SSH Server :

  program  = "sshd"
  logdir   = "/var/log/sshd"

Mail :

  facility = "ftp-mail-news"
  logdir   = "/var/log/mail"

Snort:
  program   = "snort"
  command  = "/usr/local/sbin/pwdfail.sh"

Everything important :

  facility = "*"
  logdir   = "/var/log/everything"

Everything very important :

  facility = "*"
  logdir   = "/var/log/critical"

</pre>

<p>
This is basically a standard configuration with a few modifications, like a minimum logging level at 7, which means that everything will be logged.
</p>

<p>
pwdfail.sh for postfix.
</p>

<pre caption = "postfix' pwdfail.sh">
#! /bin/sh
echo "$3" | mail -s "Warning (program : $2)" root
</pre>

<p>
pwdfail.sh for qmail.
</p>

<pre caption = "qmail's pwdfail.sh">
#!/bin/sh
echo "To: root
Subject:Failure (Warning: $2) 
$3
" | /var/qmail/bin/qmail-inject -f root
</pre>

<p>
More information can be found in the <uri link="http://metalog.sourceforge.net">metalog</uri> website.
</p>


</body>
</section>
<section>

<title>Syslog-ng</title>
<body>

<p>
Syslog-ng provide some of the same features that syslog and metalog has with a small difference. It can filter messages based on level and content (like metalog), provide remote logging like syslog, handle log from syslogd (even streams from Solaris, write to a TTY, execute programs and it can act as a logging server. Basically it is the best of both loggers combined with advanced configuration.
</p>

<p>
A classic configuration file slightly modified.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/syslog-ng/syslog-ng.conf">
options { long_hostnames(off); sync(0); };

#source where to read log
source src { unix-stream("/dev/log"); internal(); };
source kernsrc { file("/proc/kmsg"); };

#define destinations
destination authlog { file("/var/log/auth.log"); };
destination syslog { file("/var/log/syslog"); };
destination cron { file("/var/log/cron.log"); };
destination daemon { file("/var/log/daemon.log"); };
destination kern { file("/var/log/kern.log"); };
destination lpr { file("/var/log/lpr.log"); };
destination user { file("/var/log/user.log"); };
destination mail { file("/var/log/mail.log"); };

destination mailinfo { file("/var/log/mail.info"); };
destination mailwarn { file("/var/log/mail.warn"); };
destination mailerr { file("/var/log/mail.err"); };

destination newscrit { file("/var/log/news/news.crit"); };
destination newserr { file("/var/log/news/news.err"); };
destination newsnotice { file("/var/log/news/news.notice"); };

destination debug { file("/var/log/debug"); };
destination messages { file("/var/log/messages"); };
destination console { usertty("root"); };
destination console_all { file("/dev/tty12"); };
destination xconsole { pipe("/dev/xconsole"); };

#create filters
filter f_auth { facility(auth); };
filter f_authpriv { facility(auth, authpriv); };
filter f_syslog { not facility(authpriv, mail); };
filter f_cron { facility(cron); };
filter f_daemon { facility(daemon); };
filter f_kern { facility(kern); };
filter f_lpr { facility(lpr); };
filter f_mail { facility(mail); };
filter f_user { facility(user); };
filter f_debug { not facility(auth, authpriv, news, mail); };
filter f_messages { level(info..warn) 
	and not facility(auth, authpriv, mail, news); };
filter f_emergency { level(emerg); };

filter f_info { level(info); };
filter f_notice { level(notice); };
filter f_warn { level(warn); };
filter f_crit { level(crit); };
filter f_err { level(err); };
filter f_failed { match("failed"); };
filter f_denied { match("denied"); };

#connect filter and destination
log { source(src); filter(f_authpriv); destination(authlog); };
log { source(src); filter(f_syslog); destination(syslog); };
log { source(src); filter(f_cron); destination(cron); };
log { source(src); filter(f_daemon); destination(daemon); };
log { source(kernsrc); filter(f_kern); destination(kern); };
log { source(src); filter(f_lpr); destination(lpr); };
log { source(src); filter(f_mail); destination(mail); };
log { source(src); filter(f_user); destination(user); };
log { source(src); filter(f_mail); filter(f_info); destination(mailinfo); };
log { source(src); filter(f_mail); filter(f_warn); destination(mailwarn); };
log { source(src); filter(f_mail); filter(f_err); destination(mailerr); };

log { source(src); filter(f_debug); destination(debug); };
log { source(src); filter(f_messages); destination(messages); };
log { source(src); filter(f_emergency); destination(console); };

#default log
log { source(src); destination(console_all); };
</pre>

<p>
Very easy to configure but also very easy to miss something in the configuration file since it is huge. The author still promises some extra features like encryption, authentication, compression and MAC (Mandatory Access Control) control. With these options it will be a perfect for network logging. since the attacker cannot spy on the log.
</p>

<p>
And syslog-ng does have other advantages. It does not have to run as root!.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Mounting of partitions</title>
<body>

<p>
When mounting an ext2, ext3 or a reiserfs partition, you have several options you can apply to the <path>/etc/fstab</path>. The options are:
</p>

<ul>

<li>
nosuid - Will ignore the SUID bit and make it just like an ordinary file.
</li>

<li>
noexec - Will prevent from executing files from this partition.
</li>

<li>
nodev - Ignores devices. 
</li>
</ul>

<p>
Unfortunately these settings can easily be circumvented by executing a non-direct path. However setting /tmp to noexec will stop about 99% of all script kiddies since their exploits are designed to be executed directly from /tmp.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/fstab">
/dev/sda1 /boot ext2 noauto,noatime 1 1
/dev/sda2 none swap sw 0 0
/dev/sda3 / reiserfs notail,noatime 0 0
/dev/sda4 /tmp reiserfs notail,noatime,nodev,nosuid,noexec 0 0
/dev/sda5 /var reiserfs notail,noatime,nodev 0 0
/dev/sda6 /home reiserfs notail,noatime,nodev,nosuid 0 0
/dev/sda7 /usr reiserfs notail,noatime,nodev,ro 0 0
/dev/cdroms /cdrom0 /mnt/cdrom iso9660 noauto,ro 0 0
proc /proc proc defaults 0 0
</pre>
<warn>Placing <path>/tmp</path> in noexec mode can prevent certain scripts from executing properly</warn>
<note>Disk quotas is described in another chapter</note>

<p>
Note that I do not set <path>/var</path> in noexec or nosuid even if files normally is never executed from this mount point. The reason for this is that qmail is installed in <path>/var/qmail</path> and must be allowed to execute and access 1 suid file. I setup <path>/usr</path> in read-only mode since I never write anything there unless I want to update Gentoo. Then I remount the file system in read-write mode, update and remount again.
</p>

<note>Even if you do not use qmail, Gentoo still needs the executable bit set on <path>/var/tmp</path> since ebuilds are made here. But an alternative path can be setup if you insists on having <path>/var</path> in noexec mode.
</note>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>User/group limitations</title>
<body>

<section>
<title>/etc/security/limits.conf</title>
<body>

<p>
Controlling resource limitations can be very effective when trying to prevent a local DoS or handling the maximum allowed logins for a group or user.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/security/limits.conf">
*    soft core      0
*    hard core      0
*    hard nproc     15
*    hard rss       10000
*    -    maxlogins 2
@dev hard core      100000
@dev soft nproc     20
@dev hard nproc     35
@dev -    maxlogins 10
</pre>

<p>
If you find yourself trying to set nproc or maxlogins to 0, maybe you should be delete that user instead. The example above sets the group "dev" settings for processes, core file and maxlogins. The rest is set to a default value. 
</p>
<note><path>/etc/security/limits.conf</path> is part of the PAM package and will only apply to packages that use PAM. </note>


</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>/etc/limits</title>
<body>
<p>
limits are very similar to the limit file in <path>/etc/security/limits.conf</path>. The only differences is the format and it only works on users or wild cards (not groups). Lets have a look at decent configuration:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/limits">
*   L2 C0 U15 R10000
kn L10 C100000 U35
</pre>

<p>
Here we set the default settings and a specific setting for the user <e>kn</e>. Limits are part of the shadow package and only applies for the shadow login program. It is not necessary to set any limitations in this file, if you have set the PAM setting in your make.conf and configured PAM properly.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>

<title>Quotas</title>
<body>

<warn>
Make sure the filesystems you are working with support quotas. ReiserFS
is not one of them!
</warn>

<p>
Putting quotas on a file system prevents users from filling up the disk or writing at all. Quotas is enabled in the kernel and added to a mount point. The kernel option is enabled in the kernel configuration under <c>File systems->Quota support</c>. Apply the following setting, rebuild the kernel and reboot using the new kernel.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing quota">
# <i>emerge quota</i>
</pre>

<p>
Modify your <path>/etc/fstab</path> and add usrquota and grpquota to the partitions that you want to restrict disk usage like the example below.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/fstab">
/dev/sda1 /boot ext2 noauto,noatime 1 1
/dev/sda2 none swap sw 0 0
/dev/sda3 / reiserfs notail,noatime 0 0
/dev/sda4 /tmp ext3 notail,noatime,nodev,nosuid,noexec,usrquota,grpquota 0 0
/dev/sda5 /var ext3 notail,noatime,nodev,usrquota,grpquota 0 0
/dev/sda6 /home ext3 notail,noatime,nodev,nosuid,usrquota,grpquota 0 0
/dev/sda7 /usr reiserfs notail,noatime,nodev,ro	0 0
/dev/cdroms/cdrom0 /mnt/cdrom iso9660 noauto,ro 0 0
proc /proc proc defaults 0 0
</pre>

<p>
On every partition that you have enabled quotas, create the quota files (quota.user and quota.group) and place them in the root of the partition.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the quota files">
# <i>touch /tmp/quota.user</i>
# <i>touch /tmp/quota.group</i>
# <i>chmod 600 /tmp/quota.user</i>
# <i>chmod 600 /tmp/quota.group</i>
</pre>

<p>
This step has to be done on every partition where quotas is enabled. After adding and configuring the quota files, we need to add a script to the run level that turns quota on every time we boot. Copy and paste the following script to a file called <path>/etc/init.d/quotas</path>. Simply create the file (it does not exist) and make it executable.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/init.d/quotas">
#!/sbin/runscript

depend() {
	need localmount
}

start() {
        if [ -x /sbin/quotacheck ] 
        then 
               ebegin "Checking quotas. This may take some time." 
               /sbin/quotacheck -avug 
               eend $?
        fi 
        if [ -x /sbin/quotaon ] 
        then 
               ebegin "Turning on quota." 
               /sbin/quotaon -avug 
               eend $?
        fi
}

stop() {
        if [ -x /sbin/quotaon ] 
        then 
	       ebegin "Turning off quota."
               /sbin/quotaoff
	       eend $?
        fi
}
</pre>

<p>
Add it to the run level with <c>rc-update add quotas default</c> and add a quotacheck (crontab -e) to do periodic scans once a week: <c>0 3 * * 0 /sbin/quotacheck -avug</c>.
</p>

<p>
After rebooting the machine, it is time to setup the quotes for users and groups. <c>edquota -u kn</c> will start the editor defined in $EDITOR (Default is nano) and let you edit the quotas of the user kn. -g will do the same thing just with groups.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting up quota's for user kn">
Quotas for user kn: 
/dev/sda4: blocks in use: 2594, limits (soft = 5000, hard = 6500) 
         inodes in use: 356, limits (soft = 1000, hard = 1500)
</pre>

<p>
For more detail read <e>man edquota</e> or <uri link="http://www.tldp.org/HOWTO/mini/Quota.html">The quota mini howto</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>/etc/login.defs</title>
<body>
	    
<p>
If the policy states that users should change their password every other week. Change the value PASS_MAX_DAYS to 14, PASS_WARN_AGE to 7. It is also recommended that you use password aging since brute force will find any password, its just a matter of time. We also encourage you to set LOG_OK_LOGINS to yes.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>/etc/login.access</title>
<body>
<p>
The login.access file is also part of the shadow package, which gives a login access control table. The table is used to control who can and cannot login based on user name, group name or host name. Per default, all users on the system are allowed to login so the file is only filled with comments and examples. Whether you are securing your server or workstation, we recommend that you setup this file so no one other than yourself (the admin) has access to the console.
</p>
<note>These settings does not apply for root.</note>

<pre caption="/etc/login.access">
-:ALL EXCEPT wheel sync:console
-:wheel:ALL EXCEPT LOCAL .gentoo.org
</pre>

<warn>
Be careful when configuring these options, since mistakes will leave you out with no access to the machine.
</warn>
<note>
These settings does not apply to SSH since SSH does not execute /bin/login per default. This can be enabled by using the "UseLogin yes" in <path>/etc/ssh/sshd_config</path>. It will make SSH use login and the settings will apply.
</note>

<p>
This will setup login access so members of wheel can login on the console or if their origin is from the gentoo.org domain. Maybe too paranoid, but better safe then sorry.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>File permissions.</title>
<body>

<section>
<title>World readable.</title>
<body>

<p>
Normal users should not have access to configuration files or passwords. An attacker can steal passwords from a database or website and deface or even worse, delete data. This is why its important that the permissions are correct. If you are sure that a file is only used by root, assign it with the permissions 0600 and assign the file to the correct user with chown.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>World/Group writable.</title>
<body>

<pre caption="Finding world-writable files and directories">
# <i>/usr/bin/find / -type f \( -perm -2 -o -perm -20 \) \ 
   -exec ls -lg {} \; 2>/dev/null >writable.txt</i>
# <i>/usr/bin/find / -type d \( -perm -2 -o -perm -20 \) \ 
   -exec ls -ldg {} \; 2>/dev/null >>writable.txt</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will create a huge file with permission of all files having either write permission set to the group or everybody. Check the permissions and eliminate world writable files to everyone, by executing <path>/bin/chmod o-w</path> on the files.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SUID/SGID files</title>
<body>

<p>
SUID/SGID files (files with the superuser bit set) is a way for a normal user to do stuff that only root normally is allowed. These files can lead to local root compromise (if they contain security holes) because the file is executed with root permissions. These files are dangerous and should be avoided at any cost. If you do not use the files use chmod 0 on them or unmerge the package they came from (check the package with qpkg -f. If you do not already have it installed simply <c>emerge gentoolkit</c> it). Otherwise just turn the suid bit off with chmod -s.
</p>

<pre caption="Finding setuid files">
# <i>/usr/bin/find / -type f \( -perm -004000 -o -perm -002000 \) \ 
  -exec ls -lg {} \; 2>/dev/null >suidfiles.txt</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will create a file containing a list of all the SUID/SGID files.
</p>

<pre caption="List of setuid binaries">
/bin/su
/bin/ping
/bin/mount
/bin/umount
/var/qmail/bin/qmail-queue
/usr/bin/chfn
/usr/bin/chsh
/usr/bin/crontab
/usr/bin/chage
/usr/bin/expiry
/usr/bin/sperl5.6.1
/usr/bin/newgrp
/usr/bin/passwd
/usr/bin/gpasswd
/usr/bin/procmail
/usr/bin/suidperl
/usr/lib/misc/pt_chown
/usr/sbin/unix_chkpwd
/usr/sbin/traceroute
/usr/sbin/pwdb_chkpwd
</pre>

<p>
By default Gentoo Linux does not have a lot of SUID files (it depends on what you installed), but you might get a list like the one above. Most of the commands should not be used by normal users, only root. Switch off the suid bit on ping, mount, umount, chfn, chsh, newgrp, suidperl, pt_chown and traceroute by <c>chmod -s</c> on every file. Don't remove the bit on su, qmail-queue or unix_chkpwd. Removing will prevent you from su'ing and receiving mail. By removing the bit you remove the possibility of a normal user (or an attacker) to gain root access through any of these files.
</p>

<p>
The only SUID files that I have on my system are su, passwd, gpasswd, qmail-queue, unix_chkpwd and pwdb_chkpwd. But if you are running X, you might have some more, since X needs the access.
</p>

</body>
</section>


</body>
</section>


<section>
<title>PAM (Pluggable Authentication Modules)</title>
<body>

<p>
PAM is a suite of shared libraries that provide an alternative way of making authentication in programs. The PAM settings of Gentoo Linux is pretty reasonable, but there is always room for improvement.
</p>
<note>This chapter will have no effect if you did not include the PAM in your USE option in <path>/etc/make.conf</path></note>

<p>Install cracklib</p>

<pre caption="Installing cracklib">
# <i>emerge cracklib</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/pam.d/passwd">
auth	 required pam_pwdb.so shadow nullok
account	 required pam_pwdb.so
password required pam_cracklib.so difok=3 retry=3 minlen=8 dcredit=2 ocredit=2 
password required pam_pwdb.so md5 use_authtok
session	 required pam_pwdb.so
</pre>

<p>
This will add the cracklib which will ensure that the users use a minimum password length of 8 characters and it consists of minimum 2 digits, 2 others and there must be more than 3 characters different from the last password. This forces the user to choose a good password (password policy). Check the <uri link="http://www.kernel.org/pub/linux/libs/pam/Linux-PAM-html/pam-6.html#ss6.3">PAM</uri> documentation for more options.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/pam.d/sshd">
auth	 required pam_pwdb.so nullok 
auth     required pam_shells.so
auth	 required pam_nologin.so
auth	 required pam_env.so
account	 required pam_pwdb.so
password required pam_cracklib.so difok=3 retry=3 minlen=8 dcredit=2 ocredit=2 use_authtok
password required pam_pwdb.so shadow md5
session	 required pam_pwdb.so
session	 required pam_limits.so
</pre>

<p>
Every other service that is not configured with a PAM file in <path>/etc/pam.d</path> will use the "other" rule. The default settings are set to deny as it should. But I like to have a lot of logs and that is why I added pam_warn.so. The last configuration is pam_limits which is controlled by <path>/etc/security/limits.conf</path>. See chapter on these settings.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/pam.d/other">
auth     required pam_deny.so 
auth     required pam_warn.so 
account  required pam_deny.so 
account  required pam_warn.so 
password required pam_deny.so 
password required pam_warn.so 
session  required pam_deny.so 
session  required pam_warn.so
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>TCP Wrappers</title>
<body>

<p>
Is a way of controlling access to services normally run by inetd (which Gentoo does not have) but it can also be used by xinetd and other services.
</p>
<note>The use in make.conf should contain tcpd and the service should be executing tcpd in its server argument (in xinetd). See the chapter on xinetd for more information</note>

<pre caption="/etc/hosts.deny">
ALL:PARANOID
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/hosts.allow">
ALL: LOCAL @wheel
time: LOCAL, .gentoo.org
</pre>

<p>
As you can see the format is very similar to the one in <path>/etc/login.access</path>. Tcpd supports a specific service and they do not work in the same area of security. These settings only apply to services using tcp wrappers.
</p>

<p>
It is also possible to execute commands when a service is accessed (can be used when activating relaying for dial in users) but its not recommended since people tend to create more problems than they are trying to solve. An example could be that you configure a script to send an email every time someone hits the deny rule, but then an attacker could DoS attack you by keep accessing. This will create a lot of I/O and mails so don't do it!. Read the <c>man 5 hosts_access</c> for more information.
</p>

</body>
</section>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>

-- Tightening the security after/during installation end --

-- Kernel security start --

<chapter>
<title>Kernel security</title>

<section>
<title>Removing functionality</title>
<body>

<p>
Basic rule when configuring the kernel is to remove everything, you do not need. This will create a small kernel but also remove the vulnerabilities that may lie inside drivers and other features.
</p>

<p>
Also consider turning off loadable module support. Even though it is possible to add modules (root kits) without this features, it does make it harder for normal attackers to install root kits via kernel modules.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>/proc (kernel flags)</title>
<body>

<p>
Many kernel parameters can be altered through the /proc file system or by using sysctl.
</p>

<p>
To dynamically change kernel parameters and variables on the fly you need CONFIG_SYSCTL defined in your kernel. This is default in a standard 2.4 kernel.
</p>

<pre caption="Drop ping-packets">
# <i>/bin/echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/icmp_echo_ignore_all</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will disable icmp type 0 (also known as ping) packages. The reason for this is that icmp can contain payload with other information then you think. Administrators use ping as a diagnostic tool and often complain if they cannot ping. There is no reason for an outsider to be able to ping. But some times it can be handy for insiders to be able to ping. Then this can be solved by disabling icmp type 0 in the firewall.
</p>

<pre caption="Ignore broadcast pings">
# <i>/bin/echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/icmp_echo_ignore_broadcasts</i>
</pre>

<p>
This disables response to broadcasts.
</p>

<p>
You don't want yourself becoming a smurf amplifier. Smurf amplifier or X-mass trees is a method that allows an attacker to send a moderate amount of traffic and cause a virtual explosion of traffic at the intended target.
</p>

<pre caption="Disable source routed packets">
# <i>/bin/echo "0" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/all/accept_source_route</i>
</pre>

<p>
Disables source routed packets
</p>

<p>
Don't accept source routed packets. Attackers can use source routing to generate traffic pretending to be from inside your network, but is routed back along the path from which it came, so attackers can compromise your network. Source routing is rarely used for legitimate purposes so disable it.
</p>

<pre caption="Disable redirect acceptance">
# <i>/bin/echo "0" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/all/accept_redirects</i>
</pre>

<p>
Disable ICMP redirect acceptance. ICMP redirects can be used to alter your routing tables, possibly to a bad end.
</p>

<pre caption="Protect against bad error messages">
# <i>/bin/echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/icmp_ignore_bogus_error_responses</i>
</pre>

<p>
Enable protection against bad error messages.
</p>

<pre caption="Enable reverse path filtering">
# <i>for i in /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/*; do
        /bin/echo "1" > $i/rp_filter
done</i>
</pre>

<note>
If you turn on IP forwarding, you will also get this result.
</note>

<p>
Turn on reverse path filtering. This helps make sure that packets use legitimate source addresses, by automatically rejecting incoming packets if the routing table entry for their source address does not match the network interface they are arriving on. This has security advantages because it prevents IP spoofing, <c>however it can be a problems if you use asymmetric routing</c> (packets from you to a host take a different path than packets from that host to you) or if you operate a non-routing host which has several IP addresses on different interfaces.
</p>

<pre caption="Log all spoofed, source routed and redirect packets">
# <i>/bin/echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/all/log_martians</i>
</pre>

<p>
Log spoofed packets, source routed packets and redirect packets.
</p>

<pre caption="Activate IP forwarding">
# <i>/bin/echo "0" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward</i>
</pre>

<p>
Make sure that IP forwarding is turned off. We only want this for a multi-homed host.
</p>

<p>All these settings will be reset then the machine is rebooted. So I suggest that you add the following script to the run level and make it executable.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/init.d/procparam">
#!/sbin/runscript

depend() {
 use checkroot
}

start() {
 ebegin "Setting /proc options."
 /bin/echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/icmp_echo_ignore_all
 /bin/echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/icmp_echo_ignore_broadcasts
 /bin/echo "0" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/all/accept_source_route
 /bin/echo "0" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/all/accept_redirects
 /bin/echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/icmp_ignore_bogus_error_responses
 for i in /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/*; do
   /bin/echo "1" > $i/rp_filter
 done
 /bin/echo "1" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/conf/all/log_martians
 /bin/echo "0" > /proc/sys/net/ipv4/ip_forward
 eend 0
}
</pre>

<p>And add it to the run level <c>rc-update add procparam default</c>.</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Kernel patches</title>
<body>
<section>
<title>Grsecurity</title>
<body>

<p>
The patch from <uri link="http://grsecurity.net">Grsecurity</uri> is standard in the Gentoo kernel but per default disabled. Here is how you enable it:
</p>

<p>
Configure your kernel as you normally do and then configure the the Grsecurity option: (choose customized) and enable the following options:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Buffer Overflow Protection</li>
<ul>
  <li>Openwall non-executable stack</li>
  <li>Gcc trampoline support</li>
</ul>

<li>Filesystem Protections</li>
<ul>
  <li>Proc restrictions</li>
  <li>Linking restrictions</li>
  <li>Secure file descriptors</li>
  <li>Chroot jail restrictions (enable all options below this option)</li>
</ul>

<li>Kernel Auditing</li>
<ul>
  <li>Log execs within chroot</li>
  <li>(Un)Mount logging</li>
  <li>Signal logging</li>
  <li>Fork failure logging</li>
  <li>Log set*ids to root</li>
  <li>Time change logging</li>
</ul>

<li>Executable Protections</li>
<ul>
  <li>Dmesg restriction</li>
  <li>Randomized PIDs</li>
  <li>Altered default IPC permissions (can prevent some program from working correct)</li>
  <li>Restricted ptrace</li>
</ul>

<li>Network Protections</li>
<ul>
  <li>Randomized IP IDs</li>
  <li>Randomized TCP source ports</li>
  <li>Altered Ping IDs</li>
  <li>Randomized TTL</li>
</ul>
<li>Miscellaneous Features</li>
<ul>
  <li>BSD-style coredumps (will create coredumps like core.named)</li>
</ul>

</ul>

<p>
Now compile and install your security enhanced kernel.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Kerneli</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.Kerneli.org">Kerneli</uri> is a patch that adds encryption to the existing kernel. By patching your kernel you will get new options like: Cryptographic ciphers, digest algorithms and cryptographic loop filters.
</p>
<warn>The kerneli patch is currently not in a stable version for the latest kernel, so be careful when using.</warn>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Other kernel patches</title>
<body>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="http://www.openwall.com">The OpenWall Project</uri> (not for 2.4 kernels)</li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.lids.org">Linux Intrusion Detection System</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.rsbac.org">Rule Set Based Access Control</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.nsa.gov/selinux">NSA's security enhanced kernel</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://sourceforge.net/projects/wolk/">Wolk</uri></li>
</ul>

<p>
And there is probably a lot more .. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

-- Kernel security end --

-- Securing Services start --

<chapter>
<title>Securing Services</title>

<section>
<title>Using xinetd</title>
<body>
<p>
xinetd is a replacement for inetd (which Gentoo does not have), the internet services daemon. It supports access control based on the address of the remote host and the time of access. It also provide extensive logging capabilities, including server start time, remote host address, remote user name, server run time, and actions requested.
</p>

<p>
As with all other services its important to have a good default configuration. But since xinetd is used by root and supports protocols that you might not know how they work we recommend not to use it. But if you want to use it anyway here how you can add some security to it:
</p>

<pre caption="Install xinetd">
# <i>emerge xinetd tcp-wrappers</i>
</pre>

<p>
And edit the configuration file:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/xinetd.conf">
defaults
{
 only_from      = localhost
 instances      = 10
 log_type       = SYSLOG authpriv info
 log_on_success = HOST PID
 log_on_failure = HOST
 cps            = 25 30
}

# This will setup pserver (cvs) via xinetd with the following settings:
# max 10 instances (10 connections at a time)
# limit the pserver to tcp only
# use the user cvs to run this service
# bind the interfaces to only 1 ip
# allow access from 10.0.0.*
# limit the time developers can use cvs from 8am to 5pm
# use tpcd wrappers (access control controlled in 
# <path>/etc/hosts.allow</path> and <path>/etc/hosts.deny</path>)
# max_load on the machine set to 1.0
# The disable flag is per default set to no but I like having 
# it in case of it should be disabled
service cvspserver
{
 socket_type    = stream
 protocol       = tcp
 instances      = 10
 protocol       = tcp
 wait           = no
 user           = cvs
 bind           = 10.0.0.2
 only_from      = 10.0.0.0
 access_times   = 8:00-17:00
 server         = /usr/sbin/tcpd
 server_args    = /usr/bin/cvs --allow-root=/mnt/cvsdisk/cvsroot pserver
 max_load       = 1.0
 log_on_failure += RECORD
 disable        = no
}
</pre>

<p>
For more information read the <c>man 5 xinetd.conf</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>ssh</title>
<body>

<p>
The only securing that OpenSSH needs is turning on a stronger authentication based on public key encryption. To many sites (like <uri>http://www.sourceforge.net</uri>, <uri>http://www.php.net</uri> and <uri>http://www.apache.org</uri>) have all suffered unauthorized intrusion to their systems due to password leaks or bad passwords.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/ssh/sshd_config">
#Only enable version 2
Protocol 2

#No direct root access
PermitRootLogin no

#Turn on RSA key authentication
RSAAuthentication yes
PubkeyAuthentication yes
AuthorizedKeysFile      .ssh/authorized_keys

#Disable .rhost files and normal password auth.
RhostsAuthentication no
PasswordAuthentication no
PermitEmptyPasswords no

AllowHosts *.gentoo.org

#Noone else than members of wheel or admin should have access
AllowGroups wheel admin

#And 2 users
AllowUsers kn bs

#add logging level
SyslogFacility AUTH
LogLevel INFO

#bind
ListenAddress 127.0.0.1
</pre>

<p>
Now all your users have to do, is create a key (on their machine they want to login from) with the following command
</p>

<pre caption="Create a RSA keypair">
# <i>/usr/bin/ssh-keygen -t rsa</i>
</pre>

<p>
Type in a passphrase
</p>

<pre caption="Output of ssh-keygen">
Generating public/private rsa key pair.
Enter file in which to save the key (/home/kn/.ssh/id_rsa):<c>[Press enter]</c>
Created directory '/home/kn/.ssh'.
Enter passphrase (empty for no passphrase): <c>[Enter passphrase]</c>
Enter same passphrase again: <c>[Enter passphrase again]</c>
Your identification has been saved in /home/kn/.ssh/id_rsa.
Your public key has been saved in /home/kn/.ssh/id_rsa.pub.
The key fingerprint is:
07:24:a9:12:7f:83:7e:af:b8:1f:89:a3:48:29:e2:a4 kn@knielsen
</pre>

<p>
This will add two files in your <path>~/.ssh/</path> directory called id_rsa and id_rsa.pub. The file called id_rsa is your private key and should be kept from other people than yourself. The other file id_rsa.pub is to be distributed to every server that you have access to. Add the key to the users home directory in <path>~/.ssh/authorized_keys</path> and the user should be able to login.
</p>

<p>Now your users should guard this private key well. Put it on a media that they always carry with them or keep it on their workstation (put this in the <uri link="#doc_chap2">password</uri> policy).
</p>

<p>More on <uri link="http://www.openssh.org">OpenSSH</uri> can be found at their website</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Securing X</title>
<body>

<p>
Per default XFree is configured to act as a Xserver. This can be dangerous since X uses unencrypted tcp connections and listens for xclients. If you do not need this service disable it! But if you depend on using your workstation as a Xserver use the <path>/usr/X11R6/bin/xhost</path> command with caution. This command allows clients from other hosts to connect and use your display. This can become handy if you need an X application from a different machine and the only way is through the network. The syntax is <path>/usr/X11R6/bin/xhost +hostname</path>
</p>
<warn>Don't ever use the xhost + feature! This will allow any client to connect and take control of your X. If an attacker can get access to your X, he can log your keystrokes and control your desktop.</warn>

<p>
A more secure solution is to disable this feature completely by starting you X with <c>startx -- -nolisten</c> tcp or disable it permanently in the configuration file by changing the line 
</p>
<pre caption="/usr/X11R6/bin/startx">
defaultserverargs=""
</pre>

<p> to </p>
<pre caption="/usr/X11R6/bin/startx">
defaultserverargs="-nolisten tcp"
</pre>

<p>
To make sure that <c>startx</c> doesn't get overwritten when you emerge
a newer XFree you must protect it. Add the following line to
<path>/etc/make.conf</path>:
</p>

<pre caption = "/etc/make.conf">
CONFIG_PROTECT_MASK="/usr/X11R6/bin/startx"
</pre>

<p>
If you use a graphical login manager you need a different approach.
</p>

<p>gdm (Gnome Display Manager)</p>

<p>Change:</p>
<pre caption="/etc/X11/gdm/gdm.conf">
[server-Standard]
command=/usr/X11R6/bin/X
</pre>
<p>
to
</p>
<pre caption="/etc/X11/gdm/gdm.conf">
[server-Standard]
command=/usr/X11R6/bin/X -nolisten tcp
</pre>

<p>xdm (X Display Manager) and kdm (Kde Display Manager)</p>

<p>Change</p>
<pre caption="/etc/X11/xdm/Xservers">
:0 local /usr/bin/X11/X 
</pre>

<p>to</p>

<pre caption="/etc/X11/xdm/Xservers">
:0 local /usr/bin/X11/X -nolisten tcp 
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Print services</title>
<body>

<section>
<title>Lpd</title>
<body>
<p>
TODO
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Pdq</title>
<body>

<p>http://pdq.sourceforge.net/</p>

<p>
TODO
</p>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</section>



<section>
<title>FTP</title>
<body>
<p>
FTP (File Transfer Protocol) is in general a bad idea. It uses unencrypted data, listens on 2 ports (normally port 20 and 21), support for anonymous users and is what some attackers are looking for (for trading warez). If you can avoid it use sftpd or http instead since the ftp protocol contains several security problems. If not, secure your services as good as you can and prepare yourself.
</p>

<section>
<title>Pure-ftpd</title>
<body>

<p>
Pure-ftpd is an branch of the original trollftpd. Modified for security reasons and functionality by Frank Dennis.
</p>

<p>
Use virtual users (never system accounts) by enabling the AUTH option. Set it to -lpuredb:/etc/pureftpd.pdb and create your users by using <path>/usr/bin/pure-pw</path>. 
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/conf.d/pure-ftpd">
## Number of simultaneous connections in total, and per ip ##
MAX_CONN="-c 30"
MAX_CONN_IP="-C 10"

## Don't allow uploads if the partition is more full then this var ##
DISK_FULL="-k 90%"

AUTH="-lpuredb:/etc/pureftpd.pdb"

## Misc. Others ##
MISC_OTHER="-A -E -X -U 177:077 -d -4 -L100:5 -I 15"
</pre>

<p>
And configure your MISC_OTHER setting for not allowing anonymous (-E), chroot everyone (-A), Users can not read or write to files beginning with a . (dot) (-X), max idle time (-I), limit recursion (-L) and a reasonable umask. And do __not__ use the option -w or -W! If you want to have a warez site, stop reading this doc!.
</p>

<p>
More can be read at <uri>http://www.pureftpd.org</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Proftpd</title>
<body>

<p>
Proftpd has had several security problems, but they seem to have fixed most of them. Still apply some enhancements:</p>

<pre caption="/etc/proftpd/proftpd.conf">
ServerName "My ftp daemon"
#Don't show the ident of the server
ServerIdent on "Go away"

#Makes it easier to create virtual users
RequireValidShell off

#Use alternative password and group file (passwd uses crypt format)
AuthUserFile "/etc/proftpd/passwd"
AuthGroupFile "/etc/proftpd/group"

# Permissions
Umask 077

# Timeouts and limitations
MaxInstances 30
MaxClients 10 "Only 10 connections allowed"
MaxClientsPerHost 1 "You have already logged on once"
MaxClientsPerUser 1 "You have already logged on once"
TimeoutStalled 10
TimeoutNoTransfer 20
TimeoutLogin 20

#Chroot everyone
DefaultRoot ~

#don't run as root
User  nobody
Group nogroup

#Log every transfer
TransferLog /var/log/transferlog

#Problems with globbing
DenyFilter \*.*/
</pre>

<p>
The rest is up to you and your reading ability (<uri>http://www.proftpd.org</uri>).
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Vsftpd</title>
<body>

<p>
Vsftpd (stands for very secure ftp) is a small ftp daemon running a reasonably default configuration. It is simple and does not have as many features (like virtual users) as pureftp and proftp.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/vsftpd">
anonymous_enable=NO
local_enable=YES

#read only
write_enable=NO

#enable logging of transfers
xferlog_std_format=YES

idle_session_timeout=20
data_connection_timeout=20
nopriv_user=nobody

chroot_list_enable=YES
chroot_list_file=/etc/vsftpd/chrootlist

ls_recurse_enable=NO
</pre>

<p>
As you see there is no way for this service to have individual permissions and no default chroot action. But when it comes to anonymous settings it quite good. Sometimes it can be nice to have a anonymous ftp server (for sharing open source) and this server really applies for that.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Apache</title>
<body>

<p>
Apache (1.3.26) comes with a pretty decent configuration file but again. We need to improve some things, like binding to one address and keep it from leaking information. These are the options that you should apply the configuration file:
</p>

<p>
If you have added ssl to your <path>/etc/make.conf</path> before installing apache, you should have access to a ssl enabled server. Just add the following line to enable it.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/conf.d/apache">
HTTPD_OPTS="-D SSL"
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/apache/conf/apache.conf">
#Make it listen on your ip
Listen 127.0.0.1
BindAddress 127.0.0.1
#It is not a good idea to use nobody or nogroup - 
#for every service not running as root 
#(just add the user apache with group apache)
User apache
Group apache
#Will keep apache from telling about the version
ServerSignature Off
ServerTokens min
</pre>

<p>
Apache is compiled with --enable-shared=max and --enable-module=all. This will per default enable all modules so you should out comment all modules in the LoadModule section (LoadModule and AddModule) that you do not use. Restart the service by executing <c>/etc/init.d/apache restart</c>.
</p>

<p>
Documentation can be found at <uri>http://www.apache.org</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Mail</title>
<body>


<section>
<title>Postfix</title>
<body>
TODO!
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Qmail</title>
<body>
<p>
Qmail is considered to be the most secure mail server. It is written with security (and paranoia) in mind. It does not allow relaying per default and have not had a security hole since 1996. Simply <c>emerge qmail</c> and go configure!
</p>
</body>
</section>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>DNS</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo supports two different dns servers, Bind and djbdns.
</p>

<section>
<title>Bind</title>
<body>

<p>
Bind is known for its security history that should not be taken lightly. As with any other service it should __never__ run as root so please don't change the default configuration for this service. Per default Gentoo does not setup any configuration for this services so you have to add your own dns zones to <path>/etc/bind/named.conf</path>. But since the security lies not only within the domain server daemon but also in the protocol it should be properly configured.
</p>

<p>
People often ask, why not use djbdns (very secure dns by D.J. Bernstein) and the answer is: Bind does have features that djbdns does not, like support for IPv6 (not without a patch anyway).
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/bind/named.conf">
#setup access control
acl "mynet" { 10.0.0.0/24; };

options {
  directory "/var/bind";
  pid-file "/var/run/named/named.pid";
#allow "mynet" to make queries
  allow-query { "mynet"; };
#don't allow zone transfers
  allow-transfer { none; };
  forward only;
  forwarders { 10.0.0.2; };
#Only provide recursive service to "mynet"
  recursion no;
  allow-recursion { mynet; };
# Bind to an interface
  listen-on { 10.0.0.1; };
# Don't show the version
  version "Go away";
};

key "rndc-key" {
  algorithm hmac-md5;
  secret "o1BYkYC+bXeZgHDsrVBwRQ==";
};

#allow only control from localhost and with a key
controls {
  inet 127.0.0.1 port 953
  allow { 127.0.0.1; } keys { "rndc-key"; };
};
</pre>

<p>
This is a default good configuration. However, Bind version 9 has a special chroot functionality that you should use. Here is how you create your chrooted bind:
</p>

<pre caption="Prepairing a chroot environment">
# <i>mkdir -p /chroot</i>
# <i>mkdir /chroot/dns</i>
# <i>mkdir /chroot/dns/dev</i>
# <i>mkdir /chroot/dns/etc</i>
# <i>mkdir /chroot/dns/var</i>
# <i>mkdir /chroot/dns/var/run</i>
# <i>mkdir /chroot/dns/var/run/named</i>
# <i>chown -R named:named /chroot/dns/var/run/named</i>
# <i>cp -R /etc/bind /chroot/dns/etc/.</i>
# <i>cp /etc/localtime /chroot/dns/etc/localtime</i>
# <i>cp -R /var/bind /chroot/dns/var/.</i>
# <i>mknod /chroot/dns/dev/zero c 1 5</i>
# <i>chmod 666 /chroot/dns/dev/zero</i>
# <i>mknod /chroot/dns/dev/random c 1 8</i>
# <i>chmod 666 /chroot/dns/dev/random</i>
# <i>cp -a /dev/log /chroot/dns/dev/log</i>
# <i>cd /chroot/dns</i>
# <i>chattr +i etc etc/localtime var</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will create a chrooted environment in <path>/chroot</path>. Now all we have to do is modify the init script for supporting the new environment. Edit <path>/etc/init.d/named</path> and add <c>-t /chroot/dns</c> to the start function. You may also want to change the stop function to point to the correct pid file in <path>/chroot/var/run/named/named.pid</path>. Restart your DNS server.
</p>
<note>
An attacker can escape a chrooted jail, if he is good enough (see how to prevent this in the kernel patch section)
</note>

<p>
Documentation can be found at the <uri link="http://www.isc.org/products/BIND/bind9.html">Internet Software Consortium</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Djbdns</title>
<body>

<p>
There is really not much to say about djbdns except that the author is willing to bet <uri link="http://cr.yp.to/djbdns/guarantee.html">money</uri> on how secure it is. So go and try it: <uri>http://www.djbdns.org/</uri> it is very different from the way Bind v.9 works but you will get the hang of it.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Samba</title>
<body>

<p>
Samba is a protocol to share files with Microsoft/Novell networks and it should __not__ be used over the Internet. But nevertheless it needs securing.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/samba/smb.conf">
[global]
  #Bind to an interface
  interfaces = eth0 10.0.0.1/32

  #Make sure to use encrypted password
  encrypt passwords = yes
  directory security mask = 0700

  #allow traffic from 10.0.0.*
  hosts allow = 10.0.0.

  #Enables user authentication 
  #(don't use the share mode)
  security = user
  
  #Disallow privileged accounts
  invalid users = root @wheel

  #Add a max size of usage in kilobytes
  max disk size = 102400

  #Uphold the password policy
  min password length = 8
  null passwords = no

  #Use PAM (if added support)
  obey pam restrictions = yes
  pam password change = yes
</pre>

<p>
Make sure that permissions are set correct on every share and remember to read the <uri link="http://www.samba.org">documentation</uri>
</p>

<p>
Now restart the server and add the users who should have access to this service. This is done though the <path>/usr/bin/smbpasswd</path> with the parameter -a
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Chroot or virtual servers.</title>
<body>
<p>
Chrooting a service is a way of limiting a service (or user) environment to only accessing what it should and not gaining access (or information) that could lead to root access. By running the service as another user than root (nobody, apache, named) an attacker can only access files with the permissions of this user. This means that an attacker cannot gain root access even if the services has a security flaw.
</p>

<p>
Some services like pure-ftpd and bind has features for chrooting, and other services has not. If the service supports it, use it, otherwise you have to figure out how to create your own. Lets see how to create a chroot, for a basic understanding of how chroots work, we will test it with bash (easy way of learning).
</p>

<p>
Create a directory in <path>/</path> called chroot (<c>mkdir chroot</c>). And find what dynamic libraries that bash is compiled with (if it is compiled with -static this step is not necessary):
</p>

<p>
The following command will create a list of libraries used by bash. 
</p>

<pre caption="Get listing of used libraries">
# <i>ldd /bin/bash</i>
  libncurses.so.5 => /lib/libncurses.so.5 (0x4001b000)
  libdl.so.2 => /lib/libdl.so.2 (0x40060000)
  libc.so.6 => /lib/libc.so.6 (0x40063000)
  /lib/ld-linux.so.2 => /lib/ld-linux.so.2 (0x40000000)
</pre>

<p>
Now lets create the environment for bash.
</p>

<pre caption="Create chroot-environment for bash">
# <i>mkdir /chroot/bash</i>
# <i>mkdir /chroot/bash/bin</i>
# <i>mkdir /chroot/bash/lib</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next copy the files used by bash (<path>/lib</path>) to the chrooted lib and copy the bash command to the chrooted bin directory. This will create the excact same environment, just with less functionality. After copying try it out: <c>chroot /chroot/bash</c>. If you get an prompt saying <c>/</c> it works!. Otherwise it will properly tell you what a file is missing. Some shared libraries depend on each other.
</p>

<p>
You will notice that inside the chroot nothing works except echo. This is because we have no other commands in out chroot environment that bash and "echo" is a build-in functionality.
</p>

<p>
This is basically the same way you would create a chrooted service. The only difference is that services sometimes rely on devices and configuration files in <path>/etc</path>. Simply copy them (devices can be copied with cp -a) to the chrooted environment, edit the init script to use chroot before executing. It can be difficult to find what devices and configuration files a services need. This is where the <c>strace</c> command becomes handy. Start the service with <path>/usr/bin/strace</path> bash and look for open, read, stat and maybe connect. This will give you a clue on what files to copy. But in most cases just copy the passwd file (edit the copy and remove users that has nothing to do with the service), <path>/dev/zero</path>, <path>/dev/log</path> and <path>/dev/random</path>.
</p>

<p>
Another way of creating a more secure environment is by using a virtual server environment. This will create a copy of the existing Linux and boots it in a virtual mode. This means that if the server is compromised its only the virtual server that has been compromised and not the real installation.
</p>

<p>
Examples of virtual servers:
</p>

<ul>

<li>
<uri link="http://user-mode-linux.sourceforge.net">Usermode linux</uri> and an howto about <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/uml.html">user mode linux</uri>.
</li>

<li>
<uri link="http://www.solucorp.qc.ca/miscprj/s_context.hc">Virtual private servers</uri>
</li>

</ul>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

-- Securing Services end --

-- Firewalls --

<chapter>
<title>Firewalls</title>

<section>
<title>A firewall</title>
<body>

<p>
People often think that a firewall is the ultimate security, but they are wrong. In most cases a mis configured firewall gives worse security that not having one at all. A firewall is also a piece of software and should be treated the same way as any other service, because is just as likely to have bugs (security holes).
</p>

<p>
So think before implementing one! Do you really need one ? If you think you need one write a policy on how it should work, what type of firewall and who should operate it.
</p>

<p>
Firewalls are used for two purposes:
</p>

<ul>
<li>To keep users (worms/attackers) out</li>
<li>To keep users (employees/children) in</li>
</ul>

<p>
Basically there are three types of firewalls:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Packet filtering</li>
<li>Circuit relay</li>
<li>Application gateway</li>
</ul>

<p>
A firewall should be a dedicated machine running no services (or ssh as the only one) and secured the way this guide recommends it to be.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Packet filtering</title>
<body>

<p>
All network traffic is in the form of packets. Large traffic is also split up into small packets for easy handling and then reassembled when arriving at it's destination. Every packet contains information on how and where is should be delivered. And these information is exactly what a packing filtering firewall uses. Filtering is based on:
</p>

<ul>

<li>Allow or disallow packets based on source/destination IP address.</li>
<li>Allow or disallow packets based on source/destination port.</li>
<li>Allow or disallow packets according to protocol.</li>
<li>Allow or disallow packets according to flags within a specific protocol</li>

</ul>

<p>
Basically filtering on all data within the header of a packet and not it's content.
</p>

<p>
Weaknesses:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Address information in a packet can potentially be a bogus address or as we say <e>spoofed</e> be the sender</li>
<li>Data or requests within the allowed packet may contain unwanted data that the attacker can exploit known bugs in the services on or behind the firewall</li>
<li>Usually single point of failure</li>
</ul>

<p>
Advantages:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Simple and easy to implement</li>
<li>Can give warnings on a possible attack before they happened (by detecting portscans)</li>
<li>Good for stopping SYN attacks</li>
</ul>

<p>
Examples of free packet filters on Linux:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.iptables.org">Iptables</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.linuxdocs.org/HOWTOs/IPCHAINS-HOWTO.html">Ipchains</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://www.smoothwall.org">SmoothWall</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Circuit relay</title>
<body>

<p>
Or circuit level gateways is a firewall that validates connections before allowing data to be exchanged. This means that is simply does not allow or deny packets based based on the header of the packet but determines whether the connection between both ends is valid according to configurable rules before it opens a session and allows data to and from the allowed source address. Filtering is based on:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Destination/source address</li>
<li>Destination/source port</li>
<li>A period of time</li>
<li>Protocol</li>
<li>User</li>
<li>Password</li>
</ul>

<p>
All traffic is validated, monitored and traffic without is disallowed.
</p>

<p>
Weakness:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
Operates at the Transport Layer and may require substantial modification of the programming which normally provides transport functions.
</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Application gateway</title>
<body>

<p>
The application level gateway is a proxy for application, exchanging data with remote system on behalf of it's clients. It is kept away from the public safely behind a DMZ or firewall with no connection from the outside. Filtering is based on:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Allow or disallow based on source/destination</li>
<li>Based on the packets content</li>
<li>Can even alter the packet content on the fly</li>
<li>Limiting file access based on file type or extension</li>
</ul>

<p>
Advantages:
</p>

<ul>
<li>Can cache files, increasing network performance</li>
<li>Detailed logging of all connections</li>
<li>Scales perfectly (some proxy servers can "share" the cached data)</li>
<li>No direct access from the outside</li>
</ul>

<p>
Weakness:
</p>

<ul>
<li>The setup is complex</li>
</ul>

<p>
Application gateways are considered to be the most secure solution since it does not have to run as root and is not public to the Internet.
</p>

<p>
Example of a free application gateway:
</p>

<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.squid-cache.org/">Squid</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Iptables</title>
<body>

<p>
In order to get iptables working, it has to be enabled in the kernel. I have added them as modules (the iptables command will load them as they are needed) and recompiled my kernel. After you have compiled it (or while compiling the kernel) you have to add the iptables commands. Just <c>emerge iptables</c> and it should work.
</p>

<p>
Now test that it works by running <c>iptables -L</c>. If it fails something is wrong and you have to check you configuration once more.
</p>

<p>
Iptables is a stateful packet filter which means that it provides greater control and greater security than ipchains (Linux version 2.2) which is not stateful. You are properly asking yourself what is the stateful part ? and what is the difference?. 
</p>

<p>
We all know that TCP are made up a series of packets. Each packet containing information about source address, the destination address and a sequence so the packets can be put back together. And we all know that TCP is connection-oriented and UDP is connectionless right? these are the states that it stores .. now you are probably asking yourself and so what ? Well I'm getting to that.
</p>

<p>
Now imagine that you have a stateless firewall (ipchains) and do not want to allow external computers to originate a connection to your internal services but how can the firewall determine whether a packet is part of an ongoing connection or not? A stateless firewall cannot distinguish between an existing connection and one that is part of a new connection by looking at the SYN flag!. 
</p>

<p>
Lets say an attacker is sending hand crafted packets (a packet created by the attacker) where he alters the SYN flags or any other flags. This is quite often that attackers do. Send packets right through the firewall altering routing tables or compromising services running on the firewall but are supposed to be safe behind a filter. A stateful firewall will keep track of all connection and can easily detect if a packet is claiming to part of en existing connect or not. When a connection, claiming to be an existing connection but is found, its marted as invalid and its possible to discard it. This will also stop the possibility of "stealth scans" since the connection was invalid.
</p>

<p>
I could probably find a dozen other reasons but I think you got the picture .. simple rules means a smaller firewall configuration meaning that its easier to maintain.
</p>

<p>
Iptables provides several other features like rate limiting. This features is extremely useful when trying to prevent a certain DoS (Denial of Service) attacks like a SYN attack. Now what is a SYN attack?
</p>

<p>
Again .. when creating a connection with TCP it uses three-way handshake to establish the connection like this:
</p>

<fig link="http://www.ibiblio.org/pub/Linux/distributions/gentoo/images/synack.jpg" short="Three-way handshake"/>

<p>
A SYN attack is when it only sends a SYN packet (header only contains SYN flag) and does not continue sending the last two packets to establish the connection. A SYN packets does not require a valid sender address (IP) because it does not need a reply. So the connection will hang until it times out. Now if the attacker sends a lot of SYN packets with a bogus sender IP, the computer waits for the response, which never comes. Depending on the timeout settings in your system, this connection could stay open for 30-60 seconds (or longer). When the connection limit table is completely occupied and unable to communicate with anyone.
</p>

<p>
This is where the rate limit becomes handy. Its possible to limit the number of SYN packets from a single source but using the <c>-m limit --limit 1/s</c>. This will limit the SYN packets to one per source and therefor restricting the SYN flood on our resources.
</p>

<p>
Now! some practical stuff!
</p>

<p>
When iptables is loaded in the kernel it has 5 hooks where you can place your rules. They are called INPUT, OUTPUT FORWARD, PREROUTING and POSTROUTING. These lists are called chains because they work by added a rules and checks the rules one at the time as they where added. If one rule deny a packet it will be dropped and does not continue down the chain.
</p>

<p>
You can place rules directly to the 5 main chains or create chains and add them to as a rule to an existing chain. Lets see how this is done
</p>

<table border="0">
  <tr>
    <th>Option:</th><th>Description:</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-A</ti><ti>Append</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-D</ti><ti>Delete</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-I</ti><ti>Insert</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-R</ti><ti>Replace</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-L</ti><ti>List</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-F</ti><ti>Delete all rules in  chain or all chains</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-Z</ti><ti>Zero counters in chain or all chains</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-C</ti><ti>Test this packet on chain</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-N</ti><ti>Create a new user-defined chain</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-X</ti><ti>Delete a user-defined chain</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-P</ti><ti>Change policy on chain to target</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-E</ti><ti>Change chain name</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-p</ti><ti>Protocol</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-s</ti><ti>Source address/mask</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-d</ti><ti>Destination address/mask</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-i</ti><ti>Input name (ethernet name)</ti>
  <tr>
  </tr>
    <ti>-o</ti><ti>Output name (ethernet name)</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-j</ti><ti>Jump (target for rule)</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-m</ti><ti>Extended match (might use extension)</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-n</ti><ti>Numeric output of addresses and ports</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-t</ti><ti>Table to manipulate</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-v</ti><ti>Verbose mode</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-x</ti><ti>Expand numbers (display exact values)</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-f</ti><ti>Match second or further fragments only</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>-V</ti><ti>Packet version</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>--line-numbers</ti><ti>Print line numbers when listing</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
First we will try to block all ICMP packages to our machine, just to get familiar with iptables.
</p>

<pre caption="Block all ICMP packages">
# <i>iptables -A INPUT -p icmp -j DROP</i>
</pre>

<p>
First we specify the chain it should be appended to. Next to specify the protocol and then the rule. The rule can be a ACCEPT, DROP, REJECT, LOG, QUEUE, MASQUERADE, a loaded module or a user defined chain. In this case we use DROP which will drop the packet without responding to the client.
</p>

<p>
Now try <c>ping localhost</c>. It will not be able to get any response since its blocking the entire ICMP protocol incoming to our machine. It will not be able to ping other machines either since its not allowed to get the ICMP packets returning from the host. Now flush the chain to get ICMP flowing again.
</p>

<pre caption="Flush all rules">
# <i>iptables -F</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now lets look at the stateful part in iptables. If we wanted to have a stateful inspection of packets incoming on eth0 we could enable it by issuing:
</p>

<pre caption="Accept packets that originate from an already established connection">
# <i>iptables -A INPUT -i eth0 -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will accept any packet already established or related in the INPUT chain. And you could drop any packet that is not in the state table by issuing <c>iptables -A INPUT -i eth0 -m state --state INVALID -j DROP</c> just before. This enables the stateful part in iptables by loading the extension state. If you wanted connection from the outside to connect to you machine you could use the <c>--state NEW</c>. Iptables contain some modules for different purposes. Some of them are: 
</p>

<table border="0">
  <tr>
    <th>Module/Match</th><th>Description</th><th>Extended options</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>mac</ti><ti>Matching extension for incoming packets mac address.</ti><ti>--mac-source</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>state</ti><ti>Enables stateful inspection</ti><ti>--state (states are ESTABLISHED,RELATED, INVALID, NEW)</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>limit</ti><ti>Rate matching limiting</ti><ti>--limit, --limit-burst</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>owner</ti><ti>Attempt to match various characteristics of the packet creator</ti><ti>--uid-owner userid --gid-owner groupid --pid-owner processid --sid-owner sessionid</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>unclean</ti><ti>Various random sanity checks on packets</ti><ti/>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
Lets try to create a user defined chain and apply it to one of the existing chains:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a userdefined chain">
<codenote>Create a new chain with one rule</codenote>
# <i>iptables -X mychain</i>
# <i>iptables -N mychain</i>
# <i>iptables -A mychain -i eth0 -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT</i>
<codenote>The default policy is all outgoing traffic is allowed. Incoming is dropped.</codenote>
# <i>iptables -P OUTPUT ACCEPT</i>
# <i>iptables -P INPUT DROP</i>
<codenote>And add it to the INPUT chain</codenote>
# <i>iptables -A INPUT -j mychain</i>
</pre>

<p>
By applying the rule to the input chain we get the policy: All is allowed out and only incoming is allowed, if its already established. This is general a bad idea. Default policies should be drop but this is just an example.
</p>

<p>
Now if you want more documentation have a look at the <uri link="http://www.iptables.org/documentation/index.html#HOWTO">iptables documentation</uri>
</p>

<p>
Lets see a full blown example. In this case my firewall/gateway policy states:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Connections to the firewall is only allowed through SSH (port 22)</li>
  <li>The local network should have access to HTTP, HTTPS and SSH (DNS should also be allowed)</li>
  <li>ICMP traffic can contain payload as should not be allowed. Of course we have to allow some ICMP traffic.</li>
  <li>Port scan should be detected and logged</li>
  <li>SYN attack should avoided</li>
  <li>All other traffic should be dropped and logged</li>
</ul>

<pre caption="/etc/init.d/firewall">
#!/sbin/runscript
IPTABLES=/sbin/iptables
IPTABLESSAVE=/sbin/iptables-save
IPTABLESRESTORE=/sbin/iptables-restore
FIREWALL=/etc/firewall.rules
DNS1=212.242.40.3
DNS2=212.242.40.51
#inside
IIP=10.0.0.2
IINTERFACE=eth0
LOCAL_NETWORK=10.0.0.0/24
#outside
OIP=217.157.156.144
OINTERFACE=eth1

opts="${opts} showstatus panic save restore showoptions rules"

depend() {
  need net procparam
}

rules() {
  stop
  ebegin "Setting internal rules"

  einfo "Setting default rule to drop"
  $IPTABLES -P FORWARD DROP
  $IPTABLES -P INPUT   DROP
  $IPTABLES -P OUTPUT  DROP

  #default rule
  einfo "Creating states chain"
  $IPTABLES -N allowed-connection
  $IPTABLES -F allowed-connection
  $IPTABLES -A allowed-connection -m state --state ESTABLISHED,RELATED -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A allowed-connection -i $IINTERFACE -m limit -j LOG --log-prefix \ 
      "Bad packet from ${IINTERFACE}:"
  $IPTABLES -A allowed-connection -j DROP

  #ICMP traffic
  einfo "Creating icmp chain"
  $IPTABLES -N icmp_allowed
  $IPTABLES -F icmp_allowed
  $IPTABLES -A icmp_allowed -m state --state NEW -p icmp --icmp-type \ 
      time-exceeded -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A icmp_allowed -m state --state NEW -p icmp --icmp-type \ 
      destination-unreachable -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A icmp_allowed -p icmp -j LOG --log-prefix "Bad ICMP traffic:"
  $IPTABLES -A icmp_allowed -p icmp -j DROP

  #Incoming traffic
  einfo "Creating incoming ssh traffic chain"
  $IPTABLES -N allow-ssh-traffic-in
  $IPTABLES -F allow-ssh-traffic-in
  #Flood protection
  $IPTABLES -A allow-ssh-traffic-in -m limit --limit 1/second -p tcp --tcp-flags \ 
      ALL RST --dport ssh -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A allow-ssh-traffic-in -m limit --limit 1/second -p tcp --tcp-flags \ 
      ALL FIN --dport ssh -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A allow-ssh-traffic-in -m limit --limit 1/second -p tcp --tcp-flags \ 
      ALL SYN --dport ssh -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A allow-ssh-traffic-in -m state --state RELATED,ESTABLISHED --dport ssh -j ACCEPT

  #outgoing traffic
  einfo "Creating outgoing ssh traffic chain"
  $IPTABLES -N allow-ssh-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -F allow-ssh-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -A allow-ssh-traffic-out -p tcp --dport ssh -j ACCEPT

  einfo "Creating outgoing dns traffic chain"
  $IPTABLES -N allow-dns-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -F allow-dns-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -A allow-dns-traffic-out -p udp -d $DNS1 --dport domain \ 
      -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A allow-dns-traffic-out -p udp -d $DNS2 --dport domain \ 
     -j ACCEPT

  einfo "Creating outgoing http/https traffic chain"
  $IPTABLES -N allow-www-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -F allow-www-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -A allow-www-traffic-out -p tcp --dport www -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A allow-www-traffic-out -p tcp --dport https -j ACCEPT

  #Catch portscanners
  einfo "Creating portscan detection chain"
  $IPTABLES -N check-flags
  $IPTABLES -F check-flags
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags ALL FIN,URG,PSH -m limit \ 
      --limit 5/minute -j LOG --log-level alert --log-prefix "NMAP-XMAS:" 
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags ALL FIN,URG,PSH -j DROP
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags ALL ALL -m limit --limit \ 
      5/minute -j LOG --log-level 1 --log-prefix "XMAS:"
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags ALL ALL -j DROP
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags ALL SYN,RST,ACK,FIN,URG \ 
      -m limit --limit 5/minute -j LOG --log-level 1 --log-prefix "XMAS-PSH:"
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags ALL SYN,RST,ACK,FIN,URG -j DROP
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags ALL NONE -m limit \ 
      --limit 5/minute -j LOG --log-level 1 --log-prefix "NULL_SCAN:"
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags ALL NONE -j DROP
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags SYN,RST SYN,RST -m limit \ 
      --limit 5/minute -j LOG --log-level 5 --log-prefix "SYN/RST:"
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags SYN,RST SYN,RST -j DROP
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags SYN,FIN SYN,FIN -m limit \ 
      --limit 5/minute -j LOG --log-level 5 --log-prefix "SYN/FIN:"
  $IPTABLES -A check-flags -p tcp --tcp-flags SYN,FIN SYN,FIN -j DROP

  # Apply and add invalid states to the chains
  einfo "Applying chains to INPUT"
  $IPTABLES -A INPUT -m state --state INVALID -j DROP
  $IPTABLES -A INPUT -j icmp_allowed 
  $IPTABLES -A INPUT -j check-flags
  $IPTABLES -A INPUT -i lo -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A INPUT -j allow-ssh-traffic-in
  $IPTABLES -A INPUT -j allowed-connection

  einfo "Applying chains to FORWARD"
  $IPTABLES -A FORWARD -m state --state INVALID -j DROP
  $IPTABLES -A FORWARD -j icmp_allowed 
  $IPTABLES -A FORWARD -j check-flags
  $IPTABLES -A FORWARD -o lo -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A FORWARD -j allow-ssh-traffic-in
  $IPTABLES -A FORWARD -j allow-www-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -A FORWARD -j allowed-connection

  einfo "Applying chains to OUTPUT"
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -m state --state INVALID -j DROP
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -j icmp_allowed
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -j check-flags
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -o lo -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -j allow-ssh-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -j allow-dns-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -j allow-www-traffic-out
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -j allowed-connection

  #Allow client to route through via NAT (Network Address Translation)
  $IPTABLES -t nat -A POSTROUTING -o $IINTERFACE -j MASQUERADE 
  eend $?
}

start() {
  ebegin "Starting firewall"
  if [ -e "${FIREWALL}" ]; then
    restore
  else
    einfo "${FIREWALL} does not exists. Using default rules."
    rules
  fi
  eend $?
}

stop() {
  ebegin "Stopping firewall"
  $IPTABLES -F
  $IPTABLES -t nat -F
  $IPTABLES -X
  $IPTABLES -P FORWARD ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -P INPUT   ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -P OUTPUT  ACCEPT
  eend $?
}

showstatus() {
  ebegin "Status"
  $IPTABLES -L -n -v --line-numbers
  einfo "NAT status"
  $IPTABLES -L -n -v --line-numbers -t nat
  eend $?
}

panic() {
  ebegin "Setting panic rules"
  $IPTABLES -F
  $IPTABLES -X
  $IPTABLES -t nat -F
  $IPTABLES -P FORWARD DROP
  $IPTABLES -P INPUT   DROP
  $IPTABLES -P OUTPUT  DROP
  $IPTABLES -A INPUT -i lo -j ACCEPT
  $IPTABLES -A OUTPUT -o lo -j ACCEPT
  eend $?
}

save() {
  ebegin "Saving Firewall rules"
  $IPTABLESSAVE &gt; $FIREWALL
  eend $?
}

restore() {
  ebegin "Restoring Firewall rules"
  $IPTABLESRESTORE &lt; $FIREWALL
  eend $?
}

restart() {
  svc_stop; svc_start
}

showoptions() {
  echo "Usage: $0 {start|save|restore|panic|stop|restart|showstatus}"
  echo "start)      will restore setting if exists else force rules"
  echo "stop)       delete all rules and set all to accept"
  echo "rules)      force settings of new rules"
  echo "save)       will store settings in ${FIREWALL}"
  echo "restore)    will restore settings from ${FIREWALL}"
  echo "showstatus) Shows the status" 
}
</pre>

<p>
Free advice when creating a firewall:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>Create your firewall policy before implementing it</li>
  <li>Keep it simple</li>
  <li>Know how the protocol works (read the <uri link="http://www.ietf.org/">RFC (Request For Comments)</uri>)</li>
  <li>Keep in mind that a firewall it just another piece of software running as root</li>
  <li>Test your firewall</li>
</ol>

<p>
If you think that iptables is hard to understand or takes to long to setup a decent firewall you could use <uri link="http://www.shorewall.net">Shorewall</uri>. It basically uses iptables to generate firewall rules, but concentrates on rules and not specific protocols.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Squid</title>
<body>

<p>
Squid is a very powerful proxy server and it can do filters, rejects allowed traffic based on: time, regular expression path/uri, source and destination address (IP), domain, browser, the authenticated username, mime-type and port (protocol). I probably forgot some features, but it can be hard to cover the entire feature list.
</p> 

<p>
In the following example I have added a banner filter instead of a filter based on porn sites. The reason for this is that Gentoo.org should <c>not</c> be listed as some porn site. And I do not want to waste my time trying to find some good sites for you.
</p>

<p>
In this case, my policy states:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Surfing (HTTP/HTTPS) is allowed during work hours (mon-fri 8-17 and sat 8-13) if they are here late they should work, not surf</li>
  <li>Download is not allowed (.exe, .com, .arj, .zip, .asf, .avi, .mpg, .mpeg etc.)</li>
  <li>We don't like banners so they are filtered and replaced with a transparent gif (this is where you get creative!)</li>
  <li>Every other connection to and from the Internet is not allowed</li>
</ul>

<p>
This is implemented in 4 "easy" steps
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/squid/squid.conf">
# Bind to a ip and port
http_port 10.0.2.1:3128

# Standard configuration
hierarchy_stoplist cgi-bin ?
acl QUERY urlpath_regex cgi-bin \?
no_cache deny QUERY

# Add basic access control lists
acl all src 0.0.0.0/0.0.0.0
acl manager proto cache_object
acl localhost src 127.0.0.1/255.255.255.255

# Add who can access this proxy server
acl localnet src 10.0.0.0/255.255.0.0

# And ports
acl SSL_ports port 443
acl Safe_ports port 80
acl Safe_ports port 443
acl purge method PURGE

# Add access control list based on regular
# expressions within urls
acl archives urlpath_regex "/etc/squid/files.acl"
acl url_ads url_regex "/etc/squid/banner-ads.acl"

# Add access control list based on time and day
acl restricted_weekdays time MTWHF 8:00-17:00
acl restricted_weekends time A 8:00-13:00

acl CONNECT method CONNECT

#allow manager access from localhost
http_access allow manager localhost
http_access deny manager

# Only allow purge requests from localhost
http_access allow purge localhost
http_access deny purge

# Deny requests to unknown ports
http_access deny !Safe_ports

# Deny CONNECT to other than SSL ports
http_access deny CONNECT !SSL_ports

# My own rules

# Add a page do be displayed when
# a banner is removed
deny_info NOTE_ADS_FILTERED url_ads

# Then deny them
http_access deny url_ads

# Deny all archives
http_access deny archives

# Restrict access to work hours
http_access allow localnet restricted_weekdays
http_access allow localnet restricted_weekends

# Deny the rest
http_access deny all
</pre>

<p>
Next fill in the files you do not want your uses to download. I have added zip, viv, exe, mp3, rar, ace, avi, mov, mpg, mpeg, au, ra, arj, tar, gz and z files.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/squid/files.acl">
\.[Zz][Ii][pP]$
\.[Vv][Ii][Vv].*
\.[Ee][Xx][Ee]$
\.[Mm][Pp]3$
\.[Rr][Aa][Rr]$
\.[Aa][Cc][Ee]$
\.[Aa][Ss][Ff]$
\.[Aa][Vv][Ii]$
\.[Mm][Oo][Vv]$
\.[Mm][Pp][Gg]$
\.[Mm][Pp][Ee][Gg]$
\.[Aa][Uu]$
\.[Rr][Aa]$
\.[Aa][Rr][Jj]$
\.[Tt][Aa][Rr]$
\.[GgZz]$
\.[Zz]$
</pre>

<note>
Please note the [] with upper and lowercase of every character. This is done so no one can fool it by accessing a file called AvI instead of avi
</note>

<p>
Next we add the regular expressions for identifying banners. You will probably be a lot more creative than me:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/squid/banner-ads.acl">
/adv/.*\.gif$
/[Aa]ds/.*\.gif$
/[Aa]d[Pp]ix/
/[Aa]d[Ss]erver
/[Aa][Dd]/.*\.[GgJj][IiPp][FfGg]$
/[Bb]annerads/
/adbanner.*\.[GgJj][IiPp][FfGg]$
/images/ad/
/reklame/
/RealMedia/ads/.*
^http://www\.submit-it.*
^http://www\.eads.*
^http://ads\.
^http://ad\.
^http://ads02\.
^http://adaver.*\.
^http://adforce\.
adbot\.com
/ads/.*\.gif.*
_ad\..*cgi
/Banners/
/SmartBanner/
/Ads/Media/Images/
^http://static\.wired\.com/advertising/
^http://*\.dejanews\.com/ads/
^http://adfu\.blockstackers\.com/
^http://ads2\.zdnet\.com/adverts
^http://www2\.burstnet\.com/gifs/
^http://www.\.valueclick\.com/cgi-bin/cycle
^http://www\.altavista\.com/av/gifs/ie_horiz\.gif
</pre>

<p>
And the last part. We want this file to be displayed when it removes a banner. It's basically a half html file with a 4x4 transparent gif image.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/squid/errors/NOTE_ADS_FILTERED">
&lt;HTML&gt;
&lt;HEAD&gt;
&lt;META HTTP-EQUIV="REFRESH" CONTENT="0; URL=http://www.insecurity.dk/images/4x4.gif"&gt;
&lt;TITLE>ERROR: The requested URL could not be retrieved&lt;/TITLE&gt;
&lt;/HEAD&gt;
&lt;BODY&gt;
&lt;H1&gt;Add filtered!&lt;/H1&gt;
</pre>

<note>
Don't close the &lt;HTML&gt; &lt;BODY&gt; tags. This will be done by squid.
</note>

<p>
As you can see squid has a lot of possibilities and it is very effective in both filtering and proxying. It can even use alternative squid proxies to scale on very large networks. The config I have listed here is mostly suited for a small network with 1-20 users.
</p>

<p>
But combining the packet filter (iptables) and the application gateway (squid) is probably the best solution, even if squid is located somewhere safe and nobody could access it from the outside. We still need to be concerned on attack from the inside.
</p>

<p>
Now you have to add the proxy server into the settings of your clients browsers. The gateway will prevent the users from having any contact with the outside unless they use the proxy.
</p>
<note>
In Mozilla this is done in Edit->Preferences->Advanced->Proxies.
</note>

<p>
It can also be done transparently by using iptables to forward all traffic out to a squid proxy. This can be done by adding a forwarding/prerouting rule on the gateway:
</p>

<pre caption="Enable portforwarding to our proxyserver">
# <i>iptables -t nat -A PREROUTING -p tcp --dport 80 -j DNAT --to proxyhost:3128</i>
# <i>iptables -t nat -A PREROUTING -p tcp --dport 443 -j DNAT --to proxyhost:3128</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Now what have we learned?</title>

<body>

<p>
We have learned that:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>A firewall can be a risk itself. A badly configured firewall is worse then not having one at all.</li>
  <li>How to setup a basic gateway and a transparent proxy</li>
  <li>The key to a good firewall is to know the protocol you want do allow</li>
  <li>That IP traffic does not always contain legitimate data. For an example ICMP packets with payload</li>
  <li>How to be prevent SYN attack</li>
  <li>Filtering HTTP traffic by removing offensive pictures and downloads of viruses.</li>
  <li>Combining packet filters and application gateways gives a better control</li>
</ol>

<p>
Now, if you <b>really</b> need to, go create a firewall that matches your needs.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

-- Intrusion detection start --

<chapter>
<title>Intrusion detection</title>

<section>
<title>Aide (Advanced Intrusion Detection Environment)</title>
<body>

<p>
Aide is a host based intrusion detection detection system (free alternative to Tripwire). And if you already know Tripwire you should have no difficulties learning the configuration file for Aide.
</p>

<p>
The configuration file is based on regular expressions, macros and rules for files and directories. We have the following macros: 
</p>

<table borlder="0">
  <tr>
    <th>Macro</th><th>Description</th><th>Syntax</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>ifdef</ti><ti>If definded</ti><ti>@@ifdef "name"</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>ifndef</ti><ti>If not defined</ti><ti>@@ifndef "name"</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>define</ti><ti>Define a variable </ti><ti>@@define "name" "value"</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>undef</ti><ti>Undefine a variable</ti><ti>@@undef "name"</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>ifhost</ti><ti>if "hostname"</ti><ti>@@ifhost "hostname"</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>ifnhost</ti><ti>if not "hostname"</ti><ti>@@ifnhost "hostname"</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>endif</ti><ti>Endif must be used after any of the above macros except define and undef</ti><ti>@@endif</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
These macros become very handy if you have more than one Gentoo box and want to use Aide on all of them. But not all machines run the same services or maybe even users.
</p>

<p>
Next we have sets of flags to check for on files and directories. These are a combination  of permissions, file
properties and cryptographic hashes/checksums.
</p>

<table border="0">
  <tr>
    <th>Flag</th><th>Description</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>p</ti><ti>permissions</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>i</ti><ti>inode</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>n</ti><ti>number of links</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>u</ti><ti>user</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>g</ti><ti>group</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>s</ti><ti>size</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>b</ti><ti>block count</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>m</ti><ti>mtime</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>a</ti><ti>atime</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>c</ti><ti>ctime</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>S</ti><ti>check for growing size</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>md5</ti><ti>md5 checksum</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>sha1</ti><ti>sha1 checksum</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>rmd160</ti><ti>rmd160 checksum</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>tiger</ti><ti>tiger checksum</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>R</ti><ti>p+i+n+u+g+s+m+c+md5</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>L</ti><ti>p+i+n+u+g</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>E</ti><ti>Empty group</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>&gt;</ti><ti>Growing logfile p+u+g+i+n+S</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
And if Aide is compiled with mhash support it does have a few other features:
</p>

<table border="0">
  <tr>
    <th>Flag</th><th>Description</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>haval</ti><ti>haval checksum</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>gost</ti><ti>gost checksum</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>crc32</ti><ti>crc32 checksum</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
Now you can create you own rules based on the above flags by combining them like:
</p>

<pre caption="Create a ruleset for AIDE">
All=R+a+sha1+rmd160
Norm=s+n+b+md5+sha1+rmd160
</pre>

<p>
The last thing we need to create our own configuration file is to see how to add a rule to a file or directory. Basically you just type the file or dir name and the rule. Aide will add all files recursively unless you specify something else.
</p>

<table border="0">
  <tr>
    <th>Flag</th><th>Description</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>!</ti><ti>Don't add this file or directory.</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>=</ti><ti>Add this directory, but not recursive.</ti>
  </tr>
</table>

<p>
So lets watch a full blown example
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/aide/aide.conf">
@@ifndef TOPDIR 
@@define TOPDIR /
@@endif

@@ifndef AIDEDIR 
@@define AIDEDIR /etc/aide
@@endif

@@ifhost smbserv
@@define smbactive
@@endif

# The location of the database to be read.
database=file:@@{AIDEDIR}/aide.db

# The location of the database to be written.
database_out=file:aide.db.new

verbose=20
report_url=stdout

# Rule definition
All=R+a+sha1+rmd160
Norm=s+n+b+md5+sha1+rmd160

@@{TOPDIR} Norm
!@@{TOPDIR}etc/aide
!@@{TOPDIR}dev
!@@{TOPDIR}proc
!@@{TOPDIR}root
!@@{TOPDIR}tmp
!@@{TOPDIR}var/log
!@@{TOPDIR}var/run
!@@{TOPDIR}usr/portage
@@ifdef smbactive
!@@{TOPDIR}etc/smb/private/secrets.tdb
@@endif
=@@{TOPDIR}home Norm
</pre>

<p>
In the above example we specify some macros with where the topdir starts and where the aide directory is. Aide checks the <path>/etc/aide/aide.db</path> file when checking for file integrity. But when updating or creating a new file it stores the information in <path>/etc/aide/aide.db.new</path>. This is done so it won't automatic overwrite the old db file. The option report_URL is a "to come" feature that really has no meaning yet. But the authors intention was that it should be able to email or maybe even execute script.
</p>

<p>
After the configuration you should create your db file by executing aide -i and then copy the file <path>/etc/aide/aide.db.new</path> to <path>/etc/aide/aide.db</path> and add the check to cron by executing crontab -e as root.
</p>
<note>Depending on you cpu, disk access and the flags you have set on files, it can take some time</note>

<pre caption="Shedule aide as a cronjob">
0 3   * * * /usr/bin/aide -u
</pre>
<note>Remember to setup so you get roots mail. Otherwise you will never know what aide reports</note>

<p>
In this case it runs once at 3pm. This is done since I do not want to disturb the users when working. Note I'm using the -u (Update) option instead of the -C (Check). Since -u also checks the files and does not overwrite the original db file it saves some time since all you need to do is to copy a file when it detects some changes. Just check the changes to see if it was yourself that made the changes or some attacker before you copy it!
</p>

<p>
Now there is some problems with storing the db files locally since the attacker will (If he knows that aide is installed) most certainly try to alter the db file, update the db file or modify <path>/usr/bin/aide</path>. So you should create a CD or other media and put a copy of the .db file and the aide binaries.
</p>

<p>
More information can be found at <uri link="http://www.cs.tut.fi/~rammer/aide.html">aide's</uri> projectpage.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Snort</title>
<body>

<pre caption="Add a user snort to the system">
# useradd snort -d /var/log/snort -s /dev/null
# chown -R snort /var/log/snort
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/conf.d/snort">
PIDFILE=/var/run/snort_eth0.pid
MODE="full"
NETWORK="10.0.0.0/24"
LOGDIR="/var/log/snort"
CONF=/etc/snort/snort.Cong
SNORT_OPTS="-D -s -u snort -dev -l $LOGDIR -h $NETWORK -c $CONF"
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/snort/snort.conf">
<codenote>Step 1</codenote>
var HOME_NET 10.0.0.0/24
var EXTERNAL_NET any
var SMTP $HOME_NET
var HTTP_SERVERS $HOME_NET
var SQL_SERVERS $HOME_NET
var DNS_SERVERS [10.0.0.2/32,212.242.40.51/32]
var RULE_PATH ./

<codenote>Step 2</codenote>
preprocessor frag2
preprocessor stream4: detect_scans detect_state_problems detect_scans disable_evasion_alerts
preprocessor stream4_reassemble: ports all
preprocessor http_decode: 80 8080 unicode iis_alt_unicode double_encode iis_flip_slash full_whitespace
preprocessor rpc_decode: 111 32771
preprocessor bo: -nobrute
preprocessor telnet_decode

<codenote>Step 3</codenote>
include classification.config

<codenote>Step 4</codenote>
include $RULE_PATH/bad-traffic.rules
include $RULE_PATH/exploit.rules
include $RULE_PATH/scan.rules
include $RULE_PATH/finger.rules
include $RULE_PATH/ftp.rules
include $RULE_PATH/telnet.rules
include $RULE_PATH/smtp.rules
include $RULE_PATH/rpc.rules
include $RULE_PATH/rservices.rules
include $RULE_PATH/dos.rules
include $RULE_PATH/ddos.rules
include $RULE_PATH/dns.rules
include $RULE_PATH/tftp.rules
include $RULE_PATH/web-cgi.rules
include $RULE_PATH/web-coldfusion.rules
include $RULE_PATH/web-iis.rules
include $RULE_PATH/web-frontpage.rules
include $RULE_PATH/web-misc.rules
include $RULE_PATH/web-attacks.rules
include $RULE_PATH/sql.rules
include $RULE_PATH/x11.rules
include $RULE_PATH/icmp.rules
include $RULE_PATH/netbios.rules
include $RULE_PATH/misc.rules
include $RULE_PATH/attack-responses.rules
include $RULE_PATH/backdoor.rules
include $RULE_PATH/shellcode.rules
include $RULE_PATH/policy.rules
include $RULE_PATH/porn.rules
include $RULE_PATH/info.rules
include $RULE_PATH/icmp-info.rules
include $RULE_PATH/virus.rules
# include $RULE_PATH/experimental.rules
include $RULE_PATH/local.rules
</pre>

<pre caption="/etc/snort/classification.config">
config classification: not-suspicious,Not Suspicious Traffic,3
config classification: unknown,Unknown Traffic,3
config classification: bad-unknown,Potentially Bad Traffic, 2
config classification: attempted-recon,Attempted Information Leak,2
config classification: successful-recon-limited,Information Leak,2
config classification: successful-recon-largescale,Large Scale Information Leak,2
config classification: attempted-dos,Attempted Denial of Service,2
config classification: successful-dos,Denial of Service,2
config classification: attempted-user,Attempted User Privilege Gain,1
config classification: unsuccessful-user,Unsuccessful User Privilege Gain,1
config classification: successful-user,Successful User Privilege Gain,1
config classification: attempted-admin,Attempted Administrator Privilege Gain,1
config classification: successful-admin,Successful Administrator Privilege Gain,1

# NEW CLASSIFICATIONS
config classification: rpc-portmap-decode,Decode of an RPC Query,2
config classification: shellcode-detect,Executable code was detected,1
config classification: string-detect,A suspicious string was detected,3
config classification: suspicious-filename-detect,A suspicious filename was detected,2
config classification: suspicious-login,An attempted login using a suspicious username was detected,2
config classification: system-call-detect,A system call was detected,2
config classification: tcp-connection,A TCP connection was detected,4
config classification: trojan-activity,A Network Trojan was detected, 1
config classification: unusual-client-port-connection,A client was using an unusual port,2
config classification: network-scan,Detection of a Network Scan,3
config classification: denial-of-service,Detection of a Denial of Service Attack,2
config classification: non-standard-protocol,Detection of a non-standard protocol or event,2
config classification: protocol-command-decode,Generic Protocol Command Decode,3
config classification: web-application-activity,access to a potentially vulnerable web application,2
config classification: web-application-attack,Web Application Attack,1
config classification: misc-activity,Misc activity,3
config classification: misc-attack,Misc Attack,2
config classification: icmp-event,Generic ICMP event,3
config classification: kickass-porn,SCORE! Get the lotion!,1
</pre>

<p>
More information can be found at <uri link="http://www.snort.org">Snorts</uri> website.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

-- Intrusion detection end --

<chapter>
<title>Changes since last version</title>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>

<p>
Version 0.1 -> 0.2
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Fixed a lot of typos found by various people (Mostly by Bjarke Sørensen)</li>
  <li>Changes to tie apache.conf (ServerTokens min)</li>
  <li>Fixed problem with pre-tags more than 80 chars wide</li>
  <li>Added a firewall chapter</li>
</ul>

<p>
Version 0.2 -> 0.4
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Added a chapter on intrusion detection.</li>
  <li>Fixed a bug in the firewall script.</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>



<chapter>
<title>FAQ</title>

<section>
<title>Answars and questions</title>
<body>

<table border="0">
  <tr>
    <th>Question</th><th>Answar</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Where can I find the latest version of this guide?</ti><ti>The lastest version should be available on <uri>http://gentoo.org</uri> and the development version at <uri>http://gentoo.insecurity.dk</uri></ti>
  </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>


</guide>
