<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/en/gentoo-ppc-faq.xml">
	<title>Gentoo Linux/PowerPC Frequently Asked Questions</title>
	<author title="Editor"><mail link="rajiv@gentoo.org">Rajiv Manglani</mail></author>
	<author title="Editor"><mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail></author>

	<abstract>This FAQ is a collection of questions and answers collected from the
	gentoo-ppc-dev mailing list and from IRC -- if you have any questions (or
	answers!) to add, please contact either an author or a member of the
	documentation team.</abstract>

  <license/>

	<version>1.6</version>
	<date>September 30, 2003</date>


	<chapter>
		<title>Installation</title>

			<section>
				<title>How do I verify with Mac OS X the downloaded ISO is not
				corrupted?  And how can I burn it with Mac OS X?</title>
				<body>

				<p>First be sure you did not mounted the ftp-server with the
				<e>Finder</e> and copied the file with drag'n'drop.  This will corrupt
				the ISO.  Instead use <c>curl</c> (with <c>curl -O
				http://path/to/iso</c>).</p>

				<p>As long as Mac OS X does not offer <c>md5sum</c>, you have to use the
				<c>openssl</c> capability to produce an md5 checksum.  Therefore type in
				Terminal.app</p>

				<pre caption="md5sum with the help of openssl">
$ <i>openssl md5 /path/to/iso</i>
<comment>This could take some time depending of the size of the ISO and your CPU</comment>
				</pre>

				<p>Now compare the output with the content of the appropriate file with
				the ending <path>.md5</path> on the server.  If it is the same, your
				download is correct.  Be sure you have <e>not</e> mounted it (e.g. with
				Disk Copy) yet!</p>

				<p>Then mark the ISO in the <e>Finder</e> an click on <e>File->Burn
				Image</e>.  Insert a blank CD-R and burn it.  You can also use <e>Disk
				Copy</e>, <e>Toast</e> or <e>XCDRoast</e> for the burn process.</p>

				<p>After that you are able to boot from your new Gentoo Linux LiveCD!</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Can I dual-boot Gentoo Linux and Mac OS X?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Yes you can! In fact, <e>yabootconfig</e> will automatically detect
				and setup <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> with Linux, Mac OS X and even
				classic Mac OS (see the <uri
				link="/doc/en/gentoo-ppc-install.xml">Gentoo PPC Install Guide</uri> for
				details on yabootconfig). The trick is in how you partition your hard
				drive. Before installing Gentoo, startup with the Mac OS X Install CD.
				Use the <c>Disk Utility</c> to partition the drive in your machine into
				two or three partitions.  Alternatively use <c>parted</c> from the
				recent LiveCD, that can handle HFS and HFS+ partitions.  Furthermore it
				is able to shrink a partition so you don't need to delete you whole
				disk.  The first should be a single partition the total size of all your
				Linux partitions (root+swap+/home etc.). The format of this partition
				does not matter. The second should be for OS X.  The third (and
				optional) partition should be for classic Mac OS. It is needed only if
				you want to put Mac OS 9 on a separate partition.</p>
				
				<note>If you want to be able to triple-boot with yaboot, Mac OS 9 needs
				to be on a separate partition from your Mac OS X installation.</note>

				<p>After partitioning, install Mac OS X and Mac OS 9 onto their
				respective partitions. Once installation is complete, start following
				the <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-ppc-install.xml">Gentoo Linux PPC Install
				Guide</uri>. When you get to the section on partitioning, use
				<c>mac-fdisk</c> to <e>delete</e> the large partition you created for
				Gentoo. In its place, create a bootstrap partition, root, swap, and any
				other partitions you want to use with Gentoo.</p>

				<p>If you have an OldWorld Macintosh (pre-iMac), follow a similar
				procedure as described above. However, use the Mac OS 9 install CD and
				the <c>Drive Setup</c> utility. OldWorld machines do not need a
				bootstrap partition.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>I have an OldWorld Macintosh and need to use BootX. However, I am
			having trouble opening the BootX installer on the PPC install CD. What can
			I do?</title>
			<body>

				<p>You will need a new version of <i>StuffIt Expander</i> to open the
				file. You can <uri
				link="http://www.stuffit.com/expander/download.html">download it</uri>
				for free.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Is it possible to boot Gentoo Linux on an OldWorld machine without
			MacOS? I would like to have a MacOS-free machine.</title>
			<body>

				<p>If you have a lot of time to experiment, you could try <uri
				link="http://penguinppc.org/projects/quik/">Quik</uri>. <e>Quik</e> is a
				bootloader for OldWorld PPC machines. If your machine uses <e>BootX</e>,
				you can use <e>Quik</e>; if it uses <e>yaboot</e>, you can't.
				<e>Quik</e> can be incredibly difficult to install, and is currently
				<e>not</e> working with gcc 3.x (read: Gentoo 1.4 or better), but the
				end result is somewhere between "neato" and "breathtaking" because MacOS
				does not have to load. Think yaboot on speed.</p>

				<p>Be sure to read the <uri
				link="http://penguinppc.org/projects/quik/quirks.shtml">Quik quirks
				page</uri>. Also see "<uri
				link="http://lppcfom.sourceforge.net/fom-serve/cache/574.html">Is Quik
				Bootloader for Mac OS Dead?</uri>" and "<uri
				link="http://www.imaclinux.net/php/imaclinux_g_h.php3?single=17+index=0">Guide:
				Quik - Direct Booting for Older PowerMacs</uri>". "<uri
				link="http://www.netbsd.org/Ports/macppc/models.html">NetBSD/macppc
				Model Support</uri>" documents OpenFirmware versions for various Apple
				and clone PowerPC machines.</p>

				<p>Thanks to vladimir for this information.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>I have a Beige G3 machine. Can I install Gentoo Linux/PPC on a
			second IDE hard drive?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Early Beige G3 machines (those with a "Rev 1" motherboard with an ATI
				RageII+ chip) do not support slave IDE drives. To use a second hard drive
				with this machine, you would have to attach it to the internal or external
				SCSI connector, use install a PCI IDE card. Later G3 machines do not have
				this limitation. See
				<uri>http://www.xlr8yourmac.com/G3-ZONE/IDE/index.html</uri> for more
				information.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>When I try and install Gentoo on my PowerBook or iBook the internal
			hard drive does not show up. What should I do?</title>
			<body>

				<p>For a PowerBook, pass <c>hda=1,1,1</c> to the kernel at boot time.
				That should solve your problems. You can do this at <e>yaboot</e> prompt
				by typing <c>boot hda=1,1,1</c>. Some iBooks need
				<c>hda=16383,16,64</c>.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>My <path>/etc/fstab</path> file has <path>/dev/BOOT</path> in it.
			Do I need to setup this line for my bootstrap partition?</title>
			<body>

				<p>No. If you are not running a separate boot partition
				(<path>/boot</path>) then you do not need this line and can safely just
				delete it from <path>/etc/fstab</path>.  The bootstrap partition is
				<e>not</e> <path>/boot</path> and is not related in anyway. In general,
				PowerPC machines do not need a separate <path>/boot</path> partition,
				and the bootstrap partition should not be mounted.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Installation is now complete. However after rebooting, I am getting
			different characters than the keys I press on my machine's keyboard. What
			should I do?</title> 
			<body>

				<p>If this is an English keymap, you likely have a kernel config issue.
				You will need to rebuild your kernel with the following options:</p>

				<pre caption="Input core support">
<comment>(these are the defaults, but check them)</comment>
 &lt;*&gt; Input core support
 &lt;*&gt;   Keyboard support 
 &lt;*&gt;   Mouse support
 (1024)   Horizontal screen resolution
 (768)    Vertical screen resolution
 &lt; &gt;   Joystick support
 &lt;*&gt;   Event interface support
				</pre>

				<pre caption="Macintosh Device Drivers">
 [*] Apple Desktop Bus (ADB) support
 [ ]    Include MacIO (CHRP) ADB driver   <comment>doesn't matter</comment>
 [*]    Use input layer for ADB devices
 [ ]      Support for ADB raw keycodes    <comment>turn this OFF</comment>
 [*]      Support for mouse button 2+3 emulation
				</pre>

				<p>This way, you will still be able to use
				<path>/proc/sys/dev/mac_hid</path> to emulate buttons 2 and 3 (see
				section 18 of the Gentoo PPC Install Guide).</p>

				<p>If, for some reason you do not want to recompile your kernel, append
				<c>keyboard_sends_linux_keycodes=1</c> to the kernel arguments in
				<path>yaboot.conf</path>. This will also correct the problem, but might
				possibly introduce other problems.</p>

				<p>Thanks to Joe McMahon for help with this answer.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Installation is now complete. However, after my machine boots into
			Gentoo and I try to emerge anything, I see errors saying it cannot 'stat'
			a file. What is wrong?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Check to see that your time is set correctly. Setting your time and
				linking <path>/etc/localtime</path> to your proper timezone (in
				<path>/usr/share/zoneinfo</path>) will solve your problems. Also make
				sure that you have <e>not</e> enabled the <e>Enhanced RTC</e> option in
				the <e>Character devices</e> section of the kernel configuration (as
				stated in install guide).</p>

			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>


	<chapter>
		<title>Laptop Support</title>
		<section>
			<title>How do I enable the full processor speed on my PowerBook while
			running Linux?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Some processors in PowerBooks start up at slower speed than they are
				designed to run. Running at this slower speed conserves battery life
				with the tradeoff of performance. The operating system on the machine
				must instruct the hardware to run at its full speed. In Mac OS X this is
				called "Reduced processor performance" or "CPU Scaling" in Linux. To
				check the current speed of your processor while running in Linux, type
				<c>cat /proc/cpuinfo</c>. In Mac OS X, you first have to turn off
				"Reduce processor performance" in the "Options" tab of the <e>Energy Saver</e>
				system preference panel. Then run <e>Apple System Profiler</e> (in
				Applications:Utilities).</p>

				<warn>Do not use this method to overclock your machine. Results are
				unpredictable if you use an improper value. We are not responsible if
				you fry your machine!</warn>

				<p>If <e>Apple System Profiler</e> reports a higher speed than what you
				get when running in Linux, you can enable the full speed of the
				processor with a simple command. First, your machine needs to be running
				kernel <c>2.4.20-pre9-ben0</c> or later. Earlier kernels do not have the
				code necessary to change the processor speed. Second, you will need to
				compile the kernel with <c>CPU Frequency scaling</c> <e>disabled</e>.
				Finally, run an appropriate command as shown in the examples below.</p>

				<pre caption="CPU Frequency scaling">
<codenote>These are examples only. Use values appropriate for your machine.</codenote>

echo "0:667000:1000000:performance" > /proc/cpufreq    <codenote>For a 1ghz PowerBook G4</codenote>
echo "0:667000:800000:performance" > /proc/cpufreq     <codenote>For an 800mhz PowerBook G4</codenote>
				</pre>

				<p>Many users will want to add this command to the end of
				<path>/etc/conf.d/local.start</path>. This file is sourced every time
				your machine starts.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>I'm running Gentoo on a PowerPC laptop. What packages should I
			install to enable laptop-specific functionality?</title>
			<body>

				<p>There are four main packages you will need to install.</p>

				<ul>
					<li><e>pmud</e> is the Power Management daemon for your hardware
					(similar to apmd on x86). Please note that pmud may also require a
					working sound device (<path>/dev/mixer</path>).</li>
					<li><e>pbbuttonsd</e> is a tool that enables the brightness and volume
					keys on most ppc laptops.  Latest versions also allow it to act as a
					pmud replacement.</li>
					<li><e>gtkpbbuttons</e> gives you a gtk front end for pbbuttonsd
					(visual feedback on button presses in X).  <e>gtkpbbuttons</e>
					requires gtk and should be added to your X session file
					(<path>~/.Xsession</path>) for best results (so that it is always
					running while in X).</li>
					<li><e>powerprefs</e> ties together with pbbuttonsd, and gives you the
					ability to edit settings such as trackpad options and various other
					preferences.</li>
				</ul>

				<p>These packages can be installed by running the appropriate commands from the list below:</p>

	<pre>
	# <c>emerge pmud; rc-update add pmud default</c> <comment>not required as pbbuttonsd is a complete replacement</comment>
	# <c>emerge pbbuttonsd; rc-update add pbbuttonsd default</c>
	# <c>emerge gtkpbbuttons</c>
	# <c>emerge powerprefs</c>
	</pre>

				<note>You should edit your <path>/etc/pbbuttonsd.conf</path> for your
				preferences.  Especially the behaviour of the Fx-keys, as pbbuttonsd
				gives you the availabilty, to use the Fx-keys in the first mode, and the
				brightness- and sound-keys with the help of Fn.</note>

				</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>How can I configure my machine's Airport or other Wi-Fi
			card?</title>
			<body>

				<p>First, make sure you have support for the airport card complied into
				the kernel, or compiled as a module and loaded. Then, <c>emerge
				wireless-tools; iwconfig</c>.</p>

				<note>Airport Extreme cards are not yet supported on Linux.</note>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Will the internal modem in an iBook2 or PowerBook work?</title>
			<body>

				<p>emerge <path>net-dialin/hcfusbmodem</path> that will provide
				<path>/dev/ttySHCF0</path>.  Then set up ppp like usual.  Further
				information about the installation can be found at
				<uri>http://www.linuxant.com/drivers/hcf/install.html</uri></p>

			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>


	<chapter>
		<title>Applications</title>
		<section>
			<title>Is there an easy way to configure X?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Thanks to Gerk, you can do <c>emerge xeasyconf; Xeasyconf</c>.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>How can I enable Direct Rendering (DRM) on rage128 or radeon
			cards?</title>
			<body>

				<p>emerge xfree (4.3.x) and xfree-drm-4.3.0.</p>

				<p>Make sure in your kernel config you have the following options set:</p>

				<pre caption="DRM kernel configuration">
Character devices ---&gt;
&lt;*&gt; /dev/agpgart (AGP Support)
[*] Apple UniNorth support
[*] Direct Rendering Manager (XFree86 DRI support)
				</pre>

				<p>Also make sure to disable both the r128 and radeon drm drivers in the
				kernel (the xfree-drm provides much updated versions that are required for
				this to work).</p>

				<pre caption="disable r128 and radeon drivers">
&lt; &gt; ATI Rage 128
&lt; &gt; ATI Radeon
				</pre>

				<p>Rebuild and install the kernel if necessary. After this, make sure you
				are booted from the native framebuffer (i.e. radeonfb or atyfb and
				<e>not</e> from offb or ofonly video), and run <c>Xeasyconf</c>.</p>

				<impo>You may need to edit your <path>XF86Config-4</path> file depending
				on your card setup. When running <c>Xeasyconf</c>, also please choose the
				"auto" option and not "ati" for your video card setup.</impo>

				<p>You can run the command <c>dmesg</c> to see which version of the radeon
				drm module is loaded. If all is correct for radeon you should see 1.7.0 or
				newer loading, if you see 1.2.x you have the kernel radeon drivers still
				compiled into your running kernel or as modules and they are loaded.
				Looking in <path>/var/log/Xfree.0.log</path> is a good place to get
				detailed information for troubleshooting.</p>

				<note>If/when you do another <c>make modules_install</c> in your current
				kernel, or you upgrade to a new kernel you will have to reemerge xfree-drm
				again.</note>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>I recently emerged XFree, but when using it, my international
			keyboard layout does not work correctly. The main keys work fine but I am
			unable to compose special characters like the "at" sign. The startx output
			says something like "could not load keymap, falling back to default
			keymap". What is wrong?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Check that the permissions on <path>/var/tmp</path> are set to
				<path>drwxrwxrwx</path>. If not, change them by typing <c>chmod a+rwx
				/var/tmp</c>. This will allow XFree to load keymaps properly again.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>When using OpenGL DRI in XFree or playing movies, the system
			sometimes freezes hard unexpectedly. What can I do?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Your system may not cope properly with AGP support. Newer kernels
				(2.4.20 or higher) and XFree 4.3 or better should solve this. Until then
				the easiest solution is to add the following line to the "Device"
				section of <path>/etc/X11/XF86Config-4</path>:</p>

				<pre caption="Forcing PCI mode for AGP-Cards">
Option       "ForcePCIMode"
				</pre>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>How do I get sound output working?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Two things are needed here. First, you have to make sure that you
				have the correct kernel options selected.  In <c>make menuconfig</c> you
				need:</p>

				<pre caption="kernel options for sound">
&lt;*&gt; Sound card support
&lt;*&gt;   PowerMac DMA sound support
				</pre>

				<p>(or selected as modules and loaded). Second, users who should have
				access to the audio devices need to be added to the appropriate group
				with the command <c>chmod -g audio [username]</c>. If
				the<c>dmasound_pmac</c> module does not load, you probably need to
				enable <c>i2c-core</c> in the kernel or as a module.</p>

				</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>How do I play Audio CDs?</title>
			<body>

				<p>NewWorld machines have no audio connection between their CD-ROM drive
				and their sound hardware. Therefore, audio information must be read as
				data and then piped to the sound hardware. This is possible using
				<e>xmms</e> and the <e>xmms-cdread</e> plugin, that reads the audio off
				the CD over the ATA cable, decodes it in software and sends it to the
				sound card over the PCI bus as digital data.  If you want 'true'
				cd-playing, you have to do the following steps:</p>

				<p>First, you will need to rebuild your kernel with the following options:</p>

				<pre caption="Kernel options for playing audio-CDs">
<codenote>In "ATA/IDE/MFM/RLL Support"</codenote>
<codenote>In "IDE, ATA, and ATAPI Block Devices"</codenote>
 &lt; &gt; Include IDE/ATAPI CDROM support  <codenote>turn this OFF</codenote>
 &lt;M&gt; SCSI emulation support           <codenote>compile this as a module</codenote>

<codenote>In "SCSI Support"</codenote>
 &lt;M&gt; SCSI support                     <codenote>compile this as a module</codenote>
 &lt;M&gt; SCSI CD-ROM support              <codenote>compile this as a module</codenote>
</pre>

				<p>Then, append <c>hdX=ide-scsi</c> to the kernel image section(s) in
				<path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> where <c>hdX</c> is the IDE device
				corresponding to your CD player. This is usually <c>hdc</c>. Type
				<c>ybin -v</c> to install the new yaboot.conf settings. Edit
				<path>/etc/group</path> add any users who should be able to play CDs to
				the <c>cdrom</c> group. You will now need to reboot your system for the
				kernel changes to take effect.</p>

				<p>Upon reboot, <c>su</c> to root and change the permissions of the cd device, then install xmms:</p>

				<pre caption="changing permission for cdrom and install xmms-read">
# <i>chown root.cdrom /dev/scsi/host0/bus0/target0/lun0/cd</i>
# <i>chmod 660 /dev/scsi/host0/bus0/target0/lun0/cd</i>
# <i>emerge xmms xmms-cdread</i>
				</pre>

				<note>Make sure to use the path corresponding to the CD drive on your
				machine.</note>

				<p>To play a CD, fire up <c>xmms</c> and enter <c>/dev/cdrom</c> as the
				file you want to play.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Can I run Mac OS or Mac OS X under Gentoo Linux?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Yes, as long as your are running Gentoo Linux/PPC on Apple hardware
				(or a Mac-clone). You will need to run <uri
				link="http://www.maconlinux.org/">Mac-on-Linux</uri>. Just <c>emerge
				mol</c>. MOL support Mac OS 7.5.2 to 9.2.2, as well as OS X 10.1 and
				10.2.  It can take over your full screen, or run in a window.</p>

				<p>For networking and sound you might install the drivers in the folder
				<path>MOL-Install</path> on your Mac OS X-Desktop.  If errors with
				networking occur, make sure you have the following kernel options
				enabled:</p>

				<p>For the dhcp server:</p>

				<ul>
					<li>Socket Filtering (CONFIG_FILTER)</li>
					<li>Packet Socket (CONFIG_PACKET)</li>
				</ul>

				<p>For NAT:</p>

				<ul>
					<li>Network packet filtering (CONFIG_NETFILTER)</li>
					<li>Connection tracking (CONFIG_IP_NF_CONNTRACK)</li> 
					<li>IP tables support (CONFIG_IP_NF_IPTABLES)</li> 
					<li>Packet filtering (CONFIG_IP_NF_FILTER)</li> 
					<li>Full NAT (CONFIG_IP_NF_NAT)</li>
					<li>MASQUERADE target support (CONFIG_IP_NF_TARGET_MASQUERADE)</li>
				</ul>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Which Portage USE flags do not work on PowerPC machines?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Look at <path>/etc/make.profile/make.defaults</path> for a list.</p>

			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>


	<chapter>
	<title>Resources</title>
		<section>
			<title>Can I buy a CD of Gentoo Linux/PPC?</title>
			<body>

				<p>Yes! We sell Gentoo on CD-ROM in our <uri
				link="http://store.gentoo.org/">Gentoo store</uri>.  You can choose
				between CDs with precompiled packages for generic ppc hardware, or
				optimized for G3 and G4 processors, or a KDE/GNOME LiveCD that boots
				directly in a live Gentoo Linux environment.</p>

			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>This FAQ hasn't answered my question. What do I do now?</title>
			<body>

				<p>A good first step is to browse through the relevant <uri
				link="/main/en/docs.xml">documentation on www.gentoo.org</uri>. Two
				PPC-specific <uri link="/main/en/lists.xml">mailing lists</uri>
				currently exist, gentoo-ppc-dev and gentoo-ppc-user.  <uri
				link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum.php?f=24">Gentoo on PPC</uri>
				(on forums.gentoo.org) is an open bulletin-board for discussion of all
				PowerPC issues. Also, there is usually a lively discussion on IRC. Join
				us on <i>#gentoo-ppc</i> on <i>irc.freenode.net</i>.</p>

				<p>General information about Linux on PowerPC can be found at <uri
				link="http://penguinppc.org/">penguinppc.org</uri> and the <uri
				link="http://lppcfom.sourceforge.net/">Linux on PowerPC
				FAQ-O-Matic</uri>. General Linux information is at <uri
				link="http://www.linuxdoc.org/">www.linuxdoc.org</uri>.</p>

			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</guide>
