<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<guide link="/doc/en/gentoo-release-policy.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Release Policy</title>
<author title = "Author">
<mail link = "drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author>
<author title = "Author">
<mail link = "avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail></author>
<author title = "Editor">
<mail link = "zhen@gentoo.org">John P. Davis</mail></author>

<license/>

<version>1.2</version>
<date>11 July 2003</date>

<abstract>The Offical Gentoo Linux Release Policy</abstract>

	<chapter>
		<title>Initial Concerns, Questions</title>
		<section>
			<title>What is the Gentoo Linux release process?</title>
			<body>
			<p>The Gentoo Linux release process is the clearly-defined and documented
			procedure that the Gentoo Linux development team uses to create new
			release candidates and new official releases of Gentoo Linux. In
			practice, it is meant to be a team-based, coordinated effort that
			involves every member of the development team.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Who is "in charge" of the Gentoo Linux release process?</title>
			<body>
			<p>While the Release Process is coordinated by the Release Coordinator and
			the releng team, the process itself is a team effort.
			There is no one person responsible for doing all or even the majority
			of the work. It is the responsibility of the Release Coordinator to
			involve the entire team in the release process, by doing
			things like posting regular updates to the -core mailing list to
			keep everyone abreast of the current release status,
			coordinating with those managing the building of stage tarballs and
			GRP package sets, and those performing QA testing. 
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Goals of the Gentoo Linux release process</title>
			<body>
			<ul>
			<li>On-time release of a new release candidate or full version of Gentoo
			Linux. </li>

			<li>Proper QA testing on the new release.</li>

			<li>Opportunity for stable changes to get into the release.</li>

			<li>To make the release process a *team* process</li>

			<li>Ensure that new official versions of Gentoo Linux are ready for the
			public. </li>
			</ul>
			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>
	
	<chapter>
		<title>How the Gentoo Linux release process works</title>
		<section>
			<title>Initial decision</title>
			<body>
			<p>The release process starts with an official decision to release a new
			version of Gentoo Linux, made by the top level management team, who then present:
			</p>
		        
			<ul>
			<li>A clear schedule for the release process, including all 
			milestones and deadlines. </li> 

			<li>A specific list of goals for this release (optional). </li>
			</ul>
		
			<p>
			The Release Coordinator then guides the release process, ensuring that the
			necessary release infrastructure is in place and functioning cohesively. The
			release coordinator then informs all developers of the start of the next phase,
			which begins immediately.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Build and test</title>
			<body>
			<p>In this phase, assigned builders for each architecture build a "generic CPU" set
			of stage tarballs using a current Portage snapshot, and
			report/fix/create bugs to fix any build-related bugs found. In addition,
			our initial QA testers use these stages and report any runtime bugs
			found.
			</p>

			<p>As new bugs in the stage tarballs are found and fixed, new releases of
			the stage tarballs are rolled up.
			These stage tarballs are posted on a
			publicly-accessible Web site so that testing can begin by developers and
			users recruited for QA efforts.
			</p>

			<p>A week after beginning, this "build an test" phase
			switches from using a *current* CVS tree to using the official
			GENTOO_x.y_SNAP_YYYYMMDDAB snapshot of the CVS tree. An effort is made
			to resolve all outstanding build/runtime issues. As bugs are fixed, new
			GENTOO_x.y_SNAP_YYYYMMDDAB (with new date) tags are made, and these
			new snapshots are used to build new bug-fixed stage tarballs.
			</p>

			<p>Ten days after the beginning of the "build and test" phase, a
			determination is made as to whether this next release will be an
			"official release" or release candidate. The Development Lead
			for each arch, the Release Coordinator,
			the Development Manager, and the Chief Architect all come
			to a final unanimous decision in this matter. 
			</p>

			<p>If quality is not where it should be, the next release should be a
			release candidate. If quality is good, all goals for the release have
			been met and major issues are resolved or resolvable in a reasonable
			time, then the next release should be an official release. 
			</p>

			<p>The latest GENTOO_x.y_SNAP_YYYYMMDDAB snapshot is used for this release.
			With generic stage tarballs for this snapshot in hand, the next phase
			begins...
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Release build and test</title>
			<body>

			<p>Immediately, a large-scale, coordinated distributed build effort begins
			to build the full new Gentoo Linux release or release candidate,
			including GRP package sets. If release candidate, a smaller subset of
			system variants (ie, i686 and maybe one more for x86) may be optionally
			chosen instead of a "full" build. During this build process, any
			last-minute quirks are ironed out. Install documentation is updated for
			the new release. Release announcements are written, but not yet made
			public. And private QA testing of the final release binaries begin as
			soon as they have finished compiling. This is our final QA verification
			before release.
			</p>

			<p>This entire phases, including creation of LiveCDs and uploading to
			mirrors, should complete in no more than 4 days.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
			<title>Release</title>
			<body>
			
			<p>The new version or release candidate of Gentoo Linux is released
			and announcements are posted in the relevant locations.</p>

			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</guide>
			

			
			
			
			
			
			
			
			
			
			
			
			
