<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/en/gentoo-ppc-install.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux/PPC 1.4 Installation Instructions</title>

<author title="Gentoo PPC lead, Maintainer">
   <mail link="pvdabeel@gentoo.org">Pieter Van den Abeele</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
   <mail link="rajiv@gentoo.org">Rajiv Manglani</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
   <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
   <!-- zhen@gentoo.org -->John P. Davis
</author>
<author title="Chief Architect">
   <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>
</author>
<author title="Reviewer">
   <mail link="peitolm@gentoo.org">Colin Morey</mail>
</author>

<license/>

<abstract>
These instructions step you through the process of installing Gentoo
Linux/PPC 1.4. The Gentoo Linux installation process supports various 
installation approaches, ranging from a 20 minute install to a compile 
everything from scratch install.
</abstract>

<version>1.6.3</version>
<date>16 August 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>Getting the CD</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo/PPC 1.4 CDs can be found in the <path>releases</path> directory on 
any of the Gentoo Mirrors or can be bought in the <uri 
link="http://store.gentoo.org">Gentoo store</uri>. 
If you prefer downloading, please have a look at the Gentoo 
mirrors list (<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/mirrors.xml</uri>) and select 
the mirror which is located closest to where you live. For the inpatient,
click <uri link="http://gentoo.oregonstate.edu/releases/ppc/">here</uri>
</p>

<p>
There are several CD flavors available, which we will discuss next.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>CD flavor: GRP 2-disc sets</title>
<body>

<p>
A 2-disc cd set is available for generic PPC, G3 and G4 powered systems. (A 2 
disc G5 set is expected soon.) The first CD of the set contains: 
</p>

<ul>
<li>
all distfiles needed for build from scratch, emerge kernel, emerge xfree, 
emerge bootloader...
</li>
<li>
a portage snapshot
</li>
<li>
a generic PPC stage1
</li>
<li>
a cpu optimized stage2 and stage3
</li>
</ul>

<p>
A stage is a unix tarball that contains a minimal Linux system that needs to 
be unpacked on an empty partition on the hard disk you wish to install Gentoo 
on. Stages also come in different sizes: A stage1 contains a very minimal 
system (only directory structure and non-bootstrapped compiler), a stage2 
tarball is a bit larger (the compiler is already bootstrapped, which saves 
you quite some time during installation) and a stage3 contains a basic Linux 
system (bootstrapped compiler and basic tools). You'll need to choose one of 
these stages later on in this document. Stages are available separately from 
all Gentoo mirrors, but GRP CD 1 already contains 1 generic PPC stage1 and 
CPU optimized stage2 and stage3.
</p>

<p>
A portage snapshot is a unix tarball that contains a directory structure 
filled with executeable installation instructions (ebuilds). ebuilds from 
the portage snapshot are used by the emerge command to install/uninstall
applications. The portage tree can be kept up to date using the internet. A 
snapshot is provided to allow for a netless install.
</p>

<p>
The <path>distfiles</path> directory on the cd contains source tarballs used to
compile core stuff from scratch. Normally source tarballs are downloaded using 
the network connection. To allow for netless install, these distfiles needed to 
be placed on the cd. Note that distfiles only contain source. Prebuild 
packages (GRP packages) are placed on CD 2. CD 2 is not bootable.
</p> 

<p>
If you want to do a quick (20 minutes) netless install, GRP is your first 
choice.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CD flavor: nostages</title>
<body>

<p>
Same as the GRP CD 1, but contains no stages, nor distfiles or portage 
snapshot. Only 70M in size. Stages can be downloaded from the Gentoo mirrors 
when booted from the livecd. Note that a network connection is required when 
you choose this cd.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CD flavor: smallestcd</title>
<body>

<p>
This CD is only around for historical reasons. It's only 15M in size
(no airport or ppc support).
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CD flavor: kde/gnome livecd</title>
<body>
<p>
This cd contains a complete live Gentoo environment featuring the KDE and 
Gnome desktop environment, an apache webserver, several webbrowsers, irc 
clients, firewall/router stuff, network auditing stuff, a lot of CLI tools... 
It can be used to fix a broken OS X filesystem. The kde/gnome livecd contains 
an entire gcc (distcc, ccache enabled) toolchain; boot all macs on your 
network using this cd and experience the power of distributed compilation. 
Other non-ppc gentoo livecds are distcc enabled too and distributed 
cross-compilation (use your x86, sparcs, etc to build for ppc or others) will 
be available soon. This cd can be used to install Gentoo, but does not contain 
GRP, distfiles, nor a portage snapshot or stages. Network connection needed 
for install.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<body>

<p>
All Gentoo Linux/PPC 1.4 boot CDs will boot any NewWorld Macs. Any 1.4 boot
CD can be easily booted on OldWorld macs by downloading BootX and starting
it (from a hfs partition) with the correct arguments. (Select 
<path>/boot/initrd.img.gz</path> as initrd, <path>/boot/vmlinux</path> as 
kernel, set initrd-size to 11000, set root to <path>/dev/ram</path> and set 
init to <path>/linuxrc</path>). Several people have installed Gentoo/PPC on 
oldworld machines (even some former <uri>http://www.apple.com/support</uri> ANS 
machines now run Gentoo/PPC). Feel free to share your experiences with the PPC 
developers by visiting the #gentoo-ppc room on irc.freenode.net. Both irssi 
and bitchX are available on all installation cdroms.
</p>

<p>
To install from the build CD, you will need to have a PowerPC 603 or
better processor on a PowerPC PCI based system or newer. Less than
128mb ram is possible but the build process could be very slow under
those conditions and could die. At the time of writing Nubus machines 
are not officially supported, but it should be noted that
developers succeeded in installing Gentoo on nubus machines (using
cross compilation and distcc). 
</p>

<p>
Now, let's quickly review the install process. We'll create partitions, 
create our file systems, and extract either a stage1, stage2 or stage3 tarball. 
If we are using a stage1 or stage2 tarball, we will take the appropriate steps 
to get our systems to stage3. Once our systems are at stage3, we can configure 
them (tweaking config files, installing a bootloader, etc) and boot them and 
have a fully-functional Gentoo Linux system. Depending on what stage of the 
build process you're starting from, here's what's required for installation:
</p>

<p>
<table>
<tr><th>stage tarball</th><th>requirements for installation</th></tr>
<tr><ti>1</ti><ti>partition/file system setup, bootstrap, emerge system, emerge kernel, final configuration</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>2</ti><ti>partition/file system setup, emerge system, emerge kernel, final configuration</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>3</ti><ti>partition/file system setup, final configuration</ti></tr>
</table>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Booting</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Once you've chosen the CD you want to use, go ahead and boot it either by
holding down the 'C' key at bootup or by running an OldWorld bootloader 
(BootX, quik). You'll be greeted by a friendly welcome message and a 
<c>boot:</c> prompt at the bottom of the screen. At this prompt, hit enter, 
and a complete Gentoo Linux environment will be loaded from the CD. 
(If you experience problems booting, choose the -safe option at boot. The safe 
option passes the following extra arguments to the kernel: 
append="video=ofonly nol3 init=/linuxrc").
</p>

<p>
Use root as username and leave the password blank to login on the live cd
(a "live" gentoo/PPC system). Logging in is not necessary on the
smallestcd.
</p>

<p>
If you're installing on a system with a non-US keymap, use the loadkeys
command to set your keymap. Keymaps can be found in 
<path>/usr/share/keymaps</path>. The smallestcd uses a menu (configuration
system) to set keymaps during boot.
</p>

<p>
A lot of linux kernel modules are available and automatically loaded if
needed. The livecds (not smallestcd) even contains multimedia stuff (ALSA,
mplayer, etc.) and can be used to play live music during installation.
(Please note that playing a high bandwidth stream will probably slow down
installation a bit.)
</p>
 
<p>
Lots of programs are available on the livecd (like irc clients,
webbrowsers, ssh, telnet, samba, talk ...) and can be used simultanuously
during installation by using Linux console. You should have a root prompt 
on the current console, but you could also open new consoles by typing 
ctrl+alt+f2, ctrl+alt+f3 (on powerbooks/ibooks possible ctrl+alt+fn+f2), to
activate other consoles.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Load kernel modules</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
We're almost ready to begin installing Gentoo Linux, and for the most part 
the Gentoo PPC ISO kernel includes any drivers you will need on most standard 
Macs (Airport, 10/100/1000mbit ethernet), but should you need any extras we 
have included a huge amount of extra modules as well. To view a list of all 
modules included look in <path>/lib/modules/*/kernel/drivers/*</path>. To load 
a particular module, type:
</p>

<pre caption = "Loading modules">
# <i>modprobe modulename</i>
<comment>(replace modulename with your desired module)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configure and Install networking</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The new boot CDs allow you to configure a working network, allowing
you to use <c>ssh</c>, <c>scp</c> or <c>wget</c> etc. as needed before even 
beginning the installation process. If you build using GRP, there is no need 
to set up networking now. There are several ways of setting up the network. 
Perhaps the most common used and also easiest is DHCP:
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>DHCP</title>
<body>

<p>
Network configuration is simple with DHCP; If your ISP is not using
DHCP, skip down to the static configuration section below.
</p>

<pre caption="Network configuration with DHCP">
# <i>dhcpcd eth0</i>
</pre>

<note>
Some ISPs require you to provide a hostname.  To do that,
add a <c>-h myhostname</c> flag to the dhcpcd command line above.
</note>

<p>
If you receive <i>dhcpConfig</i> warnings, don't panic; the errors
are most likely cosmetic.  Skip down to Network testing below.
</p>

<p>
Please note that eth0 defaults to the internal network adapter om
most ppc livecds. If you want to install gentoo using airport execute:
</p>

<pre caption="Network (airport) configuration with DHCP">
# <i>dhcpcd eth1</i>
</pre>

<p>
If your airport base station is configured to encrypt connections
using WEP, use the iwconfig command to set the correct parameters.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Static configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
We need to setup just enough networking so that we can download
sources for the system build, as well as the required localhost interface.  
If you are booted using a GRP CD 1, all necessary sources are already on the 
cd in the /mnt/cdrom/distfiles directory. Type in the following commands, 
replacing $IFACE with your network interface (typically <c>eth0</c>), $IPNUM
with your IP address, $BCAST with your broadcast address, and $NMASK with your
network mask.  For the <c>route</c> command, replace $GTWAY with your default 
gateway.
</p>

<pre caption = "Static Network Configuration">
# <i>/sbin/ifconfig $IFACE $IPNUM broadcast $BCAST netmask $NMASK</i>
# <i>/sbin/route add -net default gw $GTWAY netmask 0.0.0.0 metric 1</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now, it's time to create the <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path> (again, only needed 
when not doing netless install) file so that name resolution (finding Web/FTP 
sites by name, rather than just by IP address) will work.
</p>

<note>
For historic reasons, Gentoo uses a small text editor called
<c>nano</c> (a <c>pico</c> clone) during installation. All Gentoo/PPC
CDs also include the more popular vim and emacs. Other editors can be 
added by making a simple request to the livecd maintainer
(<mail link="pvdabeel@gentoo.org">Pieter Van den abeele</mail>)
</note>

<p>
Here's a template to follow for creating your <path>/etc/resolv.conf</path> 
file:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/resolv.conf template">
domain mydomain.com
nameserver 10.0.0.1
nameserver 10.0.0.2
</pre>

<p>
Replace <c>10.0.0.1</c> and <c>10.0.0.2</c> with the IP addresses of your
primary and secondary DNS servers respectively.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Network testing</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your network has been configured, the <c>/sbin/ifconfig -a</c> 
command should show (hopefully!) that your network card is working
(look for <e>UP</e> and <e>RUNNING</e> in the output).
</p>

<pre caption="/sbin/ifconfig for a working network card">
eth0      Link encap:Ethernet  HWaddr 00:50:BA:8F:61:7A
          inet addr:192.168.0.2  Bcast:192.168.0.255  Mask:255.255.255.0
          inet6 addr: fe80::50:ba8f:617a/10 Scope:Link
          UP BROADCAST RUNNING MULTICAST  MTU:1500  Metric:1
          RX packets:1498792 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 frame:0
          TX packets:1284980 errors:0 dropped:0 overruns:0 carrier:0
          collisions:1984 txqueuelen:100
          RX bytes:485691215 (463.1 Mb)  TX bytes:123951388 (118.2 Mb)
          Interrupt:11
</pre>
<!--
<todo>
If you have a static ppp link, ...
If you have an ADSL pppoe link, ...
</todo>
-->

<note>
Use <c>export http_proxy=http://myISPproxy:port</c> or <c>export
http_proxy=myISPproxy:port</c> if your ISP requires you to set up a
http proxy. 
</note>

<note>
Gentoo/PPC also support other types of connections (ADSL, ppp,...).
Have a look at the Gentoo/x86 installation document if you need to set
up such a connection on a Gentoo/PPC machine.
</note>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Networking is go!</title>
<body>

<p>
Networking should now be configured and useable (if needed at all :-) ).  You 
should be able to use the included <c>ssh</c>, <c>scp</c>, <c>wget</c>, ... 
commands to connect to other machines on your LAN or the Internet.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Set up partitions</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Now that the kernel can see our network card and disk controllers, it's time
to set up disk partitions for Gentoo Linux.
</p>

<p>
Here's a quick overview of the standard Gentoo Linux partition layout.
We're going to create at least three partitions: a swap partition, a root
partition (to hold the bulk of Gentoo Linux), and a special bootstrap partition.
The bootstrap partition is designed to hold the YABOOT boot loader information.
OldWorld users do not require this bootstrap partition as their machine is 
initially booted by MacOS, and BootX is used to initialize the linux kernel and
init scripts.
</p>

<p>
Now, on to file system types.  Right now, you have four file system options:
XFS, ext2, ext3 (journaling) and ReiserFS.  ext2 is the tried and true Linux
file system but doesn't have metadata journaling.  ext3 is the new version of
ext2 with both metadata journaling and ordered data writes, effectively
providing data journaling as well.  Either one of these is the recommended 
type to use for GentooPPC. ReiserFS and XFS are both newer high performance 
File systems, but are more experimental on PPC in general and are not 
recommended. Feel free to experiment with these filesystems if your machine is 
not mission-critical. 
</p>

<note>
At this point, create your partitions using mac-fdisk, <c>mac-fdisk /dev/hdx</c>
(where x is your drive letter, a, b, c - <path>/dev/sdx</path> for scsi disks).
You will need to make at a minimum a bootstrap partition (<c>b</c> in mac-fdisk)
(New World users only), a swap partition (generally 1,5* ram in your box is 
good, however I would recommend at least 512MB swap partition if you plan on 
compiling any large packages), and a root partition.  <c>?</c> at the prompt 
of mac-fdisk will give you a list of options. 
</note>

<p>
Once you've created your partitions using <c>mac-fdisk</c>, it's time to 
initialize the file systems that will be used to house our data.  Initialize 
swap as follows:
</p>

<pre caption = "Creating Swap">
# <i>mkswap /dev/hda3</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can use the <c>mke2fs</c> command to create ext2 file systems:
</p>

<pre caption = "Formatting to ext2">
# <i>mke2fs /dev/hda4</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you'd like to use ext3, you can create ext3 file systems using 
<c>mke2fs -j</c>:
</p>

<pre caption = "Formatting to ext3">
# <i>mke2fs -j /dev/hda4</i>
</pre>

<note>
You can find out more about using ext3 under Linux 2.4 at 
<uri>http://www.zip.com.au/~akpm/linux/ext3/ext3-usage.html</uri>.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Mount partitions</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Now, we'll activate our new swap, since we may need the additional virtual 
memory that provides later:
</p>

<pre caption = "Activating swap">
# <i>swapon /dev/hda3</i>
</pre>

<p>
Next, we'll create the <path>/mnt/gentoo</path> mountpoint,
and we'll mount our file system to this mountpoint.
</p>

<pre caption = "Mounting the environment">
# <i>mkdir /mnt/gentoo</i>
# <i>mount /dev/hda4 /mnt/gentoo</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you are setting up Gentoo Linux with a separate <path>/usr</path> or 
<path>/var</path>, these would get mounted to <path>/mnt/gentoo/usr</path> 
and <path>/mnt/gentoo/var</path>, respectively.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Mounting the CD-ROM</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
On the livecds, the cdrom is automatically detected and mounted in /mnt/cdrom. 
</p>

<p>
If you are booting using the smallestcd (please note that this CD is no
longer actively maintained and only around for historical reasons (no
support for wireless, ppp...)) the cdrom is not mounted under the
smallestcd  minimal Linux boot CD environment. We'll need to
mount it so that we can access the compressed build image tarball 
contained on the CD-ROM. To mount the CD-ROM, one typically types:
</p>

<pre caption = "Mounting the CD-ROM">
# <i>mount /dev/cdroms/cdrom0 /mnt/cdrom -o ro -t iso9660</i>
</pre>

<p>
With the CD-ROM mounted, you should be able to see the <c>stage???.tbz2</c> 
file(s) by typing <c>ls /mnt/cdrom/build</c>.
</p>

<note>
If you are unable to mount your cdrom, it is still possible to retrieve the 
stage1/2/3 from the gentoo mirrors using 
<c>lynx gentoo.oregonstate.edu/releases/ppc/</c>.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Unpack the stage you want to use</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
With the GRP CD 1 cdrom mounted, you should be able to see the
stage???.tbz2 tarballs in the /mnt/cdrom/ppc-stages , the
/mnt/cdrom/g3-stages or the /mnt/cdrom/g4-stages directory.
</p>

<p>
If your livecd does not contain stages or you want to use the latest, point
lynx or wget to your Gentoo mirror and download either the latest official
ppc stages from the <c>releases/ppc/1.4/stages</c> directory. For historical 
reasons, the 1.2 stages are still available in the releases/build directory, 
but these are outdated and certainly no longer actively maintained.
</p>

<impo>
Be sure to use the <c>p</c> option with <c>tar</c>.  Forgetting to do this 
will cause certain files to contain incorrect permissions.
</impo>

<impo>
If you want to build really everything from scratch, optimized for your
processor, you should use a stage1 image, however you'll also have a choice of 
a stage2 and stage3 image. These images allow you to save time at the expense 
of configurability (we've already chosen compiler optimizations and default 
USE variables for you). A stage3 is recommanded for a 20 minute GRP install.
</impo>

<pre caption = "Preparing the environment">
# <i>cd /mnt/gentoo</i>
# <i>tar -xvjpf /mnt/cdrom/build/stage?-*.tbz2</i>
# <i>mount -o bind /proc /mnt/gentoo/proc</i>
# <i>cp /etc/resolv.conf /mnt/gentoo/etc/resolv.conf</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you are booted from the GRP CD 1, copy the distfiles and the portage 
snapshot to the correct locations:
</p>

<pre caption = "Preparing the environment with GRP">
# <i>cd /mnt/gentoo/usr</i>
# <i>tar -jxvf /mnt/cdrom/portage.tbz2</i>
# <i>cp -a /mnt/cdrom/distfiles/ /mnt/gentoo/usr/portage/distfiles/</i>
</pre>

<p>
The new Gentoo system is now correctly set up, the only thing we need to do is 
to instruct the Linux booted from the livecd to switch to the new Linux in 
/mnt/gentoo:
</p>

<pre caption = "Chrooting into the new environment">
# <i>chroot /mnt/gentoo /bin/bash</i>
# <i>env-update</i>
&gt;&gt;&gt; Regenerating /etc/ld.so.cache...
# <i>source /etc/profile</i>
</pre>

<p>
After you execute these commands, you'll be "inside" your new Gentoo Linux 
environment.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Rsync</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Now, you'll need to run <c>emerge sync</c> which will connect to 
rsync.gentoo.org and download the latest version of our Portage ports tree. 
If you are doing a quick netless install, this step isn't necessary:
</p>

<pre caption = "Updating the Portage tree">
# <i>emerge sync</i>
</pre>

<p>
The Portage tree will be downloaded; it's about 10Mb in size.
</p>

<impo>
The address for the rsync server is currently 
rsync://rsync.gentoo.org/gentoo-portage. If you have trouble accessing Gentoo 
rsync, make sure you're using this address by setting it as the SYNC variable 
in your <path>/etc/make.conf</path>. If you used the portage snapshot on the 
cd, there is no need for an emerge sync. Note that emerge sync causes the 
snapshot to be updated, probably rendering some of the prebuild stuff to be 
outdated. 
</impo>

<note>
The rsync command can be configured to use an HTTP proxy if you
are behind a firewall.  To configure this item set
<c>RSYNC_PROXY="hostname:port"</c> in <path>/etc/make.conf</path> or set it as
an environment variable.
</note>

<note>
Have a look at the other settings in <path>/etc/make.conf</path> and configure 
them to your needs. If you are using GRP, you have to set ACCEPT_KEYWORDS to 
ppc (the stable profile). There are several tools available to automatically 
select the best mirror (<c>emerge mirrorselect &amp;&amp; mirrorselect -a</c>) 
or to set the use flags (<c>emerge ufed &amp;&amp; ufed</c>). Make sure that 
your CFLAGS setting corresponds to the processor of the machine you are 
installing Gentoo on. 
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Progressing from stage1 to stage2</title>
<section>
<body>

<impo>
If you are a stage2 or stage3 tarball, then we've already bootstrapped
for you.  There is no reason for you to bootstrap again, unless you decided to
do an <c>emerge sync</c> and want to ensure that you have an up-to-the-minute
current Gentoo Linux system.  Most people using stage2 or stage3 tarballs will
<i>not</i> want to bootstrap again, since it can take up to an hour even on
very fast machines.
</impo>

<p>
Now that you have a working copy of the Portage tree, people using stage1 to
install will need to bootstrap their Gentoo Linux system as follows.  First
edit the file <path>/etc/make.conf</path>.  In this file, you should set your
<c>USE</c> flags, which specify optional functionality that you would like to
be built into packages; generally, the defaults (an <e>empty</e> or unset USE
variable) are fine.  You also should set appropriate <c>CHOST</c>, <c>
CFLAGS</c> and <c>CXXFLAGS</c> settings for the kind of system that you are
creating (commented examples can be found further down in the file.)  If
necessary, you can also set proxy information here if you are behind a
firewall.
</p>

<pre caption = "Editing make.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/make.conf</i> <comment>(Adjust these settings)</comment>
</pre>

<note>
People who need to substantially tweak the build process should take a look at
the <path>/etc/make.globals</path> file.  This file comprises gentoo defaults 
and should never be touched.  If the defaults do not suffice, then new values 
should be put in <path>/etc/make.conf</path>, as entries in 
<path>make.conf</path> <comment>override</comment> the entries in 
<path>make.globals</path>.  If you're interested in tweaking USE settings, 
look in <path>/etc/make.profile/make.defaults</path>. If you want to turn off 
any USE settings found here, add an appropriate <c>USE="-foo"</c> in 
<path>/etc/make.conf</path> (to turn off the <c>foo</c> USE setting).
</note>

<p>
Now, it's time to start the "bootstrap" process.  This process will last 
1-4 hours depending on how zippy your machine is.  During this
time, the extracted build image will be prepped for compiling the rest of the
system.  The GNU compiler suite will be built, as well as the GNU C library.  
These are time consuming builds and make up the bulk of the bootstrap process:
</p>

<pre caption = "Start the bootstrapping">
# <i>cd /usr/portage</i>
# <i>scripts/bootstrap.sh</i>
</pre>

<p>
The "bootstrap" process will now begin.
</p>

<note>
Portage by default uses <path>/var/tmp</path> during package building, often
using several hundred megabytes of temporary storage. If you would like to
change where Portage stores these temporary files, set a new PORTAGE_TMPDIR 
<e>before</e> starting the bootstrap process, as follows:
</note>

<pre caption = "Configuring the temporary directory">
# <i>export PORTAGE_TMPDIR="/otherdir/tmp"</i>
</pre>

<p>
The <c>bootstrap.sh</c> will build <c>binutils</c>, <c>gcc</c>, <c>gettext</c>,
and <c>glibc</c>, rebuilding <c>binutils</c>, <c>gcc</c>, and <c>gettext</c>
after <c>glibc</c> is built.  Needless to say, this process takes a while.
Have a nice nap.  Once this process completes, your system will be in a "stage2"
state.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Progressing from stage2 to stage3</title>
<section>
<body>

<note>
If you haven't done so, please edit <path>/etc/make.conf</path> to your flavor.
</note>

<p>
Once your build image has been bootstrapped and you're at stage2 (again, if 
you're using a stage3 tarball then these steps are not required) it's time to 
build or install the rest of the base system as follows:
</p>

<pre caption = "Emerging the system packages">
# <i>export CONFIG_PROTECT=""</i>
# <i>emerge --pretend system</i>
<comment>[lists the packages to be installed]</comment>
# <i>emerge system</i>
</pre>

<note>
The <c>export CONFIG_PROTECT=""</c> line ensures that any new scripts
installed to <path>/etc</path> will overwrite the old scripts (stored in
<path>sys-apps/baselayout</path>), bypassing Portage's new config file
management support.  Type <c>emerge --help config</c> for more details.
</note>

<p>
It's going to take a while to finish building the entire base system.  Your 
reward is that it will be thoroughly optimized for your system.  The drawback 
is that you have to find a way to keep yourself occupied for some time to come. 
When <c>emerge system</c> completes, you'll have a stage3 Gentoo Linux system.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Final steps: timezone</title>
<section>
<body>

<note>
If you haven't done so, please edit <path>/etc/make.conf</path> to your flavor.
</note>

<p>
At this point, you should have a stage3 system that's ready for final 
configuration. We'll start this process by setting the time zone.  By setting 
the time zone before building the kernel we ensure that users get reasonable 
<c>uname -a</c> output.
</p>

<p>
Look for your time zone (or GMT if you are using Greenwich Mean Time) in 
<path>/usr/share/zoneinfo</path>.  Then, make a symbolic link by typing:
</p>

<pre caption = "Configuring timezone">
# <i>ln -sf /usr/share/zoneinfo/path/to/timezonefile /etc/localtime</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Kernel, system logger, and cron</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
You will now need to emerge the ppc kernel sources, this can be accomplished 
with <c>emerge sys-kernel/ppc-sources</c>. 
</p>

<p>
Once you have a Linux kernel source tree available, it's time to compile your 
own custom kernel:
</p>

<pre caption = "Compiling the kernel">
# <i>cd /usr/src/linux</i>
# <i>make menuconfig</i>
# <i>make dep &amp;&amp; make clean vmlinux modules modules_install</i>
# <i>cp vmlinux System.map /boot</i>
</pre>

<note>
You should <e>only</e> use the <c>sys-kernel/ppc-sources</c> gentoo kernels on 
PowerPC based machines.
</note>

<warn>
For your kernel to function properly, there are several options that you will
need to ensure are in the kernel proper -- that is, they should <e>be enabled 
and not compiled as modules</e>.  You will need to enable the <c>"Code maturity
level options --> Prompt for development and/or incomplete code/drivers"</c>
option to see several of these selections. Under the "File systems" section, 
be sure to enable the <c>Device File System</c> (note that you <e>don't</e> 
need to enable the "/dev/pts file system support" option). You'll also need to 
enable the <c>Virtual Memory File system</c>.  Also under <c>Macintosh Device 
Drivers</c> make sure to disable the default of <c>Support for ADB raw 
keycodes</c>. Also make sure to <e>disable</e> the <c>Enhanced RTC</c> option 
(in "Character devices") as it's not PPC friendly ATM. But turn <e>on</e> 
<c>Support for /dev/rtc</c> in "General setup". It's always a good idea to 
leave ext2 enabled whether you are using it or not. Users with OldWorld 
machines will want HFS support so they can copy compiled kernels to the MacOS 
partition. 
</warn>

<impo>
If you have an IDE CD burner and/or DVD, then you need to enable SCSI emulation
in the kernel.  Turn on "ATA/IDE/MFM/RLL support" ---> "IDE, ATA and ATAPI 
Block devices" ---> "SCSI emulation support" (I usually make it a module), 
then under "SCSI support" enable "SCSI support", "SCSI CD-ROM support" and
"SCSI generic support" (again, I usually compile them as modules).  If you
also choose to use modules, then <c>echo -e "ide-scsi\nsg\nsr_mod"
>> /etc/modules.autoload</c> to have them automatically added at boot time.  
You should also add this line to your <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> file 
<c>append="hdc=ide-scsi"</c>. 
</impo>

<impo>
If you have an OldWorld machine you will need to mount your HFS (MacOS) 
partition, then copy your kernel over so BootX can load it at startup. BootX 
will automatically find kernels in the <path>Linux Kernels</path> folder in 
the System Folder.
</impo>

<p>
Your new custom kernel (and modules) are now installed.  Now you need to 
choose a system logger that you would like to install.  We offer sysklogd, 
which is the traditional set of system logging daemons.  We also have metalog.
Power users seem to gravitate away from sysklogd (not very good performance) 
and towards metalog. If in doubt, you may want to try metalog, since it seems 
to be quite popular. To merge your logger of choice, type <e>one</e> of the 
next two lines:
</p>

<pre caption = "Emerging a system logger">
# <i>emerge app-admin/sysklogd</i>
# <i>rc-update add sysklogd default</i>
<comment>or</comment>
# <i>emerge app-admin/metalog</i>
# <i>rc-update add metalog default</i>
</pre>

<warn>
If you used the version 1.2 stage3 tarball you do not need to install a system 
logger. stage3-ppc-1.2.tbz2 includes sysklogd (although older and newer 
versions do not). If you would like to use metalog instead, you will first 
need to remove sysklogd: After installation is complete, prevent sysklogd from 
running at startup with <c>rc-update del sysklogd default</c>. Then <c>emerge 
unmerge sysklogd</c> to remove it. You will probably also have to manually 
delete the sysklogd configuration files in <path>/etc</path> (look for 
<c>cfgpro</c> in the file list while unmerging). To install metalog, run 
<c>emerge metalog</c>, then <c>rc-update add metalog default</c>.
</warn>

<impo>
Metalog flushes output to the disk in blocks, so messages aren't immediately 
recorded into the system logs.  If you are trying to debug a daemon, this 
performance-enhancing behavior is less than helpful.  When your Gentoo Linux 
system is up and running, you can send metalog a USR1 signal to temporarily 
turn off this message buffering (meaning that <c>tail -f 
<path>/var/log/everything/current</path></c> will now work in real time, as 
expected), and a USR2 signal to turn buffering back on again.
</impo>

<p>
Now, you may optionally choose a cron package that you'd like to use.  Right 
now, we offer dcron, fcron and vcron. If you don't know which one to choose, 
you might as well grab vcron.  They can be installed as follows:
</p>

<pre caption = "Emerging cron">
# <i>emerge sys-apps/dcron</i>
# <i>crontab /etc/crontab</i>
<comment>or</comment>
# <i>emerge sys-apps/fcron</i>
# <i>crontab /etc/crontab</i>
<comment>or</comment>
# <i>emerge sys-apps/vcron</i>
</pre>

<p>
Don't forget to add cron to the default runlevel so that it starts during
boot.
</p>

<pre caption="adding cron to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add &lt;name-of-/etc/init.d/cronscript&gt; default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Install additional packages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
If you're a laptop user and wish to use your pcmcia slots on your first
real reboot, you'll want to make sure you install the pcmcia-cs package.
</p>

<pre caption = "Emerging pcmcia-cs">
# <i>emerge sys-apps/pcmcia-cs</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Final steps: system configuration</title>
<section>
<title>Final steps: /etc/fstab</title>
<body>

<p>
Your Gentoo Linux system is almost ready for use.  All we need to do now is 
configure a few important system files and install the yaboot boot loader.
The first file we need to configure is <path>/etc/fstab</path>. Remember to 
specify <c>ext2</c> or <c>ext3</c> file system types as appropriate.
</p>

<p>
Use something like the <path>/etc/fstab</path> listed below, but of course be 
sure to replace "ROOT" and "SWAP" with the actual block devices you are using 
(such as <c>hda2</c>, etc.).  Note that NewWorld users do <e>not</e> add their 
bootstrap partition to this file.
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/fstab">
<comment>
# /etc/fstab: static file system information.
#
# noatime turns of atimes for increased performance (atimes normally aren't
# needed; notail increases performance of ReiserFS (at the expense of storage
# efficiency).  It's safe to drop the noatime options if you want and to
# switch between notail and tail freely.
# &lt;fs&gt;           &lt;mountpoint&gt;   &lt;type&gt;   &lt;opts&gt;          &lt;dump/pass&gt;
</comment>
/dev/ROOT           /           ext3	 noatime         0 1
/dev/SWAP           none        swap	 sw              0 0
/dev/cdroms/cdrom0  /mnt/cdrom  iso9660	 noauto,ro       0 0
proc                /proc       proc	 defaults        0 0
</pre>

</body>
</section>


<section>
<title>Final steps: set the root password</title>
<body>

<p>
Before you forget, set the root password by typing:
</p>

<pre caption = "Setting a root password">
# <i>passwd</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Final steps: /etc/hostname</title>
<body>

<p>
Edit this file so that it contains your fully-qualified domain name on a 
single line, i.e. <c>mymachine.mydomain.com</c>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Final steps: /etc/hosts</title>
<body>

<p>
This file contains a list of ip addresses and their associated hostnames.  
It's used by the system to resolve the IP addresses of any hostnames that may 
not be in your nameservers.  Here's a template for this file:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/hosts">
127.0.0.1      localhost
<comment># the next line contains your IP for your local LAN, and your associated machine name</comment>
192.168.1.1    mymachine.mydomain.com	mymachine
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Final network configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
Add the names of any modules that are necessary for the proper functioning of 
your system to <path>/etc/modules.autoload</path> file (you can also add any 
options you need to the same line). When Gentoo Linux boots, these modules 
will be automatically loaded.  Of particular importance is your ethernet card 
module, if you happened to compile it as a module:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/modules.autoload">
sungem
</pre>

<p>
Edit the <path>/etc/conf.d/net</path> script to get your network configured 
for your first boot:
</p>

<pre caption = "Configuring the network">
# <i>nano -w /etc/conf.d/net</i>
# <i>rc-update add net.eth0 default</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you have multiple network cards you need to create additional 
<path>net.eth<comment>x</comment></path> scripts for each one 
(<comment>x</comment> = 1, 2, ...):
</p>

<pre caption="Multiple network interfaces">
# <i>cd /etc/init.d</i>
# <i>cp net.eth0 net.eth<comment>x</comment></i>
# <i>rc-update add net.eth<comment>x</comment> default</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you have a PCMCIA card installed, have a quick look into 
<path>/etc/init.d/pcmcia</path> to verify that things seem all right for your 
setup, then add the following on top of your
<path>/etc/init.d/net.eth<comment>x</comment></path> file for the pcmcia
drivers to be autoloaded whenever your network is loaded:
</p>

<pre caption = "Adding pcmcia dependency">
depend() {
	need pcmcia
}
</pre>

</body>
</section>


<section>
<title>Final steps: configure basic settings (including the international keymap setting)</title>
<body>

<pre caption="basic configuration">
# <i>nano -w /etc/rc.conf</i>
</pre>

<p>
Follow the directions in the file to configure the basic settings.
All users will want to make sure that <c>CLOCK</c> is set to his/her
liking.  International keyboard users will want to set the <c>KEYMAP</c>
variable (browse <path>/usr/share/keymaps</path> to see the various
possibilities).
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Configuring the Boot Loader</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The main difference you'll find here from x86 Linux is the bootloader. 
NewWorld machines will use yaboot. OldWorld machines use BootX.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>yaboot for NewWorld machines (automatic setup using yabootconfig)</title>
<body>

<p>
You can use the new and improved <c>yabootconfig</c>, included with 
yaboot-1.3.8-r1 and later, to automatically setup yaboot. <c>yabootconfig</c> 
will auto-detect the partitions on your machine and will setup dual and triple 
boot combinations with Linux, Mac OS, and Mac OS X.
</p>

<p>
To use <c>yabootconfig</c>, your drive must have a bootstrap partition, and 
<path>/etc/fstab</path> must be configured with your Linux partitions. Both of 
these should have been done already in the steps above. To start, ensure that 
you have the latest version of yaboot installed by running <c>emerge -u
yaboot</c>. This is necessary as the latest version will be available via 
Portage, but it may not have made it into the stage files.
</p>

<p>
At the command prompt run <c>yabootconfig</c>. The program will run and it will
confirm the location of the bootstrap partition. Type <c>Y</c> if it is correct.
If not, double check <path>/etc/fstab</path>. <c>yabootconfig</c> will then 
scan your system setup, create <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> and run 
<c>mkofboot</c> for you. (mkofboot is used to format the bootstrap partition, 
and install the yaboot configuration file into it.)
</p>

<p>
You might want to verify the contents of <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path>. If you 
make changes to <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path> (like setting the default/boot 
OS), make sure to rerun <c>ybin -v</c> to apply changes to the bootstrap 
partition.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>yaboot for NewWorld machines (manual setup of yaboot.conf)</title>
<body>

<p>
If for some reason you do not want to run <c>yabootconfig</c> to automatically 
setup <path>/etc/yaboot.conf</path>, you can just edit the sample file already
installed on your system. Below is a completed yaboot.conf file:
</p>

<pre caption="/etc/yaboot.conf">
## /etc/yaboot.conf
##
## run: "man yaboot.conf" for details. Do not make changes until you have!!
## see also: /usr/share/doc/yaboot/examples for example configurations.
##
## For a dual-boot menu, add one or more of:
## bsd=/dev/hdaX, macos=/dev/hdaY, macosx=/dev/hdaZ

## our bootstrap partition:
boot=/dev/hda9

##hd: is open firmware speak for hda
device=hd:
partition=11

root=/dev/hda11
delay=5
defaultos=macosx
timeout=30
install=/usr/lib/yaboot/yaboot
magicboot=/usr/lib/yaboot/ofboot

#################
## This section can be duplicated if you have more than one kernel or set of
## boot options
#################
image=/boot/vmlinux
	label=Linux
	sysmap=/boot/System.map
	read-only
##################

macos=/dev/hda13
macosx=/dev/hda12
enablecdboot
enableofboot
</pre>

<p>
Once <path>yaboot.conf</path> is set up how you want it, you run <c>mkofboot 
-v</c> to install the settings in the bootstrap partition.  Don't forget this!
If all goes well, and you have the same options as the sample above, your next
reboot will give you a simple, five-entry boot menu.  If you update your yaboot
config later on, you'll just need to run <c>ybin -v</c> to update the bootstrap
partition - mkofboot is for initial setup only.
</p>

<note>
Yaboot has some functionality for setting config at boot time, so take a look at
<uri>http://penguinppc.org/projects/yaboot</uri> for more info.
</note>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>BootX for OldWorld machines</title>
<body>

<impo>
Follow these steps after you reboot your machine in the next step.
</impo>

<p>
Boot your machine in MacOS and open the BootX control panel. Select 
<c>Options</c>, and uncheck <c>Used specified RAM disk</c>. When you return 
to the BootX main screen, you will now find an option to specify your machine's
root disk and partition. Fill these in with the appropriate values.
</p>

<p>
BootX can be configured to start Linux upon boot. If you do this, you will 
first see your machine boot into MacOS then, during startup, BootX will load 
and start Linux. See the <uri link="http://penguinppc.org/projects/bootx/">BootX
home page</uri> for more information.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Installation complete!</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Now, Gentoo Linux is installed.  The only remaining step is to exit the 
chrooted shell, safely unmount your partitions and reboot the system:
</p>

<pre caption = "Exiting the chroot">
# <i>exit</i>  <codenote>This exits the chrooted shell; you can also type <c>^D</c></codenote>
# <i>cd / </i>
# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo/proc</i>
# <i>umount /mnt/gentoo</i>
# <i>reboot</i>
</pre>

<note>
After rebooting, it is a good idea to run the <c>update-modules</c> command to 
create the <path>/etc/modules.conf</path> file.  Instead of modifying this 
file directly, you should generally make changes to the files in 
<path>/etc/modules.d</path>. If the system is rebooted, feel free to put in 
GRP CD2 and cp -a /mnt/cdrom to /usr/portage/packages. Use emerge --usepkg to 
force emerge to use the packages in /usr/portage/packages. This will allow you 
to set up KDE/Gnome, and other big packages in a few minutes.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Extras</title>

<section>
<title>Multiple mouse button emulation</title>
<body>

<p>
You may want to add these lines to an <path>/etc/sysctl.conf</path> to enable 
multiple mouse button emulation at each boot. The key values can be obtained 
with command line utility <c>showkey</c>. Here is a sample using F11 and F12.
</p>

<pre caption = "Example configuration for sysctl.conf">
# Enable mouse button emulation
dev.mac_hid.mouse_button_emulation = 1
# Set 2nd button to 87 - F11
dev.mac_hid.mouse_button2_keycode = 87
# Set 3rd button to 88 - F12
dev.mac_hid.mouse_button3_keycode = 88
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo-Stats</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Linux usage statistics program was started as an attempt to give 
the developers a way to find out about their user base. It collects information
about Gentoo Linux usage to help us in set priorities our development. 
Installing it is completely optional, and it would be greatly appreciated if 
you decide to use it. Compiled statistics can be viewed at 
<uri>http://stats.gentoo.org/</uri>.
</p>

<p>
The gentoo-stats server will assign a unique ID to your system. This ID is 
used to make sure that each system is counted only once. The ID will not be 
used to individually identify your system, nor will it be matched against an 
IP address or other personal information. Every precaution has been taken to 
assure your privacy in the development of this system. The following are the 
things that we are monitoring right now through our "gentoo-stats" program:
</p>

<ul>
<li>installed packages and their version numbers</li>
<li>CPU information: speed (MHz), vendor name, model name, CPU flags (like "altivec")</li>
<li>memory information (total available physical RAM, total available swap space)</li>
<li>PCI cards and network controller chips</li>
<li>the Gentoo Linux profile your machine is using (that is, where the <path>/etc/make.profile</path> link is pointing to).</li>
</ul>

<p>
We are aware that disclosure of sensitive information is a threat to most 
Gentoo Linux users (just as it is to the developers).
</p>

<ul>
<li>Unless you modify the gentoo-stats program, it will never transmit sensitive information such as your passwords, configuration data, favorite movie...</li>
<li>Transmission of your e-mail addresses is optional and turned off by default.</li>
<li>The IP address your data transmission originates from will never be logged in such a way that we can identify you. There are no "IP address/system ID" pairs.</li>
</ul>

<p>
The installation is easy - just run the following commands:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing gentoo-stats">
# <i>emerge gentoo-stats</i>   <comment>(Installs gentoo-stats)</comment>
# <i>gentoo-stats --new</i>    <comment>(Obtains a new system ID)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
The second command above will request a new system ID and enter it into 
<path>/etc/gentoo-stats/gentoo-stats.conf</path> automatically. You can view 
this file to see additional configuration options.
</p>

<p>
After that, the program should be run on a regular schedule (gentoo-stats does 
not have to be run as root). Add this line to your <path>crontab</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Updating gentoo-stats with cron">
0 0 * * 0,4 /usr/sbin/gentoo-stats --update > /dev/null
</pre>

<p>
The <c>gentoo-stats</c> program is a simple perl script which can be viewed 
with your favorite pager or editor: <path>/usr/sbin/gentoo-stats</path>.
</p>

</body>

</section>

<section>
<title>Where to go from here</title>
<body>

<p>
Some very good all-arch docs are available in the docs section of the
Gentoo Main site. Prelinking your system is adviced (not necessary) if you
want bleeding edge performance (KDE startup time improves by at least 50%).
Alsa (advanced linux sound architecture) is also very good on some ppc
machines (especially newer powerbooks). If you want a highly configurable
audio system check that doc out. Applications that you really want to check out
and set up on a mac machine are pmud (advanced power management) or pbbuttons 
(if you're a powerbook owner). Setting up Xfree on PPC machines is very easy; 
<c>emerge xeasyconf &amp;&amp; Xeasyconf</c> should do.
</p>

<p>
If you have any questions or would like to get involved with Gentoo Linux 
development, consider joining our gentooppc-user and gentooppc-dev mailing 
lists (there's a "click to subscribe" link on our <uri 
link="http://www.gentoo.org/">main page</uri>). We also have a handy <uri 
link="/doc/en/desktop.xml">Desktop configuration guide</uri> that will
help you to continue configuring your new Gentoo Linux system, and a useful 
<uri link="/doc/en/portage-user.xml">Portage user guide</uri> to help 
familiarize you with Portage basics.  Enjoy and welcome to Gentoo Linux!
</p>

<p>
The <uri link="/doc/en/gentoo-ppc-faq.xml">Gentoo Linux/PowerPC FAQ</uri> 
covers frequently asked questions about running Gentoo Linux/PPC. The general 
<uri link="/doc/en/faq.xml">Gentoo Linux FAQ</uri> might also help to get you 
started, although it is geared towards x86 installations. <uri 
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum.php?f=24">Gentoo on PPC</uri> (on 
forums.gentoo.org) is a open bulletin-board for discussion of all PowerPC 
issues. Also, there is usually a lively discussion on IRC. Join us on 
<i>#gentoo-ppc</i> on <i>irc.freenode.net</i>.
</p>

<p>
Thanks and have fun with Gentoo!
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>
