<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<guide>
<title>Gentoo Linux Localization Instructions</title>
<author><mail link="holler@ahsoftware.de">
        Alexander Holler</mail>
</author>

<abstract>This instructions explains the few steps you need to follow to use Gentoo Linux 
with another language than english. It also explains what to do to get the Euro character shown.</abstract>

<chapter>
<title>Preface</title>
<section>
        <body>
                <p>As I'm a German I explain how to enable the german language. If you want 
		another language, you just have to replace the german language code <i>de</i> with 
		the corresponding code for your country, e.g. <i>fr</i> for France or <i>es</i> for Spain.
		</p>
        </body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Timezone</title>
<section>
        <body>
                <p>To enable the right timezone <path>/etc/localtime</path> should point to the 
		appropriate file with the datas for your timezone. You will find those files
		in <path>/usr/share/zoneinfo/</path>.
<pre>
# <i>ln -sf /usr/share/zoneinfo/Europe/Berlin /etc/localtime</i>
</pre>
		</p>
        </body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Hardware clock</title>
<section>
        <body>
                <p>If your hardware clock is set to local time and not to GMT you have to correct
		the variable <i>CLOCK</i> in <path>/etc/rc.conf</path>.
<pre>
 CLOCK="local"
</pre>
		</p>
        </body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Language</title>
<section>
        <body>
                <p>Telling programms what language you prefer will be done with the environment variable
		<i>LANG</i>. If you want to set the language system-wide for all users you should export 
		<i>LANG</i> in <path>/etc/profile</path>. If not, this can be done in through your private
		<path>.bashrc</path> in your home directory. You can find available languages in 
		<path>/usr/share/i18n/locales</path>.
<pre>
 export LANG="de_DE@euro"
</pre>
		</p>
        </body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Keyboard-layout (terminal)</title>
<section>
        <body>
                <p>The keyboard-layout for terminal sessions is set through <i>KEYMAP</i> in
		<path>/etc/rc.conf</path>. You will find the appropriate tables in
		<path>/usr/share/keymaps</path>. If you aren't using composed characters with
		tildes (e.g. &#245;), accent graph (e.g. &#232;) or similar, you could use the
		nodeadkeys-variants. This will save you to enter a space after typing letters
		like ~.
<pre>
 KEYMAP="de-latin1"
 # KEYMAP="de-latin1-nodeadkeys"
</pre>
		</p>
        </body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Keyboard-layout (X server)</title>
<section>
        <body>
                <p>The keyboard-layout for the X server is set with the option
		<i>XkbLayout</i> in the file <path>/etc/X11/XF86Config</path>.
<pre>
 Section "InputDevice"
     Identifier  "Keyboard1"
     ...
     Option "XkbLayout"    "de"
     # Option XkbVariant"  "nodeadkeys"
     ...
</pre>
		</p>
        </body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Euro character (terminal)</title>
<section>
        <body>
                <p>If you want to see the Euro character in a session without using X, you have
		to use a console font which contains it. The console font is set with
		<i>CONSOLEFONT</i> in <path>/etc/rc.conf</path>. Available fonts will be find in
		<path>/usr/share/consolefonts</path>.
<pre>
 CONSOLEFONT="lat0-16"
</pre>
		</p>
        </body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
        <title>Euro character (X server)</title>
<section>
        <title>General</title>
        <body>
                <p>Using the above settings and KDE you should already get the Euro character with
		Alt-Gr-E in all KDE-programs. Remaining the non-KDE-programs.
		</p><p>Unfortunately this is not as easy as the settings before. You have to set the right
		font for every single X-program. So I will just explain	how to enable the Euro character 
		for xterm and (X)Emacs. You can change the fonts for programs under X in your private
		<path>.Xdefaults</path> in your home directory. To enable it for other (new) users you could
		copy this file to <path>/etc/skel</path>.
		</p>
        </body>
</section>

<section>
        <title>Euro character for xterm</title>
        <body>
                <p>Insert the following in your <path>.Xdefaults</path>:
<pre>
 xterm*font: 7x13euro
</pre>
		</p>
        </body>
</section>

<section>
        <title>Euro character for (X)Emacs</title>
        <body>
                <p>For (X)Emacs you define the font in <path>.Xdefaults</path> as shown below:
<pre>
 Emacs.default.attributeFont: -*-courier-medium-r-*-*-*-120-*-*-*-*-iso8859-15
</pre>
		</p><p>If you are using XEmacs (not Emacs) you will have to tell him what to do with
		the <i>EuroSign</i>. This will be done through a definition in 
		<path>.xemacs/init.el</path> in your home directory:
<pre>
 (define-key global-map '(EuroSign) '[&#8364;])
</pre>
		<note>The character in the square brackets is the Euro character.</note>
		</p>
        </body>
</section>

</chapter>

<version>$Revision: 1.1 $</version>
<date>$Date: 2002/11/09 18:47:44 $</date>
</guide>
