<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<guide link="/doc/en/guide-to-mutt.xml">
<?xml-stylesheet href="xsl/guide-main.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<title>QuickStart Guide to Mutt E-Mail</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="mikpolniak@adelphia.net">Mike Polniak</mail></author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="antifa@gentoo.org">Ken Nowack</mail></author>

<abstract>This guide shows you how to begin using the powerful command line tools for email: fetchmail, procmail, mutt, and nbsmtp.</abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>19 Feb 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction to E-Mail</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>If you're not a fan of e-mail clients with fancy graphical user interfaces, or if you would just like to experiment with other mail clients before
deciding which is best for you, here is the easy way to begin using these powerful command line tools:</p>

<p><b>fetchmail->procmail->mutt->smtp</b></p>

<p>These programs are not only powerful and highly customizable but also small and efficient. Once you are up and running with this e-mail system you will
be amazed at what you can do with it.</p>

<p>Because this is a quick start guide, we will eliminate the Mail Transfer Agent (MTA) such as sendmail,postfix or exim.This means no complex MTA
configuration. It also eliminates using port 25 for mail service.</p>

<p>We can do this because fetchmail can force the mail it retrieves directly to a Mail Delivery Agent (MDA)-rather than forwarding to port 25. And we don't
need to use a complex MTA for plain old outgoing mail delivery.</p>

<p>These are the programs you will need to get your e-mail running. </p>

<pre>
# <i>emerge fetchmail procmail mutt nbsmtp</i>
</pre> 

<p>Then just four quick steps to configure files and you will be up and running a brand new e-mail system.</p>


<impo>After each step you can run a test to make sure the setup is correct.This means you will have a complete working e-mail system when you are done.</impo>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Fetchmail</title>  
<section>
<body>


<p>Fetchmail fetches mail from remote servers and forwards it to your local machines delivery system. To use it you need to set up a
<path>.fetchmailrc</path> file in your home directory like this example:</p>

<pre caption="Sample .fetchmailrc">
<i>poll mail.myisp.net  protocol pop3 user "myname" password "mypasswd"</i> 
</pre>

<p>Once you have created a .fetchmailrc file, you have to change the permissions on the file using the chmod command. The file must be readable
only by the file owner. Set the permissions with the following command:</p>

<pre>
# <i>chmod 710 .fetchmailrc</i>
</pre>

<p>To see it in action use the verbose mode (-v). To fetch all messages use -a. And you must use the option -m to tell fetchmail to send the mail to procmail.
</p>

<warn>While testing,its a good idea to tell fetchmail to keep (-k) the mailon the remote server in case something goes wrong and you need to fetch it
again.</warn> 


<p>Run it now to see fetchmail in action!</p>

<pre caption="Fetchmail test #1">
# <i>fetchmail -akv -m "/usr/bin/procmail -d %T"</i> 
</pre>

<p>Once you have a working mail system you can set this as a cron job or put it in a monitor like gkrellm. Fetchmail can also run in a daemon mode for which 
you specify a polling interval in seconds.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Procmail</title>
<section>  
<body>

<p>Procmail is the processor that filters the mail that is forwarded to it by fetchmail. It also acts as the MDA to deliver mail to your mailboxes where
mutt (your e-mail client) can read it.</p>

<p>To use procmail you need to create a .procmailrc file in your home directory.  For our quickstart purposes we will use a very simple
.procmailrc that will filter mail from three gentoo mailing lists into these mailboxes:<e>gentoo-dev, gentoo-user and gentoo-announce</e>
</p>

<note>The procmail filter rules are called recipies and i have also included recipies to filter out some spam.</note>

<pre caption="Sample .procmailrc">
MAILDIR=$HOME/MuttMail                ##you better make sure it exists
LOGFILE=$HOME/.procmaillog
LOGABSTRACT=no
#VERBOSE=on...is only used for debugging
VERBOSE=off
FORMAIL=/usr/bin/formail
NL="
"
##recipe lines begin with :0
##dont put comments on recipe lines
##disable a recipe with the false condition !
##condition lines begin with * and regex is your friend
##conditions are anded and everything after * is fed straight into egrep
##one action line follows the conditions, in this case it is a mailbox name

#catch duplicates using formail
:0 Whc: .msgid.lock
| $FORMAIL -D 16384 .msgid.cache

:0 a
$MAILDIR/duplicates

#people we always allow mail from
:0 
* ^From:.*(craig\@hotmail|renee\@local.com)
$MAILDIR/friends 

#now flush some spam out 
:0  
* ^Subject:.*(credit|cash|money|debt|sex|sale|loan)
$MAILDIR/spam

#no more html messages
:0
* ^Content-Type:.*html
$MAILDIR/junk

#now put my mail lists into mailboxes
:0 
* ^List-Id:.*gentoo-user
gentoo-user

:0 
* ^List-Id:.*gentoo-dev
gentoo-dev

:0 
* ^List-Id:.*gentoo-announce
gentoo-announce

#catch any other gentoo mail
:0 
* ^From:.*gentoo.org
gentoo

:0 
* ^From:.*@freshmeat\.net
freshmeat

################################
# Last rule: mail that gets    #
# this far goes in default box #  
################################
:0 
* .*
default

# End of file
</pre>

<note>It is only required to make the MAILDIR $HOME/MuttMail as Procmail will create all the mailbox files as needed in this directory using the names on
the action lines.For some useful links visit <uri>http://www.procmail.org/</uri> </note>

<p>You can now test .procmailrc by re-running the fetchmail command we tested in the first step. Remember the -k option to keep all mail on the remote
server so we have it if we need to rerun it.</p>


 <pre caption="Procmail test #1">
# <i>fetchmail -akv -m "/usr/bin/procmail -d %T"</i> 
</pre>

<p>Now that fetchmail and procmail have run, go to $HOME/MuttMail and read your messages with <c>less</c> or your file manager.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Mutt e-mail client</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>Mutt is used to read and compose e-mail. It is powerful and highly customizable but also small and efficient.</p>

<p>Mutt supports reading and writing of four different mailbox formats: mbox, MMDF, MH and Maildir. The mailbox type is autodetected. In our case we are
using the mbox format, where all messages of a mailbox are stored in a single file.</p>

<p>Mutt also has the ability to work with folders located on a remote IMAP server. See IMAP Support in section 4.11 of the Mutt manual and the Mutt web
site <uri>http://www.mutt.org/</uri></p>

<p>When you emerged mutt in the first step it installed a system configuration. file in <path>/etc/mutt/Muttrc</path> You also need to create a .muttrc file in your
home directory.</p>

<pre caption="Sample .muttrc">
<codenote>Be sure to read the fine Mutt manual in /usr/share/doc/mutt*</codenote>
<codenote>Any settings here override the system settings in /etc/mutt/Muttrc</codenote>

# <i>cp /etc/mutt/Muttrc ~/.muttrc</i>
# <i>nano -w .muttrc</i>
set pager_context=1                        
set pager_index_lines=6                 #show a mini-index in pager
set menu_scroll  
set pgp_verify_sig=no                   #dont show pgp in pager
set status_on_top                       #put status line at top
set sort=threads                        #sort by message threads in index

set status_format=" %r %b %f %n      Del %d      Msgs %m %l %> (%P)"
set pager_format="%-10.10i %[!%a %b %d %R]"
set date_format="!%H:%M %a %d %b     "
set index_format="%4C %Z %[%b%d] %-15.15F %s"
set folder_format="%2C %t %8s %d %N %f"

#set sendmail="/usr/bin/nbsmtp -d isp.net -h smtp.isp.net -f yourname@isp.net"

#set from="default-mailaddress"         #set to your from address
#set realname="myname"

set record="$HOME/MuttMail/sent"        #sent mail is saved here
set delete=yes                          #delete without prompting
set include=yes				#quote msg in reply	
set fast_reply=yes			#no prompting on reply
set beep=no				#no noise
set markers=no				#no + on wrapped lines
set confirmappend=no			#no prompt for save to =keep           
set to_chars=" +TCF"                    #no L for mail_list

set folder = $HOME/MuttMail
mailboxes =gentoo-user
mailboxes =gentoo-dev
mailboxes =gentoo-announce
mailboxes =gentoo   
mailboxes =freshmeat
mailboxes =duplicates
mailboxes =default  
mailboxes =sent     
mailboxes =friends  
mailboxes =junk
mailboxes =spam
mailboxes =keep

save-hook .* =keep                      #default mbox to (s)ave mail is =keep
subscribe gentoo-user gentoo-dev        #subscribed to these lists

bind pager h display-toggle-weed	#toggle headers with h key

# simulate the old url menu
macro index \cb |urlview\n 'call urlview to extract URLs out of a message'
macro pager \cb |urlview\n 'call urlview to extract URLs out of a message'

#run fetchmail by hitting key of G
macro index G "!fetchmail -a -m 'procmail -d %T'\r"
macro pager G "!fetchmail -a -m 'procmail -d %T'\r"  

#use to edit .muttrc and then source it...no restart necessary
macro generic ,sm ":source $HOME/.muttrc\r"
macro generic \cj "!rxvt -bg wheat -e joe $HOME/.muttrc\r"

# default list of header fields to weed out when displaying mail
#ignore them all and then unignore what you want to see
ignore *
unignore  Date To From: Subject X-Mailer Organization User-Agent
hdr_order Date From To Subject X-Mailer User-Agent Organization 

##your Mutt has to have some colors
##these are for four levels of quoted text
##they override the system settings in /etc/mutt/Muttrc

#color quoted green  default
color quoted1 magenta blue 
#color quoted2 yellow default
#color quoted3 red default   
#color signature cyan cyan   


#this color setup is copied from /etc/mutt/Muttrc.color
#comment it out if you want the default colors in /etc/mutt/Muttrc
# Je vois la vie en rose :-) 
color	hdrdefault	brightcyan	blue
color	header		brightwhite	blue "^from:"
color   header          brightwhite    	blue   "^subject:"

color   quoted          brightgreen     blue
color   signature       brightwhite	blue

color   indicator       blue	        green

color   error           red             black
mono    error           bold
color   status          black cyan
mono	status		bold
color   tree            yellow   	blue

color   tilde           brightmagenta   blue
color	body	brightwhite		blue	"[-a-z_0-9.]+@[-a-z_0-9.]+"
mono    body    bold                    "[-a-z_0-9.]+@[-a-z_0-9.]+"
color   body            brightyellow    black   "^Good signature"
mono    body            bold                    "^Good signature"
color   body            brightwhite     red     "^Bad signature from.*"
mono    body            bold                    "^Bad signature from.*"
color   normal          white		blue
color	message		green	black
color	attachment	brightgreen	blue

# End of file...but it can go on and on and on....:)
</pre>


<p>For the record, this is just a sample .muttrc. There are many more options that you can configure,
gpg settings for instance. Have a look at <uri>http://mutt.netliberte.org/</uri> for more examples and help.</p>

<p>You are now ready to test your .muttrc </p>

<pre caption="Testing .muttrc">
# <i>mutt -y</i>
</pre>

<p>This should open Mutt with a menu showing the Mutt mailboxes that you created in Test 2 when you ran the fetchmail command. 
</p>

<p>Type the ? for help in navigating the Mutt Mailboxes.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>SMTP</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>The final step is setting up nbsmtp the 'No-Brainer SMTP' used to send mail to your SMTP server. This setup is the easiest of all, as it only requires
adding an entry in your .muttrc file.</p>

<p>domain: The domain you want nbsmtp to say it belongs to. This will almost invariably be the same as the domain in your email address.
</p>

<p>from@addr: This is the address you want nbsmtp to say the message is from. Note that this can be different than the "From:" line in your MUA.
</p>

<p>host: This is the smtp server you are sending to.</p>

<pre caption="Adding smtp support">
# <i>nano -w .muttrc</i>
set sendmail="/usr/bin/nbsmtp -d isp.net -h smtp.isp.net -f urname@isp.net"
</pre>

<p>You are now ready to send a message. So in the Mutt pager or index hit the <c>m</c> key to compose a test message to send to your e-mail address. Mutt will
use the value of the EDITOR or VISUAL for the composition editor unless you set editor= in the .muttrc. When you are done composing hit <c>y</c> to send your
message. If there are no errors you will see 'sending mail' followed by 'New mail in =sent'
</p>

<p>Remember in .muttrc we have set where to save sent mail with:set record="$HOME/MuttMail/sent"</p>

<p>Now to complete the test, run fetchmail again to get all your mail and verify you have received the message you sent to your e-mail address. When you find
your test message, hit the <c>h</c> key to toggle a view of all the headers and see the complete mail transfer path.</p>

<note>There is one more program you probably want to add called urlview. This extracts the urls in message texts and sends them to your browser.
</note>

<pre>
# <i>emerge urlview</i> 
</pre>

<p> then create <path>~/.urlview</path> by copying the configuration file from <path>/usr/share/doc/urlview*/</path> and setting your browser command.
</p>

<p>You now have a powerful and highly customizable mail system. So read all the manuals and docs and find the many user configuration files available on the
web with 'google' procmailrc and muttrc</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
