<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/kde-config.xml,v 1.3 2004/10/20 08:50:48 swift Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/en/kde-config.xml">

<title>The KDE Configuration HOWTO</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
One of the most used desktop environments is KDE. This guide tries to describe
all aspects of KDE, including installation, configuration, usage, ...
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.3</version>
<date>October 20, 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is the K Desktop Environment?</title>
<section>
<title>The Project</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.kde.org">KDE Project</uri> is a free software project
dedicated to the development of KDE, an open source graphical desktop
environment for Linux and Unix workstations. The development is covered by
several hundred software engineers from all over the world committed to free
software development. See also <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/whatiskde/project.php">What is the KDE Project</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Software</title>
<body>

<p>
The K Desktop Environment is an easy to use desktop environment build around a
well-thought application framework to allow for application interoptability,
drag 'n drop, etc. Apart from the necessary components the KDE environment also
provides ready-to-use applications for 101 tasks: file management, internet
browser, office application, e-mail handling, ... Everything is covered by the
KDE project.
</p>

<p>
The KDE environment is available in more than 70 languages and has an immense
userbase. For those interested, there are lots of <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/screenshots/">screenshots</uri> available. For more
information on KDE, read the <uri link="http://www.kde.org/whatiskde/">What is
KDE?</uri> article on <uri link="http://www.kde.org">KDE.org</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Community</title>
<body>

<p>
Many KDE-based community sites exist. On <uri
link="http://www.kdenews.org">KDEnews.org</uri> you'll find the latest news on
KDE generally. <uri link="http://www.kdedevelopers.org">KDEdevelopers.org</uri>
is targeted at the KDE development specifically, while <uri
link="http://www.kde-forum.org">KDE-forum</uri> is better suited for the large
masses. More links can be found on the <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/family/">KDE Family page</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Installing KDE</title>
<section>
<title>What do you need?</title>
<body>

<p>
First of all, if you're interested in installing KDE (or KDE support), you will
have to make sure that your USE variable contains the <c>kde</c> and <c>qt</c>
flags. For those of you interested, Qt is the graphical widget library KDE
uses.
</p>

<p>
Second, you need to think on what you want to install from the KDE distribution.
As mentioned before, KDE is very feature-rich and embraces lots of packages. You
don't have to believe our word for it -- just check yourself :)
</p>

<note>
The "motif" USE flag is on by default; if you explicitely disabled it,
konqueror plugins will not be available.
</note>

<pre caption="Listing all packages KDE would install">
# <i>emerge --pretend kde | less</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you're not interested in installing all those packages, you can emerge the
individual packages. You will most definitely want the <c>kdebase</c> package as
it contains KDE's base packages and necessities. The following table lists some
available packages you can emerge.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Package</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeaccessibility</ti>
  <ti>
    Accessibility related programs, managed by the <uri
    link="http://accessibility.kde.org">KDE Accessibility Project</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeadmin</ti>
  <ti>
    KDE Administrative tools, such as <c>KCron</c> (Task Scheduling),
    <c>KUser</c> (User Management) and <c>KDat</c> (Backup Management)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeartwork</ti>
  <ti>
    Various art-related stuff, including screen savers and themes. See also <uri
    link="http://artist.kde.org">artist.kde.org</uri> for more KDE related
    artwork
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeedu</ti>
  <ti>
    Educational KDE applications focused on schoolchildren aged 3 to 18. See
    also the <uri link="http://edu.kde.org">KDE Edu Project</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdegames</ti>
  <ti>
    Various KDE-developed games. More information can be found at the <uri 
    link="http://games.kde.org">KDE Games Center</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdegraphics</ti>
  <ti>
    Graphic-related tools for KDE, including <c>KSnapshot</c> (Screenshot
    Software), <c>KPain</c> (Simple Graphical Editor), <c>Kpdf</c> (PDF viewer),
    <c>KIconEdit</c> (Icon Editor) and <c>KPovModeler</c> (a 3D Modeler). 
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kde-i18n</ti>
  <ti>
    Internationalisation-related files for KDE. This includes support for
    foreign languages (and currencies, number/date formats, ...) and
    documentation. See also the <uri link="http://i18n.kde.org">KDE i18n
    project</uri> for more information.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdemultimedia</ti>
  <ti>
    Multimedia-related applications, including support for CD, MP3, DVD,
    sequencing, sound and video applications. More information can be found on
    the <uri link="http://multimedia.kde.org">KDE Multimedia Project</uri>
    website.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdenetwork</ti>
  <ti>
    Network-related applications such as <c>kppp</c> (Dial-In) and <c>lisa</c>
    (Networking). Note that <c>konqueror</c> (File Manager <e>and</e> Browser) 
    is part of <c>kdebase</c>!
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdepim</ti>
  <ti>
    Personal Information Management tools, such as <c>KOrganizer</c> (Journal),
    <c>KAddressbook</c> (Address book), <c>Kontact</c> (Groupware) and
    <c>KMail</c> (E-mail). More information online at the <uri
    link="http://pim.kde.org">KDE PIM Project</uri> website.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdesdk</ti>
  <ti>
    Code development tools, including <c>KBabel</c> (Translation tool),
    <c>KBugBuster</c> (Front end for KDE bugtracking) and <c>Kompare</c> (GUI
    to see differences between files).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdetoys</ti>
  <ti>
    Various toys to amuse yourself with when you're waiting for your pizza
    delivery. You'll find applets such as <c>eyesapplet</c> and
    <c>fifteenapplet</c>, but also nifty tools like <c>amor</c> which doesn't do
    much except eat resources :)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeutils</ti>
  <ti>
    Graphical system tools such as <c>kcalc</c> (Calculator), <c>kdessh</c> (SSH
    terminal), <c>kfloppy</c> (Floppy-related actions), etc.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
For instance, to install KDE with only the network- and admin-related
applications:
</p>

<pre caption="Example installation of individual KDE components">
# <i>emerge kdebase kdenetwork kdeadmin</i>
</pre>

<p>
In case you wonder: compiling KDE does take a while :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>First Impressions</title>
<body>

<p>
Now let us take a look at the result. Now your mother has probably told you
never to work as root. So we'll take on your mother's advice and test
KDE as a user. Log in as your user and configure your session so it starts KDE
when you issue <c>startx</c>. You can do this by writing <c>exec startkde</c> in
<path>~/.xinitrc</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring your local session">
$ <i>echo "exec startkde" &gt; ~/.xinitrc</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now start up your graphical environment by running <c>startx</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Starting KDE">
$ <i>startx</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will be greeted by an application called <c>KPersonalizer</c>.
Congratulations, let's now take a look at how we can configure KDE...
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Configuring KDE</title>
<section>
<title>KPersonalizer</title>
<body>

<p>
KPersonalizer is the application that configures KDE for you. It's a very
useful wizard that allows you to quickly change KDE to suit your own needs. When
you run KDE for the first time, KPersonalizer is automatically started.
</p>

<p>
The first input KPersonalizer requests is your country and the language of your
choice. As we haven't installed the necessary language packs on your system yet,
the available languages will be very slim -- you'll probably have only English
to choose from. Don't mind this, we will change the language later on (if
applicable of course).
</p>

<p>
The second choice you're offered is the <e>System Behaviour</e>. This includes
window activation, mouse selection, etc. When you select a certain behaviour
it's description is shown to help you choose the behaviour you like. If you're
uncertain, don't panic -- you are able to change the behaviour whenever you
want.
</p>

<p>
Next KPersonalizer asks for the amount of eye-candy it should activate. The more
eye-candy you want, the funkier your KDE will be, but the more your CPU will be
stressed. However, this should be taken with a bit of salt - on a 600 Mhz CPU
with 128 Mb of memory, enabling full eye candy still results in a responsive
system.
</p>

<p>
Finally, KDE asks what style you want to use. A style defines the window
decoration, theme, button layout, etc. Try several styles to see which one you
like the most. Did we already mention KDE is fully configurable?
</p>

<p>
Now sit back and enjoy -- KDE will start up and you'll be greeted by a nice,
clean, functional desktop environment.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing Language Packs</title>
<body>

<p>
If English isn't your native language or you're just interested in working with
KDE in a foreign language, please read on. We will install the language pack(s)
for the language(s) you want to use with KDE.
</p>

<p>
Language packs are contained in the <c>kde-i18n</c> package. To install the
language packs of your choice, you need to set the <c>LINGUAS</c> variable to
the language(s) you want to use. It is adviseable to set this variable in
<path>/etc/make.conf</path> so that updating your system doesn't remove the
language packs you want.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting LINGUAS in /etc/make.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/make.conf</i>
<comment>(As an example, we install the language packs for Dutch (nl) 
 and French (fr))</comment>
LINGUAS="nl fr"
</pre>

<p>
Now run <c>emerge kde-i18n</c> to install the language packs. Once settled, fire
up KDE, then start the KDE Control Center (K-menu &gt; Settings &gt; Control
Center). This is <e>the</e> application where you can control almost every
aspect of KDE. It is much more extended than KPersonalizer.
</p>

<p>
To change your language, go to <c>Regional &amp; Accessibility</c>,
<c>Country/Region &amp; Languages</c>. Then add the language(s) of your choice.
To see your (localised) KDE in its full glory, log out and in again, and enjoy.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Graphical Login</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to use <c>kdm</c> as graphical login manager (which means you don't
have to log on onto a terminal and type <c>startx</c> every time) you first need
to look inside <path>/etc/X11/Sessions</path> to see how the KDE session is
called:
</p>

<pre caption="Checking the KDE session name">
# <i>ls /etc/X11/Sessions</i>
Xsession  fluxbox  kde-3.2.1
</pre>

<p>
In the above example, the KDE session is called <c>kde-3.2.1</c>. Let's enter
this in <path>/etc/rc.conf</path> in the variable called <c>XSESSION</c>. While
you are at it, also set the <c>DISPLAYMANAGER</c> to <c>kdm</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting XSESSION in /etc/rc.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/rc.conf</i>
<comment>(Edit the following two variables)</comment>
XSESSION="kde-3.2.1"
DISPLAYMANAGER="kdm"
</pre>

<p>
Finish up by adding <c>xdm</c> to the default runlevel:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding xdm to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add xdm default</i>
</pre>

<p>
When you reboot your system, it will use KDM as graphical login manager.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<section>
<title>KDE is extremely slow during startup</title>
<body>

<p>
Make sure your <path>/etc/hosts</path> file is correct:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    If you have a static IP address, make sure your FQDN and hostname are
    mentioned on that line, like <c>192.168.0.10 tux.mydomain tux</c>
  </li>
  <li>
    If you have a dynamic IP address or you do not have any additional
    interfaces at all, add your hostname after the localhost statement, like
    <c>127.0.0.1 localhost tux</c>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Check if you have DMA enabled for your disks:
</p>

<pre caption="Verifying DMA settings">
# <i>hdparm /dev/hda</i>
<comment>(...)</comment>
using_dma       = 1 (on)
<comment>(...)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
If you don't have an IPv6-enabled network, disable KDE's IPv6 checking by
adding the following line to <path>/etc/env.d/99kde-env</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing /etc/env.d/99kde-env">
KDE_NO_IPV6 = 1
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
