<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/kde-config.xml,v 1.15 2005/10/20 11:48:39 jkt Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/en/kde-config.xml">

<title>The KDE Configuration HOWTO</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
One of the most used desktop environments is KDE. This guide tries to describe
all aspects of KDE, including installation, configuration and usage.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.10</version>
<date>2005-10-20</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is the K Desktop Environment?</title>
<section>
<title>The Project</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.kde.org">KDE Project</uri> is a free software project
dedicated to the development of KDE, an open source graphical desktop
environment for Linux and Unix workstations. The development is carried out by
several hundred software engineers from all over the world committed to free
software development. See also <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/whatiskde/project.php">What is the KDE Project</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Software</title>
<body>

<p>
The K Desktop Environment is an easy-to-use desktop environment built around a
well thought out application framework to allow for application
interoperability, drag n drop and so on. Apart from the essential components,
the KDE environment also provides ready-to-use applications for 101 tasks: file
management, Internet browsing, office applications, e-mail handling, ...
Everything is covered by the KDE project.
</p>

<p>
The KDE environment is available in more than 70 languages and has an immense
user base. For those interested, there are lots of <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/screenshots/">screen shots</uri> available. For more
information on KDE, read the <uri link="http://www.kde.org/whatiskde/">What is
KDE?</uri> article on <uri link="http://www.kde.org">KDE.org</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Community</title>
<body>

<p>
Many KDE-based community sites exist. On <uri
link="http://www.kdenews.org">KDEnews.org</uri> you'll find the latest news on
KDE generally. <uri link="http://www.kdedevelopers.org">KDEdevelopers.org</uri>
is specifically focussed on KDE development, while <uri
link="http://www.kde-forum.org">KDE-forum</uri> is better suited for the large
masses. More links can be found on the <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/family/">KDE Family page</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Installing KDE</title>
<section>
<title>What do you need?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you're interested in installing KDE (or KDE support), you will
have to make sure that your USE variable contains the <c>kde</c> and <c>qt</c>
flags. Qt is the graphical widget library that KDE uses.
</p>

<p>
KDE is also able to automatically mount devices for you. To use this feature,
add <c>hal</c> to your USE variable.
</p>

<p>
If you do not want to use <uri link="http://www.arts-project.org/">aRts</uri>
for your all-around multimedia, disable the <c>arts</c> USE flag (it is active
by default).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing KDE &lt; 3.4</title>
<body> <!-- TODO Remove this section when 3.4 is stabilized on all archs -->

<p>
Second, you need to think on what you want to install from the KDE distribution.
As mentioned before, KDE is very feature-rich and embraces lots of packages. You
don't have to believe our word for it -- just check yourself :)
</p>

<pre caption="Listing all packages KDE would install">
# <i>emerge --pretend kde | less</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you're not interested in installing all those packages, you can emerge the
individual packages. You will most definitely want the <c>kdebase</c> package as
it contains KDE's base packages and necessities. The following table lists some
of the other available packages that you can install.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Package</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeaccessibility</ti>
  <ti>
    Accessibility related programs, managed by the <uri
    link="http://accessibility.kde.org">KDE Accessibility Project</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeadmin</ti>
  <ti>
    KDE Administrative tools, such as <c>KCron</c> (Task Scheduling),
    <c>KUser</c> (User Management) and <c>KDat</c> (Backup Management)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeartwork</ti>
  <ti>
    Various art-related stuff, including screen savers and themes. See also <uri
    link="http://artist.kde.org">artist.kde.org</uri> for more KDE related
    artwork
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeedu</ti>
  <ti>
    Educational KDE applications focused on school children aged 3 to 18. See
    also the <uri link="http://edu.kde.org">KDE Edu Project</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdegames</ti>
  <ti>
    Various KDE-developed games. More information can be found at the <uri 
    link="http://games.kde.org">KDE Games Center</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdegraphics</ti>
  <ti>
    Graphic-related tools for KDE, including <c>KSnapshot</c> (Screenshot
    Software), <c>KolourPaint</c> (Simple Graphical Editor), <c>Kpdf</c>
    (PDF viewer), <c>KIconEdit</c> (Icon Editor) and <c>KPovModeler</c>
    (a 3D Modeler).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kde-i18n</ti>
  <ti>
    Internationalization-related files for KDE. This includes support for
    foreign languages (and currencies, number/date formats, ...) and
    documentation. See also the <uri link="http://i18n.kde.org">KDE i18n
    project</uri> for more information.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdemultimedia</ti>
  <ti>
    Multimedia-related applications, including support for CD, MP3, DVD,
    sequencing, sound and video applications. More information can be found on
    the <uri link="http://multimedia.kde.org">KDE Multimedia Project</uri>
    web site.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdenetwork</ti>
  <ti>
    Network-related applications such as <c>kppp</c> (Dial-In) and <c>lisa</c>
    (Networking). Note that <c>konqueror</c> (File Manager <e>and</e> Browser) 
    is part of <c>kdebase</c>!
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdepim</ti>
  <ti>
    Personal Information Management tools, such as <c>KOrganizer</c> (Journal),
    <c>KAddressbook</c> (Address book), <c>Kontact</c> (Groupware) and
    <c>KMail</c> (E-mail). More information online at the <uri
    link="http://pim.kde.org">KDE PIM Project</uri> web site.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdesdk</ti>
  <ti>
    Code development tools, including <c>KBabel</c> (Translation tool),
    <c>KBugBuster</c> (Front end for KDE bug tracking) and <c>Kompare</c> (GUI
    to see differences between files).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdetoys</ti>
  <ti>
    Various toys to amuse yourself with when you're waiting for your pizza
    delivery. You'll find applets such as <c>eyesapplet</c> and
    <c>fifteenapplet</c>, but also nifty tools like <c>amor</c> which doesn't do
    much except eat resources :)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeutils</ti>
  <ti>
    Graphical system tools such as <c>kcalc</c> (Calculator), <c>kdessh</c> (SSH
    terminal), <c>kfloppy</c> (Floppy-related actions), etc.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
For instance, to install KDE with only the network- and admin-related
applications:
</p>

<pre caption="Example installation of individual KDE components">
# <i>emerge kdebase kdenetwork kdeadmin</i>
</pre>

<p>
In case you wonder: compiling KDE does take a while :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing KDE &gt;= 3.4</title> <!-- TODO rename to "Installing KDE" -->
<body>

<p>
More recent KDE versions (from 3.4 onwards) are presented as a plethora of
<uri link="/doc/en/kde-split-ebuilds.xml">split ebuilds</uri>, making it a tad
more difficult to know what to install and what not. Gentoo does provide a few
meta packages that will pull in a certain amount of KDE packages for you:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    If you want a full-blown KDE installation, install <c>kde-meta</c>. 
    This package will pull in all KDE applications as dependencies. 
  </li>
  <li>
    If you want a basic KDE installation, install <c>kdebase-startkde</c>. You
    can always install additional KDE applications when you want.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
These two possibilities are the extreme limits; you are probably interested in
a safe mixture of the two :) To make your decision process somewhat easier, the
following table gives a short, very incomplete yet useful overview of some of
the available KDE packages.
</p>

<p>
These packages are <e>not</e> part of the <c>kdebase-startkde</c> installation.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Ebuild name</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>amarok</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With <uri link="http://amarok.kde.org/">amaroK</uri> you have a powerful 
    music player for Unix/Linux.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>k3b</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://www.k3b.org/">K3B</uri> is a complete CD/DVD burning
    utility with Audio support. Burning CDs was never this easy.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kaffeine</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://kaffeine.sourceforge.net/">Kaffeine</uri> is a full
    featured multimedia-player for KDE.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kate</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The <uri link="http://kate.kde.org/">KDE Advanced Text Editor</uri>, a
    multi-document editor with syntax highlighting, code folding and more.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kcontrol</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The KDE Control Center.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kicker</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The KDE kicker application is the well-known KDE application launcher panel.
    It contains the K Menu and is able to run docked applets like the pager,
    task bar, clock, ...
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kmail</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Organize your e-mails efficiently with <uri
    link="http://kmail.kde.org/">KMail</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>knetattach</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With KNetAttach (also known as the <e>Network Folder Wizard</e>), you can
    easily add additional network folders to your KDE desktop.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>konqueror</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With <uri link="http://konqueror.kde.org/">Konqueror</uri> you have a
    featureful file manager and web browser.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>konsole</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://konsole.kde.org/">Konsole</uri> is the KDE terminal
    emulator.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kontact</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://kontact.kde.org/">Kontact</uri> is the KDE Personal
    Information Manager, helping you manage your communications more easily,
    organize your work faster and work together more closely.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kopete</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://kopete.kde.org/index.php">Kopete</uri> is KDE's Instant
    Messenger supporting all known IM protocols.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>korganizer</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://korganizer.kde.org/">Korganizer</uri> is the calendar and
    scheduling application for KDE.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kpdf</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With <uri link="http://kpdf.kde.org/">KPDF</uri> you can view and work with
    PDF files. It has very unique features which enhance your viewing pleasure
    enormously.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kscd</c></ti>
  <ti>
    kscd is a graphical CD player for KDE.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>ksnapshot</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With ksnapshot you can take screen shots from your desktop.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kuickshow</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The KDE kuickshow application is able to browse amongst and display 
    various image formats.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
And this is just a small tip of the iceberg. If you want to know more about all
possible KDE applications, take a look inside the <uri
link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=kde-base">kde-base
category</uri>. Their function should be available in the description.
</p>

<p>
To preview what emerge would install, use <c>emerge -p</c> together with the
<c>less</c> pager, otherwise you might not be able to see all packages.
</p>

<pre caption="Previewing the kde installation">
<comment>(Substitute with your choice of package(s))</comment>
# <i>emerge -p kdebase-startkde kicker | less</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you are happy with the proposed result, leave the <c>-p</c> out. This
building process will take some time as KDE is a big environment. Don't be
surprised when your system does not finish immediately :-)
</p>

<p>
If you want KDE to auto-mount your devices you'll need to install <c>dbus</c>,
<c>hal</c> and <c>ivman</c> as well after which you add each one of them to the
default run level:
</p>

<pre caption="Setup auto-mounting">
# <i>emerge dbus hal ivman</i>
# <i>rc-update add dbus default</i>
# <i>rc-update add hald default</i>
# <i>rc-update add ivman default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>First Impressions</title>
<body>

<p>
Let us have a look at the result. Your mother has probably told you
never to work as root. So we'll take your mother's advice and test
KDE as a user. Log in as your user and configure your session so it starts KDE
when you issue <c>startx</c>. You can do this by writing <c>exec startkde</c> in
<path>~/.xinitrc</path> (see also
<uri link="/doc/en/xorg-config.xml#using_startx">Using startx</uri> in the
<uri link="/doc/en/xorg-config.xml">X Server Configuration Howto</uri>):
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring your local session">
$ <i>echo "exec startkde" &gt; ~/.xinitrc</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now start up your graphical environment by running <c>startx</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Starting KDE">
$ <i>startx</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will be greeted by an application called <c>KPersonalizer</c>.
Congratulations, let's now take a look at how we can configure KDE...
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Configuring KDE</title>
<section>
<title>KPersonalizer</title>
<body>

<p>
KPersonalizer is the application that configures KDE for you. It's a very
useful wizard that allows you to quickly change KDE to suit your own needs. When
you run KDE for the first time, KPersonalizer is automatically started.
</p>

<p>
The first input KPersonalizer requests is your country and the language of your
choice. As we haven't installed the necessary language packs on your system yet,
the available languages will be very slim -- you'll probably have only English
to choose from. Don't mind this, we will change the language later on (if
applicable of course).
</p>

<p>
The second choice you're offered is the <e>System Behavior</e>. This includes
window activation, mouse selection, etc. When you select a certain behavior
its description is shown to help you choose the behavior you like. If you're
uncertain, don't panic -- you are able to change the behavior whenever you
want.
</p>

<p>
Next, KPersonalizer asks for the amount of eye-candy it should activate. The
more eye-candy you want, the funkier your KDE will be, but the more your CPU
will be stressed. However, this should be taken with a bit of salt - on a 600
Mhz CPU with 128 Mb of memory, enabling full eye candy still results in a
responsive system.
</p>

<p>
Finally, KDE asks what style you want to use. A style defines the window
decoration, theme, button layout, etc. Try several styles to see which one you
like the most. Did we already mention KDE is fully configurable?
</p>

<p>
Now sit back and enjoy -- KDE will start up and you'll be greeted by a nice,
clean, functional desktop environment.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing Language Packs</title>
<body>

<p>
If English isn't your native language or you're just interested in working with
KDE in a foreign language, please read on. We will install the language pack(s)
for the language(s) you want to use with KDE.
</p>

<p>
Language packs are contained in the <c>kde-i18n</c> package. To install the
language packs of your choice, you need to set the <c>LINGUAS</c> variable to
the language(s) you want to use. It is advisable to set this variable in
<path>/etc/make.conf</path> so that updating your system doesn't remove the
language packs you want.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting LINGUAS in /etc/make.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/make.conf</i>
<comment>(As an example, we install the language packs for Dutch (nl) 
 and French (fr))</comment>
LINGUAS="nl fr"
</pre>

<p>
Now run <c>emerge kde-i18n</c> to install the language packs. Once settled, fire
up KDE, then start the KDE Control Center (K-menu &gt; Control Center). This is
<e>the</e> application where you can control almost every aspect of KDE. It is
much more extended than KPersonalizer.
</p>

<p>
To change your language, go to <c>Regional &amp; Accessibility</c>,
<c>Country/Region &amp; Languages</c>. Then add the language(s) of your choice.
To see your (localized) KDE in its full glory, log out and in again, and enjoy.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Graphical Login</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to use <c>kdm</c> as graphical login manager (which means you don't
have to login to a terminal and type <c>startx</c> every time) you need
to edit a configuration file and set up your system so that it enters graphical
mode after boot, as explained below.
</p>

<p>
In <path>/etc/rc.conf</path>, set the <c>DISPLAYMANAGER</c> variable to
<c>kdm</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting DISPLAYMANAGER in /etc/rc.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/rc.conf</i>
<comment>(Edit the following variable)</comment>
DISPLAYMANAGER="kdm"
</pre>

<p>
Finish up by adding <c>xdm</c> to the default run level:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding xdm to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add xdm default</i>
</pre>

<p>
When you reboot your system, it will use KDM as the graphical login manager.
</p>

<p>
KDM will provide a list of available sessions to choose from, including KDE -
of course - and including all the other sessions installed on your system,
which KDM finds by looking in <path>/usr/share/xsessions/</path>. Thus, if you
use KDM, you don't need to edit <path>~/.xinitrc</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<section>
<title>KDE is extremely slow during startup</title>
<body>

<p>
Make sure your <path>/etc/hosts</path> file is correct:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    If you have a static IP address, make sure your FQDN and hostname are
    mentioned on that line, like <c>192.168.0.10 tux.mydomain tux</c>
  </li>
  <li>
    If you have a dynamic IP address or you do not have any additional
    interfaces at all, add your hostname after the localhost statement, like
    <c>127.0.0.1 localhost tux</c>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Check if you have DMA enabled for your disks:
</p>

<pre caption="Verifying DMA settings">
# <i>hdparm /dev/hda</i>
<comment>(...)</comment>
using_dma       = 1 (on)
<comment>(...)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
If you don't have an IPv6-enabled network, disable KDE's IPv6 checking by
adding the following line to <path>/etc/env.d/99kde-env</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing /etc/env.d/99kde-env">
KDE_NO_IPV6 = 1
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
