<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/kde-config.xml,v 1.18 2006/03/26 06:50:15 swift Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/en/kde-config.xml">

<title>The KDE Configuration HOWTO</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="greg_g@gentoo.org">Gregorio Guidi</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
One of the most used desktop environments is KDE. This guide tries to describe
all aspects of KDE, including installation, configuration and usage.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.13</version>
<date>2006-03-26</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is the K Desktop Environment?</title>
<section>
<title>The Project</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.kde.org">KDE Project</uri> is a free software project
dedicated to the development of KDE, an open source graphical desktop
environment for Linux and Unix workstations. The development is carried out by
several hundred software engineers from all over the world committed to free
software development. See also <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/whatiskde/project.php">What is the KDE Project</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Software</title>
<body>

<p>
The K Desktop Environment is an easy-to-use desktop environment built around a
well thought out application framework to allow for application
interoperability, drag n drop and so on. Apart from the essential components,
the KDE environment also provides ready-to-use applications for 101 tasks: file
management, Internet browsing, office applications, e-mail handling, ...
Everything is covered by the KDE project.
</p>

<p>
The KDE environment is available in more than 70 languages and has an immense
user base. For those interested, there are lots of <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/screenshots/">screen shots</uri> available. For more
information on KDE, read the <uri link="http://www.kde.org/whatiskde/">What is
KDE?</uri> article on <uri link="http://www.kde.org">KDE.org</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The Community</title>
<body>

<p>
Many KDE-based community sites exist. On <uri
link="http://www.kdenews.org">KDEnews.org</uri> you'll find the latest news on
KDE generally. <uri link="http://www.kdedevelopers.org">KDEdevelopers.org</uri>
is specifically focussed on KDE development, while <uri
link="http://www.kde-forum.org">KDE-forum</uri> is better suited for the large
masses. More links can be found on the <uri
link="http://www.kde.org/family/">KDE Family page</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Installing KDE</title>
<section>
<title>What do you need?</title>
<body>

<p>
If you're interested in installing KDE (or KDE support), you will
have to make sure that your USE variable contains the <c>kde</c> and <c>qt</c>
flags. Qt is the graphical widget library that KDE uses.
</p>

<p>
You should also add <c>hal</c> to your USE variable now if you want to add support
for mounting devices automatically as explained below in
<uri link="#kde_device_mounting">Setup KDE to Mount Devices</uri>.
</p>

<p>
If you do not want to use <uri link="http://www.arts-project.org/">aRts</uri>
for your all-around multimedia, disable the <c>arts</c> USE flag (it is active
by default).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing KDE as Monolithic Packages</title>
<body>

<p>
The KDE project releases new versions of its desktop environment as a set of
about 16 big packages, each containing many applications (thus they are called
"monolithic"), so you need to decide which of these packages you want to
install.
</p>

<p>
If you want to see what it looks like to have all these packages installed,
just check yourself:
</p>

<pre caption="Listing all packages KDE would install">
# <i>emerge --pretend kde | less</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you're not interested in installing all those packages, you can emerge them
individually. You will most definitely want the <c>kdebase</c> package as it
contains KDE's base packages and required dependencies. The following table
lists some of the other available packages that you can install.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Package</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeaccessibility</ti>
  <ti>
    Accessibility related programs, managed by the <uri
    link="http://accessibility.kde.org">KDE Accessibility Project</uri>
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeadmin</ti>
  <ti>
    KDE Administrative tools, such as <c>KCron</c> (Task Scheduling),
    <c>KUser</c> (User Management) and <c>KDat</c> (Backup Management).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeartwork</ti>
  <ti>
    Various art-related stuff, including screen savers and themes. See also <uri
    link="http://www.kde-artists.org/">www.kde-artists.org</uri> for more KDE related
    artwork.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeedu</ti>
  <ti>
    Educational KDE applications focused on school children aged 3 to 18. See
    also the <uri link="http://edu.kde.org">KDE Edu Project</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdegames</ti>
  <ti>
    Various KDE-developed games. More information can be found at the <uri 
    link="http://games.kde.org">KDE Games Center</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdegraphics</ti>
  <ti>
    Graphic-related tools for KDE, including <c>KSnapshot</c> (Screenshot
    Software), <c>KolourPaint</c> (Simple Graphical Editor), <c>Kpdf</c>
    (PDF viewer), <c>KIconEdit</c> (Icon Editor) and <c>KPovModeler</c>
    (a 3D Modeler).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdemultimedia</ti>
  <ti>
    Multimedia-related applications, including support for CD, MP3, DVD,
    sequencing, sound and video applications. More information can be found on
    the <uri link="http://multimedia.kde.org">KDE Multimedia Project</uri>
    web site.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdenetwork</ti>
  <ti>
    Network-related applications such as <c>Kopete</c> (Multi-Protocol Instant
    Messaging), <c>kppp</c> (Dial-In) and <c>KSirc</c> (IRC client).  Note that
    <c>konqueror</c> (File Manager <e>and</e> Browser) is part of <c>kdebase</c>!
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdepim</ti>
  <ti>
    Personal Information Management tools, such as <c>KOrganizer</c> (Journal),
    <c>KAddressbook</c> (Address book), <c>Kontact</c> (Groupware) and
    <c>KMail</c> (E-mail). More information online at the <uri
    link="http://pim.kde.org">KDE PIM Project</uri> web site.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdesdk</ti>
  <ti>
    Code development tools, including <c>KBabel</c> (Translation tool),
    <c>KBugBuster</c> (Front end for KDE bug tracking) and <c>Kompare</c> (GUI
    to see differences between files).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdetoys</ti>
  <ti>
    Various toys to amuse yourself with when you're waiting for your pizza
    delivery. You'll find applets such as <c>eyesapplet</c> and
    <c>fifteenapplet</c>, but also nifty tools like <c>amor</c> which doesn't do
    much except eat resources :)
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kdeutils</ti>
  <ti>
    Graphical system tools such as <c>kcalc</c> (Calculator), <c>kdessh</c> (SSH
    terminal), <c>kfloppy</c> (Floppy-related actions), etc.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>kde-i18n</ti>
  <ti>
    Internationalization files for KDE. This includes translated
    documentation. See also the <uri link="http://i18n.kde.org">KDE i18n
    project</uri> for more information.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
For instance, to install KDE with only the network- and admin-related
applications:
</p>

<pre caption="Example installation of individual KDE components">
# <i>emerge kdebase kdenetwork kdeadmin</i>
</pre>

<p>
In case you wonder: compiling KDE does take a while.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing KDE as Split Packages</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to have even more control on what parts of KDE you install, you
have the possibility to install just the single KDE applications that you need.
To know more about the ebuilds for the individual KDE programs see the <uri
link="/doc/en/kde-split-ebuilds.xml">Split Ebuilds HOWTO</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Knowing what to install and what not is a tad more difficult with split ebuilds.
However, Gentoo does provide a few meta packages that will pull in a certain
amount of KDE packages for you:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    If you want a full-blown KDE installation, install <c>kde-meta</c>. 
    This package will pull in all KDE applications as dependencies. 
  </li>
  <li>
    If you want a basic KDE installation, install <c>kdebase-startkde</c>. You
    can always install additional KDE applications when you want.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
These two possibilities are the extreme limits; you are probably interested in
a safe mixture of the two :) To make your decision process somewhat easier, the
following table gives a short, very incomplete yet useful overview of some of
the available KDE packages.
</p>

<p>
These packages are <e>not</e> part of the <c>kdebase-startkde</c> installation.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Ebuild name</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>akregator</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The application to easily manage and browse internet RSS feeds.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>juk</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The playlist oriented media player, with a look and feel resembling Apple's
    iTunes.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kate</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The <uri link="http://kate.kde.org/">KDE Advanced Text Editor</uri>, a
    multi-document editor with syntax highlighting, code folding and more.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kcontrol</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The KDE Control Center.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kicker</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The KDE kicker application is the well-known KDE application launcher panel.
    It contains the K Menu and is able to run docked applets like the pager,
    task bar, clock, ...
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kmail</c></ti>
  <ti>
    Organize your e-mails efficiently with <uri
    link="http://kmail.kde.org/">KMail</uri>.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>knetattach</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With KNetAttach (also known as the <e>Network Folder Wizard</e>), you can
    easily add additional network folders to your KDE desktop.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>knode</c></ti>
  <ti>
    KNode is the powerful KDE newsreader.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>konqueror</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With <uri link="http://konqueror.kde.org/">Konqueror</uri> you have a
    featureful file manager and web browser.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>konsole</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://konsole.kde.org/">Konsole</uri> is the KDE terminal
    emulator.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kontact</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://kontact.kde.org/">Kontact</uri> is the KDE Personal
    Information Manager, helping you manage your communications more easily,
    organize your work faster and work together more closely.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kopete</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://kopete.kde.org/index.php">Kopete</uri> is KDE's Instant
    Messenger supporting all known IM protocols.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>korganizer</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://korganizer.kde.org/">Korganizer</uri> is the calendar and
    scheduling application for KDE.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kpdf</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With <uri link="http://kpdf.kde.org/">KPDF</uri> you can view and work with
    PDF files. It has very unique features which enhance your viewing pleasure
    enormously.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kscd</c></ti>
  <ti>
    kscd is a graphical CD player for KDE.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>ksnapshot</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With ksnapshot you can take screen shots from your desktop.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kuickshow</c></ti>
  <ti>
    The KDE kuickshow application is able to browse amongst and display 
    various image formats.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
And this is just the tip of the iceberg. If you want to know more about all
possible KDE applications, take a look inside the <uri
link="http://packages.gentoo.org/packages/?category=kde-base">kde-base
category</uri>. Their function should be available in the description.
</p>

<p>
To preview what emerge would install, use <c>emerge -p</c> together with the
<c>less</c> pager, otherwise you might not be able to see all packages.
</p>

<pre caption="Previewing the kde installation">
<comment>(Substitute with your choice of package(s))</comment>
# <i>emerge -p kdebase-startkde kicker | less</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you are happy with the proposed result, leave the <c>-p</c> out. This
building process will take some time as KDE is a big environment. Don't be
surprised when your system does not finish immediately.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>External KDE applications</title>
<body>

<p>
The number of KDE applications is not limited to those shipped with the
official KDE releases, but includes hundreds of other applications that use the
KDE framework and libraries.  Here we list just a few of the most popular ones.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Ebuild name</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>koffice</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://www.koffice.org/">KOffice</uri> is the comprehensive KDE
    office suite, featuring applications for word processing (KWord),
    spreadsheet calculations (KSpread), presentation (KPresenter), image
    manipulation (Krita), database management (Kexi) and much more.
    Just as KDE can be installed through the <c>kde</c> or <c>kde-meta</c>
    ebuilds, you can install KOffice as a single package (<c>koffice</c>) or as
    a set of individual packages (<c>koffice-meta</c>).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>amarok</c></ti>
  <ti>
    With <uri link="http://amarok.kde.org/">amaroK</uri> you have a powerful 
    music player for Unix/Linux.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>k3b</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://www.k3b.org/">K3B</uri> is a complete CD/DVD burning
    utility with Audio support. Burning CDs was never this easy.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><c>kaffeine</c></ti>
  <ti>
    <uri link="http://kaffeine.sourceforge.net/">Kaffeine</uri> is a full
    featured multimedia-player for KDE.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>First Impressions</title>
<body>

<p>
Let us have a look at the result. Your mother has probably told you
never to work as root. So we'll take your mother's advice and test
KDE as a user. Log in as your user and configure your session so it starts KDE
when you issue <c>startx</c>. You can do this by writing <c>exec startkde</c> in
<path>~/.xinitrc</path> (see also
<uri link="/doc/en/xorg-config.xml#using_startx">Using startx</uri> in the
<uri link="/doc/en/xorg-config.xml">X Server Configuration Howto</uri>):
</p>

<pre caption="Configuring your local session">
$ <i>echo "exec startkde" &gt; ~/.xinitrc</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now start up your graphical environment by running <c>startx</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Starting KDE">
$ <i>startx</i>
</pre>

<p>
You will be greeted by an application called <c>KPersonalizer</c>.
Congratulations, let's now take a look at how we can configure KDE...
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Configuring KDE</title>
<section>
<title>KPersonalizer</title>
<body>

<p>
KPersonalizer is the application that configures KDE for you. It's a very
useful wizard that allows you to quickly change KDE to suit your own needs. When
you run KDE for the first time, KPersonalizer is automatically started.
</p>

<p>
The first input KPersonalizer requests is your country and the language of your
choice. As we haven't installed the necessary language packs on your system yet,
the available languages will be very slim -- you'll probably have only English
to choose from. Don't mind this, we will change the language later on (if
applicable of course).
</p>

<p>
The second choice you're offered is the <e>System Behavior</e>. This includes
window activation, mouse selection, etc. When you select a certain behavior
its description is shown to help you choose the behavior you like. If you're
uncertain, don't panic -- you are able to change the behavior whenever you
want.
</p>

<p>
Next, KPersonalizer asks for the amount of eye-candy it should activate. The
more eye-candy you want, the funkier your KDE will be, but the more your CPU
will be stressed. However, this should be taken with a bit of salt - on a 600
Mhz CPU with 128 Mb of memory, enabling full eye-candy still results in a
responsive system.
</p>

<p>
Finally, KDE asks what style you want to use. A style defines the window
decoration, theme, button layout, etc. Try several styles to see which one you
like the most. Did we already mention KDE is fully configurable?
</p>

<p>
Now sit back and enjoy -- KDE will start up and you'll be greeted by a nice,
clean, functional desktop environment.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Installing Language Packs</title>
<body>

<p>
If English isn't your native language or you're just interested in working with
KDE in a foreign language, please read on. We will install the language pack(s)
for the language(s) you want to use with KDE.
</p>

<p>
Language packs are contained in the <c>kde-i18n</c> package. To install the
language packs of your choice, you need to set the <c>LINGUAS</c> variable to
the language(s) you want to use. It is advisable to set this variable in
<path>/etc/make.conf</path> so that updating your system doesn't remove the
language packs you want.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting LINGUAS in /etc/make.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/make.conf</i>
<comment>(As an example, we install the language packs for Dutch (nl) 
 and French (fr))</comment>
LINGUAS="nl fr"
</pre>

<p>
Now run <c>emerge kde-i18n</c> to install the language packs. Once settled, fire
up KDE, then start the KDE Control Center (K-menu &gt; Control Center). This is
<e>the</e> application where you can control almost every aspect of KDE. It is
much more extended than KPersonalizer.
</p>

<p>
To change your language, go to <c>Regional &amp; Accessibility</c>,
<c>Country/Region &amp; Languages</c>. Then add the language(s) of your choice.
To see your (localized) KDE in its full glory, log out and in again, and enjoy.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Graphical Login</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to use <c>kdm</c> as graphical login manager (which means you don't
have to login to a terminal and type <c>startx</c> every time) you need
to edit a configuration file and set up your system so that it enters graphical
mode after boot, as explained below.
</p>

<p>
In <path>/etc/rc.conf</path>, set the <c>DISPLAYMANAGER</c> variable to
<c>kdm</c>.
</p>

<pre caption="Setting DISPLAYMANAGER in /etc/rc.conf">
# <i>nano -w /etc/rc.conf</i>
<comment>(Edit the following variable)</comment>
DISPLAYMANAGER="kdm"
</pre>

<p>
Finish up by adding <c>xdm</c> to the default runlevel:
</p>

<pre caption="Adding xdm to the default runlevel">
# <i>rc-update add xdm default</i>
</pre>

<p>
When you reboot your system, it will use KDM as the graphical login manager.
</p>

<p>
KDM will provide a list of available sessions to choose from, including KDE -
of course - and including all the other sessions installed on your system,
which KDM finds by looking in <path>/usr/share/xsessions/</path>. Thus, if you
use KDM, you don't need to edit <path>~/.xinitrc</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section id="kde_device_mounting">
<title>Setup KDE to Mount Devices</title>
<body>

<!-- TODO add pmount package when pmount is in arch.
     Also, add pmount to the default runlevel -->

<p>
KDE gives you the power to mount devices such as CDROMs or USB sticks through a
single click in a graphical interface.  To accomplish this goal you need to
have KDE compiled with <c>hal</c> in your USE variable and to have
<c>dbus</c> and <c>hal</c> installed on your system.  You should
also add <c>dbus</c> and <c>hal</c> to the default runlevel and add yourself to
the <c>plugdev</c> group.
</p>

<pre caption="Setup device mounting">
# <i>emerge --noreplace dbus hal</i>
# <i>rc-update add dbus default</i>
# <i>rc-update add hald default</i>
<comment>Add &lt;user&gt; to the plugdev group</comment>
# <i>gpasswd -a &lt;user&gt; plugdev</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can also have your devices automatically mounted without interaction, you
just need to install <c>ivman</c> and add it to the default runlevel.
</p>

<pre caption="Setup auto-mounting">
# <i>emerge --noreplace ivman</i>
# <i>rc-update add ivman default</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Managing KDE Installations</title>
<section>
<title>Multiple Installations</title>
<body>

<p>
One peculiarity of the way KDE is managed in Gentoo is that when a new series
of KDE appears (such as the 3.5.x series, which supersedes the 3.4.x series)
it will be installed alongside the old one and will not overwrite it.  So if
for instance you had KDE 3.4 already installed and you emerge KDE 3.5,
you will have two versions, one installed in <path>/usr/kde/3.4/</path> and
the other in <path>/usr/kde/3.5/</path>.
</p>

<p>
It should be noted that your settings for different KDE installations will be
kept separate in the home directory.  KDE 3.4 reads its settings from the
directory <path>/home/&lt;user&gt;/.kde3.4</path>, and the first time you run
KDE 3.5 a directory named <path>/home/&lt;user&gt;/.kde3.5</path> will be
created by migrating the settings in the 3.4 directory and will be then used to
store preferences and data.
</p>

<p>
Another important remark to keep in mind when upgrading your KDE installation
is that you could have problems with the external KDE applications you have
installed (such as <c>koffice</c>, <c>amarok</c> or <c>k3b</c>) until you
recompile them against the new KDE version.  So as soon as you start using the
new KDE you should reemerge them to make them link against the new libraries.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Unmerging Old Versions</title>
<body>

<p>
Having multiple versions of KDE installed poses the problem of how to remove
the old ones when we decide that they are not needed anymore.  Unfortunately
portage does not support unmerging a package with all its dependencies with a
single command, so if for instance you run <c>emerge --unmerge kde</c> you will
not remove the actual kde packages.
</p>

<p>
To remove a KDE installation (e.g. KDE 3.4), the single packages have to be
removed.
</p>

<pre caption="Removing KDE 3.4 packages">
# <i>emerge --unmerge =arts-3.4* =kdelibs-3.4* =kdebase-3.4* ...</i>
</pre>

<p>
Obviously this is very frustrating if you have many KDE packages installed.
However this operation can be automated in many ways.  The following one is
an example.
</p>

<p>
First we list all the packages that we want to remove. We use the <c>equery</c>
command for this, part of the <c>app-portage/gentoolkit</c> package:
</p>

<pre caption="Listing packages to remove">
<comment>(List all the installed KDE packages)</comment>
# <i>equery list kde-base/</i>
<comment>(List all the installed KDE packages and select the ones from KDE 3.4)</comment>
# <i>equery list kde-base/ | grep 3.4</i>
</pre>

<p>
At this point you should double-check that the list corresponds to the packages
that should be removed from the system.  If you think it is ok, you can go on
and pass the list to the <c>emerge --unmerge</c> command.
</p>

<pre caption="Removing selected packages">
# <i>equery list kde-base/ | grep 3.4 | xargs emerge --unmerge --pretend</i>
</pre>

<p>
Check again the output and reissue the command without <c>--pretend</c> to
start the unmerging process.
</p>

<p>
After the job has completed, the directory <path>/usr/kde/3.4/</path> should
contain only a few files (mainly configuration files, portage has a policy to
never touch configurations).  If you desire, you can safely wipe out
<path>/usr/kde/3.4/</path> with its content to remove what remains of KDE 3.4.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<section>
<title>KDE is extremely slow during startup</title>
<body>

<p>
Make sure your <path>/etc/hosts</path> file is correct:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    If you have a static IP address, make sure your FQDN and hostname are
    mentioned on that line, like <c>192.168.0.10 tux.mydomain tux</c>
  </li>
  <li>
    If you have a dynamic IP address or you do not have any additional
    interfaces at all, add your hostname after the localhost statement, like
    <c>127.0.0.1 localhost tux</c>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Check if you have DMA enabled for your disks:
</p>

<pre caption="Verifying DMA settings">
# <i>hdparm /dev/hda</i>
<comment>(...)</comment>
using_dma       = 1 (on)
<comment>(...)</comment>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
