<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/nano-basics-guide.xml,v 1.10 2004/08/05 13:10:43 swift Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/doc/en/nano-basics-guide.xml">

<title>Nano Basics Guide</title>

<author title="Gentoo Doc Editor"><!-- meekrob@gentoo.org -->
  Sherman Boyd
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>This is a simple introduction to nano.  To get you familiar with it's basic functions, fast.</abstract>

<version>1.2</version>
<date>August 05, 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Nano Basics</title>
<section>
<title>Purpose</title>
<body>
<p>
This guide was written to cover basic operations in nano, and is meant to be very concise.  For more information about nano check out:
</p><p>
<uri>http://www.nano-editor.org</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Opening and creating files</title>
<body>
<p>
Opening and creating files is simple in nano, simply type:
</p>

<pre>
# <i>nano filename</i>
</pre>

<p>
Nano is a modeless editor so you can start typing immediately to insert text.  If you are editing a configuration file like <path>/etc/fstab</path> use the -w switch, for example:
</p>

<pre>
# <i>nano -w /etc/fstab</i>
</pre>

<warn>It is very, very important that you use the -w switch when opening a config file.  Failure to do so may keep your system from booting or other bad things.</warn>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Saving and exiting</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to save the changes you've made, press <c>Ctrl+O</c>. To exit
<c>nano</c>, type <c>Ctrl+X</c>. If you ask <c>nano</c> to exit a modified file,
it will ask you if you want to save it. Just press <c>N</c> in case you don't,
or <c>Y</c> in case you do. It will then ask you for a filename. Just type it 
in and press <c>Enter</c>.
</p>

<p>
If you accidentally confirmed that you want to save the file, but you actually
don't, you can always cancel by pressing <c>Ctrl+C</c> when you're prompted for
a filename.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cutting and pasting</title>
<body>
<p>
To cut a single line line you use <c>^K</c>.  You simply hold down <c>CTRL</c> and <c>k</c> at the same time.  The line dissapears.  To paste it you simply move the cursor to where you want to paste and punch <c>^U</c> (<c>CTRL u</c>) on your keyboard.  BAM!  The line reapears.  Suppose you need to move a whole paragraph.  To move multiple lines simply cut each line one at a time, and then paste.  BAM!  The whole paragraph appears wherever you want it.	</p>
<p>
If you need a little more fine grained control then you need to mark the text.  Move the cursor to the beginning of the text you want to cut.  Hit <c>^^</c> (that's <c>ctrl ^</c> or <c>ctrl 6</c>).  Now move your cursor to the end of the text you want to cut.  The desired text should be highlighted now.  If need to cancel your text marking simply hit <c>^^</c> again.  Click <c>^K</c> to cut the text.  Use <c>^U</c> to paste it.  BAM!  Now that's cooking.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Searching for text</title>
<body>
<p>
Searching for a string is easy as long as you think <e>"WhereIs"</e> instead of <e>"Search"</e>.  Simple hit <c>^W</c> (<c>CTRL w</c>) and type in your search string.  Like I said, easy.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>More options</title>
<body>

<p>
If you're interested in tweaking nano, be sure to read
<path>/etc/nanorc</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Wrap up</title>
<body>
<p>
That is all!  Thanks to kiyose and quazion from #gentoo.  Again, for more information about nano check out:
</p><p>
<uri>http://www.nano-editor.org</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>

 
