<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link = "/doc/en/policy.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Development Policy</title>
<author title="Original Author">Owen Stampflee</author> 
<author title="Author"><mail link="karltk@gentoo.org">Karl Trygve Kalleberg</mail></author> 
<author title="Author/Editor"><mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail></author> 
<author title="Editor"><mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail></author> 
<author title="Editor"><mail link="avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail></author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="vapier@gentoo.org">Mike Frysinger</mail></author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="carl@gentoo.org">Carl Anderson</mail></author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="liquidx@gentoo.org">Alastaire Tse</mail></author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail></author>

<abstract>
This guide is meant to be the authoritative written reference for Gentoo Linux development policy.
It will be updated periodically to reflect new developer procedures.
</abstract>

<version>1.0.2</version>
<date>26 June 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>General guidelines</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Here are some general development guidelines to follow:</p>
<ul>

<li>Always check in your changes with repoman; use repoman commit instead of cvs commit.</li>

<li>If a package is either broken in its current version or it has a really
nasty build/install process, take a look at how other distributions do it: <ul>
<li><uri>http://cvs.mandrakesoft.com/cgi-bin/cvsweb.cgi/SPECS/</uri></li>
<li><uri>http://www.debian.org/distrib/packages</uri></li> </ul> </li>
   
<li>Your package, when complete and unmasked, is supposed to "just work" for
the end-user. Tweaking the installed product to get it to work should be
optional; thus you need to install the package with reasonable default
settings.</li>

<li>Don't be afraid to consult our on-line documentation and ebuilds written
and maintained by more senior developers. Feel free to contact senior
developers directly with any technical or policy questions.</li>

<li>Be cautious about what you commit. Remember that your commits
can potentially harm thousands of users. If your commits cause any breakage
in the tree, they must be fixed in a timely fashion.</li>

</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Ebuild policy</title>
<section>
<title>Naming policy</title>
<body>

<p>Ebuild file names consist of four logical sections:</p>

<p><c>pkg-ver{_suf{#}}{-r#}.ebuild</c></p>

<note>The brackets (<c>{}</c>) deliniate optional fields and do not appear in
the literal package name. <c>#</c> represents any non-zero positive
integer.</note>

<p>
The first section, <c>pkg</c>, is the package name, which should 
only contain lowercase letters, the digits 0-9, and any number of single 
hyphen (<c>-</c>) characters. Examples: <c>util-linux</c>, 
<c>sysklogd</c>, <c>glibc</c>. We have some packages in Portage that 
don't follow these rules, but <i>your</i> packages should.
</p>

<p>
The second section, <c>ver</c>, is the version of the package, which 
should
normally be same as the version on the main source tarball. The version is
normally made up of two or three (or more) numbers separated by periods, such
as <c>1.2</c> or <c>4.5.2</c>, and may have a single letter immediately
following the last digit; e.g., <c>1.4b</c> or <c>2.6h</c>. The package 
version is joined to the package name with a hyphen. Examples: 
<c>foo-1.0</c>, <c>bar-2.4.6</c>.
</p>

<p>
The third section, <c>{_suf{#}}</c>, is optional may contain one of 
these predefined suffixes, listed in least-recent to most-recent order:
</p>

<table>
 <tr><th>Suffix</th><th>Meaning</th></tr>
 <tr><ti><c>_alpha</c></ti><ti>Alpha release</ti></tr>
 <tr><ti><c>_beta</c></ti><ti>Beta release</ti></tr>
 <tr><ti><c>_pre</c></ti><ti>Prerelease</ti></tr>
 <tr><ti><c>_rc</c></ti><ti>Release candidate</ti></tr>
 <tr><ti><c>_p</c></ti><ti>Patch level (normally accompanied by trailing integer)</ti></tr>
 <tr><ti>(none)</ti><ti>Normal release</ti></tr>
</table>

<p> 
Any of these suffixes may be immediately followed by a non-zero positive
integer, e.g., <c>linux-2.4.0_pre10</c>. Assuming identical version parts, the
suffixes are ordered as follows (lower means older): <c>_alpha</c> &lt;
<c>_beta</c> &lt; <c>_pre</c> &lt; <c>_rc</c> &lt; (no suffix) &lt;
<c>_p</c>
</p>
       
<p>
When comparing identical suffixes with trailing integers, the one with the
larger integer will be considered most recent. Example: <c>foo-1.0_alpha4</c>
is more recent than <c>foo-1.0_alpha3</c>.
</p>

<p>
The fourth section of the package name is the Gentoo Linux-specific revision
number (<c>{-r#}</c>). This section, like the suffix, is also optional.
<c>#</c> is a non-zero positive integer; e.g.,  <c>package-4.5.3-r3</c>. 
</p>

<p>
This revision number is independent of the version of the source tarball and
is used to inform people that a new and improved Gentoo Linux revision of a
particular package is available. Initial releases of ebuilds must have no
revision number; e.g., <c>package-4.5.3</c> and are considered by 
Portage to have a revision number of zero. This means that counting goes 
as follows: <c>1.0</c> (initial version), <c>1.0-r1</c>, <c>1.0-r2</c>, 
etc. 
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Versioning and revision bumps</title>
<body>

<p>
Package revision numbers should be incremented by Gentoo Linux developers
when the ebuild has changed to the point where users would want to upgrade.
Typically, this is the case when fixes are made to an ebuild that affect the
resultant installed files, but the ebuild uses the same source tarball as the
previous release.  If you make an internal, stylistic change to the ebuild that
does not change any of the installed files, then there is no need to bump the
revision number.  Likewise, if you fix a compilation problem in the ebuild that
was affecting some users, there is no need to bump the revision number, since
those for whom it worked perfectly would see no benefit in installing a new
revision, and those who experienced the problem do not have the package
installed (since compilation failed) and thus have no need for the new revision
number to force an upgrade.
</p>

<impo>
Whenever you create a new revision of an ebuild, be sure to update the
<path>ChangeLog</path> file in the ebuild directory. Failing to do so is
considered to be in very poor taste and may result in disciplinary
action.
</impo>

<p>
Ebuilds should be based on the previous version of the ebuild to ensure 
that fixes aren't dropped accidentally. Fixes should include appropriate 
comments in the ebuild explaining what they are for and why they are 
needed. If you are not familiar with the fixes, or unable to determine 
if they are still needed, you should not be updating the ebuild.
</p>

</body> 
</section> 

<section>
<title>Virtuals</title>
<body>

<p>
Portage supports a concept called "virtual" packages. Using virtual
packages, it is possible to have a particular category/package name map to
another. 
</p>

<p>
Here's an example of how to use virtual packages. Let's say you create
a new cron package called <c>foocron</c>. Gentoo Linux is currently set up so
that things that need a cron package of some kind depend on the
<c>virtual/cron</c> package. This allows ebuilds to ensure that there is some
kind of cron available while allowing users the flexibility to install the cron
package that they prefer. To plug your <path>foocron-1.0.ebuild</path> into
this system, you'd add a line to the ebuild that reads:
</p>

<pre>
PROVIDE="virtual/cron"
</pre>

<p>
Now, when <c>foocron-1.0</c> is installed, the <c>virtual/cron</c> package
will be registered. If you didn't have any cron package installed before, this
would mean that any package <e>depending</e> on <c>virtual/cron</c> would have
that dependency fully satisfied. Note that it is possible to specify a
<c>PROVIDE</c> value for any type of package -- it need not begin with
<c>virtual/</c>. However, you <e>should</e> use the <c>virtual/</c> category
unless you are using the <c>PROVIDE</c> functionality to handle packages that
have been renamed.  
</p>

<p>
There is a second component to the Gentoo Linux virtuals implementation.
What would happen if there were no installed package that provided
<c>virtual/cron</c>? How would Portage choose the "correct" cron to install to
satisfy the <c>virtual/cron</c> dependency? Portage takes care of this
situation by using a profile-specific virtual mapping file called
<path>virtuals</path> which is stored in the profile directory
<path>/etc/make.profile</path>. If you take a look at your
<path>virtuals</path> file, you'll find that the contents look something like
this: 
</p>

<pre caption="Sample virtuals file">
virtual/lpr             net-print/cups
virtual/python          dev-lang/python
virtual/mta             net-mail/ssmtp
</pre>

<p>
The first line of this file tells Portage that if a package depends on
<c>virtual/lpr</c> and no <c>virtual/lpr</c> is installed and no
<c>virtual/lpr</c> package is available in the Portage tree, then
<c>net-print/cups</c> should be installed to satisfy this dependency.
<c>net-print/cups</c> contains a line that reads <c>PROVIDE="virtual/lpr"</c>
so that future dependencies on <c>virtual/lpr</c> will be satisfied.
</p>

<p>
Now for the developer guidelines. If you were to add the <c>foocron</c>
package, you would obviously want to ensure that all programs that depend upon
<c>virtual/cron</c> are able to work correctly with it. And if you were to add
a package named <c>foobarosity</c> that depended on <c>virtual/cron</c>, you
should likewise ensure that all packages that provide <c>virtual/cron</c> will
be satisfactory for the proper functioning of <c>foobarosity</c>.
</p>

<p>
Before creating new virtual packages, please begin a discussion on the
internal developer mailing list about that virtual. Keeping developers
informed of new virtuals is essential to ensure their uniform use.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CVS sources policy</title>
<body>

<p>
There are two different ways to build an ebuild based on sources from a CVS
development tree. The first and traditional way is to create a "CVS snapshot"
ebuild by creating your own tarball snapshot of the upstream CVS tree,
mirroring the sources on our official distfile repository, and writing an
ebuild to specifically use this tarball snapshot. These types of CVS ebuilds
will be referred to as "CVS snapshot ebuilds" below.
</p> 

<p>
The other method of
creating a CVS-based ebuild is to use <path>cvs.eclass</path> to create a
"live" CVS ebuild. Such an ebuild will dynamically grab the latest development
sources from a CVS repository at "fetch" time, ensuring that the sources are as
up-to-date as possible. These types of CVS ebuilds will be referred to as
"'live' ebuilds" below.
</p>

<p>
The following paragraphs detail the policy relating to the use of CVS-based
ebuilds.  Note that there are strict rules relating to the addition of such
ebuilds to the Portage tree.
</p>

<p>
Snapshot cvs ebuilds are greatly preferred over "live" <path>cvs.eclass</path>
cvs ebuilds.
</p> 

<p>
Snapshot cvs ebuilds are allowed if a cvs snapshot contains known fixes that
are needed for proper operation of a software package, or if the cvs version of
a particular software package is known to or has been proven to simply "work
better" than the normal release version.
</p>

<p>
"Live" <path>cvs.eclass</path> ebuilds are generally only intended for the
convenience of developers and should always be masked with a <c>~[arch]</c>
keyword. It is impossible to guarantee the reliability of a "live"
<path>cvs.eclass</path> ebuild since the upstream cvs tree may change at any
time, which is why they should always be masked.
</p> 

<p>
Whether a "live" cvs ebuild or a "snapshot" CVS ebuild, <b>you the
developer are responsible for ensuring that the ebuild works correctly</b>.
This is particularly difficult to do with "live" cvs ebuilds for obvious
reasons.
</p>

<p>
If ebuilds (of any kind) do not work correctly or are flaky, they should be
fixed or removed from the Portage tree. If they are "live" ebuilds, they may be
<c>~[arch]</c> keyword masked for their lifetime (this special exception is
detailed below). 
</p>

<p>
If a user or users specifically request a "live" cvs ebuild, you can add one
for them. It should have a <c>~[arch]</c> keyword so that other users don't
merge it unsuspectingly. 
</p>

<p>
This way, the user(s) requesting them (likely developers) can install
them but other users will be protected from merging them accidentally.
Again, this only applies to situations where a user or users
specifically request a "live" <path>cvs.eclass</path> CVS ebuild. Snapshot
ebuilds should only be added to the Portage tree with the intention that they
are stable and provide better functionality than the normal release versions
of said software.
</p>

<impo>
Snapshot ebuilds of <e>pre-release</e> CVS sources should be named as
follows: <path>foo-x.y_preYYYYMMDD.ebuild</path>.  <c>foo</c> is the package
name, <c>x.y</c> is the version number of the <e>upcoming</e> release,
<c>_pre</c> is a literal string, and <c>YYYYMMDD</c> is a timestamp of the day
the CVS snapshot was taken. Use this naming convention to ensure that a
<c>x.y.1</c> release version won't be considered to be older than a <c>x.y</c>
snapshot, while at the same time ensuring that the official <c>x.y</c> release
will be considered <e>newer</e> than your CVS snapshot version. For CVS
snapshots of <e>already-released</e> CVS sources, use the format
<path>foo-x.y_pYYYYMMDD.ebuild</path> (notice the <c>_p</c> for "patchlevel.")
This will ensure that your CVS ebuild will be considered <e>newer</e> than the
standard <c>x.y</c> release.
</impo>

<impo>
Currently, the policy for naming "live" cvs ebuilds is to ensure that the
package name ends with <c>-cvs</c>. In the future, a <c>_cvs</c> version suffix
will likely be added to Portage and this policy will be updated.
</impo>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>User-submitted ebuilds</title>
<body>

<p>
User-submitted ebuilds should never be blindly trusted and should always be
well-tested and audited before being committed to CVS. <b>If a user-submitted
ebuild has problems, you will be held accountable.</b> By committing it to CVS,
you are vouching that the ebuild meets all Gentoo Linux development standards.
</p>

<p>Make sure that the user-submitted ebuild doesn't contain custom headers like this:</p>

<pre caption="A custom header that should be transferred to the ChangeLog">
# Ebuild updated by: me &lt;me@me.com&gt;
</pre>

<p>
This information should be added to the <path>ChangeLog</path> using proper ChangeLog
comment syntax. <b>Always ensure that the ChangeLog gives proper credit to the user
who submitted the ebuild. This information should appear in the first ChangeLog entry.</b>
</p>

<p>Also ensure that any new ebuilds you commit contain the following line:</p>
<pre>
# &#36;Header: &#36;
</pre>
<p>Quite a few user-submitted ebuilds are based on files from rsync, which can contain
incorrect header lines.</p>

<p>
Encourage users to submit diffs to existing ebuilds if they are submitting
an upgrade.  By doing this, we can help avoid the re-introduction of
previously-fixed bugs into our "new" ebuilds. If you are not working from a user-submitted
diff but a complete ebuild, then use the <c>diff</c> command to see what has changed, keeping
an eye open for anything from our current ebuild that should appear in the new ebuild, or
anything in the new ebuild that should be fixed or removed.
</p>

<p>
In general, let the user do the work required to get his or her ebuild up to par, unless
you <e>want</e> to clean up the ebuild on his or her behalf.  Even so, it's often better
to have the user do the work so that they can learn from their mistakes and submit cleaner ebuilds
in the future. Be sure to be thankful for any submission, even if it isn't very good. Be polite
but honest -- if an ebuild isn't usable, the user can be told in a way that does not insult their
current ebuild-writing abilities. Remember that the user who submitted that broken ebuild may
be a skilled and productive member of our project in the future -- that 
is, if they receive the right amount of encouragement and support and 
continue to improve in their abilities.
</p>

</body>
</section>


</chapter> 

<chapter>
<title>QA policy</title>
<section>
<title>Portage release policy</title>
<body>
<note>As of 17 Dec 2002, Nick Jones (carpaski) is the Portage Maintainer.</note>

<p>
Only the Portage Maintainer has the
authority to roll new releases of Portage for use by users, either
masked or unmasked versions. <b>No one</b> else is allowed to roll new
releases of Portage. 
</p>

<p>
The only exception to this rule is for situations where the Portage Maintainer may be
unavailable for extended periods of time and there is a major bug in
Portage. In this emergency situation, it would be allowable for a senior
developer to test the fix and then roll a new release. 
</p>

<p>
Before using this "escape clause," please ask yourself: is the Portage Maintainer really
unavailable? Is this fix really so super-important that it gets on our
Portage tree within an hour? Have you tested <e>all</e> of your new code to
make sure that it works well? <b>This is important!</b> Remember that if your
version of Portage is broken, it will create <e>major problems</e> for all
our users, <e>especially</e> if it is unmasked. Please only use this "escape
clause" when <e>absolutely</e> necessary -- when the consequences of <e>not</e>
using the escape clause are too high. 
</p>

<p>
And if you do, the emergency fix should be a coordinated effort among
all developers currently available online (to test the new version, etc)
and not be a "lone ranger" commit. There should be a post to the gentoo-core mailing list about
the new "emergency" version to keep everyone in the loop and to explain
why it was needed and why waiting for the Portage Maintainer wasn't an option.
</p>

<p>
The Portage Maintainer <e>does</e> allow certain special people to commit to the Portage
development cvs tree. 
However, even if you are one of these people, this
privilege does not entitle you to roll up new Portage releases. This is
the Portage Maintainer's job. He/she will review and properly QA test your changes before rolling
up a new Portage release. Please allow this work to be done by the Portage Maintainer -- do not break
these rules. It is our hope that this clarified policy will help to
prevent future Portage QA issues.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Masked packages</title>
<body>

<p>
<path>/usr/portage/profiles/package.mask</path> contains a list of 
packages that should not be merged
by users and comments detailing the specific reason why. Package.mask
is used to prevent merging of packages that are broken, break something else, or badly
need testing before going into ~ARCH KEYWORDS in the tree. When adding to package.mask,
always commit package.mask prior to committing the masked ebuild. This prevents
the ebuild from hitting users before the updated package.mask does.
</p>

<p>
Great care must be taken any time a package is removed from <path>package.mask</path>.
Keep in mind that if an ebuild is in <path>package.mask</path>, it's there for a reason.
If you didn't mask the ebuild, always contact the developer listed in the
<path>package.mask</path> comments prior to taking any action. Additionally, if the 
masked ebuild is a core package, a dependency of a core package, or the unmasking
has any possibility for adverse effects, the change must be discussed internally
on the developer mailing list.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>~ARCH in KEYWORDS</title>
<body>
<p>
The purpose of ~arch is for testing new packages added to Portage. This 
is <e>not</e> the equivalent of "testing" of "unstable" in other
distributions. It is also independent of "stable" or
"development/unstable" releases designated by the developer(s).
</p>
<p>
Any new package that enters Portage must be marked ~arch for the
architecture(s) that this version is known to work on. The developer who
commits the ebuild must verify it is in working order, and the KEYWORDS
are correct.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Moving package versions from ~ARCH to ARCH</title>
<body>
<p>
When a package version has proved stable for sufficient time and the
Gentoo maintainer of the package is confident that the upgrade will not
break a regular Gentoo user's machine, then it can be moved from ~ARCH
to ARCH. An indication of the package's stability would be no verified
or unresolved bug report for a month after the version's introduction.
</p>
<p>
It is up to the maintainer of the package to deem which versions are
stable or if development versions should be in <path>package.mask</path>
or left in ~arch.
</p>
<p>
You must also ensure that all the dependencies of such a package version
are also in ARCH.
</p>
<warn>
The ~ARCH step may <e>only</e> be ignored <e>if and only if</e> the
concerned package version contains a security fix or is needed to fix an
important bug in the Gentoo system. 
</warn>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Variables</title>

<section>
<title>Required variables</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo Linux policy requires that all ebuilds contain <c>KEYWORDS</c>, <c>LICENSE</c>,
and <c>SLOT</c> variables. <c>HOMEPAGE</c>, <c>SRC_URI</c> and <c>DESCRIPTION</c>
should also be included except for special circumstances. <c>DEPEND</c> (and if
necessary, <c>RDEPEND</c>) should be included if your package has any build or
runtime dependencies, respectively.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>DEPEND and RDEPEND</title>
<body>

<p>
Use <c>DEPEND</c> to define the dependencies required for building a
particular package, and set <c>RDEPEND</c> to the dependencies required to
<e>run</e> a particular package. You only need to explicitly specify <c>RDEPEND</c>
if the ebuild's runtime dependencies are different than what you specified in
<c>DEPEND</c>; if not specified, <c>RDEPEND</c> will default to your <c>DEPEND</c>
settings. <b>Never</b> set <c>RDEPEND</c> to <c>DEPEND</c> yourself in an ebuild.
<pre>
# Acceptable:
RDEPEND="${DEPEND}
	net-ftp/curl
	virtual/glibc"
# Not acceptable:
RDEPEND="${DEPEND}"
</pre>
</p>

<p>
It's also important to note that only
<c>RDEPEND</c> dependencies are satisfied when one installs a binary
<c>.tbz2</c> package; use this information to help you choose the correct
<c>RDEPEND</c> dependencies. If undefined, and ebuild's <c>RDEPEND</c> setting
will default to <c>DEPEND</c>.
</p>

<p> 
A package should depend upon the oldest version that satisfies the
dependency. If it works with <c>libfoo-1.2.x</c>, don't depend on
<c>libfoo-2.x</c> just because that's what you have installed.
</p>

<p>
In general, packages should depend on <c>=libfoo-1.2*</c> instead of
<c>&gt;=libfoo-1.2</c>. Otherwise, things may start breaking horribly when
<c>libfoo-2.0</c> is introduced.
</p>

<p>
Depending on a virtual package entry like <c>virtual/foo</c> will only work
when the different packages providing <c>virtual/foo</c> have identical
interfaces.  Consider <c>virtual/jdk-1.3</c> for example. Some packages don't
work with <c>ibm-jdk-1.3</c> while they do work with <c>sun-jdk-1.3</c>. For
this reason, be sure that your package is tested against all virtual providers
before unmasking.  It may be possible to only depend on a subset of those
packages in the virtual rather than the virtual itself.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Moving packages</title>
<section>
<title>Moving packages between categories</title>
<body>

<p>
From time to time, the Portage tree may need to be reorganized to split
overflowing categories into specific smaller categories. For example, if there are a 
large number of firewall-related packages in <c>net-misc</c>, splitting those into a 
smaller category would be a worthwhile reorganization, whereas breaking up 
<c>dev-perl</c> would be unlikely to make sense.
</p>

<p>
This kind of decision is not something that should be made by a single developer. It 
should first be discussed on the internal mailing list so we can share ideas on 
potentially superior solutions.
</p>

<p>
Formerly, packages were moved by adding a <c>PROVIDE</c> line to the new ebuild that 
would cause the package to satisfy the <c>DEPEND</c> settings of ebuilds that are 
unaware of the package's new location. The new and correct way to move packages is to 
add an entry to the appropriate files in <path>profiles/updates/</path> in the Portage 
tree. The format is as follows:
<pre>
move net-misc/fwbuilder net-firewall/fwbuilder
</pre>
In this case, we are moving the package <c>fwbuilder</c> from the category 
<c>net-misc</c> to <c>net-firewall</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
