<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
	
<guide link="doc/en/prelink-howto.xml">

<title>Gentoo Linux Prelink Guide</title>

<author title="Author"><mail link="cretin@gentoo.org">Stefan Jones</mail></author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">John P. Davis</mail></author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="peesh@gentoo.org">Jorge Paulo</mail></author>

<author title="Editor">
    <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
	This guide informs on how to make use of prelink support in portage
	2.0.46 and later.
</abstract>

<version>1.4</version>
<date>September 7, 2003</date>

<license/>

<chapter>
	<title>Introduction</title>
	<section>
		<title>What is Prelink and how can it help me?</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Most common applications make use of shared libraries.  These shared libraries
		need to be loaded into memory at runtime and the various symbol references need
		to be resolved.  For most small programs this dynamic linking is very quick.  But
		for programs written in C++ and that have many library dependencies, the dynamic
		linking can take a fair amount of time.
		</p>
		<p>
		On most systems, libraries are not changed very often and when a program is
		run, the operations taken to link the program are the same every time.  Prelink takes
		advantage of this by carrying out the linking and storing it in the executable, in
		effect prelinking it.  In order for the linker, you need ld-linux.so in glibc; to recognize
		the prelinking you need &gt;=glibc-2.3.1-r2.
		</p>
		<p>
		Prelinking can cut the startup times of applications.  For example, a typical KDE
		program's loading time can be cut by as much as 50%.  The only maintenance required
		is re-running prelink every time a library is upgraded for a pre-linked executable.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
		<body>
		<ul>
			<li>
			Prelinking is done via a program called, surprisingly, <path>prelink</path>.  It
			changes the binary to make it start faster.
			</li>
			<li>
			If an application's dependent libraries change after you have prelinked it, you need
			to re-prelink the application, otherwise you loose the speed advantage.  This is 
			to say, everytime you update a package via portage that updates libraries, they 
			need to be re-prelinked.
			</li>
			<li>
			The change to the binary is fully reversible.  <path>prelink</path> has an undo
			function.
			</li>
			<li>
			Newer versions of Portage can handle, via <path>prelink</path>, the changing
			MD5sums and mtimes of the binaries.
			</li>
			<li>
			You need to have glibc-2.3.1-r2 or greater installed with the binaries compiled
			with binutils-2.13.90.0.xx or greater.
			</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Setting up Prelink</title>
	<section>
		<title>Installing the Programs</title>
		<body>
		<note>
		I assume you have a Gentoo-1.4 system and it was built with gcc-3.2 or
		better and binutils-2.13.90.0.xx or better.  This needs to be so in order for your 
		binaries to be prelinkable.
		</note>
		<warn>
		You must have glibc-2.3.1-r2 or newer installed otherwise <path>prelink</path> will zap 
		all your binaries!
		</warn>

		<p>
		First update your portage tree, as many of the needed applications are new
		and bug-fixes are constantly added.
		</p>

<pre caption = "Updating your Portage Tree">
# <c>emerge sync</c>
</pre>

		<p>
		Next make sure you have portage-2.0.46 or better installed.  This is needed so
		that portage can recognize the prelinked binaries and thus uninstall them
		correctly when requested.  This is because prelinking changes the MD5sum of a
		binary.
		</p>

<pre caption = "Checking Portage Version">
# <c>emerge ">=portage-2.0.46"</c>
</pre>

		<p>
		Now you can emerge the prelinking tool.  The emerge process automatically
		verifies that your system can prelink safely.
		</p>

<pre caption = "Installing Prelink">
# <c>emerge prelink</c>
</pre>

		<p>
		A number of people get errors in emerging prelink because of the failed
		tests.  The tests were put in for safety reasons, prelink's behavior is undefined
		if you disable them.  The emerge errors are usually only dependent on the core
		packages; binutils, gcc, and glibc.  Try re-emerging those packages in that
		order.
		</p>
		<note>
		Tip: If you get an error try compiling and testing <c>prelink</c> yourself 
		(<c>./configure</c> ; <c>make</c> ; <c>make check</c> ).  On a failure you can 
		view the *.log files in the testsuite directory.  They may provide you with some 
		useful clues.
		</note>

		<p>
		If you have a set of steps that reproduces the emerge error on another system 
		please e-mail them to <mail link="cretin@gentoo.org">Stefan Jones</mail>.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Configuration</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Portage automatically generates the file <path>/etc/prelink.conf</path>
		that tells <path>prelink</path> which files to prelink.
		</p>
		<p>
		Unfortunately you cannot prelink files that were compiled by old versions 
		of binutils.  Most of these applications come from pre-compiled, binary 
		only packages which are installed in <path>/opt</path>.  Making the 
		following file will tell prelink not to attempt to prelink them.
		</p>
<pre caption="/etc/env.d/99prelink">
PRELINK_PATH_MASK="/opt"
</pre>
		<note>
		You can add more or less directories to the colon separated list.
		</note>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Prelinking</title>
	<section>
		<title>Prelink Usage</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		I use the following command to prelink all the binaries in the directories
		given by <path>/etc/prelink.conf</path>.
		</p>
<pre caption = "Prelinking listed files">
# <c>prelink -afmR</c>
</pre>

		<warn>
		It has been observed that if you are low on disk space and you prelink your
		entire system then there is a possibility that your binaries may be truncated.  
		The result being a b0rked system.  Use the <c>file</c> or <c>readelf</c> command to check
		the state of a binary file.  Alternatively, check the amount of free space on 
                your harddrive ahead of time with <c>df -h</c>.
		</warn>

		<table>
		<tr>
			<th>The options explained:</th>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<th>-a</th>
			<ti>"All": prelinks all the binaries</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<th>-f</th>
			<ti>
			Force <path>prelink</path> to re-prelink already
			prelinked binaries.  This is needed as <path>prelink</path> 
			aborts if old prelinked files are present and their library 
			dependencies have changed.
			</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<th>-m</th>
			<ti>
			Conserve the virtual memory space.  This is needed if you 
			have a lot of libraries that need to be prelinked.
			</ti>
		</tr>
		<tr>
			<th>-R</th>
			<ti>
			Random -- randomize the address ordering, this enhances 
			security against buffer overflows.
			</ti>
		</tr>
		</table>
		<note>
		For more options and details see <c>man prelink</c>.
		</note>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Known Problems and Fixes</title>
	<section>
		<title>&quot;Cannot prelink against non-PIC shared library&quot;</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The cause of this problem is from badly compiled shared libraries that were
		compiled without the -fPIC gcc option for all their object files.
		</p>
		<p>
		The following is a list of the problem libraries and which packages to
		re-emerge if you have the above error.
		</p>

<pre caption = "Fixes">
<codenote>For the ORBit library /usr/lib/libIIOP.so.0.5.17</codenote>
# <c>emerge ">=sys-apps/tcp-wrappers-7.6-r4" ORBit</c>

<codenote>For zlib library usr/lib/libz.so.1.1.4</codenote>
# <c>emerge ">=sys-libs/zlib-1.1.4"</c>

<codenote>For svgalib, /usr/lib/libsvga.so.xx</codenote>
# <c>emerge ">=media-libs/svgalib-1.9.16"</c>

<codenote>For the XFree openGL library, libGLU.so.1</codenote>
# <c>emerge ">=x11-base/xfree-4.2.1-r2"</c>

<codenote>For libpcap.so.0.6</codenote>
# <c>emerge ">=net-libs/libpcap-0.7.1-r2"</c>

<codenote>For the lcms library, /usr/lib/liblcms.so.1</codenote>
# <c>emerge ">=media-libs/lcms-1.09"</c>
</pre>
		<note>
		Many libraries link statically to zlib and/or tcp-wrappers so first try
		emerging those and re-emerging the problem library.
		</note>

		<p>
		If you are having trouble with prelinking QT/KDE, then first try upgrading to
		>=x11-base/xfree-4.2.1-r2 and >=x11-libs/qt-3.1.0-r1.  If QT still fails then try
		compiling QT without xinerama support by adding myconf="-no-xinerama ${myconf}"
		in the qt ebuild.
		</p>

		<p>
		Here are the libraries that haven't been fixed or cannot
		be fixed:
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>
			The libraries in the wine package, including winex.  Prelinking
			wouldn't speed up MS Windows executables anyway.
			</li>
			<li>
			The library in media-video/mjpegtools, 
			<path>/usr/lib/liblavfile-1.6.so.0</path>.
			</li>
		</ul>

		<p>
		If your problem library was not listed please report it with, preferably, a
		patch to add <i>-fPIC</i> to the relevant CFLAGS.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Abort while prelinking a file, like &quot;1631 Aborted ....&quot;</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		You need to use the <i>-f</i> option for <path>prelink</path>;
		i.e., reprelink the entire system from scratch.  Try <c>prelink -af</c>.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>&quot;&lt;file&gt;: error while loading shared libraries: unexpected reloc type...&quot;</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		This has been fixed in <i>sys-libs/glibc-2.3.1-r2</i> on 2002/11/18, re-emerge 
		glibc if yours is older.
		</p>
		<p>
		Also doing <c>prelink -u -a -m</c> ; <c>prelink -a -m</c> has been known
		to help.  If all else fails just do <c>prelink -u &lt;file&gt;</c>.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>I have problems with Nvidia openGL libraries</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		The accelerated openGL libraries that come in the nvidia-glx package have
		been compiled in a non-standard way and so <path>prelink</path> will throw
		warnings.  This is nothing to worry about and cannot be fixed by anyone except
		nvidia.  You can always revert to the xfree version of libGL.so if you don't need 3D
		acceleration.  The nvidia xfree driver works fine though.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>When I prelink my system some static binaries don't work anymore</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		Where glibc is concerned, there is no such thing as a 100% static binary.  If
		you statically compile a binary with glibc, it may still depend on other system
		files.  Below is an explanation by Dick Howell,
		</p>
		<p>&quot;I suppose the idea is that everything will be in the downloaded file, 
		so nothing depends on the local libraries on the target system.  Unfortunately with 
		Linux, and I think anything else using GLIBC, this still isn't quite true.  There's this 
		"libnss" (name service switch, some people seem to call it network security system) 
		which provides functions for accessing various databases for authentication, network
		information, and other things.  It's supposed to make application programs
		independent of the separately configured actual network environment of the
		machine.  A nice idea, but changes to GLIBC can lead to problems loading it.  And
		you can't statically link "libnss", since it is configured for each machine
		individually.  The problem comes, I think, mainly from statically linking other
		GLIBC libraries, notably "libpthread", "libm", and "libc", from which come
		incompatible calls to "libnss" functions.&quot;
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Prelink aborts with &quot;prelink: dso.c:306: fdopen_dso: Assertion `j == k' failed.&quot;</title>
		<body>
		<p>
		This a known problem, kindly diagnosed <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=13878">here</uri>.  
		Prelink cannot cope with UPX-compressed executables.  As of prelink-20021213 there is no 
		fix except to hide the executables while you are prelinking.  See the <uri link="#doc_chap2_sect2">Configuration section</uri> 
		above for an easy way to do this.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
    
    <section>
        <title>I use grsecurity and it seems that prelinking doesn't
        work.</title>
        <body>
        <p>
        In order to prelink on a system with grsecurity using a
        randomized mmap() base, it is necessary to turn "randomized mmap() 
        base" OFF for <path>/lib/ld-2.3.*.so</path>. This can be done with 
        the <c>chpax</c> utility, but it must be done when the file is not 
        in use (f.i. boot from a rescue CD).
        </p>
        </body>
    </section>    
    
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Conclusion</title>
	<section>
		<body>
		<p>
		Prelinking can drastically speed up the start up times for a number of
		large applications.  Support is built into Portage.  Prelinking is also safe as
		you can always undo the prelinking for any binary if you come across any
		problems.  Just remember that when you update glibc or other libraries that you 
		prelinked with, you need to rerun <path>prelink</path>!  In short good luck!
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
