<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<guide link="/doc/en/use-howto.xml">
<title>Gentoo Guide to USE flags</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">
	Seemant Kulleen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="meekrob@gentoo.org">
	Sherman Boyd</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="zhen@gentoo.org">
	John Davis</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor"><mail link="stocke2@gentoo.org">
	Eric Stockbridge</mail>
</author>

<abstract>This guide introduces you to the ultimate tool for
customizing Gentoo -- USE settings.   Not only is there a description of
each USE flag in current use, there is also a helpful guide to help you to
determine which USE flags you will need to use.</abstract>

<version>1.2</version>
<date>16 January 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>What is the use of <c>USE</c> flags anyway?</title>
<body>
<p>One of the things which attracted me, as a user, to Gentoo was the fact
that it is a highly customisable distribution.  The fact that it is a source
based distribution allows the user complete control over what kinds of
features and support are built in to the installed applications.  Moreover,
the idea of bloat reduction appealed to me -- I like not having to install
things which I do not <e>really</e> need.</p>

<p>And how, exactly, does Gentoo achieve this?  By defining <c>USE</c> settings.
Essentially, these are keywords that define options used on a system-wide
basis to configure applications during their respective compilation
procedures.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Default <c>USE</c> flags</title>
<body>
<p>Of course, Gentoo defines a set of safe default flags for you.  You will
find these in your <path>/etc/make.profile/make.defaults</path> file.</p>


<p>From the Gentoo-1.4_rc2 release, the <c>USE</c> settings are:</p>

<pre>USE="xv slang readline gpm berkdb mmx 3dnow gdbm tcpd pam libwww ssl nls
     arts perl python esd gif imlib sdl oggvorbis gnome gtk X qt
     kde motif opengl avi png tiff gif"</pre>


<warn>Instead of writing to this file, as I can see many of you scrambling to do,
it is advisable procedure to edit your <path>/etc/make.conf</path> file

In that file, you will see:</warn>

	<pre>#USE=""</pre>
<p> You would uncomment it by removing the # and adding your own custom USE
flags to that string between the quotes.</p>

<impo>Remember that <c>-flag</c> disables a flag and <c>flag</c> adds a flag.  If a flag is neither in <path>/etc/make.profile/make.defaults</path> nor in <path>/etc/make.conf</path> then its functionality is disabled.</impo>

<p>Simply uncomment that, and add whatever other flags you want to add.
"But what if I want to remove things from the make.defaults file?" I hear
you ask.  That is simply done by putting "-flag" in your
<path>/etc/make.conf</path>
file.  Mine, for example, looks like this:</p>

<pre>USE="-gnome -kde qt -arts -nls python perl oggvorbis opengl sdl
     -postgres jpeg png truetype xml xml2 dvd avi aalib mpeg encode fbcon
     mmx"</pre>

<p>Now that you know how to enable extra flags, and disable existing flags,
let us examine what these flags actually do.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Available <c>USE</c> flags</title>

<section>
<title>Where to find USE Flags</title>
<body>

<note>If you want to add a use flag, add it to <path>use.desc</path> and upload it to CVS.
<path>use.desc</path> is what this list is generated from. </note>

<p>You can find an automagically updated database of USE flags here: </p>
<p><uri link="/dyn/use-index.xml">USE Flags</uri> </p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Feedback</title>
<body>
<p>
For any feedback regarding the USE flags, please fill out a bug report at <uri>http://bugs.gentoo.org</uri> and assign it to seemant@gentoo.org</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
