<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/qa/proxy-maintainers/index.xml,v 1.22 2015/01/22 00:31:20 idella4 Exp $: -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<!-- <project link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/index.xml"> -->

<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Proxy_Maintainers">
<name>Proxy Maintainers</name>
<longname>Gentoo Proxy Maintaining Team</longname>

<date>2013-08-16</date>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="hwoarang@gentoo.org">Markos Chandras</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="pinkbyte@gentoo.org">Sergey Popov</mail>
</author>

<description>
Proxy maintainers is a group of developers maintaining abandoned packages on behalf of Gentoo users.
</description>

<longdescription>

<p>Gentoo currently has quite a few packages that lack a maintainer. To prevent treecleaners from removing those packages,
a maintainer has to be found as soon as possible. The overall goal of this project is to act as a primary contact point
between developers and users who want to maintain abandoned packages. Users are more than welcome to contact us and express
their interest in maintaining a package assigned to 'maintainer-needed@gentoo.org'.
</p>

</longdescription>

<goals>

<p>
To enhance the user-developer cooperation in maintaining packages.
</p>

</goals>

<dev role="Lead">pinkbyte</dev>
<dev>hwoarang</dev>
<dev>maksbotan</dev>
<dev>titanofold</dev>
<dev>qnikst</dev>
<dev>yngwin</dev>
<dev>xmw</dev>
<dev>mrueg</dev>
<dev>tomwij</dev>
<dev>idella4</dev>

<herd name="proxy-maintainers" />

<extrachapter>
<title>Contact</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Proxy Maintainer project is available at <mail>proxy-maint@gentoo.org</mail>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>How do I know which packages are orphaned?</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/index.xml">Treecleaners</uri> maintain an up-to-date list of <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/maintainer-needed.xml">orphaned packages</uri>. Choose your favorite package and contact us to express your interest.
</p>
<note>
Please note that packages which have been abandoned by their upstream maintainers do not qualify as orphaned packages. We don't want to maintain dead packages and they will be removed in the near future.
</note>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>What it takes to be a Proxied Maintainer</title>
<section>
<title>Enthusiasm</title>
<body>
<p>
Proxied Maintainers should be interested in the packages that they are maintaining.
By becoming a Proxied Maintainer you are essentially the person in charge of that package
in Gentoo.  When users have questions regarding a package and how it works in Gentoo, you
and will be the person that those questions are directed towards.  We would
like you to enjoy the maintaince and not feel as though it is a chore.  To that end we are
looking for enthusiastic people.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Teamwork</title>
<body>
<p>
Your work will be reviewed by your a member of the team for violations of Gentoo QA policy;
much of the policy is based more on common sense and less on specific rules.  If your work
does not meet QA your, one of us will notify you of where this occurs and will help you fix
the problems to ensure that you work meets guidelines and can be included in the Gentoo
package repository.  Please do not take offense to these suggestions; all criticism should
be intended as constructive criticism.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Interest</title>
<body>
<p>
Similarly in the vein above, don't Proxy-Maintain a package you know very little about
unless you are dead sure you can get up to speed on it.  For many packages this is not a
big problem (many are quite small).  However for larger applications and/or libraries it
is important to have prior knowledge about the package in question.  Bugs about the package
will be directed toward you (and also your Commiter).  However as Proxied-Maintainer you are
responsible for responding to the bugs with patches/comments/etc.  Be prepared to do this.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Patience</title>
<body>
<p>
Due to the increased number of packages this team maintains, we may forget or be slow in
committing your fixes. Please be patient with us; however, don't be afraid to prod every
once in a while on the status of your patches or ebuilds if we are not responsive.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>QA/Required knowledge and tools</title>
<body>
<p>We understand that you may have limited experience with Gentoo ebuilds. Therefore, you should have a brief look on the <uri link="http://devmanual.gentoo.org">devmanual</uri> and the <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~zmedico/portage/doc/man/repoman.1.html">required tools</uri> in order to make sure your ebuild meets our QA standards.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Help for Developers who act as proxy maintainers</title>
<section>
<title>Bugs assigned to maintainer-needed@gentoo.org</title>
<body>
<p>Developers who participate in this project should encourage users to participate in this project when they notice a open bug for an orphaned package. <uri link="default-comment.txt">This</uri> template (or a similar one) can be used to inform users about this project.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
