<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
  <name>Gentoo MIPS</name>

  <description>
	The Gentoo/MIPS Project provides the Gentoo GNU/Linux operating 
	system for mips-based platforms.
  </description>

  <longdescription>
	Gentoo/MIPS is a port of the Gentoo GNU/Linux and the Gentoo 
	Portage package management system to mips-based platforms.  Primary 
	focus is on the Silicon Graphics (SGI) line of mips-based workstations, 
	specifically the Indy and Indigo2.  Support is also available for the
	Cobalt Mincroserver Qube2/RaQ2 units and the SGI O2 R5000 units.
  </longdescription>


  <dev role="Port Founder" description="Gentoo/MIPS">tuxus</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="Porting">peitolm</dev>
  <dev role="Strategic Manager" description="Gentoo/MIPS">kumba</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="Porting">wesolows</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="SGI O2/Origin">iluxa</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="Vim, Fluxbox, Porting">ciaranm</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="X/KDE">psi29a</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="X/GNOME">geoman</dev>
  <dev role="member" description="SGI Octane/Origin">hardave</dev>


  <extrachapter position="top">
    <title>News</title>

    <section>
      <title>(21 Jul 2004): Site Updates</title>
      <body>
        <p>It's been awhile since the last update to the site, so people are likely wondering what all 
           has been going on recently.  For starters, we have a new developer to join the team, 
           Hardave Riar.  He joined a couple weeks ago to assist in various porting tasks, but will 
           also assist in Octane work as Linux support for the system becomes better.</p>

        <p>Newer stages for the 2004.2 release are available at the following locations:<br />
        <ul>
          <li>SGI: <uri>http://dev.gentoo.org/~kumba/mips/releases/2004.2/</uri></li>
          <li>Cobalt: <uri>http://dev.gentoo.org/~kumba/mips/cobalt/releases/2004.2/</uri></li>
        </ul></p>

        <p>The official release date for 2004.2 was missed, so the stages are only on the above site 
           for now.  2004.3 should be our next official release.</p>

        <p>&#160;</p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>(07 Mar 2004): New MIPS Developer (again!)</title>
      <body>
        <p>We have yet another new developer to join the MIPS ranks!  Stephen Becker, a.k.a. geoman, will 
	also work on Xfree86/Desktop related stuff, with Bret (psi29a).</p>

        <p>&#160;</p>
      </body>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>(04 Mar 2004): New MIPS Developer</title>
      <body>
        <p>We have a new developer to join the MIPS ranks.  Please give a warm welcome to Bret Curtis, 
	a.k.a., psi29a.  Bret will be handling stuff in the Xfree86 and Desktop related sections, like KDE, 
	Gaim, X-Chat and such.  As an example of what Xfree86 and KDE 3.x looks like on an Indy desktop, 
	take a look at the three screenshots below:</p>

        <p><uri link="http://www.mindwerks.net/~psi/indy/screenshot.jpeg">Screenshot 1</uri><br />
           <uri link="http://www.mindwerks.net/~psi/indy/screenshot2.jpeg">Screenshot 2</uri><br />
           <uri link="http://www.mindwerks.net/~psi/indy/screenshot3.jpeg">Screenshot 3</uri>
        </p>
        <p>&#160;</p>
      </body>
    </section>

  </extrachapter>


  <extraproject name="Documentation" lead="kumba">
	<p>Maintaining and updating documentation for Gentoo/MIPS.</p>
  </extraproject>

  <extraproject name="Stages/Netboot" lead="kumba">
	<p>Creation of the Gentoo/MIPS stages for installation.  A stage tarball is
	a UNIX compressed tar archive of a chrootable environment for installing
	Gentoo.</p>

	<p>Netboot images are for the initial booting of an environment to unpack
	the stages and install Gentoo.</p>
  </extraproject>

  <extraproject name="SGI O2 Porting" lead="iluxa">
	<p>The stabilization of the linux kernel on SGI O2 systems and sucessful
	installation and running of Gentoo/MIPS in a multi-user environment.  If 
	you have an SGI O2 with an R5000 or R12000 CPU and wish to help with this
	subproject, then this is the team you will want to contact.</p>
  </extraproject>

  <extraproject name="Cobalt Mips" lead="kumba">
	<p>Creation of installation stages and documentation for installing Gentoo/MIPS 
	on the Cobalt Microserver RaQ[2]/Qube[2] machines.</p>
  </extraproject>

  <extraproject name="LiveCD" lead="kumba">
	<p>The creation and maintainence of a LiveCD for installing
	Gentoo/MIPS.</p>
  </extraproject>


  <extrachapter position="bottom">
    <title>Installation Guide, Mailing Lists, and IRC Channel</title>
    <section>
      <body>
	<p>Those interested in running Gentoo/MIPS on an SGI mips-based system 
	can get started by reading the 
	<uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~kumba/mips/docs/gentoo-mips-install.html">
	Installation Guide</uri>.  Help can be obtained by subscribing to the 
	<i>gentoo-mips</i> mailing list.  More information about subscribing to a 
	Gentoo mailing list can be found on the 
	<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml">Mailing Lists</uri> page.</p>

	<p>Those with access to an IRC Client can join <i>#gentoo-mips</i> on 
	<i>irc.freenode.net</i> for general questions, help, or just to talk with 
	others using Gentoo/MIPS.</p>

      </body>
    </section>
  </extrachapter>

  <task lead="kumba">
    <name>Cobalt Mips Support</name>
    <description>Creation of installable stages, documentation, and netboots for Coablt systems</description>
    <startdate>Late 2003</startdate>

    <milestone finished="yes">
      <enddate>2003-09-01</enddate>
      <description>
	Installation of a Gentoo system overtop of a Debian install.
      </description>
    </milestone>

    <milestone finished="yes">
      <enddate>2004-01-31</enddate>
      <description>
	Creation of installable stages for mipsel targets for Cobalt systems.
      </description>
    </milestone>

    <milestone finished="yes">
      <enddate>?</enddate>
      <description>
	Creation of netboots to allow the installation of Gentoo install stages via gentoo-supported medium.
      </description>
    </milestone>

    <milestone finished="no">
      <enddate>?</enddate>
      <description>
	Creation of installation documentation for Cobalt, and integration into existing Gentoo/MIPS install docs.
      </description>
    </milestone>
  </task>

  <herd name="mips"/>

</project>
