<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/index.xml,v 1.97 2013/10/12 11:19:58 hwoarang Exp $ -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>undertakers</name>
<longname>Gentoo Developer Relations Undertakers</longname>

<date>2013-10-11</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="kloeri@gentoo.org">Bryan Østergaard</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="rane"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="hwoarang"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="pacho"/>
</author>

<description>
The Developer Relations Undertakers project handles developer retirement, both
when developers announce their retirement as well as due to developer
inactivity.
</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
The Developer Relations Undertakers project handles developer retirement, both
when developers announce their retirement as well as due to developer
inactivity.
</p>

</longdescription>

<dev role="lead">hwoarang</dev>
<dev role="member">pacho</dev>
<dev role="member">phajdan.jr</dev>
<dev role="member">djc</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Steps to retire a developer</title>
<section>
<body>

<ol>
  <li>Check CVS and bugzilla activity:
  <ul>
    <li>
      You can use the <c>history</c> subcommand of <c>cvs</c>,
      which will display you the activity of the developer in question across
      all CVS repositories. Use it like this: <c>cvs history -c -u dev | sed
      's/^.\{2\}//g' | sort | less</c>
    </li>
    <li>
      Additionally we have the CVS slacker report mails from flycatcher (aka
      cvs.gentoo.org) to <c>retirement@gentoo.org</c> the 1st of every month
    </li>
    <li>
      Check <uri
      link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/custom_userhistory.cgi?matchstr=DEVELOPER@gentoo.org">http://bugs.gentoo.org/custom_userhistory.cgi?matchstr=DEVELOPER@gentoo.org</uri>
      to see the last few bugzilla activities. Activity is defined very broadly
      in this case so commenting, changing resolution, CC'ing etc. all count as
      activity. You need to look at each of those bugs to decide if the activity
      is related to development.
    </li>
	<li>Alternatively, you can use <uri link="scripts/retstats.py.txt">this</uri> script(deprecated) to view the cia.vc and bugzilla activity for a specific developer.</li>
  </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    Try talking to the project lead(s), if the developer looks inactive. He
    might be active in ways we can't determine easily. Put in some effort to
    contact the developer (either IRC or via email) before starting the actual
    retirement process. When sending an email to the developer in question, make
    sure you tell him, that he might get retired due to being inactive. Also,
    whenever sending emails in undertakers business, CC
    <c>retirement@gentoo.org</c>.
  </li>
  <li>
  	If the developer is inactive for more than two months, send him the 
	<uri link="/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/first-mail.txt">first mail</uri>
	asking him to consider removing himself from packages that he is not interested
	to maintain anymore. Those packages should be announced as unmaintained to the
	<c>gentoo-dev</c> mailing list and re-assigned to maintainer-needed@gentoo.org
	until another developer or proxy-maintainer steps up and take care of them.
  </li>
  <li>
	Then search for the New Developer bug, if the developer predates recruitment bugs
	(there was no recruitment bug), open a new bug. Change <c>Summary</c> to 
	<e>Packages reassignment: Full Name (nickname)</e>. Reassign the bug to
	<c>retirement@gentoo.org</c>(Retirement Admin) and change <c>Status Whiteboard</c>
	to <e>first-mail-sent: yy-mm-dd</e>. Make sure the developer is <b>CC'ed</b> on 
	the bug. Once situation is clarified, close the bug as FIXED.
  </li>	                            
  <li>
    After four months from the first e-mail, if you still believe the developer is inactive,
	reopen the Packages reassignment bug. Change <c>Summary</c> to 
	<e>Retire: Full Name (nickname)</e> and change <c>Status Whiteboard</c> to 
	<e>second-mail-sent: yy-mm-dd</e>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Send him the <uri
    link="/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/second-mail.txt">second mail</uri> and
    wait a minimum of one month, to give the developer adequate time to respond
    on the bug or to the mail. If you get no response during that period, send
    the <uri link="/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/third-mail.txt">third mail</uri>.
    Don't forget to change Status Whiteboard to <e>third-mail-sent</e> and to 
    update the date there. Remember that <c>retirement@gentoo.org</c> must be CC'ed
    ALL mails and ALL responses must be forwarded there.
  </li>
  <li>
    Consider any responses carefully. We're supposed to help Gentoo (in this
    case by keeping the developer base "clean"), not to retire as many
    developers as possible.
  </li>
  <li>Close the bug if the developer is still considered active</li>
  <li>
    If the developer doesn't respond within six months or is otherwise still
    considered inactive, state that on the bug and ask Infra to start <uri
    link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/retire-process.xml">retirement
    process</uri>). Also make sure you change the <c>Status Whiteboard</c> to
    <c>infra-retire yyyy-mm-dd</c>.
  </li>
  <li>
    Retirement procedure looks like this:
  <ul>
    <li>
      Clean up the tree and herds from the yet-retired developer. Use the
      <c>retire.py</c> script (which is available in <uri
      link="http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/scripts/">gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/scripts/</uri>)
      for that purpose, but make sure to review its output <b>before</b>
      committing!
    </li>
    <li>
      Clean up any <c>metadata.xml</c> the developer in question might be
      mentioned in. This is accomplished by running <c>retire.py --metadata-dev devname
      /path/to/gentoo-x86</c>. Review the output, and apply it to current CVS,
      but make sure you <c>cvs up</c> <b>before</b> applying it.
    </li>
    <li>
      Clean up <c>herds.xml</c> in <path>proj/en/metastructure/herds/</path>.
      Remove the developer in question from any herds he might be listed in. To
      find those, you might want to run this: <c>retire.py --herds
      /path/to/userinfo.xml /path/to/herds.xml</c>. That will show you the
      developers listed as <b>retired</b> in <c>userinfo.xml</c> which are still
      listed in <c>herds.xml</c>.
    </li>
	<li>
      Clean up any project pages the developer may be listed in. Just make sure
      you don't erase them completely (for example
      <path>userrel/archives/soc/</path> is fine). Use <c>retire.py --project
      /path/to/userinfo.xml /path/to/xml/proj/en/</c> to find any stale
      entries.
    </li>
	<li>
      Search for all NEW and REOPEN bugs assigned to the retired developer on
      Gentoo Bugzilla and reassign them to herds or projects the package
      belongs to. Information to whom reassign can be obtained from
      <path>metadata.xml</path> file of that package.
    </li>
	<li>
      Wait for Infrastructure, Planet and Forums admins to retire developer in
      question before proceeding further.
    </li>
	<li>
	  If he has an account on wiki.gentoo.org, add a comment (if there is not one already) with his nickname and CC <c>wiki@gentoo.org</c>.
	</li>
    <li>
      Check group membership on cvs.gentoo.org to ensure retired devs are
      dropped from all groups by running the <c>search-retired-devs.sh</c>
      script.
    </li>
    <li>
      Remove access to <c>#gentoo-dev</c> (access is either removed completely
      or changed to voice depending on whether they ask for it or they're still
      considered active and helpful in the channel). Ask a freenode staffer to
      reset the cloak to a non-gentoo one.
    </li>
  </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Close the bug once all of the above steps are finished!</li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Pending Retirements</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Click <uri link='https://bugs.gentoo.org/buglist.cgi?emailcc1=1&amp;list_id=2031844&amp;resolution=---&amp;emailtype1=substring&amp;query_format=advanced&amp;emailassigned_to1=1&amp;bug_status=UNCONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=CONFIRMED&amp;bug_status=IN_PROGRESS&amp;bug_status=RESOLVED&amp;bug_status=VERIFIED&amp;email1=retirement%40gentoo.org'>here</uri> to see all the pending retirements.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>
