<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>undertakers</name>
<longname>Gentoo Developer Relations Undertakers</longname>

<date>2008-01-17</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="kloeri@gentoo.org">Bryan Østergaard</mail>
</author>

<description>
The Developer Relations Undertakers project handles developer retirement, both
when developers announce their retirement as well as due to developer
inactivity.
</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
The Developer Relations Undertakers project handles developer retirement, both
when developers announce their retirement as well as due to developer
inactivity.
</p>

</longdescription>

<dev role="lead">phreak</dev>
<dev role="member">musikc</dev>
<dev role="member">rane</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Steps to retire a developer</title>
<section>
<body>

<ol>
  <li>Check CVS and bugzilla activity
  <ul>
    <li>An easy way to check CVS activity is by using the <c>history</c> 
    subcommand of <c>cvs</c>, which will display you the activity of the
	developer in question across all CVS repositories. Use it like this: 
    <c>cvs history -c -u dev | sort | less</c></li>

    <li>Additionally we have the CVS slacker report mails from stork to 
    <c>devrel@gentoo.org</c> the 1st of every month</li>
    <li>Check <uri link="http://bugday.gentoo.org/bugsgoactivity.php?id=dev">http://bugday.gentoo.org/bugsgoactivity.php?id=dev</uri>
    to see the last few bugzilla activities. Activity is defined very broadly
	in this case so commenting, changing resolution, CC'ing etc. all count as
	activity. You need to look at each of those bugs to decide if the activity
	is related to development.</li>
  </ul>
  </li>

  <li>Try talking to the project lead(s), if the developer looks inactive. He
  might be active in ways we can't determine easily. Put in some effort to
  contact the developer (either IRC or via email) before starting the actual
  retirement process. When sending an email to the developer in question, make
  sure you tell him, that he might get retired due to being inactive. Also,
  whenever sending emails in undertakers business, CC the alias when doing so.</li>

  <li>Reopen the New Developer bug. If the developer predates recruitment bugs
  (there was no recruitment bug), open a new bug for retirement purposes.  
  Retirement bugs should be in the <c>Developer Relations</c> product and
  assigned to <c>devrel@gentoo.org</c> with the developer <b>CC'ed</b>. State
  on the bug last commit and bugs activity if applicable. Also state any
  appropriate input you may have gotten from project lead(s).</li>

  <li>Make sure the developer is <b>CC'ed</b> on the bug.</li>

  <li>Wait a minimum of two weeks, to give the developer adequate time to
  respond on the bug. Often 3 or even 4 weeks are more appropriate.</li>

  <li>Consider any responses carefully. We're supposed to help Gentoo (in this
  case by keeping the developer base "clean"), not to retire as many developers
  as possible.</li>

  <li>Close the bug if the developer is still considered active.</li>

  <li>If the developer doesn't respond in the given time or is otherwise still
  considered inactive <b>CC</b> <c>infra-bugs@gentoo.org</c> on the bug and add
  a comment asking infrastructure to retire the developer (as per their 
  retirement <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/retire-process.xml">process</uri>).
  Also make sure you change the <c>Status Whiteboard</c> to 
  <c>infra-retire yyyy/mm/dd</c> (where <c>yyyy</c> is the current year,
  <c>mm</c> he current month and <c>dd</c> the current day).</li>

  <li>Remove access to #gentoo-dev (access is either removed completely or
  changed to voice depending on whether they ask for it or they're still
  considered active and helpful in the channel).</li>

  <li>Ask a freenode staffer to reset the cloak to a non-gentoo one.</li>

  <li>Update userinfo.xml with new status (ldap is done automatically by
  infrastructures script).</li>

  <li>Clean up the tree and herds from the yet-retired developer. Use the 
  <c>retire.py</c> script (which is available in <uri link="http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/scripts/">gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/scripts/</uri>) for that purpose, but make sure to review it's output
  <b>before</b> committing!
  <ol>

  <li>Clean up any <c>metadata.xml</c> the developer in question might be
  mentioned in. This is accomplished by running
  <c>retire.py --metadata dev /path/to/gentoo-x86</c>. Review the output, and
  apply it to current CVS, but make sure you <c>cvs up</c> <b>before</b>
  applying it.</li>

  <li>Clean up <c>herds.xml</c> in <path>proj/en/metastructure/herds/</path>.
  Remove the developer in question from any herds he might be listed in. To
  find those, you might want to run this:
  <c>retire.py --herds /path/to/userinfo.xml /path/to/herds.xml</c>. That will
  show you the developers listed as <b>retired</b> in <c>userinfo.xml</c> which
  are still listed in <c>herds.xml</c>.</li>

  <li>Clean up any project pages the developer may be listed in. Just make sure
  you don't erase them completely (for example <path>userrel/archives/soc/</path>
  is fine). Use 
  <c>retire.py --project /path/to/userinfo.xml /path/to/xml/proj/en/</c> to
  find any stale entries.</li>

  <li>Close the bug once all of the above steps are finished!</li>
  </ol>
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>
