<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings/summaries/2003/20031117.xml">
<title>Gentoo Managers' Meeting Summary</title>
<subtitle>17 Nov. 2003</subtitle>
<date>22 Nov. 2003</date>
<author title="Author">Brandon Hale</author>
<author title="Editor">Grant Goodyear</author>
<author title="Editor">Tal Peer</author>

<abstract>This meeting began at 1814 UTC, and the guest chair was tseng (Brandon Hale). The raw log is available <uri link="/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings/logs/2003/20031117.txt">here</uri>.</abstract>


<chapter>
<title>Catalyst</title>
<section><body><p>
Daniel Robbins (drobbins) covered the progress of Catalyst, a new system
for building stage tarballs and LiveCDs.  He explained that catalyst is
a rewrite of the original "stager" code (that was used to build the
stage-{1,2,3} tarballs) and Zhen's original catalyst code, with the goal
of providing a single program that can reliably and repeatably  build
stages, package sets, and livecds for all of our architectures.
Moreover, the catalyst code is modular, so extensions such as for a
currently-planned "tinderbox" plugin should be straightforward.  In the
future our users will be able to "emerge catalyst" and build entire
customized systems; until then interested users and developers can find
the current version of catalyst in
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/src/catalyst/?cvsroot=gentoo">CVS</uri>.
Besides describing the goals, drobbins also presented some practical
examples of how it works (see the log for more
details). The catalyst team is actively seeking bug reports for any
functionality that users or devs find lacking.    If all goes as
planned, Catalyst will be ready in the next few weeks, allowing devs and
users to reliably build customized stages and LiveCDs.
</p></body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Handbook Progress</title>
<section><body><p>
Sven Vermeulen (swift) announced that the installation segment of the
new Gentoo Handbook was ready for mass consumption. This new Gentoo
Handbook so far collects all of the information that traditionally has
been scattered throughout the plethora of architecture-specific
installation guides and assembles from them a unified, more coherent
document. The new handbook has now been added to the
docs page as the preferred installation guide, although the old
guides will
remain for a while longer for reference. Report any issues in the guide
to <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Bugzilla</uri>.
</p></body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>QA Status</title>
<section><body><p>
Wrapping up was a question from infrastructure lead Kurt Lieber
(klieber). He asked about current QA plans for Gentoo.  Although there
had been a previous plan to enact wholesale QA of the portage tree by
establishing a separate, peer-reviewed stable portage tree, that plan
had fallen by the wayside, and Kurt was curious what was currently being
done.  Seemant Kulleen (seemant) replied that the releng team is
currently handling initial QA essentially through development of
catalyst and related tools.  Meanwhile, Seemant has been gauging
interests both on #gentoo-qa and informally by talking to interested
developers, but nothing has been formalized just yet.  Pauldv noted that
the formation of ebuild herds and association of devs to shepherd them
is going quite well, so individual ebuild QA is progressing nicely.
</p></body></section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Open Floor</title>
<section><body><p>
The floor was opened to general developer questions at 1900UTC.  There
were a few more comments about QA and herds, and seemant reminded people
that whenever a new herd is added the dev doing so needs to contact
seemant, avenj, or cybersystem to get a mail alias established for the
herd.  Another issue that was raised was the idea of using catalyst for
cross-compiling.  Although there is certainly support for the idea,
cross-compiling within portage is difficult and at the moment there are
no clear solutions for how to do it cleanly.
</p>
<p>Meeting adjourned at 1910 UTC</p>
</body></section>
</chapter>
</guide>
