<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/lisp/emacs/xemacs.xml,v 1.2 2007/04/22 15:30:01 graaff Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/eselect/user-guide.xml">
<title>XEmacs on Gentoo</title>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="graaff@gentoo.org">Hans de Graaff</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document describes how XEmacs is made available in Gentoo and how
it differs from a vanilla XEmacs installation.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>2007-01-04</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>A Brief Overview</title>
<body>

<p> 
<uri link="http://xemacs.org/">XEmacs</uri> is a highly
customizable open source text editor and application development
system.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Differences for a Gentoo XEmacs installation</title>
<section>
<title>Overview</title>
<body>

<p>
Many elisp extensions for XEmacs are distributed as XEmacs
packages. Some of these packages are needed for proper operation of
XEmacs, such as the <c>app-xemacs/xemacs-base</c> package. Others are
XEmacs-specific packages of applications that are also otherwise
distributed. The packaged versions are known to work with XEmacs and
may contains XEmacs-specific enhancements. In a normal XEmacs
installation these packages can be installed using the package
manager. In Gentoo the packages are provided as ebuilds, making
updating and maintenance easier. You can find the list of all packages
in the <c>app-xemacs/*</c> category.
</p>

<p>
Gnome and GTK+ support in XEmacs currently only supports GTK 1.2
and GNOME 1.x. GNOME 1.x is no longer available through portage and
GTK 1.2 is deprecated and will be removed some time in the future. For
this reason there are no <c>gnome</c> and <c>gtk</c> USE flags for
XEmacs.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Future plans</title>
<section>
<title>Sumo packages</title>
<body>

<p> 
<uri link="http://www.xemacs.org/">XEmacs</uri> provides a large
number of packages with lisp code specifically made compatible with
XEmacs. These packages can be found in the <c>app-xemacs/*</c>
category in portage. In addition to distributing these packages as
individual archives, XEmacs also distributes two large archives with
all packages included, called the sumo packages. In portage both these
archives can be installed using the
<c>app-xemacs/xemacs-packages-sumo</c> ebuild.
</p>

<p>
This approach results in two ways to provide the same set of
packages and files. As <uri>https://bugs.gentoo.org/23949</uri>
mentions the sumo package and the other packages should really block
each other. A better solution would be to remove the sumo package
completely and instead create a meta package which would pull in all
the other packages as dependencies. This would have the same net
effect as the original sumo package of having a single package to
install all lisp code, but would avoid the problems with blocking and
overwriting files. Work is currently underway to provide such a
package. Until that time the sumo package will be updated as usual.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>XEmacs 21.5</title>
<body>

<p>
Upstream development is currently focused on XEmacs 21.5, but this
version is currently not yet stable enough for release or day-to-day
use. It is planned to add XEmacs 21.5 to Gentoo portage, but it will
be package.masked until upstream is ready to release beta-quality
versions. It is not yet clear when XEmacs 21.5 will be added to
portage, although some work has already been done.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Developer information</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The following information is only relevant to Gentoo developers or
other people who want to update or create ebuilds related to XEmacs.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Package to ebuild script</title>
<body>

<p>The app-xemacs/* ebuilds in portage are kept up-to-date with the
released set of packages using a python script called <uri
link="pebuild.gz">pebuild</uri> written by Mats Lidell.</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>



 
