<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/lisp/emacs/xemacs.xml,v 1.5 2012/10/28 15:21:09 swift Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>XEmacs on Gentoo</title>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="graaff@gentoo.org">Hans de Graaff</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document describes how XEmacs is made available in Gentoo and how
it differs from a vanilla XEmacs installation.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2008-05-10</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>A Brief Overview</title>
<body>

<p> 
<uri link="http://xemacs.org/">XEmacs</uri> is a highly
customizable open source text editor and application development
system.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Differences for a Gentoo XEmacs installation</title>
<section>
<title>Overview</title>
<body>

<p>
Many elisp extensions for XEmacs are distributed as XEmacs
packages. Some of these packages are needed for proper operation of
XEmacs, such as the <c>app-xemacs/xemacs-base</c> package. Others are
XEmacs-specific packages of applications that are also otherwise
distributed. The packaged versions are known to work with XEmacs and
may contains XEmacs-specific enhancements. In a normal XEmacs
installation these packages can be installed using the built-in XEmacs
package manager. In Gentoo the packages are provided as ebuilds,
making updating and maintenance easier. An added benefit is that the
<c>xemacs</c> USE flag can be used to pull in relevant XEmacs
packages. For example, when emerging <c>ruby</c> with the
<c>xemacs</c> USE flag you will also emerge the
<c>app-xemacs/ruby-modes</c> packages, enabling ruby support in
XEmacs. You can find the list of all packages in the
<c>app-xemacs/*</c> category.
</p>

<p>
You may find it cumbersome to install each XEmacs package
individually. The upstream solution to that is the distribution of the
SUMO archive, which contains all packages in a single archive. Gentoo
takes a different approach. You can emerge
<c>app-xemacs/xemacs-packages-all</c> to install all the XEmacs
packages that are also distributed in the SUMO archive. This installs
all the individual packages. Using the now-obsolete
<c>app-xemacs/xemacs-packages-sumo</c> is deprecated, and last rites
will be issued for it shortly. The reason for this particular approach
is described in <uri>https://bugs.gentoo.org/23949</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Gnome and GTK+ support in XEmacs currently only supports GTK 1.2
and GNOME 1.x. GNOME 1.x is no longer available through portage and
GTK 1.2 is deprecated and will be removed some time in the future. For
this reason there are no <c>gnome</c> and <c>gtk</c> USE flags for
XEmacs.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Future plans</title>

<section>
<title>XEmacs 21.5</title>
<body>

<p>
Upstream development is currently focused on XEmacs 21.5, but this
version is currently not yet stable enough for release or day-to-day
use. Unfortunately only the 21.5 versions provide proper support for
UTF-8, which is becoming more and more a requirement, so we expect to
add a 21.5 release to the main tree.</p>

<p>
Until that time experimental XEmacs 21.5 ebuilds are available from
the official xemacs overlay. You can add this overlay to your system
using layman.
</p>

<pre caption="Adding the XEmacs overlay">
# <i>layman -a xemacs</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Developer information</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The following information is only relevant to Gentoo developers or
other people who want to update or create ebuilds related to XEmacs.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Package to ebuild script</title>
<body>

<p>The app-xemacs/* ebuilds in portage are kept up-to-date with the
released set of packages using a python script called <uri
link="pebuild.gz">pebuild</uri> originally written by Mats Lidell.</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>



 
