<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/gentoo-alt/Attic/policy.xml,v 1.3 2005/10/09 23:31:14 flameeyes Exp $ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/gentoo-alt/policy.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo/ALT Policy</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="flameeyes@gentoo.org">Diego Pettenò</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
A list of policies and practices that should be followed by Gentoo/ALT
developers, to avoid problems and interferences inter-project.
</abstract>


<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2005-10-04</date>

<chapter> <!-- Intra-policy -->
<title>Intra-policy</title>

<section> <!-- Patches -->
<title>Patches</title>
<body>

<warn>
This text is still a draft, with probably big grammar problems. The policies
here stated needs to be completed and decided upon. While this warning is in
place, don't take anything here as an official policy!
</warn>

<p>
Patches added to the overlay should follow some basic polciies, thought to
simplify the process of merging them upstream, without breaking stuff. This
allows to drop the patches when new versions are released.
</p>

<p>
The first important step is to make sure that the patch applies
unconditionally, this means that after applying the patch, the sources works
fine on every system, and not just the one you're patching for. This means
that when adding code to workaround system problems, it should be protected
with the right checks (preprocessor or autoconf) so that they get ignored
when they are not needed.
</p>

<p>
Patches that changes entirely the building system of a package are usually
discouraged, try to find a mediation with upstream developers, also if that
would mean having an unusable package in the time being.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section> <!-- Behavior changes -->
<title>Behavior changes</title>
<body>

<p>
All the behavior changes that might affect Gentoo Linux users must always be
announced on gentoo-alt at least, and on gentoo-dev if they might affect
development practices.
</p>

<p>
The behavior changes should also be tested on the
<uri link="overlay.xml">gentoo-alt overlay</uri> so that it doesn't hit the
normal users before testing.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>

<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; -->
