<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>Gentoo Linux 1.4 x86 Maintenance Release 1</title>
<author title="Chief Architect">
    <mail link="drobbins@gentoo.org">Daniel Robbins</mail>
</author>

<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>16 Oct 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>This document contains information related to the Gentoo Linux 1.4 for x86 Maintenance Release 1,
which was built and released on 11 September, 2003. Gentoo Linux 1.4-MR1 is available from our various
<uri link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri> in the <path>releases/x86/1.4</path> directory. The
Maintenance Release 1 LiveCDs have build dates of 20030911.</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Linux 1.4 for x86 MR1 Errata</title>
<section>

<body>
<p>This section contains information related to known issues in Gentoo Linux 1.4 for x86 MR1.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Installation documentation</title>
<body>
<p>If you browse the contents of Disc 1 using an already-running
operating system, you will see <path>/install.html</path> and <path>/install.pdf</path> files in the
root directory of the CD-ROM. These files contain up-to-date installation instructions for this release.
The <path>install.pdf</path> documentation is readable in <b>Acrobat Reader</b> (<c>acroread</c> under
Linux) or <c>xpdf</c>. It is also in a compact form that is well-suited for printing before you begin
the installation process.</p>
<p><e>However, if you boot
Disc 1 (rather than browse its contents on an already-installed system,) these files can be found in
<path>/mnt/cdrom</path> and can be viewed by typing <c>links /mnt/cdrom/install.html</c>.</e></p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>libaspell.so.15 not found</title>
<body>
<p>If any application returns a <c>libaspell.so.15 not found</c> message, simply type <c>emerge -k aspell</c>
as root to correct this situation. This will allow programs such as <c>gaim</c> to work properly. This problem
was caused by a missing runtime dependency in the aspell eclass and is fixed in our "live" Portage tree.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>openoffice-bin does not start</title>
<body>
<p>The <c>openoffice-bin</c> package in 1.4 for x86 MR1 does not function properly. We are currently looking
into this issue and expect to have openoffice working properly for our next official release.</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Evolution won't start</title>
<body>
<p>If evolution won't start due to it not being able to find the Evolution shell, type in the following
command as root:</p>

<pre># <c>bonobo-activation-sysconf --add-directory /usr/lib/bonobo/servers</c>
</pre>

<p>Then exit and restart X, and Evolution should start normally.</p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
