<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
	<name>kernel</name>
	<longname>Gentoo Kernel Project</longname>
	<description>The Gentoo Kernel project has the goal of bringing a consistent 
kernel featureset across all architectures supported by Gentoo Linux</description>
	<longdescription>
<p>
More and more Gentoo users are emerging from unknown locations. They
want to have a good and stable experience with their favorite
distribution, Gentoo Linux. The kernel they use is an important part of
their experience. Because Gentoo Linux wants the best for it's users,
Gentoo Linux provides them with several possible kernel tree's, each
with their own expertise and features.
</p>
<p>
In order to provide a rich choice of high quality kerneltrees Gentoo
Linux must test and combine several kernelpatches before they can offer
finished ebuilds to the users. This is where the Gentoo Kernel
Project comes into play.
</p>
	</longdescription>
<goals><p>
The Gentoo Kernel Project tries to give the best possible 
kernel featuresets across all platforms. By having a clearly set 
management team with published objectives, established timelines, and 
project accountability, the project will help bring the end-user 
experience for our kernels to even higher levels.
</p></goals>
	<extraproject name="alpha-sources" lead="wwoods">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting alpha processors</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="arm-sources">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting arm processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="gentoo-sources" lead="pfeifer">
		Feature-rich, high-performance Gentoo Kernel for x86 processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="gs-sources" lead="livewire">
		Gentoo Kernel created for stability, supporting x86 processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="hppa-sources" lead="gmsoft">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting pa-risc processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="mips-sources" lead="kumba">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting MIPS processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="pfeifer-sources" lead="pfeifer">
		Developmental Gentoo Kernel which moves it's code base
		into gentoo-sources
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="ppc-sources" lead="kain">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting PPC processors, including
		ppc-sources-benh, ppc-sources-crypto, ppc-sources-dev
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="sparc-sources" lead="joker">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting SPARC processors
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="xfs-sources" lead="livewire">
		Gentoo Kernel supporting x86 processors and XFS
		filesystem. Used by the Gentoo LiveCD
	</extraproject>
	<extrachapter position="subproject">
	<title>Other Kernels (not patched by Gentoo)</title>
	<section>
	<body>
	<p>
	Gentoo provides ebuilds for other linux kernels such as vanilla-sources, ac-sources, ck-sources, etc,... While not official supported and provided as a courtesy to our user base, info on such kernels can be found <uri link="otherkernels.xml">here</uri>.
	</p>
	</body>
	</section>
	</extrachapter>
	<dev role="lead" description="head kernel guru">pfeifer</dev>
	<dev description="sparc-sources lead">joker</dev>	
	<dev description="gs-sources/xfs-sources lead">livewire</dev>	
	<dev description="mips-sources lead">kumba</dev>	
	<dev description="hppa-sources lead">gmsoft</dev>	
	<dev description="ppc-sources lead">kain</dev>	
	<dev description="alpha-sources lead">wwoods</dev>	
	<dev description="Documentation guru">swift</dev>	
	
<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Other info</title>
<section>
<title>Quality Objectives</title>
<body>
<p>
Each subproject must make sure that the kernel ebuilds they provide
adhere to the following quality demands:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Each kernel ebuild must compile and work on as many systems as
possible before committing to the Portage tree (even if
<path>package.mask</path> is used).</li>
<li>Each kernel ebuild should not have Gentoo-specific bugs on
<uri>http://bugs.gentoo.org/</uri> in the last 1-2 weeks after being
released before moving from <path>~ARCH</path> to <path>ARCH</path></li>
<li>Every kernel-tree released by the Gentoo Kernel Project must have a
clear description on what it contains (patches) and what philosophy is
behind it's existence</li>
<li>Any kernel feature that has a userspace utility, must have the appropriate userspace utility ready for inclusion in portage before the kernel is released (ie. evms2, freeswan, USAGI,...). The 2 should be released @ the same time.</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Timeline Objectives</title>
<body>

<p>
As kernels continue to develop in a vast pace, the Gentoo Kernel Project
must make sure that it keeps track of all kerneltrees it provides so
that our users will receive the latest and greatest kerneltrees in a
timely fashion without losing the quality they are accustomed to.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Accountability</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo Kernel Project cannot guarantee that the provided
kernel ebuilds work on your system, but it will bring a Best Effort to
help every user with problems concerning the kernel ebuilds.
</p>

<p>
Certain ebuilds are however not officially supported:
<c>development-sources</c> and <c>mm-sources</c> are both based on the
Linux 2.5 development tree and should be seen as unstable. These kernels
are not for the faint of heart, and are only provided for de Gentoo
users that know what they are getting into.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<extrachapter>
<title>Project Documentation</title>
<section>
<title>Roadmap</title>
<body>
<p>
As with most projects, the Gentoo Kernel Project and it's subprojects
use a roadmap to inform the users and developers about current
development items, near-future integrations, seeable future enhancements
and far future proposals.
</p>
<p>
You can view our roadmap <uri link="roadmap.xml">here</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Kernel Documentation</title>
<body>
<p>
In order for our users to be able to pick the best kernel ebuild we
provide them with a <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-kernel.xml">Kernel Guide</uri>
in which all available kernel ebuilds are listed and described.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Linux Enhancement Proposals</title>
<body>
<p>
The following GLEPs handle kernel-specific items and are therefor aimed
at the Gentoo Kernel Project:
</p>
<p>
No GLEPs so far.
</p>

<table>
 <tr>
  <th>GLEP</th>
  <th>Description</th>
  <th>Involved Developers</th>
  <th>Status</th>
 </tr>
 <tr>
  <ti><uri
  link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-XXXX.html">XX</uri></ti>
  <ti>Proposal to foo bar bleh bla bla.</ti>
  <ti>john doe, mike bike</ti>
  <ti>Working on it, Implemented, No Implementation Needed,
  Dismissed</ti>
 </tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<extrachapter>
<title>Mailing lists</title>
<section>
<title>gentoo-kernel@gentoo.org</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo Kernel Mailing List
</p>
<p>
Subscription information: Closed for now 
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>
