<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- $Header: -->
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<sections>

<date>2006-05-04</date>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
This section aims to explain the Gentoo development hierarchy and gives
developers an insight to how Gentoo Linux development management is
structured.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>A short history of Gentoo's management structure</title>
<body>

<p>
The first attempt to come up with a management structure to solve problems
with coordination and communication issues was made in 2003 with the
structure described in 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0004.xml">GLEP 4</uri>.
As Gentoo grew larger over the time, some problems with the management 
structure were discovered and a new one was needed to solve these issues.
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0039.html">GLEP 39</uri> 
describes both the reasons behind this as well as the outcome of the 
discussion.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Current Management structure according to GLEP 39</title>
<body>

<p>
A project is a group of developers working towards a goal (or a set of goals).
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    A project exists if it has a web page at <uri
    link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/">www.gentoo.org/proj/en/&lt;project
    name&gt;</uri> that is maintained. ("Maintained" means that the information
    on the page is factually correct and not out-of-date.) If the webpage isn't
    maintained, it is presumed dead.
  </li>
  <li>
    It may have one or many leads, and the leads are selected by the members of
    the project. This selection must occur at least once every 12 months and
    may occur at any time.
  </li>
  <li>
    It may have zero or more sub-projects. Sub-projects are just projects that
    provide some additional structure, and their web pages are in the project's
    space.
  </li>
  <li>Not everything (or everyone) needs a project.</li>
  <li>Projects need not be long-term.</li>
  <li>Projects may well conflict with other projects. That's okay.</li>
  <li>
    Any dev may create a new project just by creating a new page (or, more
    realistically, directory and page) in
    <path>gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en</path>.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Global issues will be decided by an elected Gentoo council.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    There will be a set number of council members. (For the first election that
    number was set to 7 by acclamation.)
  </li>
  <li>
    Council members will be chosen by a general election of all devs once per
    year.
  </li>
  <li>The council must hold an open meeting at least once per month.</li>
  <li>
    Council decisions are by majority vote of those who show up (or their
    proxies).
  </li>
  <li>
    If a council member (or their appointed proxy) fails to show up for two
    consecutive meetings, they are marked as a slacker.
  </li>
  <li>
    If a council member who has been marked a slacker misses any further
    meeting (or their appointed proxy doesn't show up), they lose their
    position and a new election is held to replace that person. The newly
    elected council member gets a 'reduced' term so that the yearly elections
    still elect a full group.
  </li>
  <li>
    Council members who have previously been booted for excessive slacking may
    stand for future elections, including the election for their replacement.
    They should, however, justify their slackerness and should expect to have
    it pointed out if they don't do so themselves.
  </li>
  <li>The 'slacker' marker is reset when a member is elected.</li>
  <li>
    If any meeting has less than 50% attendance by council members, a new
    election for all places must be held within a month. The 'one year' is then
    reset from that point.
  </li>
  <li>Disciplinary actions may be appealed to the council.</li>
  <li>
    A proxy must not be an existing council member, and any single person may
    not be a proxy for more than one council member at any given meeting.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Consequences of Gentoo's management structure</title>
<body>

<p>
As a consequence of the new management structure, global decisions will be made
by the elected council. This should give Gentoo a general direction - smaller
issues affecting only a project or two should be decided inside the projectss
involved, probably with input from other developers. The council should be a
fair representation of the developer base as every developer is able to vote,
so interests should be represented in a fair way. If the council does a bad job
and the developer base is unhappy with its work, the council can be voted out.
</p>

<p>
Decisions within a project can be made by the people inside project itself, of
course coordination between the projects is necessary. The (sub-)project leads
are usually responsible for doing this.
</p>

<p>
Most projects have an Operational and Strategic lead, but basically it is up to
the project what positions are created and how they are called - this also
applies to sub-projects.
</p>

<p>
Some projects appoint a contact person for communication to another project
e.g. a developer within the forums project who is responsible for communication
with the infrastracture project.
</p>

<p>
All in all, the current structure has no clear list of responsibilities the
project leads are supposed to satisfy. They are chosen by the members of the
project, the practical responsibility of a lead is "whatever the members
require", and if that isn't satisfied, the members can get a new lead (if they
can find somebody to take the job!).
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- FIXME TODO...

<section>
<title>Decision making</title>
<body>
<p>
Currently, GLEPs (Gentoo Linux Enhancement Proposals) can be approved
or rejected by the appropriate top-level manager under which the GLEP
falls. If there is no clearly-defined manager under which the GLEP
falls, the GLEP will be voted upon by the Managers and Chief
Architect, and must be approved unanimously. In all cases, a public,
written explanation must be provided detailing why the GLEP was
approved or rejected, either by the manager who approved/rejected it,
or the head of the GLEP sub-project (Grant Goodyear) if the GLEP was
voted upon by the management team. This summary is meant to reflect
the decision that was made by some of the managers at an early manager
meeting.
</p>

<p>
Currently, there is no formal general voting procedure in place. In
the interim, any item to be voted upon must be approved by "votable"
by the Chief Architect. Before voting takes place, all managers must
have an opportunity to present their ideas before the other managers,
with the general originator(s) of the idea having the opportunity to
present first. After that, the Chief Architect and Managers can
present their ideas, with the Chief Architect having the opportunity
to present last. After this has happened, voting can take place, and
the item will be approved on an unanimous vote. Managers or the Chief
Architect can choose to abstain from voting, and the vote can still
pass with abstainers as long as at least 50% of the members have
voted. The voting must take place at an official managers
meeting. Non-attending managers are allowed to vote via email. The
vote must be officially tallied and posted to the managers list.
</p>

<p>
The reason for the "Chief Architect approval" clause it to prevent the
voting process from being abused by allowing voting items that make no
sense, such as those that begin with a "Should we continue to," where
a "nay" result would result in a change in existing policy, as well as
preventing managers for requesting that every small decision be voted
upon. We currently have no clear policy to determine what is a
"votable" item, and without this policy there needs to be some method
to determine what is "votable" and what affects some immutable part of
Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
This section is subject to additional clarification and refinement in
the future, as is the rest of this document. The purpose of this
section is to document our currently-existing procedures rather than
define ideal or "final" procedures.
</p>
</body>
</section>
-->

</sections>
