<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/devrel/handbook/hb-introduction-staffers.xml,v 1.1 2008/10/01 17:08:39 rane Exp $ -->

<sections>
<version>1</version>
<date>2008-09-13</date>

<section>
<title>Gentoo Staff Member policy</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Running a Linux distribution has multiple aspects and many of them aren't
directly connected to coding. Every distribution needs people to run its
servers, help its community, provide documentation, handle project's finances
and legal issues and serve many other tasks. Their contributions are as
important as code contributions. These developers are called staff members in
Gentoo.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Types of staff members</title>
<body>

<p>
The following list contains all types of staff members we are currently
recruiting in Gentoo:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/infrastructure/">Gentoo Infrastructure</uri> project members</li>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/gdp/">Gentoo Documentation</uri> editors and translators</li>
  <li><uri link="/news/en/gmn/">Gentoo Monthly Newsletter</uri> editors and translators</li>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/forums/">Gentoo Forums</uri> global moderators and administrators</li>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/devrel/">Gentoo Developer Relations</uri> members</li>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/userrel/">Gentoo User Relations</uri> members</li>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/pr/">Gentoo Public Relations</uri> members</li>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/security/">Gentoo Security</uri> GLSA coordinators</li>
  <li><uri link="/proj/en/sunrise/">Gentoo Sunrise</uri> developers</li>
  <li><uri link="/foundation/en">Gentoo Foundation</uri> officers</li>
</ul>

<impo>
If the project you want to contribute to as a staff member isn't on this list
and you think it should, please contact <mail link="devrel@gentoo.org">Developer
Relations</mail> about policy change.
</impo>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>How is staff member access different from ebuild developer access?</title>
<body>

<p>
Access is assigned based on the responsibilities of the Staff Member.  All
Gentoo Developers are provided with an gentoo.org mail address, ssh access to
dev.gentoo.org (for shell, ldap, public_html, etc) as well as cvs access to
gentoo's web/project pages.  As a staff member you will not be granted access to
the ebuild tree, as ebuild developers are, but may be granted access to other
area's based on your need and responsibilities.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>How can I become a Gentoo staff member?</title>
<body>

<p>
You have to work with members of the project you wish to help. You are invited
to the team when your level of contributions and expertise justify you becoming
a developer in that project. It may take time and may also require passing
internal recruitment procedures within that project first. Those procedures are
in place to ensure you know what your future function within Gentoo involves,
they are created and maintained by the project itself.
</p>

<p>
When you are ready, you will need to look for a mentor and a developer bug will
be filed for you after your mentor has approved your <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz/staff-quiz.txt">staff
quiz</uri>.
Once a recruiter has been assigned to your developer bug, both of you will need
to schedule your review. Please see the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/recruiters/mentor.xml">mentoring
guide</uri> for more information.
</p>

<note>
As a staff member who isn't going to work on ebuilds, you won't be asked
technical questions about them. All that will be required from you at this stage
of your recruitment is a good understanding of Gentoo internals.
</note>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>
I would like to be recruited as a staff member but also plan joining other
projects in future
</title>
<body>

<p>
Every Gentoo developer can join any project (s)he wishes if developers
of the project agree with that. Before you can start contributing to the
ebuild tree though, you will have to apply for ebuild developer recruitment.
This means you need a mentor, a history of technical contributions (bug fixes,
overlays, etc...) and adequate training. Please contact recruiters about this.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>How is retirement handled for staff members?</title>
<body>

<p>
You have to either remain active within the project you have joined or move to
other projects. If there are no projects within Gentoo you're active in, you are
subject for retirement via <uri link="/proj/en/devrel/undertakers/">Gentoo
Undertakers</uri> procedures.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
