<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="Presidents Report for the Gentoo Foundation Inc. 2011 to 2012l">
<title>Presidents Report for the Gentoo Foundation Inc. 2011 to 2012</title>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="neddyseagoon@gentoo.org">NeddySeagoon</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
Presidents Report for the Gentoo Foundation Inc.. 2011 to 2012
</abstract>
<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>
<version>1</version>
<date>2012-08-13</date>
<chapter>
<title>Summary</title>
<section>
<title>Reporting Period</title>
<body>
<p>
This report period covers the period from April 2011, which was the last Annual General Meeting (AGM), to June 2012 which is the end of the Gentoo Foundation financial year.
</p>
<p>
The reporting period was extended as the Trustees elected to move the AGM from April to August. This allows the Treasurer to report on a complete financial year. 
The April AGM date has proved inconvenient for several years and was only selected as it was 12 months since the reinvigorated Gentoo Foundation Inc., commenced working to restore 
its good standing, which was lost in 2007 after the annual reports failed to reach the New Mexico (NM) authorities.
</p>
<p>
The June/July annual trustee election with the AGM in August is a pattern the board intend to continue. It allows the annual reports to be prepared following the end of the Gentoo 
Foundations Inc trading year, before being voted on at the AGM and submitted to the New Mexico authorities before the November 15th deadline. 
</p>
<p>
Our 501c3 application has progressed more slowly than anyone would like but further progress has been made. 
The Foundation has engaged a <uri link="http://www.kpmcpa.com/">Certified Public Accountant</uri> (CPA) to assist with the application and our annual reports.
</p>
<p>
However, the Internal Revenue Service (IRS) are progressing 501c3 status for all FOSS organisations, such as the Gentoo Foundation Inc., very slowly, some have been rejected. There appears to be no clear IRS policy. The continued delay may allow trustees to evaluate the option to become a Public Benefit Corporation instead. This is a relatively new legal entity. 
</p>                        
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
  
<chapter>
<title>August 2012 Trustee Election Results</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
At the trustee elections in June 2012, Roy Bamford (NeddySeagoon) and David Abbott (dabbott) retired by rotation leaving two seats to be contested.
</p>
<p>
The results of the poll closing in early August  were:</p>
<ol>
<li>Roy Bamford (NeddySeagoon)</li>
<li>David Abbott (dabbott)</li>
<li>Alec Warner (antarus)</li>
<li>Patrick Lauer (patrick)</li>
</ol>
<p>
Roy Bamford and David Abbott were reelected for a further two year term.
</p>
<p>
The trustees would like to thank all the election candidates and the elections project for providing the election officials.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Membership List Management</title>
<body>        
<p>
In line with the bylaws, ballots cast in 2011 and 2012 will be used to remove inactive members from the Gentoo Foundation Inc. membership list.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
  
<chapter>
<title>Highlights of the Reporting Period</title>
<section>
<title>Register for Operations in the State of Missouri</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo Foundation Inc. has registered to conduct business in the State of Missouri.  
This makes it easy for our Treasurer to visit the bank in person when the occasion demands. We are now registered in both New Mexico and Missouri.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>  
<title>Foundation Funded Giveaways</title>
<body>

<ul>
<li><uri link="http://softwarelivre.org/fisl12">fisl12</uri></li>
<li><uri link="http://serres.fosscomm.gr/">Fosscomm 2012</uri> (in Greek) </li> 
<li>LinuxExpo</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Funding for MIPS Systems</title>
<body>
<p>
Funding was provided for three MIPS based boxes to allow the MIPS team to build stage3 tarballs for several MIPS architectures and allow a system for development work.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>David Abbott Became Secretary</title>
<body>
<p>
Our Secretary took over the role of Treasurer when Joshua Jackson resigned.  This was always intended to be a temporary, short term arrangement,
 as both roles are too much for a single individual. 
The single point of failure was also a risk to the Gentoo Foundation Inc. These officer roles have been separated with David Abbott taking on the Secretary 
duties. 
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Larry The Cow Larry Logo</title>
<body>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.fonthead.com/freeware">Larry the Cow</uri> has been associated with Gentoo from the very early days of Gentoo. Larry is actually a font glyph from <uri>http://www.fonthead.com</uri>.  
Over the years, the licensing associated with Larry has become more restrictive. 
After a brief correspondence, with Larrys creator, Fonthead Design Inc. agreed to license the font glyph we know as Larry under a Creative Commons license.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Artwork Competition Prizes - Larry the Cow T Shirts</title>
<body>
<p>
With the clarification of Larrys legal status above, the Foundation was able to create Larry the Cow merchandise.  Some of the first T-Shirts were offered as prizes in the 2012 artwork competition.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>http://www.gentoo.xxx Domain Availability</title>
<body>
<p>
The .xxx TLD names, intended for 'adult' content were made available during the reporting period.  There was a pre registration period when owners of similar names could buy or block the .xxx TLD. The trustees discussed taking up the gentoo.xxx TLD name but decided against it on the grounds that Gentoo did not want to use it and we should not set a precedent for collecting domain names we don't particularly want.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SFLC Change of Personnel</title>
<body>
<p>
Our contact at the <uri link="http://www.softwarefreedom.org/">Software Freedom Law Centre</uri> (SFLC) (Karen) changed employers. As a result, responses from the SFLC stopped for a while. We now have a new contact (Aaron) there. The SFLC supports the Gentoo Foundation Inc. on a pro bono basis.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Trademark Renewal</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo Foundation Inc. renewed the Gentoo trademarks for a period of 10 years.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>New Master Distfiles Machine</title>
<body>
<p>
The Foundation funded a new Master Distfiles Machine, which is now located at the Open Source Lab in Oregon State University. 
</p>
</body>
</section>
 
<section>
<title>Activity Tracker</title>
<body>
<p>
Rich Freeman has produced and populated a Foundation Activity tracker. Its a list of the regular task to be performed by the Gentoo Foundation Inc. officers, when the tasks are due and the office 
holder responsible for initiating them. It will help ensure the our legal obligations are carried out and help provide continuity in the event of a complete change of the board all at the 
same time.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Ganeti Cluster Virtual Machines</title>
<body>
<p>
With help from a major donor, the Foundation has funded a Ganeti cluster to host Virtual Machines for use by Gentoo developers. This system is not yet live but should be in the coming 
weeks.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gentoo Logo Usage Policy </title>
<body>
<p>
The trustees debated tidying up and clarifying the Gentoo logo usage policy. As commercial requests would still need to be considered on a case by case basis, it was agreed that it would 
not save the trustees any time and the matter was dropped.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
  
<chapter>
<title>Closing Remarks</title>
<section>
<title>Look Back Over The Year</title>
<body>
<p>
Compared to other businesses, the Gentoo Foundation Inc. has had a reasonably good year. With four active years behind us, the 
Foundation has shown that it is a reliable active body. 
Both Gentoo and the Gentoo Foundation Inc. need to attract more members who are interested in the various facets of business 
administration to ensure the long term continuity of the Gentoo Foundation Inc. as an independent entity.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Looking to the Future</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo needs to reorganise along the lines of a conventional business structure. This is mainly so that external entities find 
the Foundation easier to relate to, deal with and therefore donate to.  We will be considerably more attractive to USA tax paying donors when 
our form 1023 is filed and more attractive still when we look like a conventional corporation.
</p>
<p>
It is still far from clear that The Gentoo Foundation contains people with the required skills and the interest to operate a successful business
on a volunteer basis, nor that the Foundation can grow big enough on the back of the Gentoo distribution to pay for the skills needed.  However, four years on from coming back from the 
dead, the Gentoo Foundation Inc. is stronger and more visible than it has ever been.  
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
