<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd"> 

<guide link="index.xml">
	
<title>Rule Set Based Access Control (RSBAC) for Linux - Quickstart</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="albeiro@gentoo.pl">Michal Purzynski</mail>
</author>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="kang@gentoo.org">Guillaume Destuynder</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
RSBAC is Mandatory Access Control security system based on Role Compatibility model. It can enforce access rules on your operating systems.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version> 
<date>1 June 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Project Description</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This project manages the RSBAC support in Gentoo. This includes providing kernels with RSBAC support (based on the hardened-sources), administration utilites to manage and write strong Gentoo-specific policies.
RSBAC works on many different architectures using both the 2.4 and 2.6 Linux kernels.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Project Goals</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
This project aims to make RSBAC available to more users, improve it, and improve it's integration in 
Gentoo Linux. We are developing a policy for the base system and the common daemons, as well as other 
popular programs. Currently we are mostly targetting servers, but desktops will also be supported in the future.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>What is RSBAC</title>
<section>
<title>RSBAC in a nutshell</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.rsbac.org">RSBAC</uri> (Rule Set Based Access Control) is free Open Source (GPL) Linux kernel security extension. RSBAC's main concept is modularity. It uses <uri link="http://rsbac.org/models.htm">several</uri> well-known and new security models, including MAC, ACLs and RC among a few others. RSBAC has control over individual users and program network accesses using any combination of the possible security models. It is also as extensible as it is modular: you can write your own models for runtime registration. Finally, RSBAC provides an excellent support for the most newest stable and development Linux kernels.It is in production use from January 2000 and has proven to be very stable. You are also suggested to read the more detailled <uri link="overview.xml">Overview</uri></p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>A complete security solution for Gentoo</title>
<body>

<p>
However, RSBAC itself is not a complete security solution by itself: it only gives the possibility of applying security models. Fortunately, it works well with other Hardened projects (such as PaX) to brings you a complete solution.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Developers</title>
<section>
<body>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Developer</th>
  <th>Nickname</th>
  <th>Role</th>
  </tr>
<tr>
  <ti><uri link="mailto:albeiro@gentoo.pl">Michal Purzynski</uri></ti>
  <ti>Albeiro</ti>
  <ti>Not yet assigned</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><uri link="mailto:kang@gentoo.org">Guillaume Destuynder</uri></ti>
  <ti>kang</ti>
  <ti>Not yet assigned</ti>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Resources</title>
<section>
<title>Hardened RSBAC</title>
<body>

<p>
The resources offered by the RSBAC hardened project are:
</p>
<ul>
  <li><uri link="intro.xml">Introduction to RSBAC</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="overview.xml">RSBAC overview</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="compat.xml">RSBAC Compatibliity list</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="quickstart.xml">RSBAC Quickstart</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="examples.xml">Administration examples in RSBAC</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>

