<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>

<name>RSBAC</name>
<longname>Rule Set Based Access Control</longname>

<description>
RSBAC is Mandatory Access Control security system based on the Role Compatibility model. It can enforce access rules on your operating system.
</description>

<longdescription>
This project manages the RSBAC support within Gentoo. This includes providing kernels with RSBAC support (based on the hardened-sources), administration utilites to manage and write strong Gentoo-specific policies. RSBAC works on many different architectures using both the 2.4 and 2.6 Linux kernels.
</longdescription>

<goals>
This project aims to make RSBAC available to more users, improve it, and improve it's integration in Gentoo Linux. We are developing a policy for the base system and the common daemons, as well as other popular programs. Currently we are mostly targetting servers, but desktops will also be supported in the future.
</goals>

<extrachapter position="goals">
<title>What is RSBAC?</title>
<section><body>
<p>
  <uri link="http://www.rsbac.org/">RSBAC</uri> (Rule Set Based Access Control) is free Open Source (GPL) Linux kernel security extension. RSBAC's main concept is modularity. It uses <uri link="http://rsbac.org/models.htm">several</uri> well-known and new security models, including MAC, ACLs and RC among a few others. RSBAC has control over individual users and program network accesses using any combination of the possible security models. It is also as extensible as it is modular: you can write your own models for runtime registration. Finally, RSBAC provides an excellent support for the most newest stable and development Linux kernels.It is in production use from January 2000 and has proven to be very stable. You are also suggested to read the more detailled <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/rsbac/overview.xml">overview</uri>.
</p>
<p>
 However, RSBAC itself is not a complete security solution by itself: it only gives the possibility of applying security models. Fortunately, it works well with other Hardened projects (such as PaX) to brings you a complete solution.
</p>
</body></section>
</extrachapter>

<dev role="lead" description="Base policy, documentation, x86">kang</dev>

<extraproject name="x86" lead="kang">
  Support for the x86 architecture.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Documentation" lead="kang">
  Full documentation for the RSBAC project.
</extraproject>

<plannedproject name="Base Policy">
  RSBAC policy for the core system, including users, administrators, and
  daemons in the system profile.
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Desktop">
  RSBAC	support on desktops.
</plannedproject>

<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/rsbac/overview.xml">RSBAC Overview</resource>
<resource link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/rsbac/quickstart.xml">RSBAC Quickstart</resource>

<extrachapter position="resources">
<title>How Do I Use This?</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
  RSBAC can be installed new on a system by following the above install guide
  for your architecture.  If there is not an install guide for your architecuture
  yet, it is still possible to install by following the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/index.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>.
  When the system is installed, convert it to RSAC by using the
  Quickstart Guide.

</p>
<p>
  Converting a preexisting Gentoo installation to RSBAC can be done by
  following the Quickstart Guide.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
  To participate in the RSBAC project first join the mailing list at
  <i>gentoo-hardened@gentoo.org</i>. Then ask if there are plans to support
  something that you are interested in, propose a new subproject that you are
  interested in or choose one of the planned subprojects to work on. You may talk
  to the developers and users in the IRC channel <i>#gentoo-hardened</i> on
  <i>irc.freenode.net</i> for more information or just to chat about the project
  or any subprojects. If you don&#39;t have the ability to actively help by
  contributing work we will always need testers to use and audit the RSBAC
  policies. All development, testing, and productive comments and feedback will
  be greatly appreciated.

</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
