<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd"> 

<guide link="overview.xml">
	
<title>Rule Set Based Access Control (RSBAC) for Linux - Overview</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="ao@rsbac.org">Amon Ott</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor"> 
  <mail link="albeiro@gentoo.pl">Michal Purzynski</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="kang@gentoo.org">Guillaume Destuynder</mail>
</author>  

<abstract>
This document should give you an overview of RSBAC access control system.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version> 
<date>2 June 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Key features</title>

<section>
<body>

<ul>
<li>Free Open Source (GPL) Linux kernel security extension</li>
<li>Independent of governments and big companies</li>
<li>Several well-known and new security models, including MAC, ACL and RC</li>
<li>Control over individual users and program network accesses</li>
<li>Any combination of models is possible</li>
<li>Easily extensible: write your own model for runtime registration</li>
<li>Supports all the current kernels</li>
<li>Stable for production use</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>What is RSBAC?</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>	
RSBAC is a flexible, powerful and fast open source access control
framework for current Linux kernels, which has been in stable production
use since January 2000 (version 1.0.9a). The full developement has been done independentely, and no existing access control code has been reused.
</p>

<p>
The standard package includes a range of access control models like MAC,
RC, ACL (see below). Furthermore, the runtime registration facility
(REG) makes it easy to implement your own access control model as a kernel
module and get it registered at runtime.
</p>

<p>
The RSBAC framework is based on the <uri link="http://www.acsac.org/secshelf/book001/09.pdf">Generalized Framework for Access Control (GFAC)</uri> by Abrams and LaPadula. All security relevant system calls
are extended by security enforcement code. This code calls the central
decision component, which in turn calls all active decision modules and
generates a combined decision. This decision is then enforced by the
system call extensions.
</p>

<p>
Decisions are based on the type of access (request type), the access
target and on the values of attributes attached to the subject calling and
to the target to be accessed. Additional independent attributes can be
used by individual modules, e.g. the privacy module (<uri link="#doc_chap3_sect4">PM</uri>). All attributes
are stored in fully protected directories, one on each mounted device.
Thus changes to attributes require special system calls provided.
</p>

<p>
From version 1.2.0, all types of network accesses can be controlled
individually for all users and programs. This gives you full control over
their network behaviour and makes unintended network accesses easier to
prevent and detect.
</p>

<p>
As all types of access decisions are based on general decision requests,
many different security policies can be implemented as a decision module.
Apart from the builtin models shown below, the optional Module
Registration (REG) allows for registration of additional, individual
decision modules at runtime.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Implemented models</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
In the RSBAC version 1.2.3, the following modules are included. Please
note that all modules are optional.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>MAC</title>	
<body>
<p>
Bell-LaPadula Mandatory Access Control (compartments limited to a number of 64)
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>FC</title>	
<body>
<p>
Functional Control. A simple role based model, restricting access
to security information to security officers and access to system
information to administrators.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>SIM</title>
<body>
<p>
Security Information Modification. Only security administrators
are allowed to modify data labeled as security information
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>PM</title>
<body>
<p>
Privacy Model. <uri link="http://www.cs.kau.se/~simone/">Simone Fischer-Huebner</uri>'s Privacy Model in its
first implementation. See RSBAC <uri link="http://rsbac.org/niss98.htm">paper on PM implementation</uri>
for the National Information Systems Security Conference (NISSC 98)
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>MS</title>
<body>
<p>
Malware Scan. Scan all files for malware on execution (optionally
on all file read accesses or on all TCP/UDP read accesses), deny
access if infected. Currently the Linux viruses Bliss.A and
Bliss.B and a handfull of others are detected. From v1.2.0, a
generic interface allows to replace the scanning engine through a
kernel module at runtime. Also see RSBAC <uri link="http://rsbac.org/nordse98.htm">Approaches to
Integrated Malware Detection and Avoidance</uri> for The Third
Nordic Workshop on Secure IT Systems (Nordsec'98)
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>FF</title>	
<body>
<p>
File Flags. Provide and use flags for dirs and files, currently
execute_only (files), read_only (files and dirs), search_only
(dirs), secure_delete (files), no_execute (files), add_inherited
(files and dirs), no_rename_or_delete (files and dirs, no
inheritance) and append_only(files and dirs). Only FF security
officers may modify these flags.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>RC</title>
<body>
<p>
Role Compatibility. Defines roles and types for each target type
(file, dir, dev, ipc, scd, process). For each role, compatibility
to all types and to other roles can be set individually and with
request granularity. For administration there is a fine grained
separation-of-duty. Granted rights can have a time limit. Please
also refer to the <uri link="http://rsbac.org/rc-nordsec2002/index.html">Nordsec 2002 RC Paper</uri> for the detailed model
design and specification.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>AUTH</title>	
<body>
<p>
Authorization enforcement. Controls all CHANGE_OWNER requests for
process targets, only programs/processes with general setuid
allowance and those with a capability for the target user ID may
setuid. Capabilities can be controlled by other
programs/processes, e.g. authentication daemons.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>ACL</title>
<body>
<p>
Access Control Lists. For every object there is an Access Control
List, defining which subjects may access this object with which
request types. Subjects can be of type user, RC role and ACL
group. Objects are grouped by their target type, but have
individual ACLs. If there is no ACL entry for a subject at an
object, rights are inherited from parent objects, restricted by an
inheritance mask. Direct (user) and indirect (role, group) rights
are accumulated. For each object type there is a default ACL on
top of the normal hierarchy. Group management has been added in
version 1.0.9a. Granted rights and group memberships can have a
time limit.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CAP</title>	
<body>
<p>
Linux Capabilities (new in 1.2.0). For all users and programs you
can define a minimum and a maximum Linux capability set ("set of
root special rights"). This lets you e.g. run server programs as
normal user, or restrict rights of root programs in the standard
Linux way.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>JAIL</title>	
<body>
<p>
Process Jails (new in 1.2.1). This module adds a new system call
rsbac_jail, which is basically a superset of the FreeBSD jail
system call. It encapsulates the calling process and all
subprocesses in a chroot environment with a fixed IP address and a
lot of further restrictions.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>RES</title>	
<body>
<p>
Linux Resources (new in 1.2.2). For all users and programs you can
define a minimum and a maximum Linux process resource set (e.g.
memory size, number of open files, number of processes per user).
Internally, these sets are applied to the standard Linux resource
flags.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<body>
<p>	   
All decision modules are described in detail on the module description
page.
</p>

<p>
A general goal of RSBAC design has been to some day reach the (obsolete)
Orange Book (TCSEC) B1 level. Now it is mostly targeting to be useful as
secure and multi-purposed networked system, with special interest in
firewalls.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>

