<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/portage/doc/pip/Attic/pip000.xml,v 1.23 2006/04/06 00:30:50 chriswhite Exp $ -->

<guide link="/proj/en/portage/doc/pip/pip000.xml" lang="en" disclaimer="draft">
<title>PIP 000: Portage Improvement Proposal (PIP) Template</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>
<author title="GuideXML Editory">
  <mail link="chriswhite@gentoo.org">Chris White</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-04-04</date>
<chapter>
<title>PIP 000: Portage Improvement Proposal (PIP) Template</title>
<section>
<title>Motivation</title>
<body>

<p>
Clearly state the problem that your PIP is trying to solve.  State the 
current implementation ( if any ) and how it is problemative.  Attempt 
to present how your PIP solves the problem.  PIP's that do not solve 
problems are generally much more difficult to pass.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Specification</title>
<body>

<p>
Place the specification for your PIP here.  The specification should 
explain what your PIP does, what if affects, how it is arranged...etc.  
Most of the details of many PIPs go in this section.  In short, How Does 
Your PIP Work?
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Rationale</title>
<body>

<p>
This section is for concerns raised during the discussion of the PIP, 
both in IRC and via E-mail.  When discussing the PIP, what issues came 
up and how were they solved?  This section is a record of the 
deliberation you had while coming up with and finalizing this PIP.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Backwards Compatability</title>
<body>

<p>
All PIPs must have this section, if there are no backwards compatability 
issues then say that there are none.  Otherwise please address issues 
that your PIP may have with older versions of portage, trees, and any 
database-like items that may be broken or modified by your PIP.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reference Implementation</title>
<body>

<p>
Usually one links to patches to implement the PIP.  This section is 
definately encouraged for all PIPs but is not required at present.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Copyright</title>
<body>

<p>
Most PIPs are either Public Domain or the 
<uri link="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5">CC-BY-SA license</uri>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
