<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/proj/en/base/embedded/gnap-userguide.xml">
<title>Gentoo Network APpliance User Guide</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="koon@gentoo.org">Koon</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document describes what GNAP is, how to build it, and how
to use it.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>DEcember 3, 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>Why GNAP ?</title>
<section>
<title>The name</title>
<body>

<p>
The acronym GNAP stands for Gentoo Network APpliance. The following figure
should give you the big picture:
</p>

<figure link="gnap/gnap.jpg" short="GNAP! GNAP!" caption="GNAP development"/>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The need</title>
<body>

<p>
More seriously, GNAP comes from the need to build old-PC based network
appliances like internal routers or firewalls without the need for a complete
installation. I have a bunch of old PCs with fragile components and want to be
able to easily switch PCs in case of failure. Using removable media with a
burned-on configuration is the most flexible way I found. When it fails,
just put the media on another machine.
</p>

<p>
I started by using 
<uri link="http://leaf.sourceforge.net/mod.php?mod=userpage&amp;menu=910&amp;page_id=36">LEAF Bering-uClibc</uri>
floppy-based firewalls but was quickly
undermined by problems: media fragility, difficulty to automate creation of
floppies and lack of easy extensibility.
I switched to LEAF Bering-uClibc
<uri link="http://leaf.sourceforge.net/doc/guide/bubooting.html#id2572755">CDROM-based configurations</uri>,
with a web-based automated ISO generation. This solved most of the
problems but the extensibility problems remain, and maintaining the web-app
was becoming a nightmare.
</p>

<p>
I finally chose to leverage 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/catalyst/">Gentoo Catalyst</uri>
power to build custom LiveCDs,
solving both the extensibility problem and the non-standard solution
maintenance. The idea was to have a generic LiveCD core that I could build once
and use everywhere, and burn on the CD a specific configuration overlay to
customize the appliance role. This simplifies CD generation as you don't have
to go through the whole Catalyst process to customize a specific LiveCD.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What you should read</title>
<body>

<p>
If you just want to build a customized GNAP LiveCD using an existing GNAP core,
please proceed directly to the
<uri link="#doc_chap3">How to use a GNAP core to build a custom LiveCD</uri>
chapter. If you want to
build your own GNAP core, please read the following section.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>How to build a GNAP Core</title>
<section>
<title>Prerequisites</title>
<body>

<p>
You'll need root rights (needed by Catalyst) to build a GNAP Core. You'll also
need to have the following packages installed:
</p>

<ul>
<li>dev-util/catalyst (version 1.0.9)</li>
<li>sys-fs/squashfs-tools</li>
</ul>

<p>
Finally you'll need an uclibc/hardened stage2 tarball as seed stage.
The current one is named <path>stage2-x86-uclibc-hardened-2004.3.tar.bz2</path>
and it is available for download
<uri link="http://gentoo.osuosl.org/experimental/x86/embedded/stages/">here</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Catalyst spec files and support files</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="gnap/gnap-sources-current.tar.bz2">GNAP Sources</uri>
contains the <c>gnap_make</c> build script, Catalyst configuration
files, the portage configuration and the kernel configuration used for
the current version of GNAP. You should download and unpack it, then
update the <c>storedir</c> parameter in the <path>gnapcatalyst.conf</path>
file so that it points to a temporary build directory.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Building a GNAP Core from scratch</title>
<body>

<p>
Once you edited the file, you should use <c>gnap_make</c> to call the
Catalyst stages and the tarball creation, with the <c>-s</c> parameter
to designate the stage2 tarball seed:
</p>

<pre caption="Building a new GNAP Core tarball in one step">
# ./gnap_make -s ../stage2-x86-uclibc-hardened-2004.3.tar.bz2
</pre>

<p>
This will take a <e>very</e> long time to complete, and should produce
a nice GNAP Core tarball with a version stamp based on current date.
</p>

<p>
If you want to reuse a previously built (or officially downloaded) Portage
snapshot, you should copy the portage-YYYYMMDD.tar.bz2 file to the
<path>storedir/snapshots</path> subdirectory, then use the following command:
</p>

<pre caption="Building from a YYYYMMDD snapshot">
# ./gnap_make -s ../stage2-x86-uclibc-hardened-2004.3.tar.bz2 YYYYMMDD
</pre>
<p>
In case of failure, or if you just want to re-run some final stages, you might
want to specify which Catalyst stages gnap_make should call. You can do this
by providing the snapshot timestamp to reuse, the GNAP version timestamp to 
reuse, and the stage names (<c>snapshot</c>, <c>stage3</c>,
<c>livecd-stage1</c>, <c>livecd-stage2</c>) and/or the special
<c>tarball</c> target (which builds the final GNAP Core tarball) as parameters:
</p>

<pre caption="Calling only the two final stages of a 20041012 GNAP build, using a prebuilt 20041008 Portage snapshot">
# ./gnap_make 20041008 20041012 livecd-stage2 tarball
</pre>


</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Customizing your GNAP Core</title>
<body>

<p>
You may want to change the kernel sources used in the GNAP Core (you may even
have to, if the configured sources are no longer in portage). To do that, you
should edit the <path>kernel/sources.conf</path> file to point to the right
sources name and configuration file.
</p>

<p>
You can also change the subarch and profile used to build the GNAP Core
(by default, an <e>x86</e> subarch with <e>hardened/x86/2.6</e> profile),
by editing the <path>specs/common.conf</path> file.
</p>

<p>
To add new software packages, you should add them to the
<path>specs/packages.conf</path> file. To start new daemons by default,
you should add them to the <c>livecd/rcadd</c> option of the
<path>specs/livecd.conf</path> file.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>How to use a GNAP Core to build a custom LiveCD</title>
<section>
<title>Requirements</title>
<body>

<p>
You'll just need the
<uri link="gnap/gnap-tools-current.tar.bz2">GNAP Tools</uri>, a 
<uri link="gnap/gnap-core-current.tar">GNAP Core tarball</uri>
and the app-cdr/cdrtools package installed.
You don't need to be root to build a custom GNAP LiveCD.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The overlay.conf file</title>
<body>

<p>
The overlay.conf file controls general customization options. It's the only
mandatory file in your overlay directory. Here you can decide localization
options and which features should be enabled on your customized LiveCD:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
 <th>Option</th>
 <th>Values</th>
 <th>Default</th>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>TIMEZONE</ti>
 <ti>The <uri link="http://leaf.sourceforge.net/doc/guide/buci-tz.html">uclibc-compliant timezone code</uri>.</ti> 
 <ti>empty (UTC)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>KEYMAP</ti>
 <ti>Console keymap value. Example: <c>fr</c></ti>
 <ti><c>us</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>NBCARDS</ti>
 <ti>Number of connected network cards you want to start.</ti>
 <ti><c>1</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>IP_RELAY</ti>
 <ti>Should IP relaying be active at startup ?</ti>
 <ti><c>no</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>NET_CONFIG</ti>
 <ti>Is network configured by static files or DHCP. Example: <c>dhcp</c></ti>
 <ti><c>static</c></ti>
</tr>

<tr>
 <ti>USE_SSH</ti>
 <ti>Set to <c>yes</c> to have the OpenSSH daemon run at startup. Note that
     if keys are not generated they will be during the first startup.</ti>
 <ti><c>no</c> (do not run)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>USE_FW</ti>
 <ti>Set to <c>yes</c> to have the Shorewall IPTables firewall run at startup.
     Note that you should overlay files in the <path>etc/shorewall</path>
     directory to configure non-default Shorewall options.</ti>
 <ti><c>no</c> (do not run)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>USE_CBQ</ti>
 <ti>Set to <c>yes</c> to have the CBQ traffic control run at startup.
     Note that you should overlay files in the <path>etc/cbqinit</path>
     directory with the CBQ configuration files to use.</ti>
 <ti><c>no</c> (do not run)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>USE_VPN</ti>
 <ti>Set to <c>yes</c> to have the OpenVPN daemon run at startup. Note that
     you should overlay files in the <path>etc/openvpn</path> directory with
     the OpenVPN configuration files to use.</ti>
 <ti><c>no</c> (do not run)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>USE_DNSDHCP</ti>
 <ti>Set to <c>yes</c> to have the DNSMasq daemon run at startup. Note that
     you should overlay a <path>etc/dnsmasq.conf</path> file with
     the DNSMasq configuration file to use.</ti>
 <ti><c>no</c> (do not run)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
 <ti>NTPSERVER</ti>
 <ti>The name of the NTP server to use as a time synchronisation source.</ti>
 <ti>empty (do not synchronise time using NTP)</ti>
</tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The overlay directory</title>
<body>

<p>
The overlay directory contains files that will be used to replace default files
on the LiveCD root filesystem just after startup. This directory must contain
at least a <path>etc</path> subdirectory with a <path>etc/overlay.conf</path>
in it.
</p>

<p>
Files commonly replaced include <path>etc/hostname</path> (to set a host name),
<path>etc/shadow</path> (to set a root password) or <path>etc/conf.d/net</path>
(to set network configuration).
</p>

<note>
The GNAP tools contain typical overlays for various roles in the examples
subdirectory.
</note>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Generating and burning</title>
<body>

<p>
You should use the <c>gnap_overlay</c> script from the gnap-tools package.
For example, to build an <path>myfirewall.iso</path> LiveCD using the
<path>gnap-0.3-20041008.tar</path> GNAP Core and the 
<path>overlays/myfirewall</path> overlay directory:
</p>

<pre caption="Example of gnap_overlay use">
$ ./gnap_overlay gnap-0.3-20041008.tar overlays/myfirewall myfirewall.iso
</pre>

<p>
Then you should burn this ISO file and test. CD-RW is recommended :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Generating and writing to hard disk, CF...</title>
<body>

<p>
The <c>gnap_overlay</c> script from the gnap-tools package can also be used
to create a bootable hard drive (hard disk, DiskOnModule, CF card...) with
the GNAP configuration on it. First the target must be properly set up. You
will need to install a Master Boot Record on it :
</p>

<pre caption="Creation a MBR on device /dev/sda">
# dd if=mbr/mbr.bin of=/dev/sda bs=512 count=1
</pre>

<p>
You must also create an active partition on the device, using fdisk. Then
you can call (as root) gnap_overlay to write to the disk. You'll need to know
the name of the partition to write to, as seen by the host you use to write
to the device. You'll also need to know the name of the partition as it will be
seen in the GNAP system as it boots on the device. For example, a CF card can
be seen on the host as /dev/sdb1 and by a Soekris system as /dev/hda1.
</p>

<pre caption="Writing GNAP to the disk">
# ./gnap_overlay -t disk gnap-0.3-20041008.tar overlays/myfirewall /dev/sda1 hda1 cache
</pre>

<note>
cache is an optional parameter you can use to tell GNAP to cache the squashfs
filesystem once at strtup to avoid multiple read access that can wear the
device.
</note>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
