<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>

<name>Embedded</name>
<longname>Embedded Gentoo</longname>

<description>
  Embedded Gentoo brings the flexibity of Gentoo to embedded systems.
</description>

<longdescription>
  This project manages embedded system support in Gentoo.  The project is 
  responsible for overseeing the build infrastructure for creating images 
  to be installed onto embedded systems.  Also included is the support of 
  specific types of embedded systems and development tools.
</longdescription>

<goals>
  The intention of the project is to make Gentoo viable for embedded systems.  
  This includes creating a system for cross compiling and building the image 
  for an embedded system on a Gentoo workstation.  The base install image 
  should be minimal, with different libc options.  Building on this base, 
  the system can be customized for the particular system.
</goals>

<dev role="lead">pebenito</dev>
<dev role="Single Boards">solar</dev>
<dev role="ARM, Cross Compiling">vapier</dev>
<dev role="Misc">dragonheart</dev>
<dev role="ARM, Handhelds">yvasilev</dev>
<dev role="AVR">gustavoz</dev>
<dev role="AVR">brix</dev>

<extraproject name="Build">
  System tools for building and loading the system.  Includes cross compiling
  and libc (glibc/uClibc).
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Tools">
  Tools for embedded system development (dev-embedded)
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Single Boards">
  Support for single board systems.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="Handhelds" lead="yvasilev">
  Support for handheld devices, such as PDAs like iPAQ and Zaurus.
</extraproject>
<extraproject name="GNAP" lead="Koon">
  <uri link="/proj/en/base/embedded/gnap.xml">Gentoo Network APpliance</uri> project.
</extraproject>

<plannedproject name="Misc Devices">
  Support for miscellaneous embedded systems
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Security">
  Implementation of security measures
</plannedproject>
<plannedproject name="Real Time">
  Enhancements for real time operation
</plannedproject>

<herd name="dev-embedded"/>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Recommended Reading</title>
<section>
<body>
<p> 
At the Linux World Expo (2005 Boston) O'Reilly donated a few copies of 
<uri link="http://www.oreilly.com/catalog/belinuxsys"> Building Embedded 
Linux Systems</uri>. We are thankful and highly suggest you pick up a 
copy if you're a new or intermediate embedded linux user.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>I Want to Participate (User)</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To participate in the Embedded Gentoo project first join the mailing list at 
<mail link="gentoo-embedded@gentoo.org">gentoo-embedded@gentoo.org</mail> (see 
the <uri link="/main/en/lists.xml">mailing lists page</uri> for more info).  
Then ask if there are plans to support something that you are interested in, 
propose a new subproject that you are interested in or choose one of the 
planned subprojects to work on.  You may talk to the developers and users in 
the IRC channel <i>#gentoo-embedded</i> on <i>irc.freenode.net</i> for more 
information or just to chat about the project or any subprojects.  If you 
don&#39;t have the ability to actively help by contributing work we will 
always need testers to maintain the stability of the project.  All 
development, testing, and productive comments and  feedback will be greatly 
appreciated.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Vendor Notes</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
  If you're a product vendor and would like for our embedded project to 
  add support for your device or product lines then you're encouraged to 
  contact us if you're able to make donations in the form of hardware or in 
  the form of coding by your internal engineers. Vendors that make a 
  significant hardware donation will be listed on our sponsors page.
</p>
<p>
  Also note that some of our embedded developers may be willing to
  support your device for you on a contract basis for the planning,
  building, regression, optimization, deployment and update phases
  of your project. You may contact the Gentoo Foundation or the 
  developer directly on the individual level for more information.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
