<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-ia64-medium.xml,v 1.1 2006/09/03 05:02:44 vapier Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>4.0</version>
<date>2006-08-30</date>

<section>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Before we start, we first list what hardware requirements you need to
successfully install Gentoo on your box. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Hardware Requirements</title>
<body>

<p>
Pretty much every IA64 should be able to boot Gentoo.  At the moment we only
have LiveCDs, so your machine must have a CDROM drive installed.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>The Gentoo Installation CDs</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
The <e>Gentoo Installation CDs</e> are bootable CDs which contain a
self-sustained Gentoo environment. They allow you to boot Linux from the CD.
During the boot process your hardware is detected and the appropriate drivers
are loaded. They are maintained by Gentoo developers.
</p>

<p>
All Installation CDs allow you to boot, set up networking, initialize your
partitions and start installing Gentoo from the Internet. We currently provide
two Installation CDs which are equaly suitable to install Gentoo from, as long
as you're planning on performing an Internet-based installation using the 
latest version of the available packages.
</p>

<impo>
If you wish to install Gentoo without a working Internet connection, or would
like to use one of the provided installers, please use the installation
instructions described in the <uri link="2006.1/">Gentoo 2006.1
Handbooks</uri>.
</impo>

<p>
The Installation CD that we currently provide for IA64:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    The Gentoo <e>Minimal</e> Installation CD, a small, no-nonsense, bootable 
    CD which sole purpose is to boot the system, prepare the networking and 
    continue with the Gentoo installation.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Gentoo Minimal Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
The Minimal Installation CD is called <c><keyval id="min-cd-name"/></c> and
takes up only <keyval id="min-cd-size"/> MB of diskspace. You can use this
Installation CD to install Gentoo, but <e>only</e> with a working Internet
connection.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Minimal Installation CD</th>
  <th>Pros and Cons</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>+</th>
  <ti>Smallest download</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>-</th>
  <ti>
    Contains no stage3 tarball, no Portage snapshot, no prebuilt packages and
    is therefore not suitable for networkless installation
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>The Stage3 Tarball</title>
<body>

<p>
A stage3 tarball is an archive containing a minimal Gentoo environment,
suitable to continue the Gentoo installation using the instructions in this
manual. Previously, the Gentoo Handbook described the installation using one of
three stage tarballs. While Gentoo still offers stage1 and stage2 tarballs, the
official installation method uses the stage3 tarball. If you are interested in
performing a Gentoo installation using a stage1 or stage2 tarball, please read
the Gentoo FAQ on <uri link="/doc/en/faq.xml#stage12">How do I Install Gentoo
Using a Stage1 or Stage2 Tarball?</uri>
</p>

<p>
Stage3 tarballs can be downloaded from <path><keyval
id="release-dir"/>stages/</path> on any of the <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">Official Gentoo Mirrors</uri> and are not provided
on the LiveCD.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Download, Burn and Boot a Gentoo Installation CD</title>
<subsection>
<title>Downloading and Burning the Installation CDs</title>
<body>

<p>
You have chosen to use a Gentoo Installation CD. We'll first start by 
downloading and burning the chosen Installation CD. We previously discussed 
the several available Installation CDs, but where can you find them? 
</p>

<p>
You can download any of the Installation CDs from one of our <uri
link="/main/en/mirrors.xml">mirrors</uri>. The Installation CDs are located in
the <path><keyval id="release-dir"/>installcd/</path> directory.
</p>

<p>
Inside that directory you'll find ISO-files. Those are full CD images which you
can write on a CD-R.
</p>

<p>
In case you wonder if your downloaded file is corrupted or not, you can check
its MD5 checksum and compare it with the MD5 checksum we provide (such as
<path><keyval id="min-cd-name"/>.DIGESTS</path>). You can check the MD5
checksum with the <c>md5sum</c> tool under Linux/Unix or <uri
link="http://www.etree.org/md5com.html">md5sum</uri> for Windows.
</p>

<p>
Another way to check the validity of the downloaded file is to use GnuPG to
verify the cryptographic signature that we provide (the file ending with
<path>.asc</path>). Download the signature file and obtain the public key:
</p>

<pre caption="Obtaining the public key">
$ <i>gpg --keyserver subkeys.pgp.net --recv-keys 17072058</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now verify the signature:
</p>

<pre caption="Verify the cryptographic signature">
$ <i>gpg --verify &lt;signature file&gt; &lt;downloaded iso&gt;</i>
</pre>

<p>
To burn the downloaded ISO(s), you have to select raw-burning. How you
do this is highly program-dependent. We will discuss <c>cdrecord</c> and
<c>K3B</c> here; more information can be found in our <uri
link="/doc/en/faq.xml#isoburning">Gentoo FAQ</uri>.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    With cdrecord, you simply type <c>cdrecord dev=/dev/hdc &lt;downloaded iso 
    file&gt;</c> (replace <path>/dev/hdc</path> with your CD-RW drive's 
    device path).
  </li>
  <li>
    With K3B, select <c>Tools</c> &gt; <c>CD</c> &gt; <c>Burn Image</c>. Then
    you can locate your ISO file within the 'Image to Burn' area. Finally click
    <c>Start</c>.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Booting the Installation CD</title>
<body>

<p>
Once you have burnt your installation CD, it is time to boot it.
Remove all CDs from your CD drives, and insert the Gentoo
InstallCD. Reboot your system and wait for the EFI firmware to load on
the console. The exact option to select will differ depending on your
hardware.
</p>

<p>
Most implementations usually present an option directly on the first
menu (the EFI Boot Manager). The exact wording would differ but would
usually be something like &quot;CD Boot&quot;, &quot;Removable Media
Boot&quot; or &quot;Internal Bootable DVD&quot;. Select this option.
</p>

<p>
If your EFI implementation does not present such an option, you can
boot the CD using the EFI Shell. All implementations will present an
option to enter the shell on the Boot Manager menu. Select this
option. The EFI Shell will display a list of usable block devices
(<c>blk<b>n</b>:</c>) and also a list of filesystems the EFI Shell
can actually access (<c>fs<b>n</b>:</c>).
</p>

<p>
In most cases the option you want will be the <c>fs0:</c> choice;
regardless, (provided the CD drive recognizes the CD), you should
see one <c>fs<b>n</b></c> entry for your CD drive (the CD drive's
EFI device path will contain <c>CDROM</c> in the wording). Enter
<c>fs<b>n</b>:</c>, replacing <b>n</b> as required and including
the colon, followed by the Enter key. Next just type <c>elilo</c>
followed by the Enter key.
</p>

<p>
You will now be greeted by the ELILO boot message and asked to
enter a kernel to boot as well as any additional options to pass
to the kernel command line. In most cases just hit the Enter key
or wait five seconds. Only one kernel is supplied on the IA64
InstallCD, the <c>gentoo</c> kernel.
</p>

<p>
Several kernel aliases are provided which add extra options to
the kernel command line, which you may have to use instead of
the default <c>gentoo</c> option depending on your hardware:
</p>

<p>
The <c>gentoo-serial</c> option forces a serial console on the first
serial port (ttyS0) at 9600bps. This may be required on some older EFI
implementations where the kernel can't detect what console to use. You
should try this option if booting the default <c>gentoo</c> kernel
produces no output and if you are using a serial console. If you use a
serial console which is not connected to the first serial port you
must manually select the console by typing <c>gentoo
console=ttyS#,9600</c> where <c>#</c> is the number of the serial
port. You should <b>not</b> have to do this in normal circumstances,
this is only sometimes required for quirky EFI implementations.
</p>

<p>
The <c>gentoo-sgi</c> option forces a serial console on the <c>ttySG0</c>
serial port at 115200bps. This should only be needed on SGI hardware, and
if the console is properly selected in the default EFI settings, or if you
are using a video console this option should not be required.
</p>

</body>
<body>

<p>
You can also provide kernel options. They represent optional settings
you can (de)activate at will.
</p>

<pre caption="Options available to pass to your kernel of choice">
- agpgart       loads agpgart (use if you have graphic problems,lockups)
- ide=nodma     force disabling of DMA for malfunctioning IDE devices
- doscsi        scan for scsi devices (breaks some ethernet cards)
- dopcmcia      starts pcmcia service for PCMCIA cdroms
- nofirewire    disables firewire modules in initrd (for firewire cdroms,etc)
- nokeymap      disables keymap selection for non-us keyboard layouts
- docache       cache the entire runtime portion of CD in RAM, allows you
                to umount /mnt/cdrom to mount another CD.
- nodetect      causes hwsetup/kudzu and hotplug not to run
- nousb         disables usb module load from initrd, disables hotplug
- nodhcp        dhcp does not automatically start if nic detected
- nohotplug     disables loading hotplug service
- noapic        disable apic (try if having hardware problems nics,scsi,etc)
- noevms        disable loading of EVMS2 modules
- nolvm2        disable loading of LVM2 modules
- noload=module1,[module2,[...]]
                disable loading of specific kernel modules
</pre>

<p>
You will then be greeted with a boot screen. If you are installing
Gentoo on a system with a non-US keyboard, make sure you select the
layout at the prompt. If no selection is made in 10 seconds the
default (US keyboard) will be accepted and the boot process will
continue. Once the boot process completes, you will be automatically
logged in to the "Live" Gentoo Linux as "root", the super user. You
should have a root ("#") prompt on the current console. If you are
using a video console and have a keyboard connected you can also
switch to other consoles by pressing Alt-F2, Alt-F3 and Alt-F4. Get
back to the one you started on by pressing Alt-F1.
</p>

<p>
Now continue with <uri link="#hardware">Extra Hardware Configuration</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="hardware">
<title>Extra Hardware Configuration</title>
<body>

<p>
When the Installation CD boots, it tries to detect all your hardware devices
and loads the appropriate kernel modules to support your hardware. In the vast
majority of cases, it does a very good job. However, in some cases it may not
auto-load the kernel modules you need. If the PCI auto-detection missed some of
your system's hardware, you will have to load the appropriate kernel modules
manually. 
</p>

<p>
In the next example we try to load the <c>8139too</c> module (support for 
certain kinds of network interfaces):
</p>

<pre caption="Loading kernel modules">
# <i>modprobe 8139too</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Tweaking Hard Disk Performance</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are an advanced user, you might want to tweak the IDE hard disk
performance using <c>hdparm</c>. With the <c>-tT</c> options you can
test the performance of your disk (execute it several times to get a
more precise impression):
</p>

<pre caption="Testing disk performance">
# <i>hdparm -tT /dev/hda</i>
</pre>

<p>
To tweak, you can use any of the following examples (or experiment
yourself) which use <path>/dev/hda</path> as disk (substitute with your
disk):
</p>

<pre caption="Tweaking hard disk performance">
<comment>(Activate DMA:)</comment>
# <i>hdparm -d 1 /dev/hda</i>

<comment>(Activate Safe Performance Options:)</comment>
# <i>hdparm -d 1 -A 1 -m 16 -u 1 -a 64 /dev/hda</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="useraccounts">
<title>Optional: User Accounts</title>
<body>

<p>
If you plan on giving other people access to your installation
environment or you want to chat using <c>irssi</c> without root privileges (for
security reasons), you need to create the necessary user accounts and change 
the root password.
</p>

<p>
To change the root password, use the <c>passwd</c> utility:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing the root password">
# <i>passwd</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter your new password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter your password)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
To create a user account, we first enter their credentials, followed by
its password. We use <c>useradd</c> and <c>passwd</c> for these tasks.
In the next example, we create a user called "john".
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a user account">
# <i>useradd -m -G users john</i>
# <i>passwd john</i>
New password: <comment>(Enter john's password)</comment>
Re-enter password: <comment>(Re-enter john's password)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
You can change your user id from root to the newly created user by using
<c>su</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Changing user id">
# <i>su - john</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Starting the SSH Daemon</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to allow other users to access your computer during the
Gentoo installation (perhaps because those users are going to help you
install Gentoo, or even do it for you), you need to create a user
account for them and perhaps even provide them with your root password 
(<e>only</e> do that <e>if</e> you <b>fully trust</b> that user).
</p>

<p>
To fire up the SSH daemon, execute the following command:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting the SSH daemon">
# <i>/etc/init.d/sshd start</i>
</pre>

<p>
To be able to use sshd, you first need to set up your networking. Continue with
the chapter on <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=3">Configuring your Network</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
</sections>
