<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/hb-install-ia64-disk.xml,v 1.1 2006/09/03 05:02:44 vapier Exp $ -->

<sections>

<version>2.2</version>
<date>2005-06-10</date>

<section>
<title>Introduction to Block Devices</title>
<subsection>
<title>Block Devices</title>
<body>

<p>
We'll take a good look at disk-oriented aspects of Gentoo Linux
and Linux in general, including Linux filesystems, partitions and block devices.
Then, once you're familiar with the ins and outs of disks and filesystems,
you'll be guided through the process of setting up partitions and filesystems
for your Gentoo Linux installation.
</p>

<p>
To begin, we'll introduce <e>block devices</e>. The most famous block device is
probably the one that represents the first IDE drive in a Linux system, namely
<path>/dev/hda</path>. If your system uses SCSI or SATA drives, then your
first hard drive would be <path>/dev/sda</path>.
</p>

<p>
The block devices above represent an abstract interface to the disk. User
programs can use these block devices to interact with your disk without worrying
about whether your drives are IDE, SCSI or something else. The program can
simply address the storage on the disk as a bunch of contiguous,
randomly-accessible 512-byte blocks.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Partitions</title>
<body>

<p>
Although it is theoretically possible to use a full disk to house your Linux
system, this is almost never done in practice. Instead, full disk block devices
are split up in smaller, more manageable block devices. On <keyval id="arch"/>
systems, these are called <e>partitions</e>. 
</p>

<p>
Itanium systems use EFI, the Extensible Firmware Interface, for booting.  The
partition table format that EFI understands is called GPT, or GUID Partition
Table.  The partitioning program that understands GPT is called "parted", so
that is the tool we will use below.  Additionally, EFI can only read FAT
filesystems, so that is the format to use for the EFI boot partition, where the
kernel will be installed by "elilo".
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Advanced Storage</title>
<body>

<p>
The <keyval id="arch"/> Installation CDs provide support for EVMS and LVM2.
EVMS and LVM2 increase the flexibility offered by your partitioning setup.
During the installation instructions, we will focus on "regular" partitions,
but it is still good to know EVMS and LVM2 are supported as well.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Designing a Partitioning Scheme</title>
<subsection>
<title>Default Partitioning Scheme</title>
<body>

<p>
If you are not interested in drawing up a partitioning scheme for your system,
you can use the partitioning scheme we use throughout this book:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Partition</th>
  <th>Filesystem</th>
  <th>Size</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><path>/dev/sda1</path></ti>
  <ti>vfat</ti>
  <ti>32M</ti>
  <ti>EFI Boot partition</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><path>/dev/sda2</path></ti>
  <ti>(swap)</ti>
  <ti>512M</ti>
  <ti>Swap partition</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><path>/dev/sda3</path></ti>
  <ti>ext3</ti>
  <ti>Rest of the disk</ti>
  <ti>Root partition</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
If you are interested in knowing how big a partition should be, or even how
many partitions you need, read on. Otherwise continue now with partitioning
your disk by reading <uri link="#parted">Using parted to Partition your
Disk</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>How Many and How Big?</title>
<body>

<p>
The number of partitions is highly dependent on your environment. For instance,
if you have lots of users, you will most likely want to have your
<path>/home</path> separate as it increases security and makes backups easier.
If you are installing Gentoo to perform as a mailserver, your
<path>/var</path> should be separate as all mails are stored inside
<path>/var</path>. A good choice of filesystem will then maximise your
performance. Gameservers will have a separate <path>/opt</path> as most gaming
servers are installed there. The reason is similar for <path>/home</path>:
security and backups. You will definitely want to keep <path>/usr</path> big:
not only will it contain the majority of applications, the Portage tree alone
takes around 500 Mbyte excluding the various sources that are stored in it.
</p>

<p>
As you can see, it very much depends on what you want to achieve. Separate
partitions or volumes have the following advantages:
</p>

<ul>
<li>
  You can choose the best performing filesystem for each partition or volume
</li>
<li>
  Your entire system cannot run out of free space if one defunct tool is
  continuously writing files to a partition or volume
</li>
<li>
  If necessary, file system checks are reduced in time, as multiple checks can
  be done in parallel (although this advantage is more with multiple disks than
  it is with multiple partitions)
</li>
<li>
  Security can be enhanced by mounting some partitions or volumes read-only,
  nosuid (setuid bits are ignored), noexec (executable bits are ignored) etc.
</li>
</ul>

<p>
However, multiple partitions have one big disadvantage: if not configured
properly, you might result in having a system with lots of free space on one
partition and none on another. There is also a 15-partition limit for SCSI and
SATA.
</p>

<p>
As an example partitioning, we show you one for a 20GB disk, used as a
demonstration laptop (containing webserver, mailserver, gnome, ...):
</p>

<pre caption="Filesystem usage example">
$ <i>df -h</i>
Filesystem    Type    Size  Used Avail Use% Mounted on
/dev/hda5     ext3    509M  132M  351M  28% /
/dev/hda2     ext3    5.0G  3.0G  1.8G  63% /home
/dev/hda7     ext3    7.9G  6.2G  1.3G  83% /usr
/dev/hda8     ext3   1011M  483M  477M  51% /opt
/dev/hda9     ext3    2.0G  607M  1.3G  32% /var
/dev/hda1     ext2     51M   17M   31M  36% /boot
/dev/hda6     swap    516M   12M  504M   2% &lt;not mounted&gt;
<comment>(Unpartitioned space for future usage: 2 GB)</comment>
</pre>

<p>
<path>/usr</path> is rather full (83% used) here, but once
all software is installed, <path>/usr</path> doesn't tend to grow that much.
Although allocating a few gigabytes of disk space for <path>/var</path> may
seem excessive, remember that Portage uses this partition by default for
compiling packages. If you want to keep <path>/var</path> at a more reasonable
size, such as 1GB, you will need to alter your <c>PORTAGE_TMPDIR</c> variable
in <path>/etc/make.conf</path> to point to the partition with enough free space
for compiling extremely large packages such as OpenOffice.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="parted">
<title>Using parted to Partition your Disk</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
The following parts explain how to create the example partition layout
described previously, namely:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Partition</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><path>/dev/sda1</path></ti>
  <ti>EFI Boot partition</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><path>/dev/sda2</path></ti>
  <ti>Swap partition</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><path>/dev/sda3</path></ti>
  <ti>Root partition</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
Change your partition layout according to your own preference.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Viewing the Current Partition Layout</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>parted</c> is the GNU partition editor.
Fire up <c>parted</c> on your disk (in our example, we use
<path>/dev/sda</path>):
</p>

<pre caption="Starting parted">
# <i>parted /dev/sda</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once in <c>parted</c>, you'll be greeted with a prompt that looks like this:
</p>

<pre caption="parted prompt">
GNU Parted 1.6.22
Copyright (C) 1998 - 2005 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This program is free software, covered by the GNU General Public License.

This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without
even the implied warranty of MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the GNU
General Public License for more details.

Using /dev/sda
(parted)
</pre>

<p>
At this point one of the available commands is <c>help</c>, which you should use
if you want to see the other available commands.  Another command is
<c>print</c> which you should type next to display your disk's current partition
configuration:
</p>

<pre caption="An example partition configuration">
(parted) <i>print</i>
Disk geometry for /dev/sda: 0.000-34732.890 megabytes
Disk label type: gpt
Minor    Start       End     Filesystem  Name                  Flags
1          0.017    203.938  fat32                             boot
2        203.938   4243.468  linux-swap
3       4243.469  34724.281  ext3
</pre>

<p>
This particular configuration is very similar to the one that we recommend
above.  Note on the second line that the partition table is type is GPT.  If it
is different, then the ia64 system will not be able to boot from this disk.
For the sake of this guide we'll remove the partitions and create them anew.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Removing all Partitions</title>
<body>

<note>
Unlike fdisk and some other partitioning programs which postpone committing
changes until you give the write instruction, parted commands take effect
immediately.  So once you start adding and removing partitions, you can't
simply quit without writing them... they've already been written.
</note>

<p>
The easy way to remove all partitions and start fresh, which guarantees that we
are using the correct partition type, is to make a new partition table using the
<c>mklabel</c> command.  After you do this, you will have an empty GPT partition
table.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a new partition table">
(parted) <i>mklabel gpt</i>
(parted) <i>print</i>
Disk geometry for /dev/sda: 0.000-34732.890 megabytes
Disk label type: gpt
Minor    Start       End     Filesystem  Name                  Flags
</pre>

<p>
Now that the partition table is empty, we're ready to create the
partitions. We will use a default partitioning scheme as discussed previously.
Of course, don't follow these instructions to the letter if you don't want the
same partitioning scheme!
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Creating the EFI Boot Partition</title>
<body>

<p>
We first create a small EFI boot partition. This is required to be a FAT
filesystem in order for the ia64 firmware to read it.  Our example makes this
32 megabytes, which is appropriate for storing kernels and elilo configuration.
You can expect each ia64 kernel to be around 5 megabytes, so this configuration
leaves you some room to grow and experiment.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the boot partition">
(parted) <i>mkpart primary fat32 0 32</i>
(parted) <i>print</i>
Disk geometry for /dev/sda: 0.000-34732.890 megabytes
Disk label type: gpt
Minor    Start       End     Filesystem  Name                  Flags
1          0.017     32.000  fat32
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Creating the Swap Partition</title>
<body>

<p>
Let's now create the swap partition.  The classic size to make the swap
partition was twice the amount of RAM in the system.  In modern systems with
lots of RAM, this is no longer necessary.  For most desktop systems, a 512
megabyte swap partition is sufficient.  For a server, you should consider
something larger to reflect the anticipated needs of the server.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the swap partition">
(parted) <i>mkpart primary linux-swap 32 544</i>
(parted) <i>print</i>
Disk geometry for /dev/sda: 0.000-34732.890 megabytes
Disk label type: gpt
Minor    Start       End     Filesystem  Name                  Flags
1          0.017     32.000  fat32
2         32.000    544.000
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Creating the Root Partition</title>
<body>

<p>
Finally, let's create the root partition.  Our configuration will make the root
partition to occupy the rest of the disk.  We default to ext3, but you can use
ext2, jfs, reiserfs or xfs if you prefer.  The actual filesystem is not created
in this step, but the partition table contains an indication of what kind of
filesystem is stored on each partition, and it's a good idea to make the table
match your intentions.
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the root partition">
(parted) <i>mkpart primary ext3 544 34732.890</i>
(parted) <i>print</i>
Disk geometry for /dev/sda: 0.000-34732.890 megabytes
Disk label type: gpt
Minor    Start       End     Filesystem  Name                  Flags
1          0.017     32.000  fat32
2         32.000    544.000
3        544.000  34732.874
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Exiting parted</title>
<body>

<p>
To quit from parted, type <c>quit</c>.  There's no need to take a separate step
to save your partition layout since parted has been saving it all along.  As you
leave, parted gives you reminder to update your <c>/etc/fstab</c>, which we'll
do later in this guide.
</p>

<pre caption="Quit from parted">
(parted) <i>quit</i>
Information: Don't forget to update /etc/fstab, if necessary.
</pre>

<p>
Now that your partitions are created, you can now continue with <uri
link="#filesystems">Creating Filesystems</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section id="filesystems">
<title>Creating Filesystems</title>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your partitions are created, it is time to place a filesystem on them. 
If you don't care about what filesystem to choose and are happy with what we use
as default in this handbook, continue with <uri 
link="#filesystems-apply">Applying a Filesystem to a Partition</uri>.
Otherwise read on to learn about the available filesystems...
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Filesystems?</title>
<body>

<p>
The Linux kernel supports various filesystems. We'll explain ext2, ext3,
ReiserFS, XFS and JFS as these are the most commonly used filesystems on Linux
systems.
</p>

<p>
<b>vfat</b> is the MS-DOS filesystem, updated to allow long filenames.  It is
also the only filesystem type that the EFI firmware on ia64 systems understand.
The boot partition on ia64 systems should always be vfat, but for your data
partitions you should use one of the other filesystems listed below.
</p>

<p>
<b>ext2</b> is the tried and true Linux filesystem but doesn't have metadata
journaling, which means that routine ext2 filesystem checks at startup time can
be quite time-consuming. There is now quite a selection of newer-generation
journaled filesystems that can be checked for consistency very quickly and are
thus generally preferred over their non-journaled counterparts. Journaled
filesystems prevent long delays when you boot your system and your filesystem
happens to be in an inconsistent state.
</p>

<p>
<b>ext3</b> is the journaled version of the ext2 filesystem, providing metadata
journaling for fast recovery in addition to other enhanced journaling modes like
full data and ordered data journaling. ext3 is a very good and reliable
filesystem.
</p>

<p>
<b>ReiserFS</b> is a B*-tree based filesystem that has very good overall 
performance and greatly outperforms both ext2 and ext3 when dealing with small 
files (files less than 4k), often by a factor of 10x-15x. ReiserFS also scales 
extremely well and has metadata journaling. As of kernel 2.4.18+, ReiserFS is 
solid and usable as both general-purpose filesystem and for extreme cases such 
as the creation of large filesystems, the use of many small files, very large 
files and directories containing tens of thousands of files. 
</p>

<p>
<b>XFS</b> is a filesystem with metadata journaling which comes with a robust
feature-set and is optimized for scalability. We only recommend using this
filesystem on Linux systems with high-end SCSI and/or fibre channel storage and
an uninterruptible power supply. Because XFS aggressively caches in-transit data
in RAM, improperly designed programs (those that don't take proper precautions
when writing files to disk and there are quite a few of them) can lose a good
deal of data if the system goes down unexpectedly.
</p>

<p>
<b>JFS</b> is IBM's high-performance journaling filesystem. It has recently 
become production-ready and there hasn't been a sufficient track record to 
comment positively nor negatively on its general stability at this point.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection id="filesystems-apply">
<title>Applying a Filesystem to a Partition</title>
<body>

<p>
To create a filesystem on a partition or volume, there are tools available for 
each possible filesystem:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Filesystem</th>
  <th>Creation Command</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>vfat</ti>
  <ti><c>mkdosfs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ext2</ti>
  <ti><c>mke2fs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>ext3</ti>
  <ti><c>mke2fs -j</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>reiserfs</ti>
  <ti><c>mkreiserfs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>xfs</ti>
  <ti><c>mkfs.xfs</c></ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>jfs</ti>
  <ti><c>mkfs.jfs</c></ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
For instance, to have the boot partition (<path>/dev/sda1</path> in our
example) as vfat and the root partition (<path>/dev/sda3</path> in our example)
as ext3, you would run the following commands:
</p>

<pre caption="Applying a filesystem on a partition">
# <i>mkdosfs /dev/sda1</i>
mkdosfs 2.10 (22 Sep 2003)

# <i>mke2fs -j /dev/sda3</i>
mke2fs 1.36 (05-Feb-2005)
Filesystem label=
OS type: Linux
Block size=4096 (log=2)
Fragment size=4096 (log=2)
4382336 inodes, 8752348 blocks
437617 blocks (5.00%) reserved for the super user
First data block=0
268 block groups
32768 blocks per group, 32768 fragments per group
16352 inodes per group
Superblock backups stored on blocks: 
        32768, 98304, 163840, 229376, 294912, 819200, 884736, 1605632, 2654208, 
        4096000, 7962624

Writing inode tables: done                            
Creating journal (8192 blocks): done
Writing superblocks and filesystem accounting information: done

This filesystem will be automatically checked every 26 mounts or
180 days, whichever comes first.  Use tune2fs -c or -i to override.
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Activating the Swap Partition</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>mkswap</c> is the command that is used to initialize swap partitions:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating a Swap signature">
# <i>mkswap /dev/sda2</i>
</pre>

<p>
To activate the swap partition, use <c>swapon</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Activating the swap partition">
# <i>swapon /dev/sda2</i>
</pre>

<p>
Create and activate the swap with the commands mentioned above.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Mounting</title>
<body>

<p>
Now that your partitions are initialized and are housing a filesystem, it is
time to mount those partitions. Use the <c>mount</c> command. Don't forget to
create the necessary mount directories for every partition you created. As an
example we mount the root and boot partition:
</p>

<pre caption="Mounting the root partition">
# <i>mount /dev/sda3 /mnt/gentoo</i>
</pre>

<note>
Unlike some of the other architectures supported by Gentoo, <path>/boot</path>
is not mounted on ia64.  The reason for this is that the EFI boot partition will
be automatically mounted and written by the elilo command each time that you run
it.  Because of this, /boot resides on the root filesystem and is the storage
place for the kernels referenced by your elilo configuration.
</note>

<note>
If you want your <path>/tmp</path> to reside on a separate partition, be sure to
change its permissions after mounting: <c>chmod 1777 /mnt/gentoo/tmp</c>. This
also holds for <path>/var/tmp</path>.
</note>

<p>
We will also have to mount the proc filesystem (a virtual interface with the 
kernel) on <path>/proc</path>. But first we will need to place our files on the partitions.
</p>

<p>
Continue with <uri link="?part=1&amp;chap=5">Installing the Gentoo
Installation Files</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</sections>
