<section>
<subsection>
<title>Introduction to Block Devices</title>
<subsubsection>
<title>Block Devices</title>
<body>

<p>
We'll take a good look at disk-oriented aspects of Gentoo Linux
and Linux in general, including Linux filesystems, partitions and block devices.
Then, once you're familiar with the ins and outs of disks and filesystems,
you'll be guided through the process of setting up partitions and filesystems
for your Gentoo Linux installation.
</p>

<p>
To begin, we'll introduce <e>block devices</e>. The most famous block device is
probably the one that represents the first IDE drive in a Linux system, namely
<path>/dev/hda</path>. If your system uses SCSI drives, then your first hard
drive would be <path>/dev/sda</path>.
</p>

<p>
The block devices above represent an abstract interface to the disk. User
programs can use these block devices to interact with your disk without worrying
about whether your drives are IDE, SCSI or something else. The program can
simply address the storage on the disk as a bunch of contiguous,
randomly-accessible 512-byte blocks.
</p>

</body>
</subsubsection>
<subsubsection>
<title>Partitions and Slices</title>
<body>

<p>
Although it is theoretically possible to use a full disk to house your Linux
system, this is almost never done in practice. Instead, full disk block devices
are split up in smaller, more manageable block devices. On x86-based systems,
these are called <e>partitions</e>. Other architectures call those
<e>slices</e>.
</p>

</body>
</subsubsection>
<subsubsection>
<title>Partitions</title>
<body>

<p>
Partitions are only used on x86-based systems. They are divided in three types:
<e>primary</e>, <e>extended</e> and <e>logical</e>.
</p>

<p>
A <e>primary</e> partition is a partition of which the information is stored in
the MBR (master boot record). As an MBR is very small (512 bytes) only four
primary partitions can be defined (for instance, <path>/dev/hda1</path> to
<path>/dev/hda4</path>).
</p>

<p>
An <e>extended</e> partition is a special primary partition (meaning the
extended partition must be one of the four possible primary partitions) which
contains more partitions. Such a partition didn't exist in the beginning, but as
four partitions is too little, it is brought to life to extend this formatting
scheme without loosing backwards compatibility.
</p>

<p>
A <e>logical</e> partition is a partition inside the extended partition. Their
definitions aren't placed inside the MBR, but are declared inside the extended
partition. 
</p>

</body>
</subsubsection>
<subsubsection>
<title>Logical Volumes</title>
<body>

<p>
Some people might find partitions and slices too restrictive. If you feel the
same way, you should take a look at LVM -- the <e>Logical Volume Manager</e>.
</p>

<p>
With LVM, you create partitions (or slices) the normal way, but you won't use
them to house your Linux system. Instead, you add another layer of storage
(namely the LVM layer) on which you install Gentoo. But what are the benefits of
LVM?
</p>

<p>
With LVM you can easily resize the volumes on which you have installed Gentoo.
You can also take a snapshot of a volume without freezing the system, making
your backup strategy more transparent for the users (and less troublesome).
Another advantage is that you can add several disks to a single volume (meaning
if one of your volumes is low on free space, you can extend it without having to
copy over files). 
</p>

<p>
An LVM is structured in three abstract items. You have a <e>physical volume</e>,
which is a collection of partitions, slices or disks which you want to use for
LVM. Then you have a <e>volume group</e> to which you assign certain physical
volumes. This volume group contains several <e>logical volumes</e> which are 
some sort of virtual partitions.
</p>

</body>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Designing a Partitioning Scheme</title>
<body>

<p>
How to partition? Present default (<path>/dev/hda1, /dev/hda2,
/dev/hda3</path>) but also LVM. 
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Using fdisk on x86 to Partition your Disk</title>
<subsubsection>
<body>

<impo>
Only users with <e>x86</e> based systems should read this part.
</impo>

</body>
</subsubsection>
<subsubsection>
<title>Viewing the Current Partition Layout</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>fdisk</c> is a popular and powerful tool to split your disk into partitions
or slices. Throughout the rest of this section we will use partitions for both
partitions or slices. Fire up <c>fdisk</c> on your disk (in our example, we use
<path>/dev/hda</path>):
</p>

<pre caption="Starting fdisk">
# <i>fdisk /dev/hda</i>
</pre>

<p>
Once in <c>fdisk</c>, you'll be greeted with a prompt that looks like this:
</p>

<pre caption="fdisk prompt">
Command (m for help): 
</pre>

<p>
Type <c>p</c> to display your disk's current partition configuration:
</p>

<pre caption="An example partition configuration">
Command (m for help): <i>p</i>

Disk /dev/hda: 240 heads, 63 sectors, 2184 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 15120 * 512 bytes

Device Boot    Start       End    Blocks   Id  System
/dev/hda1             1        14    105808+  83  Linux
/dev/hda2            15        49    264600   82  Linux swap
/dev/hda3            50        70    158760   83  Linux
/dev/hda4            71      2184  15981840    5  Extended
/dev/hda5            71       209   1050808+  83  Linux
/dev/hda6           210       348   1050808+  83  Linux
/dev/hda7           349       626   2101648+  83  Linux
/dev/hda8           627       904   2101648+  83  Linux
/dev/hda9           905      2184   9676768+  83  Linux

Command (m for help): 
</pre>

<p>
This particular disk is configured to house seven Linux filesystems (each with a
corresponding partition listed as "Linux") as well as a swap partition (listed
as "Linux swap"). As you may have guessed, this example was for an x86-based
system. An example layout for a Sparc architectures is:
</p>

<pre caption="Another example partition configuration">
Command (m for help): <i>p</i>

Disk /dev/hda: 240 heads, 63 sectors, 2184 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 15120 * 512 bytes

Device    Flag    Start       End    Blocks   Id  System
/dev/hda1             1        14    105808+  83  Linux
/dev/hda2            15        49    264600   82  Linux swap
/dev/hda3             0        70    519168    5  Whole Disk
/dev/hda4            50        70    158760   83  Linux

Command (m for help): 
</pre>

<p>
This particular disk is configured to house two Linux filesystems (each with a
corresponding partition listed as "Linux") as well as a swap partition (listed
as "Linux swap").
</p>

</body>
</subsubsection>
<subsubsection>
<title>Clearing the Partition Scheme</title>
<body>

<p>
We will first remove all existing partitions from the disk. Type <c>d</c> to
delete a partition. For instance, to delete an existing <path>/dev/hda1</path>:
</p>

<pre caption="Deleting a partition">
Command (m for help): <i>d</i>
Partition number (1-4): <i>1</i>
</pre>

<p>
The partition has been scheduled for deletion. It will no longer show up if you
type <c>p</c>, but it will not be erased until your changes have been saved. If
you made a mistake and want to abort without saving your changes, type <c>q</c>
immediately and hit enter and your partition will not be deleted.
</p>

<p>
Now, assuming that you do indeed want to wipe out all the partitions on your
system, repeatedly type <c>p</c> to print out a partition listing and then type
<c>d</c> and the number of the partition to delete it. Eventually, you'll end 
up with a partition table with nothing in it:
</p>

<pre caption="An empty partition table">
Disk /dev/hda: 30.0 GB, 30005821440 bytes
240 heads, 63 sectors/track, 3876 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 15120 * 512 = 7741440 bytes

Device Boot    Start       End    Blocks   Id  System

Command (m for help):
</pre>

<p>
Now that the in-memory partition table is empty, we're ready to create the
partitions. We will use a default partitioning scheme as discussed previously.
Ofcourse, don't follow these instructions to the letter if you don't want the
same partitioning scheme!
</p>

</body>
</subsubsection>
<subsubsection>
<title>Creating the boot partition</title>
<body>

<p>
We first create a small boot partition. Type <c>n</c> to create a new partition,
then <c>p</c> to select a primary partition, followed by <c>1</c> to select the
first primary partition. When prompted for the first cylinder, hit enter. When
prompted for the last cylinder, type <c>+32M</c> to create a partition 32 Mbyte
in size:
</p>

<pre caption="Creating the boot partition">
Command (m for help): <i>n</i>
Command action
  e   extended
  p   primary partition (1-4)
<i>p</i>
Partition number (1-4): <i>1</i>
First cylinder (1-3876, default 1): <comment>(Hit Enter)</comment>
Using default value 1
Last cylinder or +size or +sizeM or +sizeK (1-3876, default 3876): <i>+32M</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now, when you type <c>p</c>, you should see the following partition printout:
</p>

<pre caption="Created boot partition">
Command (m for help): <i>p</i>

Disk /dev/hda: 30.0 GB, 30005821440 bytes
240 heads, 63 sectors/track, 3876 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 15120 * 512 = 7741440 bytes

Device Boot    Start       End    Blocks   Id  System
/dev/hda1          1        14    105808+  83  Linux
</pre>

</body>
</subsubsection>
<subsubsection>
<title>Creating the Swap Partition</title>
<body>

<p>
Let's now create the swap partition. To do this, type <c>n</c> to create a new 
partition, then <c>p</c> to tell fdisk that you want a primary partition. Then 
type <c>2</c> to create the second primary partition, <path>/dev/hda2</path> in
our case. When prompted for the first cylinder, hit enter. When prompted for 
the last cylinder, type <c>+512M</c> to create a partition 512MB in size. After
you've done this, type <c>t</c> to set the partition type, <c>2</c> to select 
the partition you just created and then type in <c>82</c> to set the partition 
type to "Linux Swap". After completing these steps, typing <c>p</c> should
display a partition table that looks similar to this:
</p>

<pre caption="Partition listing after creating a swap partition">
Command (m for help): <i>p</i>

Disk /dev/hda: 30.0 GB, 30005821440 bytes
240 heads, 63 sectors/track, 3876 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 15120 * 512 = 7741440 bytes

Device Boot    Start       End    Blocks   Id  System
/dev/hda1          1        14    105808+  83  Linux
/dev/hda2         15        81    506520   82  Linux swap
</pre>

</body>
</subsubsection>
<subsubsection>
<title>Creating the Root Partition</title>
<body>

<p>
Finally, let's create the root partition. To do this, type <c>n</c> to create a 
new partition, then <c>p</c> to tell fdisk that you want a primary partition. 
Then type <c>3</c> to create the third primary partition, <path>/dev/hda3</path>
in our case. When prompted for the first cylinder, hit enter. When prompted for
the last cylinder, hit enter to create a partition that takes up the rest of the
remaining space on your disk. After completing these steps, typing <c>p</c> 
should display a partition table that looks similar to this:
</p>

<pre caption="Partition listing after creating the root partition">
Command (m for help): <i>p</i>

Disk /dev/hda: 30.0 GB, 30005821440 bytes
240 heads, 63 sectors/track, 3876 cylinders
Units = cylinders of 15120 * 512 = 7741440 bytes

Device Boot    Start       End    Blocks   Id  System
/dev/hda1          1        14    105808+  83  Linux
/dev/hda2         15        81    506520   82  Linux swap
/dev/hda3         82      3876  28690200   83  Linux
</pre>


</body>
</subsubsection>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Using fdisk on Alpha to Partition your Disk</title>

</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Using fdisk on SPARC to Partition your Disk</title>

</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Using mac-fdisk on PPC to Partition your Disk</title>

</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Using fdisk on HPPA to Partition your Disk</title>

</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Optional: Using LVM</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>pvcreate</c>, <c>vgcreate</c>, <c>lvcreate</c>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Mounting</title>
<body>

<p>
Mount the created partitions under <path>/mnt/gentoo</path>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
