<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<sections>
<section>
<title>Documentation</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Congratulations! You now have a working Gentoo system. But where to go from
here? What are your options now? What to explore first? Gentoo provides its
users with lots of possibilities, and therefore lots of documented (and less
documented) features.
</p>

<p>
You should definately take a look at our <uri
link="/doc/en/portage-user.xml">Portage User Guide</uri> which explains how to
keep your software up to date, and how to install more software. If you want to
know everything about Portage (but you lack the confidence to read the
sourcecode :) you should read the <uri link="/doc/en/portage-manual.xml">Portage
Manual</uri> which is a very extensive look at Portage and Portage Internals.
</p>

<p>
If you want to know more about how USE interacts, read the <uri
link="/doc/en/use-howto.xml">USE Howto</uri> which introduces USE flags to you
and helps you decide what USE flags you need.
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in optimizing your system for desktop-use, or you want to
learn how to configure your system to be a full working desktop system, consult
our extensive <uri link="/doc/en/desktop.xml">Desktop Configuration Guide</uri>.
</p>

<p>
For a full listing of all our available documentation check out our <uri
link="/doc/en/index.xml">Documentation Resources</uri> page.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Online</title>
<body>

<p>
You are of course always welcome on our <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri> or on one of our many 
<uri link="/main/en/irc.xml">Gentoo IRC channels</uri>.
</p>

<p>
We also have several <uri 
link="/main/en/lists.xml">mailinglists</uri> open to all 
our users. Information on how to join is contained in that page.
</p>

<p>
We'll shut up now and let you enjoy your installation :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
</sections>
