<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/doc/en/handbook/index.xml,v 1.2 2003/11/15 13:53:33 swift Exp $ -->

<guide>
<title>Gentoo Handbook</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="swift@gentoo.org">Sven Vermeulen</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The Gentoo Handbook is an effort to centralise documentation into a coherent
handbook. Information that cannot be inserted coherently is not taken into
account.
</abstract>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>November 6, 2003</date>
<license/>

<chapter>
<title>The Gentoo Handbook Effort</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Welcome to the Gentoo Handbook page. This page will give you some explanation
about the <uri link="handbook.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri> and should answer most
of your questions regarding the handbook. We will talk about the ideas behind
the handbook, its current status, the future plans, how bugreports are handled
etc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>View the Handbook</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Currently, we only provide the handbook in online-accessible form. We are
working on a PDF-version.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Format</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti><uri link="handbook.xml">HTML</uri></ti>
  <ti>Perfect for Online-viewing</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Information about the handbook</title>
<section>
<title>Goal</title>
<body>

<p>
The goal of the Gentoo Handbook is to create a coherent document that describes
every possible aspect of Gentoo Linux. It combines already existing guides in
one, consistent book so that the same document is used for every possible
architecture, every install, every user. This not only makes it easier for us to
maintain, but also for the user to see that the differences are slim, and that
other architectures are not seen as a seperate entity.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Status</title>
<body>

<p>
At this time, the first part on <uri link="handbook.xml?part=1">Installing
Gentoo</uri> is finished and has had the first review. It should be production
ready, but it is not the official installation guide yet. For this to happen we
need much more user input on possible errors, difficulties etc.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Future</title>
<body>

<p>
When the part on the Gentoo Installation is official, we will start with
integrating existing Gentoo-specific documentation in the handbook. This
includes how software is managed, how the init-system works, how to configure
the various services etc. This will also include the existing <uri
link="/doc/en/portage-user.xml">Portage User</uri> and <uri
link="/doc/en/portage-manual.xml">Portage Manual</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Reporting bugs and enhancement requests</title>
<body>

<p>
If you find a bug in the handbook, please visit our <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">Gentoo Linux Bugzilla</uri> and create a bug for
<e>Docs-user</e>, Component <e>Handbook</e>. 
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
