<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<news gentoo="yes" category="main">
	<poster>drobbins</poster>
	<date>19 Jan 2002</date>
	<title>Gentoo news and Linux/Athlon CPU issue found</title>
	<summary>
<p><b>Portage 1.8.5+ (our ports system) now has a number of really nice new
features</b>, including faster merging, path sandboxing, <c>emerge update</c>,
an <c>emerge update --world</c> functionality.  You can use <c>emerge
update</c> to update the "core" packages on your system, or use <c>emerge
update --world</c> to update all packages on your system to the most recent
version.  <b>Also note that Portage can now be accessed using anonymous CVS in
addition to rsync.</b> You can find more information on how to do this in <uri
link="http://lists.gentoo.org/pipermail/gentoo-dev/2002-January/008954.html">this
gentoo-dev mailing list post</uri>.</p>

<p><b>[corrections made 05 Feb 2002 -DR]</b> That's the good news.  The bad
news is that a an Athlon/AGP stability problem has been discovered that affects
Linux 2.4. </p>

	</summary>
	
	<body>

<p><b>Portage 1.8.5+ (our ports system) now has a number of really nice new
features</b>, including faster merging, path sandboxing, <c>emerge update</c>,
an <c>emerge update --world</c> functionality.  You can use <c>emerge
update</c> to update the "core" packages on your system, or use <c>emerge
update --world</c> to update all packages on your system to the most recent
version.  <b>Also note that Portage can now be accessed using anonymous CVS in
addition to rsync.</b> You can find more information on how to do this in <uri
link="http://lists.gentoo.org/pipermail/gentoo-dev/2002-January/008954.html">this
gentoo-dev mailing list post</uri>.</p>

<p><b>[corrections made 05 Feb 2002 -DR]</b> That's the good news.  The bad
news is that a <b>an Athlon CPU bug has been discovered, and it affects Linux
2.4</b>.  Here are the details.  As you may know, x86 systems have
traditionally managed memory using 4K pages.  However, with the introduction of
the Pentium processor, Intel added a new feature called <i>extended paging</i>,
which allows 4Mb pages to be used instead.  Here's the problem -- <b>many
Athlon and Duron CPUs experience memory corruption when extended paging is used
in conjunction with AGP.  And, this problem hits us because Linux 2.4 kernels
compiled with a <c>Pentium-Classic</c> or higher <c>Processor family</c> kernel
configuration setting will automatically take advantage of extended paging (for
kernel hackers out there, this is the <c>X86_FEATURE_PSE</c> constant defined
in <c>include/asm-i386/cpufeature.h</c>.)</b></p>

<p> Fortunately, there is a quick and easy fix for this problem.  If you have
been experiencing lockups on your Athlon, Duron or Athlon MP system when using
AGP video, try passing the <c>mem=nopentium</c> option to your kernel (using
GRUB or LILO) at boot-time.  This tells Linux to go back to using 4K pages,
avoiding this CPU bug.  In addition, it should also be possible to avoid this
problem by not using AGP on affected systems.  As soon as I discovered that
this CPU bug existed (which happened, unfortunately, because <e>my</e> CPU has
the bug), I informed kernel hacker Andrew Morton of the issue; he put me in
touch with Alan Cox.  Alan is going to try to add some kind of Athlon/AGP CPU
bug detection code to the kernel so that it will be able to auto-downgrade to
4K pages when necessary. <b>[Update: there seems to be some agreement on the
Linux fix needed to solve this problem, but no one has created an actual patch
as of 05 Feb 2002]</b></p>


<p>The unfortunate thing about this situation is that AMD and others have known
of this issue since <b>September 2000</b>.  In fact, AMD's CPG technical
marketing division announced the issue on September 21, 2000 in a technical
note entitled <i>Microsoft Windows 2000 Patch for AGP Applications on AMD
Athlon and AMD Duron Processors</i> (Technical Note TN17 revision 1).  And, the
kind folks at AMD even created a simple patch for Windows 2000 that disables
extended paging by tweaking the registry.  However, apparently AMD didn't
realize that Linux 2.4 also uses extended paging when the kernel is compiled
with a <c>Pentium-Classic</c> or higher <c>Processor family</c> kernel
configuration setting.   And, it looks like no one in the Linux community
noticed that this "Microsoft Windows 2000/AGP Athlon/Duron issue" also applied
to Linux 2.4 systems, probably because it was presented by AMD technical
marketing as just that -- a Windows 2000-related AGP problem. An unfortunate
miscommunication, which has resulted in lots of problems for Athlon, Duron and
Athlon MP users.  <i>Here's something that's even more unsettling -- consider
what kind of Linux users actually use AGP.  That's right -- desktop users.  And
in what area has Linux been struggling?  Yes, the desktop.  One wonders how
many negative desktop Linux experiences have resulted from this unfortunate
problem.</i>  I don't know if any particular party is to blame for this issue.
After all, AMD <e>did</e> prominently announce this issue when it was
discovered.  But due to an apparently unfortunate series of events, us Linux
people never benefitted from this knowledge.  But Microsoft Windows 2000 and XP
users did.  Let's hope that all parties involved can keep things like this from
happening in the future.</p>

<p>The good news is that we now have the information to work around this
problem, and (hopefully) soon the Linux kernel itself will be able to detect
and adjust for this particular issue.  Many thanks to Terrence Ripperda of
NVIDIA, Andrew Morton and Alan Cox for informing/communicating/investigating
this issue respectively. :)</p>

	</body>
</news>
