<?xml version='1.0'?>

<news gentoo="no" category="linux">
	<poster>drobbins</poster>
	<date>25 Feb 2002</date>
	<title>Guru Medication Error -- missing patches?</title>

<summary>
<p><b>You've probably heard rumors and grumblings about how Linux kernel
development has severe problems, is about to implode, or even worse.</b>
We'll leave it up to you to decide whether these rumors are true.
However, we'd like to bring to your attention a problem that definitely
does exist and needs fixing.  What is it?  Large Linux companies like <uri link="http://www.redhat.com">Red Hat</uri>
and <uri link="http://www.mandrake.com">MandrakeSoft</uri> put a lot of effort into creating really spiffy patched
kernels.  Sometimes, obvious bugs are fixed along the way.  The problem is that many of these no-brainer patches
languish in their respective kernel source SRPMS and never get incorporated into the stock kernel.  <b>While this is
certainly not a violation of the GPL on the part of the distro companies (the GPL requires that modifications be made <e>available</e>, but does not
require that anyone is <e>informed</e> of these modifications or that important bug fixes are actually applied), it certainly has a negative impact on Linux as a whole.</b>
In effect, if you do not use distro X or Y, then <e>you do not benefit from these fixes.</e>  Without focusing on 
assigning blame, we'd like to encourage everyone to do what they can to get good patches flowing to Marcelo so he can
incorporate them into the stock kernel.  Here's an example of a "no brainer" patch from Mandrake's cooker kernel that
was created nearly a year ago (back in the era of 2.4.3-ac4) yet has still not been incorporated into the stock kernel.
Was it never submitted?  Was it forgotten or lost?  I don't particularly care, as long as this general situation
gets addressed.  No-brainer patch follows...
</p>
</summary>

<body>

<p><b>You've probably heard rumors and grumblings about how Linux kernel
development has severe problems, is about to implode, or even worse.</b> We'll
leave it up to you to decide whether these rumors are true.  However, we'd like
to bring to your attention a problem that definitely does exist and needs
fixing.  What is it?  Large Linux companies like <uri
link="http://www.redhat.com">Red Hat</uri> and <uri
link="http://www.mandrake.com">MandrakeSoft</uri> put a lot of effort into
creating really spiffy patched kernels.  Sometimes, obvious bugs are fixed
along the way.  The problem is that many of these no-brainer patches languish
in their respective kernel source SRPMS and never get incorporated into the
stock kernel.  <b>While this is certainly not a violation of the GPL on the
part of the distro companies (the GPL requires that modifications be made
<e>available</e>, but does not require that anyone is <e>informed</e> of these
modifications or that important bug fixes are actually applied), it certainly
has a negative impact on Linux as a whole.</b> In effect, if you do not use
distro X or Y, then <e>you do not benefit from these fixes.</e>  Without
focusing on assigning blame, we'd like to encourage everyone to do what they
can to get good patches flowing to Marcelo so he can incorporate them into the
stock kernel.  Here's an example of a "no brainer" patch from Mandrake's cooker
kernel that was created nearly a year ago (back in the era of 2.4.3-ac4) yet
has still not been incorporated into the stock kernel.  Was it never submitted?
Was it forgotten or lost?  I don't particularly care, as long as
this general situation gets addressed.  No-brainer patch follows...  </p>

<pre>
--- linux/mm/bootmem.c.chmou    Thu Apr 12 04:13:23 2001
+++ linux/mm/bootmem.c  Thu Apr 12 04:13:57 2001
@@ -86,7 +86,8 @@
 
        if (end > bdata->node_low_pfn)
                BUG();
-       for (i = sidx; i &lt; eidx; i++)
+       /* subtle: eidx is the last index we need to reserve */
+       for (i = sidx; i &lt;= eidx; i++)
                if (test_and_set_bit(i, bdata-&gt;node_bootmem_map))
                        printk("hm, page %08lx reserved twice.\n", i*PAGE_SIZE);
 }
</pre>

<p> While this patch may not be very significant, it doesn't take a genius to
figure out that 20 or 30 similar missing patches could have a big effect on the
quality of the Linux kernel.  And of course, many of these ignored fixes <e>are
significant</e>.  Ignoring bug fixes wastes user and developer time, and makes
Linux a not-so-fun place to be.  If we're truly concerned about having a
quality kernel, happy users and continued growth in the desktop, server and
enterprise markets, then we need to treat every single bug fix as a prized
possession.  A certain number of man hours went in to tracking down and
producing each fix, and if they are forgotten or ignored, then those man hours
were wasted.  And if these fixes only appear in "special" kernels, then the
benefit of these fixes is diminished incredibly.  It is already difficult
enough to investigate a problem a user is having, track it down, and create a
patch in order to fix it.  In fact, the Linux community is already pretty bad
at doing this.  So, if already-tracked-down and verified fixes get ignored --
well, we simply can't allow that to happen and expect to have a viable kernel.
In order for Linux to gain maximum benefit from its distributed development
model, it's absolutely essential that nothing falls through the cracks.  We ask
that everyone do their part.</p>

<p>To help:
<ul>
<li>Join the Kernel Janitor project effort: <uri>http://kerneljanitors.org</uri></li>
<li>Stop by #kerneljanitor on irc.openprojects.net</li>
<li>Dig through an up-to-date production kernel from a major distro; submit essential patches upstream</li>
</ul>
</p>

</body>

</news>


