<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<news gentoo="no" category="linux">
	<poster>drobbins</poster>
	<date>26 Feb 2002</date>
	<title>Guru Medication Error Redux</title>

<summary>

<p><b>Hiya Slashdotters!  From the Slashdot comments related to the original
"Guru Meditation Error -- missing patches?" news item, I see that many of you
still doubt that this missing patch problem actually exists.  Fair enough.
After all, what exactly was fixed by that bootmem patch mentioned
previously?</b> In a Slashdot post, Alan Cox contends that the patch was
submitted by MandrakeSoft, but couldn't be proved to be correct so it was not
applied.  Yet in Mandrake's own SRPM, the bootmem patch has a one line comment
that reads <c>Fix an off by one error that results in memory overwrites</c>.
Now, I would contend that MandrakeSoft isn't simply adding this patch to their
kernel for the thrill of it, but it is in fact doing it to fix a problem
encountered in the field.  After all, they took the time out of their busy
lives to track down the problem and create a patch for it in the first place.
Why patch what isn't broken?  But in all honesty, I don't know; since I'm not
in contact with the kernel developers at MandrakeSoft, I'm not one to say.
</p>
<p>
<b>Comments from Andrea Archangeli:</b> <e>"While I agree on parts of the article,
the patch you mention is buggy, if you find it in the Mandrake kernel, that's a
bug in Mandrake that wastes one more page of ram than necessary (it's an
harmless bug though)."</e></p>

<p><b>While I chose a bad example for my original post, the problem I
described is certainly very real.  It took me all of 15 minutes browsing the
~50 Mandrake kernel patches to find a significant hardware compatibility
patch that is not yet in the -ac, -aa or stock kernels.  Without this patch,
many modern Athlon/VIA 82c686b systems will not work correctly with ATAPI
ZIP250 drives.  Of the kernel sources I looked at, this fix only appears to be available in the Mandrake kernel.
</b> Click on "full story" for in-depth information.</p>

</summary>

<body>
<p><b>Hiya Slashdotters!  From the Slashdot comments related to the original
"Guru Meditation Error -- missing patches?" news item, I see that many of you
still doubt that this missing patch problem actually exists.  Fair enough.
After all, what exactly was fixed by that bootmem patch mentioned
previously?</b> In a Slashdot post, Alan Cox contends that the patch was
submitted by MandrakeSoft, but couldn't be proved to be correct so it was not
applied.  Yet in Mandrake's own SRPM, the bootmem patch has a one line comment
that reads <c>Fix an off by one error that results in memory overwrites</c>.
Now, I would contend that MandrakeSoft isn't simply adding this patch to their
kernel for the thrill of it, but it is in fact doing it to fix a problem
encountered in the field.  After all, they took the time out of their busy
lives to track down the problem and create a patch for it in the first place.
Why patch what isn't broken?  But in all honesty, I don't know; since I'm not
in contact with the kernel developers at MandrakeSoft, I'm not one to say.
</p>
<p>
<b>Comments from Andrea Archangeli:</b> <e>"While I agree on parts of the article,
the patch you mention is buggy, if you find it in the Mandrake kernel, that's a
bug in Mandrake that wastes one more page of ram than necessary (it's an
harmless bug though)."</e></p>

<p><b>While I chose a bad example for my original post, the problem I
described is certainly very real.  It took me all of 15 minutes browsing the
~50 Mandrake kernel patches to find a significant hardware compatibility
patch that is not yet in the -ac, -aa or stock kernels.  Without this patch,
many modern Athlon/VIA 82c686b systems will not work correctly with ATAPI
ZIP250 drives.  Of the kernel sources I looked at, this fix only appears to be available in the Mandrake kernel.
</b> Click on "full story" for in-depth information.</p>

<p>For more information on this VIA 82c686b/ATAPI ZIP250 problem,
visit <uri link="http://paulbristow.net/linux/idefloppy.html">The IDE-floppy Driver Documentation for Linux page</uri>.  On the page, there is <uri link="http://paulbristow.net/linux/via-patch-paul">a patch for kernel 2.4.14</uri> that solves this bug.  In the patch, the author describes the problem as follows:</p>
<pre>
+ * Ver 0.98  Nov  8 01   There is a bug with the Via82c686b chip when used with
+ *		an ATAPI ZIP drive. The problem occurs when issuing write 
+ *		commands to the drive, and it doesn't happen with the promise
+ *		pdc20265 chipset. Both Skip Gaede (sgaede@mediaone.net) and
+ *		Timo Teras (timo.teras@iki.fi) discovered that including
+ *		a delay fixed the problem. Gadi Oxman suggested using the timer
+ *		queue instead of counting, and Timo implemented code to limit
+ *		the delay to machines having the via chipset. A delay of 50
+ *		msec works on my system. The variable ticks is exposed 
+ *		in /proc/ide/hdx/settings. Each tick is 10 msec. If ticks is
+ *		set to zero, the driver reverts to the old algorithm. --Skip
</pre>

<p>Later in the patch, a delay is added to the code as follows:</p>
<pre>
+/* 
+ * default delay for VIA chipset (50 ms, or 5 ticks)
+ * This value is exposed as the variable ticks and may be adjusted if necessary.
+ * On my system, a 1200 mhz Athlon with the Asus A7V133 board. this is the minimum 
+ * delay. If set to zero, the standard algorithm is used. Note: my board also has a 
+ * Promise PDC20265 (ATA100) controller. The ZIP drive works fine on the other chipset.
+ */
+#define IDEFLOPPY_TICKS_DELAY		((50 * HZ) / 1000)	
+
</pre>

<p>For most kernels, this will result in <c>IDEFLOPPY_TICKS_DELAY</c> set to <c>5</c>, since
<c>HZ</c> is normally set to <c>100</c>.  And also notice that in the patch comments, the author
points out that <e>a setting of 5 is the minimum delay necessary to get his ZIP250 working with
his Asus A7V133 board (a popular board)</e>.  So, what ide-floppy.c fixes are in the various
kernel patches/releases out there?  Here's a table of the delay setting used in various patches:
</p>

<table>
<tr><th>Kernel release</th><th>IDEFLOPPY_TICKS_DELAY value</th></tr>
<tr><ti>2.4.18 (stock)</ti><ti>(none)</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>Andrea Archangeli 2.4.18-rc4-aa1</ti><ti>(none)</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>Alan Cox 2.4.19-pre1-ac1</ti><ti><c>3</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>Red Hat Rawhide 2.4.17-0.18</ti><ti><c>3</c></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>Mandrake Cooker 2.4.17.20mdk-1-1mdk</ti><ti><c>5</c></ti></tr>
</table>

<p>Based upon a simple and logical interpretation of this data, it would seem
that if you have affected hardware and use a <e>stock or -aa</e> kernel, you will
experience problems with your ZIP250 (2.4.18 and 2.4.14's <c>ide-floppy.c</c>
are almost completely identical, except for a single <c>#ifdef</c>).  If you
use a recent -ac or Rawhide kernel, you <e>may or may not</e> experience
problems, and if you use a Mandrake kernel then you will most likely <e>not</e>
experience problems with your ZIP250.  Even if the -ac and rawhide kernels
contain additional fixes so that a delay of 3 will work on all systems, their
<c>3</c> setting does not scale if the <c>HZ</c> value of your kernel changes.
And even if a flat setting of <c>3</c> is simply not an issue and works for
everyone, then it's still the case that those using stock or -aa kernels will not
have this fix at all and thus will still have problems.  At least, this is my
interpretation of the data.  Feel free to compare the various sources and
verify this for yourself.  </p>

<p>I feel that this simple example demonstrates that we <e>could</e> do a
better job getting important patches into the stock kernel in a more timely
manner.  As you can see, this particular patch was released by Paul Bristow on
November 8, 2001.  I'm writing this editorial on February 26, 2002, and people
who use the stock and -aa (and very likely -ac and Rawhide) kernels are still
going to be bitten by this bug.  And, this means that as the Gentoo Linux
development lead, I am still forced to scavenge for patches from Mandrake, Red
Hat and others in order to ensure that the Gentoo Linux kernel works for as
many people as possible.</p>

<p>In closing, I also want to make it clear that I am not trying to bash those
kernel developers who work for major distros and develop these patches.
Obviously, they are extremely valued members of the Linux community.  In fact,
they have a unique role in the Linux community.  Because they work for major
distros, they must address real problems that their customers face in the real
world, ensuring that their particular kernel works perfectly for the greatest
number of possible users.  Having a kernel that works for 95% of their
users isn't good enough.  And the large distro companies are kept accountable
as well -- if their kernel doesn't work, <e>they</e> look bad because their
logo is on the CD, and <e>they</e> risk the possibility that the user may try
<e>another</e> distro or OS in hopes of better results.  Because of this, I'd
contend that the bulk of patches included in Red Hat, Mandrake and other "big
name" distros are generally focused on addressing problems that real users
experience in the field -- they are about helping users.  Yes, there are
certainly <e>some</e> unnecessary patches and <e>a few</e> that are purely
experimental or performance-enhancing.  But the majority of them are there to
fix stuff.  All I ask is that we ensure that these real-world user-oriented
fixes make it in to the stock kernel so that all Linux users, no matter what
distribution they happen to use, can benefit from them.</p>

</body>

</news>


