<?xml version='1.0'?>

<news gentoo="yes" category="moo">
	<poster>drobbins</poster>
	<date>29 Nov 2002</date>
	<title>Miscellaneous Yummy News</title>
<body>

<p><b>The Gentoo Linux 1.4 release is planned for some time in late December
2002.</b> Thanks to our first corporate sponsorship, I'm now able to work on
Gentoo Linux full-time. Right now, I'm catching up on a big back-log of work
like our transition to a new server infrastructure, which included a move to a
new mailing list manager (apologies for the bumpy ride, searchable mailing list
archives will be online soon) and new <uri
link="http://www.axkit.org">AxKit</uri> XML application server for the Web
site. The most significant task remaining before 1.4 is released is the
creation of an enhanced version of our LiveCD for x86 systems.  The x86 LiveCD
is one of the few parts of Gentoo Linux that is still developed by me
exclusively. As my back-log of work gets whittled away, I'll have time to get
x86 LiveCD-ng ready and then get our capable
development team involved in its development and maintainance.</p>

<p><b>Recent developments in the Gentoo Linux world include the addition of
"fakeroot" (non-root building) to Portage by J. Robert Ray</b>, as well as
continued expert maintenance and development of Portage by Nick Jones. Stefan
Jones (unrelated to Nick, as far as we know :) is spearheading an effort to add
flexible and safe library prelinking support to Gentoo Linux, which will likely
be an option for Gentoo Linux 1.4. In addition, Dan Armak and the KDE team are
getting ready for KDE 3.1, and it looks like 3.1 may be included in Gentoo
Linux 1.4 as well. On the "future plans" front, there is discussion about using
XML for our ebuild ChangeLogs, as well as plans to get Gentoo Linux Security
Announcements available on the Web site.</p>

<p>On the articles front, <uri
link="http://www-106.ibm.com/developerworks/linux/library/l-fs13/">Part 2 of my
EVMS series</uri> is now online at IBM developerWorks. Also, I am now writing
articles for <b>Intel</b>. To find them, go to <uri>http://www.intel.com</uri>
and search for "Daniel Robbins". You may find my two-part <e>Stateful iptables
firewalls</e> series to be useful if you'd like to learn how to design a
stateful Linux firewall from scratch -- and what
all those netfilter <c>iptables</c> commands actually do :)</p>

</body>
</news>


