<?xml version='1.0'?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<news gentoo="yes" category="moo">
	<poster>drobbins</poster>
	<date>24 Apr 2002</date>
	<title>CheapBytes now selling Gentoo Linux CDs</title>
<body>
<p>
<b><uri link="http://cart.cheapbytes.com/cgi-bin/cart/0070010805">CheapBytes is now selling</uri> Gentoo Linux/x86 1.1a i686 CDs for $5 USD apiece! :)</b>  Note that this CD will allow a build from scratch for *all* systems, but also has pre-built stuff for i686+ CPUs.  We plan to add more CD offerings (sources, pre-built binaries, Gentoo/PPC and Sparc) in the near-future, so stay tuned.  In the meantime, being able to order our latest CD for $5 ain't too shabby :)</p>

<p><b>Gentoo/Sparc status update:</b> Thanks to Maarten Thibaut, Gentoo Linux/Sparc and Sparc64 development is moving along quite well and Gentoo Linux/Sparc and Sparc64 were recently mentioned on the <uri link="http://www.ultralinux.org">UltraLinux</uri> site.  For those interested, Gentoo Linux/Sparc installation tarballs can be gotten from <uri link="http://www.ibiblio.org/gentoo/releases/build/1.1a/">ibiblio</uri> (as well as our mirrors.)  Sparc64 tarballs, a Sparc ISO and (I hope!) documentation are being worked on and will be available in the near future.  Thanks again to Maarten for getting Gentoo/Sparc and Sparc64 off the ground!</p>

<p>I'd also like to alert everyone to the many new <uri link="/index-docs.html">documentation resources</uri> on the site.  For your convenience, these resources are also listed on the left side of the main gentoo.org page.  We have new documentation about <uri link="/doc/use-howto.html">USE variables</uri>, <uri link="/doc/eclass-howto.html">eclasses</uri> (creating OOP-like inherited ebuilds), <uri link="/doc/java.html">how Java is set up</uri> under Gentoo Linux, enhancing <uri link="/doc/gentoo-security.html">Gentoo Linux security</uri>, <uri link="/doc/gentooppc-quickstart.html">Gentoo Linux/PPC installation</uri>, documentation on our <uri link="/doc/rc-scripts.html">rc-scripts</uri> as well as important updates to existing documentation.  We also have a bunch of new IRC channels listed on the left side of our main page for your chatting pleasure.  Enjoy!
</p>

</body>
</news>


