<?xml version='1.0'?>

<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<news gentoo="yes" category="gentoo">
<poster>swift</poster>
<date>31 December 2004</date>
<title>Moving into 2005</title>

<summary>
The last GWN has shown us what an entire year can bring to a distribution such
as Gentoo. We have grown, expanded, and evolved, yet we remained the same 
flexible distribution that we always were. We would like to thank everyone 
involved for all their efforts, wish them the best for 2005, and hope that 
we can continue to work closely to improve Gentoo even more.
</summary>

<body>
<p>
<b>
The last <uri link="/news/en/gwn/20041229-newsletter.xml">GWN</uri> has shown 
us what an entire year can bring to a distribution such as Gentoo. We have 
grown, expanded, and evolved, yet we remained the same flexible distribution 
that we always were. We would like to thank everyone involved for all their
efforts, wish them the best for 2005, and hope that 
we can continue to work closely to improve Gentoo even more.
</b>
</p>

<p>
First of all, we would like to thank you, the Gentoo user, for your continuous
belief in Gentoo. It is because of the high requirements that you have 
that we innovate. Keep raising the bar, and we will keep improving 
our distribution. We welcome all feedback, all bugreports 
&lt;<uri>http://bugs.gentoo.org</uri>&gt;, all thoughts, and all ideas
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/index.xml</uri>&gt; for improvement.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank our community for their everlasting dynamism.
Thanks to them our forums &lt;<uri>http://forums.gentoo.org</uri>&gt; are a
well-known source for fast and accurate support. Thanks to them, our
mailinglists &lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/lists.xml</uri>&gt; are 
filled with ideas and productive discussions. It is for our community that we 
live and we are grateful for the faith that the community has in us.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank Daniel Robbins for the wonderful distribution that he
created and shaped, and for the official Gentoo Store 
&lt;<uri>http://store.gentoo.org</uri>&gt; he currently runs. It is 
because of his vision that Gentoo exists. We wish him and his family the 
best for 2005.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank all Package Maintainers 
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/metastructure/herds/herds.xml</uri>&gt; 
for their efforts to keep our Portage tree &lt;<uri>http://packages.gentoo.org</uri>&gt;
up to date and filled with amazing software titles. These developers
are sometimes under great pressure to update their package, yet
they continue to work with dedication and precision.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank all Porting Teams 
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/base/index.xml</uri>&gt; for their 
constant efforts to get Gentoo to run on various architectures. Thanks to 
your actions, we have support for x86, PowerPC, PowerPC64, Sparc64, MIPS, 
AMD64, HPPA and Alpha with work on the way for ARM, and IA64.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank the Portage developers 
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/portage/index.xml</uri>&gt; 
for their innovative approach to software management and 
maintenance. With each new release we find advancements on existing actions 
and new features. Every time we again find groundbreaking improvements
implemented in this core application, we must remember that these developments
are made by people who are giving their time to make our computer experience
better.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank the Documentation developers 
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/gdp/index.xml</uri>&gt;
for their everlasting work on the successful documentation that
Gentoo produces, and the translation teams for the tremendous work they put in
the internationalisation of our documentation. You guide our users through the
wonderful world of Gentoo - keep up the good job!
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank the Infrastructure developers 
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/infrastructure/index.xml</uri>&gt;, and
mirror admins who keep our distribution running. The results of their 
endeavours are visible every day by the availability of our website, 
forums, bugtracking, mailinglist, mirrors, CVS server, etc. Not everybody 
knows that this is a full-time job. Thank you very much.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank everyone involved in our Release Engineering process 
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/index.xml</uri>&gt; for the 
howling energy they put in each new release, in the time-consuming testing and
verification of the release media, and the perpetual support through various
channels for our LiveCDs. Our appreciation goes with you and your work.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank the Development Relations project 
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/index.xml</uri>&gt; for their hard
work in recruitment, developer training, and their governing hand which resolves
disputes between developers time and time again. Your indispensable work is
frequently target of flames, yet we can't thank you enough for your perseverance
without which Gentoo would stall. Thank you very much.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank the developers that take part in the diverse amount of
Projects &lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/index.xml</uri>&gt; that 
improve Gentoo on several fields, ranging from Desktop experience
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/desktop/index.xml</uri>&gt; over the 
Security &lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/security/index.xml</uri>&gt; 
and Hardened &lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/hardened/index.xml</uri>&gt;
initiatives to the ongoing maintenance and development of kernel trees 
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/kernel/index.xml</uri>&gt;.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank the <uri
link="/news/en/gwn/20041229-newsletter.xml#doc_chap3">GWN crew</uri> for their
unceasing dynamism and never-ending work they put in each Weekly Newsletter
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/news/en/gwn/gwn.xml</uri>&gt;. Your work is 
frequently the source of information that our users consult for the Gentoo 
hilights and related news. You always work under pressure to get the next 
release available for the next deadline. Thank you very much.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank all upstream developers, without whom this project would
be impossible. It is you who make GNU/Linux possible, and you who develop the
various packages included within Gentoo. Thank you.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank our Sponsors
&lt;<uri>http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/sponsors.xml</uri>&gt; for
their trust in Gentoo which help us improve and maintain the distribution we 
all love. Their contributions help us to remain a top-distribution, now and
later. 
</p>

<p>
And finally, we would like to thank everyone we forgot to mention who
contributed to Gentoo in many, many ways. You are truely what gives a Free
Software project it's appealing charm. Thank you very much.
</p>

<p>
And of course, our best wishes for 2005 to all of you!
</p>

</body>
</news>
