<?xml version='1.0'?>

<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<news gentoo="yes" category="main">
<poster>Jeffrey Forman</poster>
<date>30 November 2004</date>
<title>Gentoo Linux 2005.0 Story Clarification</title>

<body>

<p>
As many of you already know, there was a <uri link="http://news.zdnet.co.uk/software/linuxunix/0,39020390,39175014,00.htm">recent article</uri> regarding the 2004.3 and 2005.0 releases posted on the ZDNet UK web site. In this article, the reporter presented much of the information given to her by Chris Gianelloni incorrectly. Chris does not think Mrs. Marson did this intentionally but rather out of a lack of understanding of some of the things she was told. Although the 2005.0 release will include an X-based experimental LiveCD, it will not be the primary release. The <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/">Release Engineering</uri> team plans to release 2005.0 just like 2004.3, with minimal, universal, and package CDs.</p>

<p>Another thing mentioned in the article was a graphical installer. Although there are plans on having a <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/installer/index.xml">graphical installer for Gentoo</uri>, it is far from complete. Chris told Mrs. Marson that there would be a limited-functionality version of this installer on the experimental CD that would support AMD64 and x86. It will most likely be curses-based, or possibly GTK+, if the interface is completed, and it will not have any of the enterprise-ready features, such as machine cloning. At one point, Mrs. Marson quotes Chris as saying, "The graphical installer will have lots of facilities like Red Hat kickstart. You can create a script, containing details on, for example, what packages you want installed. You can then feed the same script to the installer on every machine, so that it will install identically." Chris did say this, but he also said this functionality would not be available for some time.</p>

<p>Although Mrs. Marson was correct in the features that will some day come to Gentoo, her timetable was incorrect. One thing that is definitely positive is that this has shed quite a bit of light on our installer project, which has been working away and deserves all our support. We can only hope that this will end up a positive experience for us all.</p>

<p>UPDATE (1 Dec 2004): ZDNet UK has gotten in touch with Chris Gianelloni and has corrected the mistakes in the article.  The old article is no longer on the ZDNet UK site and only the corrected article remains.  Gentoo would like to thank ZDNet UK for their quick response in this matter.</p>

</body>
</news>
