<?xml version='1.0'?>

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/news/20041018-redesignwinner.xml,v 1.1 2004/10/18 18:06:36 swift Exp $ -->

<!-- No dtd due to irregularity in summary -->

<news gentoo="yes" category="moo">
<poster>swift</poster>
<date>18 October 2004</date>
<title>Redesign contest: And the winner is... Aaron Shi</title>
<summary>

<p>
The <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=227589">voting</uri> on
our <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri> has selected
<b>Aaron Shi as the winner of the Gentoo Website Redesign Contest</b>!
Congratulations! For those of you wondering what the design looks like, take a
peek at Aaron's <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/wwwcontest/contest1_front.png">front
design</uri> and <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/wwwcontest/contest1_handbook.png">handbook
design</uri>.
</p>

</summary>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=227589">voting</uri> on
our <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri> has selected
<b>Aaron Shi as the winner of the Gentoo Website Redesign Contest</b>!
Congratulations! For those of you wondering what the design looks like, take a
peek at Aaron's <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/wwwcontest/contest1_front.png">front
design</uri> and <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/images/wwwcontest/contest1_handbook.png">handbook
design</uri>.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank all participants for their efforts. We have seen great
designs throughout the last months and wish all contributors the best with their
further endeavours. Thank you, thank you, and once again thank you.
</p>

<p>
Now that the election is over, a team of developers will work closely with Aaron
Shi to tune the design further. This tuning will be based on comments made 
during the contest without touching the design itself.
</p>

<p>
Next, XHTML pages will be drafted based on this layout. Most of the Gentoo
developers care about standards; it will come to no surprise when we tell you
that we will code the page with the appropriate standards (such as XHTML and 
CSS) in mind.
</p>

<p>
Our website pages are all written in XML and converted to XHTML with the use of
XSL transformations. Our next (and final) step is therefore the merger of the 
XHTML code in our XSL stylesheets. 
</p>

</body>
</news>
