<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<news gentoo="yes" category="main">
	<poster>Tim Yamin</poster>
	<date>2006-02-27</date>
	<title>Release Announcement: Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
<body>
<p><b>
The Gentoo Release Engineering team proudly announces the release of
Gentoo Linux 2006.0. Gentoo Linux 2006.0, the first release in the
2006 series, represents improvements across many architectures
since the 2005.1 release.
</b></p>

<p>
Major highlights in the release include KDE 3.4.3, GNOME 2.12.2, XFCE
4.2.2, GCC 3.4.4 and a 2.6.15 kernel. This is also the first release
with the Gentoo Linux Installer officially debuting on the x86 LiveCD,
which will fully replace the Universal and PackageCD set. The LiveCD
also features a fully-fledged Gnome environment. Later releases will
include KDE support as well as a new LiveDVD.
</p>

<p>
The PPC64 team has made significant improvements in its release
media. IBM's hardware donation to the team greatly helped this and
ensured a smooth release. The CDs feature 64-bit kernels and 32-bit
userlands rather than the previous pure 64-bit environment. Optimized
stages are available for the G5 and POWER5 processors, making Gentoo
the first distribution compile time optimized for the POWER5 processor
via a power5 profile. The new release includes an experimental CD with
full framebuffer support for dual-core G5 machines along with thermal
management features. This makes Gentoo the first to market with
release media with this level of support.
</p>

<p>
PPC and PPC64 profiles received further reorganization. They now match
those of other 32/64-bit architectures such as SPARC and MIPS,
unifying the look of the tree and allowing easier creation of specific
profiles (for example, for server use) in the future. The PPC discs
improve support for newer Apple laptops such as the last series of
PowerBooks, which 2005.1 did not support, and feature improved
OldWorld support with BootX on the universal CDs. The PPC team now
produces the PackageCDs in a G4 and a ppc-generic configuration,
especially useful for older and slower machines.
</p>

<p>
The Hardened team is pleased to release both 2.4 and 2.6 kernel
targeted stages for the x86 platform. The previously experimental
non-multilib AMD64 stages are now part of the 2006.0 release, while
Hardened Gentoo with multilib on AMD64 has become possible and the
team is releasing experimental stages.
</p>

<p>
The 2006.0 AMD64 release moves EM64T support out of the experimental
realm. The InstallCDs feature support for NVIDIA SATA and for
SysKonnect Yukon2 network cards as well as the inclusion of 32-bit Java Support. An experimental LiveCD is also available, featuring the Gentoo Linux Installer. 
</p>

<p>
The Alpha team now provides split NPTL profiles as part of the 2006.0
release -- NPTL must use a 2.6 kernel, and those who require a 2.4
kernel or do not wish to enable NPTL can use the no-nptl subprofile
instead to not take advantage of the new threading model. Stage
tarballs are now provided for both variants, and the InstallCD
provides both 2.4 and 2.6 kernels.
</p>

<p>
SPARC has moved to GCC 3.4.5 from the older 3.3 series and also to
glibc 2.3.5 from 2.3.3 -- the profile features a 2.6 kernel and
headers. However, this feature remains experimental and the SPARC team
built the release media with the 2.4 subprofile. Testing from SGI
Quality Assurance allowed the IA64 team to update its InstallCD to
boot on SGI Prism machines.
</p>

<p>
Gentoo Linux is a community-driven project committed to producing a
high-quality open source distribution; more information regarding this
release, such as detailed release notes will be available on the
Gentoo Release Engineering team's project page.
</p>

<p><b>
You may obtain Gentoo Linux 2006.0 via our <uri link="/main/en/where.xml">
bouncer system</uri>, or if you prefer, contribute to the available bandwith
by using our <uri link="http://torrents.gentoo.org">BitTorrent tracker</uri>.
</b></p>
</body>
</news>
