<?xml version='1.0'?>

<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<news gentoo="yes" category="gentoo">

<!-- Enter your name here -->
<poster>Christel Dahlskjaer</poster>

<!-- Date to be displayed - usually the GWN release date -->
<date>2006-08-16</date>

<!-- Title of the news item - don't forget to change the date -->
<title>Gentoo provides social workspaces to close the gap between users and developers.</title>
<body>

<!-- Alter to your own likings -->
<p>The Gentoo Overlays project, together with other groups including 
Gentoo Infrastructure and User Relations, is pleased to announce 
the availability of a new service to provide a single source for 
development overlays. Stuart Herbert, the founder of the project, 
envisions this service, overlays.gentoo.org, as a way to create social 
workspaces where developers can collaborate with each other and with
users to improve the Gentoo experience for everyone.
</p>

<p>
'Overlays' are collections of additional packages for Gentoo. They are
maintained and distributed separately from Gentoo's main package tree,
and they allow anyone to deliver extra packages for the award-winning
Gentoo Linux distribution.
</p>

<p>The social workspaces, hosted on overlays.gentoo.org, provide a testing
ground and development sandbox for teams within Gentoo to
collaborate directly with Gentoo users. Together, developers and users
will work on new packages for Gentoo and on improving existing packages
already included with Gentoo.
</p>

<p>Users interested in joining the volunteer-driven Gentoo project can gain
experience with Gentoo package development in a real-world setting,
backed by mentoring from experienced Gentoo developers. This will
greatly improve the recruitment process for Gentoo developers and users
alike. There are also many users who have extremely valuable
contributions to make, but for one reason or another don't want to
become a full Gentoo developer. With the workspaces provided by the
Overlays project, they can still contribute directly to projects within
Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
One Gentoo project that has pioneered the use of overlays in
this way is the Gentoo PHP project. Luca Longinotti, lead developer of
the PHP project, was originally recruited through his contributions to
the project's overlay. "I really appreciate the overlays idea," he
says. "At the beginning, when I started to work on PHP on Gentoo, Stuart
and I were constantly mailing patches and ideas to each other. We had to
work that way because I was not a Gentoo developer, and that was the
only way. Then he set up the PHP Overlay, and it helped us immensely to
collaborate, try out new, and exciting ideas. We use it now successfully
to test new packages and releases of PHP-related software. I think it's
because of the PHP Overlay that in the end I got involved enough to
become a full Gentoo developer."
</p>

<p>
Workspaces hosted on overlays.gentoo.org are created at the request of
Gentoo projects and individual Gentoo developers. Gentoo users who wish
to contribute to a workspace should contact the workspace's owners. They
can do this by visiting <uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org">http://overlays.gentoo.org/</uri>,
where they will find information on each social workspace.
</p>

<p>
For more information, see the home of <uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org">Social Workspaces</uri>, 
and the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/overlays">Overlays Project page.</uri> 
</p>
</body>
</news>

