<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<news gentoo="yes" category="main">
<poster>dberkholz</poster>
<date>2008-01-23</date>
<title>Public beta release planned for 2008.0 release cycle</title>
<body>

<table>
  <tr>
    <th colspan="2">Tentative schedule (dates may change):</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Feb. 1</ti>
    <ti>Snapshot of the tree taken</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Feb. 25</ti>
    <ti>Docs due to GDP from release coordinators</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Feb. 25</ti>
    <ti>Snapshot frozen for beta</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Feb. 29</ti>
    <ti>Docs finalized</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Mar. 3</ti>
    <ti>Beta1 released</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Mar. 14</ti>
    <ti>Final upload</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
    <ti>Mar. 17</ti>
    <ti>Release</ti>
  </tr>
</table>


  <p>
    Public beta releases play a major role in the <uri
    link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/releng/">Release Engineering
    team's</uri> revamped plans for 2008.0. Releng lead <mail
    link="wolf31o2">Chris Gianelloni</mail> said he hoped beta releases would
    increase community participation as well as the quality of the final
    release. These feature-complete public betas will require the earlier
    development of release materials, another component of the 2008.0
    changes. To ensure sufficient time for beta testing, a mandatory 2-week
    testing period will follow the beta release.
  </p>

  <p>
    A comprehensive testing checklist will be developed on the <uri
    link="http://archives.gentoo.org/gentoo-releng/">gentoo-releng mailing
    list</uri>, as will a list of which details of testers' machines and
    environments they should turn in to developers. In the past, testers often
    provided insufficient information to releng developers because of vague
    instructions. Now, a new form will include all of the required questions
    and details. "Sadly you almost want a beta that phones home as to what it
    was successfully run on," said <mail link="tgall">Tom Gall</mail>. <mail
    link="opfer">Christian Faulhammer</mail> suggested using a hardware
    reporting tool such as <uri
    link="http://packages.gentoo.org/package/app-admin/hwreport">app-admin/hwreport</uri>.
  </p>

  <p>
    More news on the 2008.0 release will appear over the next few days.
  </p>
</body>
</news>
