<?xml version='1.0'?>

<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<news gentoo="yes" category="linux">
  <poster>dberkholz</poster>
  <date>2008-07-06</date>
  <title>Gentoo Linux 2008.0 released</title>
  <body>
    <p>
      <b>The 2008.0 final release is out!</b> Code-named "It's got what plants
      crave," this release contains numerous new features including an updated
      <uri link="/proj/en/releng/installer/">installer</uri>, improved
      hardware support, a complete rework of profiles, and a move to Xfce
      instead of GNOME on the LiveCD. LiveDVDs are not available for x86 or
      amd64, although they may become available in the future. The 2008.0
      release also includes updated versions of many packages already
      available in your ebuild tree.
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li><b>Updated installer</b>: The installer now only performs
      networkless installations using the packages and ebuild tree on
      the LiveCD. It also contains numerous fixes for extended and
      logical partitions.</li>
      <li><b>Improved hardware support</b>: Moving to the 2.6.24 kernel added
      many new drivers for hardware released since the 2007.0 release.</li>
      <li><b>Complete rework of profiles</b>: Restructuring profiles allowed
      significant cleanup of redundancies, reducing developer maintenance and
      confusion. The difference for you is that profiles now appear in
      <path>/usr/portage/profiles/</path> under <path>default/linux/</path>
      instead of <path>default-linux/</path>. See the <uri
      link="/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml">upgrading guide</uri> for more
      details.</li>
      <li><b>Xfce instead of GNOME on the LiveCD</b>: To save space,
      the LiveCDs switched to the smaller Xfce environment. This means
      that a binary installation using the LiveCD will install Xfce,
      but you're still free to build GNOME or KDE from source.</li>
      <li><b>No LiveDVDs on x86 or amd64</b>: In the interest of getting the
      release out, the <uri link="/proj/en/releng/">release engineering
      team</uri> decided to postpone LiveDVDs because of problems in their
      generation. They may show up later&mdash;if so, we'll let you know.</li>
      <li><b>Updated packages</b>: Highlights of the 2008.0 release include
      <uri link="/proj/en/portage/">Portage</uri> 2.1.4.4, a 2.6.24 kernel,
      Xfce 4.4.2, gcc 4.1.2 and glibc 2.6.1.</li>
    </ul>

    <p>
      A big thanks goes out to our <uri link="/proj/en/releng/">release
      engineering team members</uri> for their hard work over many months to
      turn 2008.0 into reality.
    </p>

    <p>
      <b>Get the new release from our <uri
      link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/where.xml">"Get Gentoo!"
      page</uri></b>.
    </p>

    <p>
      <uri
      link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-699099.html">Discuss
      this!</uri>
    </p>
  </body>
</news>
