<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<news gentoo="yes" category="gentoo">

<!-- Enter your name here -->
<poster>dberkholz</poster>

<!-- Date to be displayed - usually the GWN release date -->
<date>2008-09-04</date>

<!-- Title of the news item - don't forget to change the date -->
<title>Get involved: Bugday coming up Saturday</title>

<body>

<!-- Alter to your own likings -->
<p>
  <b>What:</b> Gentoo contributors get together to help each other fix bugs
</p>

<p>
  <b>Where:</b> irc.freenode.net, #gentoo-bugs 
</p>

<p>
  <b>When:</b> Saturday, September 6, in a timezone near you
</p>

<p>
  <b>What do you need to bring?</b>
</p>

<ul>
  <li>A Gentoo system, an Internet connection and an IRC client</li>
  <li>Your bug. If you don't have one, we will find you one to suit your area
  of interest and your skills</li>
  <li>Your favorite editor</li>
  <li>A way to test that your bug is fixed (asking people counts!)</li>
  <li>You <b>don't</b> need to know C, C++, or bash</li>
</ul>

<p>
  <b>What's a bug?</b> Gentoo's way of tracking change requests. A change
  request can be anything from "I've found a typo in foo" to "I've built this
  really useful program called bar but there's no ebuild for it." Bugs have
  various levels of helpfulness, from identifying the existence of a problem
  to localizing the problem to providing the patch to fix it.
</p>

<p>
  There are bugs in documentation such as man pages as well as ebuilds and the
  source code that Gentoo distributes. These bugs are problem reports. Bugs
  for things Gentoo doesn't do yet but you think should be done are feature
  requests. <b>Bugday is more about fixing problems than adding features</b>,
  but you won't be turned away if you want help with a new feature.
</p>

<p>
  <b>Want to know more about Bugday?</b> It's held on the first Saturday of
  every month. It's an opportunity for everyone to contribute to making Gentoo
  better, and eventually you might even become a Gentoo developer. See the
  <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/bugday/index.xml">Bugday project
  page</uri> for more details.
</p>

<p>
  <b>Bugday is about community spirit</b>. Gentoo is a community&mdash;there
  is no "me" and "them", there is only "we," so instead of lobbying for "them"
  to fix your particular bug, work together to fix it! Bugday is an
  opportunity to get help to help yourself.
</p>

<p>
  If you've been wanting to get involved but weren't sure how, Bugday is a
  great way for you to see what goes on in making a distribution and get
  involved in Gentoo.
</p>

<p>
  <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-705932.html">Discuss
  this!</uri>
</p>

<p>
  <e>Roy Bamford contributed the draft for this announcement.</e>
</p>

</body>

</news>
