<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<news gentoo="yes" category="gentoo">

<poster>antarus</poster>
<date>2009-03-15</date>
<title>New stages available for arm/sh</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo embedded team would like to announce that we will be automatically
building and releasing stages for ARM and SuperH/SH.  We hope these stages will
help out people interested in developing embedded linux applications.
</p>

<p>
On the ARM side, we are currently releasing stages for the following CHOSTs:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>arm-unknown-linux-gnu (old ABI, in progress)</li>
  <li>armv4l-unknown-linux-gnu (old ABI, in progress)</li>
  <li>armv4tl-softfloat-linux-gnueabi (EABI)</li>
  <li>armv5tel-softfloat-linux-gnueabi (EABI)</li>
</ul>

<p>
On the SuperH/SH side, we are currently releasing stages for the following
processors:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>sh4</li>
  <li>sh4a</li>
</ul>

<p>
The stages are available under the <path>/releases/arm/autobuilds</path>
directory for ARM and <path>/releases/sh/autobuilds</path> for SH at your
favorite <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/main/en/mirrors2.xml">mirror</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Because building stages for these architectures takes a while, we plan on 
releasing stages on a monthly or bi-monthly basis. If you would like to talk
about Gentoo on those architectures, please join us on #gentoo-embedded @ 
irc.freenode.net.
</p>

<p>
We would like to thank <uri link="http://www.qnap.com">QNAP Inc.</uri>
and <uri link="http://www.marvell.com">Marvell Technology Group</uri>
for providing us with support and hardware for ARM based chips.  However we
would like to expand our ARM support to the armv6 and armv7 processors.  If you
or your company can provide us with some hardware we would greatly appreciate
it. Please contact the <mail link="arm@gentoo.org">Gentoo ARM team</mail> if
you or your company are able to assist us.
</p>

<p>
We would like to also thank <uri link="http://www.renesas.com">Renesas Technology Corp.</uri>
who has graciously provided us hardware and support for the SuperH platform.
</p>
</body>
</news>
