<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE news SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<news gentoo="yes" category="gentoo">
<poster>quantumsummers</poster>
<date>2009-11-04</date>
<title>Gentoo KDE3 Deprecation Notice</title>
<body>
<p><b>
Please turn your KDE radio on, and make sure to increase the volume to its maximum
level for this important message.
</b></p>
<p>
After multiple setbacks we have finally managed to <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=287697">stabilise</uri> KDE4
on both major desktop architectures (amd64 and x86), with other teams to follow.
</p>
<p>
For this and other reasons as <uri link="http://archives.gentoo.org/gentoo-desktop/msg_a3e260bd0545cb4e763c81bc60f81de2.xml">discussed</uri>
, those of you who still use KDE3 should be seriously considering an upgrade in the near future.
</p>

<p>
The KDE3 support is being <b>deprecated</b> with immediate effect. This means that
ebuilds are dropping KDE3 support where they were broken, or clashing with
KDE4.
</p>

<p>
If you wish to still use KDE3, and you want to help others with having KDE3
around, drop a mail to <mail link="kde@gentoo.org"/>, where we can give you commit access
to the <uri link="http://git.overlays.gentoo.org/gitweb/?p=proj/kde-sunset.git">special overlay</uri> which will specifically contain only KDE3 packages.<br />
This overlay (named <b>kde3</b>) can be easily used via <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/overlays/userguide.xml">layman</uri>.
</p>

<p>
Sadly upstream is not supporting KDE3 anymore and we simply lack the
manpower to keep support for both (as you might have noticed in the past few
months KDE3 has become more and more rusty for which we humbly apologize).
</p>

<p>
Sorry to bring you the bad news and with hope that KDE4 will suit your needs,
</p>

<p>
<mail link="scarabeus"/><br />
KDE Teams substituting Lead
</p>

<p>
KUDOS to <mail link="nirbheek"/> and <mail link="dabbott"/> for helping to put this announcement
together and <mail link="antarus"/> for proofreading it.
</p>
</body>
</news>
