<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/news/Attic/2009-screenshot-contest.xml,v 1.1 2010/01/14 14:05:00 dabbott Exp $ -->

<guide link="/main/en/shots.xml" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Screenshot Contest 2009</title>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="hwoarang@gentoo.org">Markos Chandras</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
<mail link="dabbott@gentoo.org">David Abbott</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Second Gentoo Screenshot Contest
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>0.4</version>
<date>2009-07-13</date>

<chapter>
<title>General information</title>
<section>
<title>Disclaimer</title>
<body>
<p>The screenshots submitted are contributed by various Gentoo users and
    developers. Upon request of further details on a specific screeshot, one
    may try to locate the author in #gentoo channel on the freenode network or
    in our <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org">gentoo forums</uri>. </p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Judges</title>
<body>
<p>
The Judges will consist of one active developer and two independent Gentoo
users.  </p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Submission Rules</title>
<body>
<p>
The following rules apply to this contest
</p>
<ol>
<li>Each contestant is only allowed to make up to one submission.</li>
<li>The image resolution must be strictly between 1024x768 and 1920x1200
    pixels.</li> <li>The images must be in 'png' format.</li>
<li>One must prove the origin of their screenshot being a Gentoo Linux machine.
    For this, an open terminal with emerge --info |head -n 1</li> </ol>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Contest Details</title>
<body>
<ol> <li>The 2009 Screenshot contest is part of the Gentoo 10 Year Anniversary
        Celebration.</li> <li>The 3 best screenshots will be posted on the <uri
            link="2009-anniversary-announcement.xml">
            Gentoo 10 Year Anniversary Party Page.</uri></li> <li>Here we will
        compare the current screenshots with screenshots from the early
        days.</li> <li>The submission deadline is 2009-09-15 and the winner
        will be announced on the 10 year anniversary date of 2009-10-04.</li>
</ol> <note> The Gentoo branding project may wish to recreate your
ideas,therefore please note down all the resources you used in detail.  </note>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter>
<title>How to submit your brand new screenshot</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
<b>By submiting your screenshot you agree to the terms under the <uri
    link="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5/"> Creative Commons -
    Attribution / Share Alike license.</uri> </b></p> 
<p>
Please provide the following information in your submission e-mail:
</p>
<ol>
<li>Username (if you have any, on gentoo forums or irc so that the other users
    may contact you if needed) </li> <li>Name (optional)</li> <li>Provide
    details (links, resources etc.) of your screenshot components such as
    themes, icons, wallpaper etc.</li> <li>Please provide the specs of your box
    so we can compaire it with the systems from the past.</li> </ol>
    <p><b>Screenshots should be mailed to <mail
                link="gentoo-pr@lists.gentoo.org">Gentoo PR
                Project</mail></b></p> <impo> Your email will be kept private.
</impo> </body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
