<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>userreps</name>
<longname>User Representatives</longname>
<date>2006-09-24</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="rfish@gentoo-userreps.org">Richard Fish</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="christel@gentoo.org">Christel Dahlskjaer</mail>
</author>

<description>Gentoo User Representatives (userreps) form part of Gentoo User Relations 
(userrel) and are elected each year by Gentoo users to represent them and present their 
views and feedback to the development community.</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
Gentoo User Representatives (userreps) form part of Gentoo User
Relations (userrel) and are elected each year by Gentoo users to
represent them to the development community.  Our mission is to help
improve communications between the Gentoo developers and users.  Our
goals are to ensure that users have the information they need about the
developments in Gentoo, and ensure developers have the information they
need to make Cool New Things (TM).
</p>
We work towards those goals by:<br />
<ul>
<li> Being involved with and engaging the user community.  You'll find us
helping to solve problems, answering questions, and basically keeping an
"ear to the ground" on the user lists, forums, and IRC channels.</li>

<li>Keeping an eye out for ideas for improvements to Gentoo, documentation
fixes, GWN articles, or additional communication channels.  Many of us
already have ideas of things that would make Gentoo better, but we
aren't above stealing (er, borrowing) yours!</li>

<li>Providing feedback to the development community as requested or
necessary.  This includes feedback both on Gentoo itself and on the
quantity and quality of communications to users.</li>

<li>Encouraging users to participate in the Gentoo development process by
interacting with developers in constructive ways, including presenting 
their own ideas for improvements to Gentoo.</li>
</ul>
<p>
It should be noted that we are not here to interfere with the existing
communications between users and devs.  Users are welcome to contact us
regarding ideas for improvements to Gentoo, but are equally welcome to
present their ideas directly on bugzilla, the forums, or the gentoo-dev
mailing list.
</p>
</longdescription>

<extrachapter>
<title>Contacting the User Representatives</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Have a fantastic idea for improving Gentoo that you want to share? Or 
wish you had known about some bug /before/ that emerge -u command?  Or
maybe you just feel like you are in the dark about what is going on with
Gentoo and want to chat about it?  There are several channels available
for contacting the userreps.</p>

<p>
<b>Forums:</b> URL to be determined.<br />
<b>E-mail:</b> <uri link="mailto:userreps@gentoo.org">userreps@gentoo.org</uri> is an 
alias that will deliver your message to all user representatives (or should spam assassin 
be feeling cranky that day it may possibly end up in their spam bucket).<br />
<b>IRC:</b> #gentoo-userreps on irc.freenode.net, come visit us!<br />
<b>Mailing List:</b> gentoo-userrel@gentoo.org reaches all user representatives and the user 
relations team, this list is public and you can subscribe by sending a blank e-mail to 
<uri link="gentoo-userrel+subscribe@gentoo.org">gentoo-userrel+subscribe@gentoo.org</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>User Representatives for 2006/2007</title>
<section>
<body>
<table>
  <tr>
   <th>Name</th>
   <th>Nick</th>
   <th>E-mail</th>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Richard Fish</ti>
   <ti>rfish</ti>
   <ti>rfish@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Brandon Berhent</ti>
   <ti>cheater-conrad / cheater1034</ti>
   <ti>cheater1034@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Bertrand Coppa</ti>
   <ti>kopp</ti>
   <ti>kopp@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Chris Fairles</ti>
   <ti>CoffeeBuzz</ti>
   <ti>coffeebuzz@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Peter Gantner</ti>
   <ti>nephros</ti>
   <ti>nephros@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Georg Witwer</ti>
   <ti>loki99</ti>
   <ti>loki99@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Emil Jacobs</ti>
   <ti>Q-collective</ti>
   <ti>qcollective@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Fabio Erculiani</ti>
   <ti>lxnay</ti>
   <ti>lxnay@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Markus Flaig</ti>
   <ti>toskala</ti>
   <ti>toskala@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>George Prowse</ti>
   <ti>cokehabit</ti>
   <ti>cokehabit@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
  <tr>
   <ti>Fernando Vasquez</ti>
   <ti>likewhoa</ti>
   <ti>likewhoa@gentoo-userreps.org</ti>
  </tr>
</table>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Role Description and Social Contract</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
The initial role description can be found <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/userrel/userrep.xml">here</uri>, 
the role was deliberately left somewhat fluid as to allow the userbase to help form it as necessary.</p>
<p>
The User Representatives have written and agreed upon a 'Social Contract', of which they have decided to work by and 
adhere through through-out the period they have been elected for. You may read their social contract 
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/userrel/userreps/social.xml">here</uri>.</p>
<p>
The User Representives also have a more informal website over at <uri link="http://www.gentoo-userreps.org">http://www.gentoo-userreps.org</uri> 
where you can find more information about the representatives and their activities.</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>
