<?xml version='1.0' encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide link="/security/en/index.xml">

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="genone@gentoo.org">genone</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="plasmaroo@gentoo.org">plasmaroo</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="solar@gentoo.org">solar</mail>
</author>
<abstract>Security</abstract>

<version>0.1</version>
<date>20031027</date>

<chapter>
	<title>Release Plan (initial draft)</title>
	<body>
	<p>
	The following release plain details the necessary steps a Gentoo Security developer must take to release a new GLSA.
	</p>
	<ul>
		<li>A developer would write an XML GLSA, using a normal editor or a specialty tool such as GLSAMaker.  As part of this process, the dev should ensure the following steps are completed:</li>
			<ul>
				<li>ensure syntactical correctness of the GLSA XML using tools such as <c>xmllint</c>. This is done automatically by GLSAMaker.</li>
				<li>check for semantical errors, such as non-existant packages and/or versions as well as incorrect dates, etc.</li>
				<li>gpg-sign the XML GLSA with the developers key.  <em>All GLSAs MUST be signed by the sending developer</em>. GLSAMaker produces detached signatures for distribution: for inline signing of the text, this must be done manually. This is mainly to ease usage with mail clients which GPG-sign emails. The XML is signed in a detached signature to help parsers parse the XML.</li>
				<li><c>cvs commit</c> the XML GLSA and the signature to <path>gentoo-x86/glsa/</path> using a defined naming of YYYYMMDD-&lt;package&gt;-glsa.xml</li>
				<li><c>cvs commit</c> the XML GLSA and the signature to <path>gentoo/xml/htdocs/security/en/glsa/</path> using the same naming scheme</li>
				<li>edit the GLSA index page (<path>gentoo/xml/htdocs/security/en/glsa/index.xml</path>) to include the new GLSA</li>
			</ul>		
	</ul>
	<p>
	Once completed, these steps ensure that the GLSA is then available over the website and over the rsync tree.  Users will be able to retrieve the new GLSA either by checking the web site or simply running <c>emerge sync</c>.
	</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
<chapter>
	<title>GLSAMaker</title>
	<body>
	<p>
	GLSAMaker is a tool designed to speed up the creation of GLSAs. It is written in Qt, and available from CVS in <path>CVSROOT-&gt;gentoo-projects/gentoo-security/GLSA/Client</path>. Run the <c>GLSAMaker-QtBuilder.sh</c> script to produce an executable. Any problems or questions should be addressed to <mail link="plasmaroo@gentooorg">plasmaroo</mail>.
	</p>
	</body>
</chapter>
</guide>
