<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/new-dev-training.xml">
<title>Assigning copyright to Gentoo</title>
<author title = "Author"><mail link = "avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail></author>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>08 Dec 2003</date>

<abstract>Information on copyright assignment</abstract>

	<chapter>
		<title>Assigning copyright to Gentoo Technologies</title>
		<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
			<body>		
			<p>Copyright assignment refers to the process of legally changing
				the ownership of intellectual property, such as a piece of code,
				to a new entity. In this case, it involves reassignment from contributors
				to the organization. This is a necessary step to ensure that Gentoo
				is legally able to pursue and defend against litigation. Towards this
				end, it is necessary to obtain signatures from contributors. The
				signed document does two things: it turns copyright over to Gentoo,
				and in return it guarantees that the contributed code will never
				be relicensed under a license materially different from the GNU
				General Public License (or, in the case of documentation,
				the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License). This protects
				both the organization and individual contributors.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>Process</title>
			<body>
			<p>There are two necessary steps: the submission of a GPG public key and the submission of
				a signature on the copyright assignment document. GPG public keys should be mailed to
				<mail link="submissions@gentoo.org">submissions@gentoo.org</mail>. The assignment
				document should be printed, signed, and faxed to a number that will be provided.
				It is available online at <uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/assignment.txt</uri>.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>FAQ</title>
			<body>
			<p>Q: Why is copyright assignment necessary?</p>
			<p>A: Copyright assignment legally ensures that Gentoo is capable of legally defending itself.
				Without copyright ownership, Gentoo has no legal standing in litigation.
				Additionally, these documents ensure that the integrity of contributed code will be
				protected (for example, the license will never be modified to be more restrictive).</p>
			<p>Q: What is the scope of this? Does this affect things I do outside of Gentoo?</p>
			<p>A: No. The scope of the agreement is limited to what is defined in the work description
				section.</p>
			<p>Q: Does this only apply to official developers?</p>
			<p>A: No. Anyone contributing over a page of work must also assign copyright to Gentoo.
				GPG keys should be sent to <mail link="submissions@gentoo.org">submissions@gentoo.org</mail>
				with submitted work either attached or indicated via a URL.
				Contributors who need to submit forms can contact <mail link="recruiters@gentoo.org">recruiters@gentoo.org</mail>.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</guide>
