<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>

<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/new-dev-training.xml">
<title>Assigning copyright to Gentoo</title>
<author title = "Author"><mail link = "avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail></author>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>08 Dec 2003</date>

<abstract>Information on copyright assignment</abstract>

	<chapter>
		<title>Gentoo policy on licenses and copyrights</title>
		<section>
		<title>Introduction</title>
			<body>		

			<p>Our project receives contributions from many people
			from all over the world.  Some of these contributions
			come from our own volunteer developers. Others come
			from users, or from large organizations like
			universities and businesses. These contributions form a
			community-developed work called Gentoo. Gentoo code is
			released under the GNU General Public License, and our
			documentation is released under the Creative Commons
			Attribution Share-Alike (CC-AS) license.</p>
		
			<p>Our code repository also contains many build scripts
			called "ebuilds." As a whole, our repository of ebuild
			scripts can be used to build an entire operating system
			that we call Gentoo Linux. It's important to note that
			while the ebuilds contain the knowledge necessary to
			build this operating system, the operating system
			itself is composed of freely-available parts that are
			generally not authored by the Gentoo development
			community, nor considered part of our repository of
			code. The primary focus of Gentoo is to create the
			tools, automation and knowledge necessary to integrate
			these freely-available parts into a working operating
			system. The works created by the Gentoo community are
			generally focused on the complex task of integrating
			the various freely-available parts into a working
			whole.  </p>
		
			<p>Sometimes, we either create or receive contributed
			"patches" for these freely-available parts, to either
			enhance their functionality, fix a bug, or for some
			other purpose. These patches are generally made
			available to the public under the license of the parent
			program. For example, for a non-Gentoo program that is
			released under the BSD license, a patch that we create
			for this program would be released by us under the same
			license of the parent program -- the BSD license. This
			is a commonly-accepted practice in the free software
			and "open source" community, as it allows patches to be
			integrated into the parent
			program's official source code without complication, if the authors of the
			parent program so desire. This practice allows free
			software to benefit from the improvements of
			others.</p>
		
			<p>Sometimes, individuals and organizations may use
			Gentoo code in ways that may violate the GNU General
			Public License or the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike
			license. In such a
			situation, steps need to be taken to correct this misuse
			of Gentoo code. These steps could conceivably involve legal
			action.</p>

			<p>If legal action is required, it is very beneficial if
			the code that is being used improperly is owned by as
			few entities as possible. This is a benefit because 
			all owners of the code in question must
			be a party in any legal action. Because we have hundreds of
			contributors to our project, it can create a logistical
			nightmare for our community project if many people own
			the code in question. Consider the effort required
			if the code in question consists of contributions from tens, possibly hundreds of people,
			who are from all parts of the globe, and who may or may not
			be currently active in Gentoo development or even able to
			be successfully contacted or tracked down.</p>

			<p>It's important for our community to be
			able to protect against misuse of our code. The best way to
			do this is to, as much as reasonably possible, assign copyrights
			of all contributed code to a single entity. This way, any
			violations of the licensing terms of Gentoo code can be addressed
			as quickly, efficiently and inexpensively as possible. In addition,
			this single entity should be bound to protect and preserve the original licensing
			terms of the code.</p>

			<p>Thus, we require all individual contributors to Gentoo
			to assign copyright for their contributed works to Gentoo Technlogies, Inc. by signing a copyright
			assignment agreement. In order to ensure that the licensing terms of your assigned works
			are protected and preserved by Gentoo Technlogies, Inc.,
			this copyright assignment agreement also contains a legally-binding commitment
			from Gentoo Technologies, Inc. that the assigned works
			will continue to remain available under licenses that are not materially different
			from the GNU General Public License and CC-SA Licenses under which they were
			originally released. This terminology will allow Gentoo
			Technologies, Inc. to "upgrade" to improved versions of these licenses
			as they become available, such as GPL version 3, but will not allow
			Gentoo Technologies, Inc. to
			release the assigned works under licenses that do not embody 
			identical principles as the licenses under which they were originally relesed. This commitment
			from Gentoo Technologies, Inc. also applies to any entities who may receive
			ownership of the 
			the works in the future, such as the not-for-profit successor to Gentoo
			Technologies, Inc. Because of this commitment, you can know that your assigned
			works will continue to be available under licensing terms that
			you fully support, and no others.</p>
			
			<p>To summarize: copyright assignment refers to the process of legally changing
				the ownership of intellectual property, such as a piece of code,
				to a new entity. In this case, it involves reassignment from contributors
				to the organization. This is a necessary step to ensure that Gentoo
				is legally able to pursue and defend against litigation. Towards this
				end, it is necessary to obtain signed copyright assignment from individual contributors. The
				signed document does two things: it turns copyright over to Gentoo Technologies, Inc.,
				and in return it guarantees that the contributed works will never
				be relicensed under a license materially different from the GNU
				General Public License (or, in the case of documentation,
				the Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike License). This allows
				the Gentoo community to take action to correct those who
				may knowingly or unknowingly violate the licensing terms of our works,
				while also ensuring that these works continue to be available under
				licensing terms that you fully support -- even if the ownership of
				these works are eventually transferred to another entity.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>Process</title>
			<body>
			<p>There are two necessary steps: the submission of a GPG public key and the submission of
				a signature on the copyright assignment document. GPG public keys should be mailed to
				<mail link="submissions@gentoo.org">submissions@gentoo.org</mail>. The assignment
				document should be printed, signed, and faxed to a number that will be provided.
				It is available online at <uri>http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/assignment.txt</uri>.
			</p>
			</body>
		</section>

		<section>
		<title>FAQ</title>
			<body>
			<p>Q: Why is copyright assignment necessary?</p>
			<p>A: Copyright assignment legally ensures that Gentoo is capable of legally defending itself.
				Without copyright ownership, Gentoo has no legal standing in litigation.
				Additionally, these documents ensure that the integrity of contributed code will be
				protected (for example, the license will never be modified to be more restrictive).</p>
			<p>Q: What is the scope of this? Does this affect things I do outside of Gentoo?</p>
			<p>A: No. The scope of the agreement is limited to what is defined in the work description
				section.</p>
			<p>Q: Does this only apply to official developers?</p>
			<p>A: No. Anyone contributing over a page of work must also assign copyright to Gentoo.
				GPG keys should be sent to <mail link="submissions@gentoo.org">submissions@gentoo.org</mail>
				with submitted work either attached or indicated via a URL.
				Contributors who need to submit forms can contact <mail link="recruiters@gentoo.org">recruiters@gentoo.org</mail>.</p>
			</body>
		</section>
	</chapter>
</guide>
