<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/qa/index.xml">
<title>Gentoo Developer Relations</title>
<subtitle>Main Page</subtitle>
<author title="Author">
   <mail link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail>
</author>
<abstract>
The Gentoo Developer Relations Project is an effort to recruit, train, and
maintain developers for the various Gentoo projects.
</abstract>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>11 July 2003</date>

<chapter>
<title>What is Gentoo Developer Relations?</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
	Gentoo Developer Relations is a project in Gentoo which aims to be a
	point of contact for prospective developers, as well as a point of
	contact for current developers.  For prospective developers, we use the
	mailing lists, the forums and the
	<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org"> Gentoo bug tracker</uri> to watch for, and invite, prospective
	developers.
</p>
<p>
	The stated goal for Gentoo Developer Relations is to act as a meeting
	point for Gentoo developers and advanced users both.  As such, Gentoo
	Developer Relations is concerned with both intra-developer relations as
	well as forming relations with advanced users and prospective
	developers.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Developer Relations Subprojects</title>

<section>
<title>Active Subprojects</title>
<body>
<p>
   The current active subprojects in Hardened Gentoo are:
<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>Description:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Intra-Developer Relations</ti>
		<ti>Here, we maintain a constantly updated roster of developers, and
		their areas of development.  Additionally, we maintain a record of
		developers' GPG public keys to provide a single area for developer
		lookup.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Recruitment and Training</ti>
		<ti>Currently, we have a process on the <uri
		link="http://bugs.gentoo.org"> Gentoo bug tracker</uri> which tracks a
		new developer's progress from initial contact through training and
		final sign up.  As part of a new developer's training, they must
		fulfill several requirements, culminating in a quiz/questionnaire.
		Every new developer is assigned to a mentor on the Gentoo
		development team.</ti>
	</tr>
</table>

</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Planned Subprojects</title>
<body>
<p>
   The current planned subprojects in Gentoo Developer Relations are:
   <table>
	<tr>
		<th>Project:</th>
		<th>Description:</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Developer Conflict Resolution</ti>
		<ti>Grant Goodyear recently proposed a GLEP (Gentoo Linux
		Enhancement Proposal) calling for an <uri
		link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0007.html">Ombudsman</uri>
		to aid in developer conflict resolution.  We would like to implement
		this plan in the near future.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Recruitment Policy</ti>
		<ti>One of the biggest questions in the user community is of how to
		become a Gentoo Developer.  We will attempt to outline our
		requirements for a prospective developer as well as provide an
		interface for prospective developers to contact.  Currently,
		interested parties can contact recruiters (at) gentoo (dot) org.</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>User Relations</ti>
		<ti>The goal of this subproject is to interface with the user
		community, to seek out motivated and skilled individuals for
		prospective hiring.  Essentially, the concerns of the community with
		respect to developer relations will be listened to, and where
		possible, addressed.</ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo Developer Relations Personnel</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
Each person working on Gentoo Developer Relations is listed here, full time
indicates that their main Gentoo position is on this project, part time
indicates that their main position lies in another area but they do
additional work with  Gentoo Developer Relations.
<table>
	<tr>
		<th>Developer Name</th>
		<th>Username</th>
		<th>Full/Part Time</th>
		<th>Areas of Responsibilty</th>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Seemant Kulleen</ti>
		<ti>seemant</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Strategic Manager</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Jon Portnoy</ti>
		<ti>avenj</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Operational Manager</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Sascha Schwabbauer</ti>
		<ti>cybersystem</ti>
		<ti>Full</ti>
		<ti>Mailing lists subscription support and Developer Roster</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Kurt Lieber</ti>
		<ti>klieber</ti>
		<ti>Part</ti>
		<ti>E-mail and CVS account and access support</ti>
	</tr>
	<tr>
		<ti>Brandy Westcott</ti>
		<ti>brandy</ti>
		<ti>Part</ti>
		<ti>User relations</ti>
	</tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>


<chapter>
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
To participate in the Gentoo Developer Relations project, please contact
seemant or avenj via email or irc.  Additionally the recruiters email
address, as listed in the above table can be contacted with the subject:
DevRel Personnel.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
