<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/policy.xml">
<title>Developer Relations Policy Guide</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="devrel@gentoo.org">Developer Relations</mail></author>

<abstract>Developer Relations Policy Guide</abstract>

<version>1.1.1</version>
<date>2005-07-10</date>

<chapter>
<title>Conflict resolution policy</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>		

<p>
While conflicts serious enough to require developer relations
involvement are rare, it's inevitable that developers will clash to
varying degrees. It's essential that the developer relations team find
fair and impartial resolutions to inter-developer problems. Although
all situations differ and exercising good judgment is necessary, these
guidelines are intended to define the most acceptable course of
action.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>When should developer relations be involved?</title>
<body>

<p>
Developer relations should only be involved in a conflict when other
attempts to solve the issue have failed.  Developers should attempt
polite discussion relating to the matter at hand to resolve conflict
between themselves.  Developers within a single top level project
(TLP) engaged in conflict may wish to consult with the TLP
manager. Although TLP managers are not necessarily qualified to
resolve personal disputes, technical issues resulting in conflict can
often be resolved within the TLP without developer relations
involvement. Personal issues should be brought to the ombudsman via
<mail link="ombudsman@gentoo.org">ombudsman@gentoo.org</mail>. Developer
relations may get involved when the above methods have failed.  For
resolution of technical conflicts spanning more than one TLP, see the
section entitled 'Presenting information to management.'
</p>

<p>
Issues not necessarily related to personal conflict, such as
intentional or repeated policy breaches, malicious or abrasive
behavior to users or developers, or similar developer-specific
behavorial problems should be brought directly to developer relations
via <mail link="devrel@gentoo.org">devrel@gentoo.org</mail>.  This
should be dealt with on a case-by-case basis by developer relations
and may require disciplinary action as defined by the section entitled
'Disciplinary action.'
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Presenting information to management</title>
<body>

<p>
Often, conflicts between managers and developers will require a
decision be made by the management team.  To avoid forcing the
management team to investigate all the data already processed by
developer relations, a condensed summary of the issues at hand as they
relate to the decision being made should be presented by developer
relations lead(s). It should be totally unbiased and present all
factual information from both sides. A recommendation may or may not
be made at the discretion of the developer relations manager(s).
Recommendations should be strictly limited to the (usually technical)
issue at hand and should be reviewed by the developer relations team
prior to submission.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Disciplinary action</title>
<body>

<p>
Disciplinary action must be decided on a case-by-case basis by the
developer relations leads. For the majority of situations requiring
disciplinary action, a warning is enough to correct future
behavior. If behavior does not improve, a probationary period with
revoked access to Gentoo infrastructure of two weeks to one month is
appropriate. If upon restoration of access negative behavior
re-occurs, removal from the project will be necessary. In extreme
cases, suspension or removal may be necessary upon a single
offense.
</p>

<p>
Except in critical situations where immediate action is required, the
developer relations leads determine appropriate disciplinary action
(if any) based on recommendations of a devrel judicial hearing
board, as described in section (2) below.  A developer upon whom
disciplinary action is so imposed may appeal this action to the
Gentoo Top Level Project managers sitting as an appeals board.
</p>
  
<p>
Upon removing a developer, the gentoo-core mailing list should be
notified. Additionally, the developer relations team and ombudsman
should be informed of the issues that led to removing or suspending a
developer. The ombudsman should keep a record of this for future
reference, which should preferably be stored on a bug. Developers who
are removed from the project may not reapply for developer status
without first being cleared by the developer relations leads and the
ombudsman.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Conflict Investigation and Adjudication</title>
<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
What follows is written as if every complaint will have one or more
complainants disputing the actions of one developer. However, it is
possible that two or more developers have lodged complaints against
each other. In such a case, all such parties are respondents, and as a
result of the investigation, hearing, and Developer Relations review,
any number of them could be sanctioned for their actions.
</p>

<p>
Note that Developer Relations does not favor using this procedure for
resolving conflicts; resolution by the Ombudsman or by the individual
managers is preferred. Consequently, this procedure explicitly allows
that if the investigators conclude that a complaint is without merit,
and that the motive for the complaint appears to be to harass another
developer, then Developer Relations may still convene a hearing. But
in this case, the apparent harasser becomes the respondent.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Policy</title>
<body>

<p>
Occasionally, conflicts within the Gentoo community will give rise to
complaints which cannot be resolved by the parties involved. These
conflicts may arise between developers, or they may arise from user
complaints against individual developers. Except in cases questioning
technical competency, resolution of complaints against a developer is
the responsibility of Developer Relations. Resolution of conflicts
among users is outside the scope of this policy.
</p>

<p>
Most of these complaints are resolved by mediation by the Ombudsman or by the
developer's (or developers') top level manager(s) working with the parties
involved.  But this is not always possible. 
</p>

<p>
When it is not possible to resolve a developer--developer or
user--developer conflict by less formal means, Developer Relations
opens a formal inquiry of the complaint. This inquiry procedes in two
stages: firstly an investigation, then followed by a hearing if necessary.
</p>

<p>
<e><b>A</b>) Investigation</e>
</p>

<p>
Complaints are investigated by an investigation board convened for the
complaint in question. This board consists of 3 Developer Relations
members who are not otherwise involved in the complaint under
investigation. This board is responsible for examining all aspects of
the complaint, using whatever records are available and discussing the
complaint with the parties involved. Although not required, it is
highly desirable that the investigators involve the developers'
managers and mentors in this process because these individuals should
be in a position to provide valuable insight into the situation which
gave rise to the complaint.
</p>

<p>
This investigation serves two purposes. The first is to make very
clear to the parties engaged in the dispute just what the facts appear
to be, and thus to expedite a settlement. A hearing can result in
adverse consequences for all parties involved, and the investigation
can help clarify matters so that the hearing can be avoided. The
second purpose is to prepare a factual basis for a hearing if a
hearing proves to be necessary.
</p>

<p>
The investigation is similar to an Anglo-American Grand Jury
investigation and so is not public. Necessarily, the responding
developer and the complainants are aware of the investigation, as also
are any other members of the Gentoo developer or user communities who
are interviewed or consulted in the course of the investigation. It
can happen that the complainant(s) wish to remain anonymous. Such
requests are honored, but they are strongly disfavored. And, the
complainants forfeit anonymity if (1) the parties cannot resolve the
dispute during the investigation, and also (2) the investigators
determine that the issues raised are such that the complainants must
also act as respondents.
</p>

<p>
The investigation process collects evidence from various sources,
including IRC logs, relevant conversations, but not excluding other
sources of information. Evidence collected by the investigation is
not limited solely to the investigation board. Evidence may come from
third parties, it is the investigation board's responsibility to
determine if the evidence is relevant and factual, and if so, it may
include that in their results.
</p>

<p>
Within 30 days of the start of the investigation, if the parties have
not yet agreed to a resolution of their dispute the investigation
board reports its results to all of Developer Relations. If the board
concludes the complaint is without merit and Developer Relations as a
whole agrees, this is reported to all parties involved along with
supporting information and the board's reasoning. This provides for
quick resolution of complaints based on honest mistakes or
misunderstandings which did not become apparent earlier in the
resolution process. However, if the developers in question to the
action do not agree with this conclusion, Developer Relations proceeds
with a hearing as described in the next section.
</p>

<p>
If the investigators conclude that there is reason to believe the
complaint has merit, or if the only purpose of the complaint is to
harass the responding developer, then Developer Relations convenes a
formal hearing into the complaint (but in the second instance, the
person initiating the complaint is now responding). The hearing
procedure is described in the next section.
</p>

<p>
<e><b>B</b>) Hearing</e>
</p>

<p>
The hearing is conducted by a panel consisting of three Developer
Relations members who are otherwise not involved in the complaint in
question. Specifically, the panel members:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    Were not involved in the investigation leading up to the
    hearing, either as investigators or as parties.
  </li>
  <li>
    Are not Top Level Managers (because of the possible appeal to
    these managers, unless such requirement is impractical, in which
    case such a manager is precluded from participating in any
    subsequent appeal).
  </li>
  <li>
    Are not predisposed to favor or to disfavor the respondent
    developer.
  </li>
</ol>

<p>
As far as is practical, the hearing is open to the developer community
and to the complainants. The complainants and respondent are
appropriate participants and unless a complainant explicitly continues
to demand anonymity, they are known to each other.  The "anonymous
complainant" situation raises precedural and credibility issues which are
not addressed by this policy.  However, if the respondent is unable to
answer the complaint because the only evidence supporting the
complaint is provided anonymously and the complaining parties remain
unwilling to support their complaint to the respondent, due process
(fundamental fairness) considerations will require dismissal.
</p>

<note>
This is what is meant by "forfeiting anonymity" in the previous section.
</note>

<p>
The Developer Relations hearing is similar to other administrative
hearings. The judicial panel reviews the investigators' report and
takes further testimony as required to reach a decision. During this
process, both the respondent and the complainant(s) are invited to
present their own cases and to clarify or rebut evidence or testimony
as they feel is necessary.  This invitation is not a license for
either party to take control of the hearing, and it remains the
panel's responsibility to run the hearing professionally and fairly.
</p>

<p>
It is strongly advised that the hearing panel treat appropriate
managers and mentors as "expert witnesses" during the evidentiary
phase. The manager and the mentor of any developer complainant or
respondent are stongly encouraged to add their special insights into
the affair.
</p>

<p>
At the end of the evidentiary phase, the hearing panel makes a formal
ruling on the merits of the complaint, and if appropriate recommends
further discipliniary action. The findings of the hearing are
referred to the Developer Relations leads for further action
consistent with these findings.
</p>

<p>
<e><b>C</b>) Challenges</e>
</p>

<p>
Both the complainant(s) and the respondent may challenge a member of
either board for cause. Such challenges are resolved by Developer
Relations, or, in extreme cases, the TLP managers acting as an appeals
board.
</p>

<p>
<e><b>D</b>) Compelled participation</e>
</p>

<p>
Neither the investigators nor the hearing panel have "subpoena"
authority; they are not empowered to compel participation from any
unwilling party, including the developers in question themselves.
However, a developer's refusal to cooperate is relevant to
the decision process.
</p>

<p>
<e><b>E</b>) Ethics</e>
</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    Developer Relations members who feel they are unable to remain
    objective in any particular case are obligated to recuse
    themselves from the hearing board. Such developers are strongly
    urged to refuse to act as investigators as well, but in
    exceptional cases this might not be possible.
  </li>
  <li>
    Malicious complaints are not acceptable. If in the course of
    conflict resolution it becomes clear that a developer's complaint
    was brought in bad faith, that itself is grounds for disciplinary
    action. There is no specific action Developer Relations can take
    against a user who is acting in bad faith, although referring such
    a user to the forum moderators and IRC channel operators for
    action consistent with their authority could well be appropriate.
  </li>
  <li>
    The intent of the procedings described in this policy is to
    provide a fair and open framework for resolving conflicts and
    complaints which arise in the Gentoo community and which cannot be
    resolved by more informal means. This policy sets out a rather
    formal procedure for resolving complaints against active Gentoo
    developers and for recommending sanctions when appropriate.
  </li>
  <li>
    Because such procedings can have substantial consequences, they
    must both <e>be</e> fair and <e>appear</e> fair. This requires that
    all parties --- investigators, the hearing panel, complainants,
    respondents, and witnesses --- deport themselves as the
    professionals they are. Once this resolution procedure is
    invoked for any particular dispute, all participants are required
    to treat others involved in the case respectfully and courteously.
    Repeated or egregious failure to do so is itself cause for
    discipline consistent with the Developer Relations policy of which
    this is a part: i.e. a hearing panel has the authority to cite hearing
    participants for contempt.
  </li>
  <li>
    Although the investigation board may accept evidence collected
    from third parties, this does not exclude evidence collected by
    the judicial board. However, it is expected that the judicial
    board members do not conduct investigations on their own merits,
    as that would short-circuit the investigative process and
    circumvent the process this policy describes. To clarify, the
    judicial board members may submit anecdoctal evidence they have
    collected, such as comments overheard on IRC, for example,that may
    not be immediately available to the investigation board. However,
    they may not conduct investigations on their own.
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Miscellany</title>
<section>
<title>Leaves of Absence</title>
<body>

<p>
Often Gentoo developers go away on vacation, have to take a
short leave for University exams, or even go on a honeymoon. While
we applaud you for having a life outside Gentoo, we would like to
know when you leave and when you are expected to return.  When
you leave, alert your immediate development group as well as
making a devaway entry.
</p>

<p>
You need to create a file called <path>.away</path> in
your <path>/home/you</path> directory.  This file will contain the
details of your absence and will be reflected
at <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/devaway">the devaway site</uri>.
That page is updated once every hour.  Upon your return, simply delete
the <path>.away</path> file from your home directory.
</p>

<p>
An extended leave of absence is defined as inactivity for any period
of time longer than 60 days. Access to Gentoo infrastructure will very
likely be disabled during this time for security reasons. This means
that access to cvs and shell access to dev will be affected -- email
will likely not.  If developer relations is not made aware prior to an
extended period of inactivity, after 60 days the developer will be
considered retired and any return will be at the discretion of the
developer relations leads and the relevant project manager, if
applicable.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Post-retirement</title>
<body>

<p>
Retired developers will have their gentoo.org email address removed
from Gentoo mailing lists to prevent mail bounces. Retired developers
are responsible for resubscribing to public lists with a non-Gentoo
email address. Gentoo email addresses for retired developers will
remain as forwards for a period of thirty (30) days to allow
developers time to transition their mail.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
