<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/devrel/policy.xml">
<title>Developer Relations Policy Guide</title>
<author title="Author"><mail link="devrel@gentoo.org">Developer Relations</mail></author>

<abstract>Developer Relations Policy Guide</abstract>

<version>1.1.2</version>
<date>2006-08-27</date>

<chapter>
<title>Conflict resolution policy</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>		

<p>
While conflicts serious enough to require developer relations
involvement are rare, it's inevitable that developers will clash to
varying degrees. It's essential that the developer relations team find
fair and impartial resolutions to inter-developer problems. Although
all situations differ and exercising good judgment is necessary, these
guidelines are intended to define the most acceptable course of
action.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>When should developer relations be involved?</title>
<body>

<p>
Developer relations should only be involved in a conflict when other
attempts to solve the issue have failed.  Developers should attempt
polite discussion relating to the matter at hand to resolve conflict
between themselves.  Developers within a single top level project
(TLP) engaged in conflict may wish to consult with the TLP
manager. Although TLP managers are not necessarily qualified to
resolve personal disputes, technical issues resulting in conflict can
often be resolved within the TLP without Developer Relations
involvement. Personal issues should be brought to the ombudsman via
<mail link="ombudsman@gentoo.org">ombudsman@gentoo.org</mail>. Developer
relations may get involved when the above methods have failed.
</p>

<p>
Issues not necessarily related to personal conflict, such as
intentional or repeated policy breaches, malicious or abrasive
behavior to users or developers, or similar developer-specific
behavioral problems should be brought directly to Developer Relations
via <mail link="devrel@gentoo.org">devrel@gentoo.org</mail>.  These
should be dealt with on a case-by-case basis by Developer Relations
and may require disciplinary action.
</p>

<p>
Any complaint which the parties are not able to resolve themselves
using the resources described above is assigned to the Conflict
Resolution subproject for resolution. This process is described in
'Disciplinary Action and Resolution'.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Disciplinary action and resolution</title>

<section>
<title>Introduction</title>
<body>

<p>
Disciplinary action must be decided on a case-by-case basis by the
Developer Relations leads. For the majority of situations requiring
disciplinary action, a warning is enough to correct future
behavior. If behavior does not improve, a probationary period with
revoked access to Gentoo infrastructure of two weeks to one month is
appropriate. If upon restoration of access negative behavior
re-occurs, removal from the project will be necessary. In extreme
cases, suspension or removal may be necessary upon a single
offense. Except in critical situations where immediate action is
required, such disciplinary action is determined by members of the
Conflict Resolution subproject.
</p>

<p>
Upon removing a developer, the gentoo-core mailing list should be
notified. Additionally, the Developer Relations team and ombudsman
should be informed of the issues that led to removing or suspending a
developer. The ombudsman should keep a record of this for future
reference, which should preferably be stored on a bug. Developers who
are removed from the project may not reapply for developer status
without first being cleared by the Developer Relations leads and the
ombudsman.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Conflict Resolution Subproject</title>
<body>

<p>
Developer Relations has established a Conflict Resolution subproject
for resolving disputes covered by this policy.  This group consists of
one Developer Relations member as a strategic lead, four active Gentoo
developers who serve as a conflict resolution board, and alternates as
determined by the lead. The lead is chosen by the active Developer
Relations members, and the lead is responsible for selecting board
members and any alternates.  Developer Relations approves or rejects
the lead's choices.
</p>

<p>
The lead of the Conflict Resolution subproject is primarily a
strategic contact between the board and the Developer Relations leads,
and as such, has no voting role in determining the resolution of any
conflict unless needed to break a tie. However, the lead should be
involved in any conflict referred to this subproject, and must be
available to provide guidance, advice, or assistance if needed. The
lead is also charged with the tasks of ensuring all subproject members
are in fact active participants, that all members are eligible to
serve, that the subproject works to establish any necessary internal
procedures, and for similar administrative actions necessary for
proper functioning of the board.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Conflict Resolution Policy</title>
<body>

<p>
Once a complaint is sent to the Conflict Resolution subproject, the
board assumes responsibility for coordinating all aspects of the
complaint. The board must act in accordance with the following
guidelines:
</p>

<p>
Disputes between developers must first be referred to an ombudsman for
mediation. This step may be omitted only upon unanimous agreement
among the board members.
</p>

<p>
Complaints that do not require mediation per se (such as repeat QA
problems) are dealt with exclusively by the board. Problems the
ombudsman cannot resolve are also returned to the board for
resolution.
</p>

<p>
In either case, once a complaint reaches the board for final
resolution, the board should act upon the complaint in a timely
manner. Although it is impossible to establish absolute time limits,
unnecessary delays are not acceptable. It is up to the board members
themselves to establish communications among themselves. IRC is the
preferred communications medium, but e-mail is an acceptable
alternative if IRC proves to be impossible.
</p>

<p>
No matter how the board chooses to carry on its business, all official
proceedings including board meetings and voting sessions must be made
public. However, discussions with parties involved in a complaint held
for the purpose of mediation may be kept private at the request either
of the parties or of the board members meeting with the parties. The
subproject lead is responsible for releasing (the public) logs or
e-mails to the devrel mail alias and for maintaining an archive of all
public documents. In the case of private discussions, a summary of the
non-sensitive parts of the discussion should be provided.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Resolution and Appeal</title>
<body>

<p>
Once the board members determine they have enough information to reach
a conclusion, they meet to make a final determination of the
appropriate resolution of the complaint. The subproject lead does not
vote in determining this final resolution unless needed to break a
tie.
</p>

<p>
Any party to a dispute resolved by the board may appeal the resolution
to the Developer Relations leads. No other developer may appeal.
</p>

<p>
In case of an appeal, the Developer Relations leads must take one of two
actions. They may deny the appeal and refer it to the Council for final
resolution.
</p>

<p>
Or, they may accept the appeal. If they accept the appeal, the leads
must immediately post the appeal to the devrel mail alias for vote on
the appeal by all of Developer Relations. Developer Relations members
then have three days in which to vote to accept or deny the appeal.
</p>

<p>
If a majority of those who vote agree with the appeal, then the appeal
is successful.  In this case, the judgment of the board is modified as
requested in the appeal.
</p>

<p>
If Developer Relations votes to deny the appeal, then the judgment of
the board is accepted unmodified. The outcome of such a vote may be
appealed to the Council for resolution, but again only parties affected
by the resolution are allowed to appeal.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Ethical Considerations</title>
<body>

<p>
For any complaint sent to the Conflict Resolution subproject, the
Developer Relations leads and the subproject lead should speak with
each board member to determine any conflict of interest issues. Board
members having a conflict of interest in any particular dispute may
not participate in the resolution of that dispute. They should be
replaced by an alternate chosen by the subproject lead.  Whether the
alternate becomes a permanent board member or whether the member
rotated out is brought back at the end of the dispute is left to the
discretion of the subproject lead.
</p>

<p>
Complaints raised about any member of the Conflict Resolution
subproject may be raised to the Developer Relations leads or at
Developer Relations meetings for discussion at any time. Under extreme
circumstances, Developer Relations as a whole may vote to remove
members from the conflict resolution subproject. Also, board members
may be replaced at the subproject lead's discretion with an
explanation to Developer Relations.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Miscellany</title>
<section>
<title>Leaves of Absence</title>
<body>

<p>
Often Gentoo developers go away on vacation, have to take a
short leave for University exams, or even go on a honeymoon. While
we applaud you for having a life outside Gentoo, we would like to
know when you leave and when you are expected to return.  When
you leave, alert your immediate development group as well as
making a devaway entry.
</p>

<p>
You need to create a file called <path>.away</path> in
your <path>/home/you</path> directory.  This file will contain the
details of your absence and will be reflected
at <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/devaway">the devaway site</uri>.
That page is updated once every hour.  Upon your return, simply delete
the <path>.away</path> file from your home directory.
</p>

<p>
An extended leave of absence is defined as inactivity for any period
of time longer than 60 days. Access to Gentoo infrastructure will very
likely be disabled during this time for security reasons. This means
that access to CVS and shell access to dev will be affected -- email
will likely not.  If developer relations is not made aware prior to an
extended period of inactivity, after 60 days the developer will be
considered retired and any return will be at the discretion of the
developer relations leads and the relevant project manager, if
applicable.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Post-retirement</title>
<body>

<p>
Retired developers will have their gentoo.org email address removed
from Gentoo mailing lists to prevent mail bounces. Retired developers
are responsible for resubscribing to public lists with a non-Gentoo
email address. Gentoo email addresses for retired developers will
remain as forwards for a period of forty-five (45) days to allow
developers time to transition their mail.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
