<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
	<name>devrel</name>
	<longname>Gentoo Developer Relations</longname>
	<description>
		The Gentoo Developer Relations Project is an effort to recruit, train,
		and maintain developers for the various Gentoo projects.
	</description>

	<longdescription>
		<p>Gentoo Developer Relations is a project in Gentoo which aims to be a
			point of contact for prospective developers, as well as a point of
			contact for current developers.  For prospective developers, we use
			the mailing lists, the forums and the
			<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org"> Gentoo bug tracker</uri> to 
			watch for, and invite, prospective developers. 
		</p>
	</longdescription>
	<goals>
		<p>The stated goal for Gentoo Developer Relations is to act as a meeting
			point for Gentoo developers and advanced users both.  As such, 
			Gentoo Developer Relations is concerned with both intra-developer 
			relations as well as forming relations with advanced users and 
			prospective developers.
		</p>
	</goals>
	
	<extraproject name="Intra-Developer Relations">
		<p>Here, we maintain a constantly updated roster of developers, and
			their areas of development.  This will be not only the devlist, but
			also the herds document, which will list the various herd projects
			in the portage tree, along with the herd manager (point of contact).
			Additionally, we maintain a record of developers' GPG public keys to
			provide a single area for developer lookup.
		</p>
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="Recruitment and Training">
		<p>Currently, we have a process on the <uri
		link="http://bugs.gentoo.org"> Gentoo bug tracker</uri> which tracks a
		new developer's progress from initial contact through training and
		final sign up.  As part of a new developer's training, they must
		fulfill several requirements, culminating in a quiz/questionnaire.
		Every new developer is assigned to a mentor on the Gentoo
		development team.</p>
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="User Relations">
		<p>The goal of
		<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/user-relations.xml"> 
		this sub-project</uri> is to interface with the user community, to seek 
		out motivated and skilled individuals for prospective hiring.  
		Essentially, the concerns of the community with respect to developer 
		relations will be listened to, and where possible, addressed.
		</p>
		<p>Potential developers should be able to easily learn about current
		projects, project goals, openings in areas where their skills may be
		used etc.  Also there are bound to be many advanced users who may not
		wish to become developers, yet do have the expertise to help enrich
		Gentoo. We will investigate ways in which these individuals might help
		the development community (via document translation, bug resolution 
		etc.)</p>
		<p>An established method of listening to user concerns regarding
		developments issues is important. The forums, IRC and mailing lists
		do a great job, but development-specific questions/suggestions/concerns
		should ideally be made available to the development community.
		Gentoo Developer Relations will aim to provide timely feedback to these
		suggestions, or forward their suggestions to the relevant
		parties.</p>
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="Manager Meetings">
		<p>The goal of
		<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/manager-meetings.xml">
		this sub-project</uri> is to ensure that the fortnightly
		Managers' Meetings are widely attended, well organised, fruitful.
		In an effort to involve non-managers, only non-managers will be
		allowed to chair the meetings.  As such, it falls into our hands to
		select the chairs (randomly after the initial test phase) for each
		meeting.</p>
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="Developer Conflict Resolution">
		<p>Grant Goodyear recently proposed a <uri
		link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/"> GLEP (Gentoo Linux
		Enhancement Proposal)</uri> calling for an <uri
		link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/glep/glep-0007.html">Ombudsman</uri>
		to aid in developer conflict resolution.  We would like to implement
		this plan in the near future.  Also pro-active policies that are
		aimed at preventing technical/interpersonal conflicts will be
		developed; set channels of communication will also be developed in which
		developers can voice concerns (anything from technical disagreements
		to developer burnout) confidentially before these concerns degenerate 
		into personal conflicts.</p>
	</extraproject>
	<extraproject name="Recruitment Policy">
		<p>One of the biggest questions in the user community is how to
		become a Gentoo Developer.  We will attempt to outline our
		requirements for a prospective developer as well as provide an
		interface for prospective developers to contact the recruitment and
		training team.  The requirements outline will include both etiquette
		and development guidelines for developers.  One idea would be to
		create a comprehensive Developers' Handbook to cover everything from
		development policy through etiquette expectations to conflict
		resolution.  Currently, interested parties can contact
		<mail link="recruiters@gentoo.org">recruiters</mail></p>
	</extraproject>

		<dev role="User Relations"> <mail link="spyderous@gentoo.org">Donnie
		Berkholz</mail>spyderous</dev>
		<dev role="Lead" description="Ombudsman Project"><mail
		link="g2boojum@gentoo.org">Grant Goodyear</mail>g2boojum</dev>
		<dev role="Lead" description="Developer Relations TLP"><mail
		link="seemant@gentoo.org">Seemant Kulleen</mail>seemant</dev>
		<dev role="infrastructure" description="E-mail and CVS account and
		access support"><mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
		klieber</dev>
		<dev role="Lead Developer" description="Developer Profiles"><mail
		link="coredumb@gentoo.org">Tal Peer</mail>coredumb</dev>
		<dev role="Operational Manager" description="Developer Relations
		TLP"><mail link="avenj@gentoo.org">Jon Portnoy</mail>avenj</dev>
		<dev role="infrastructure" description="Mailing Lists and Developer
		Roster"><mail link="cybersystem@gentoo.org">Sascha
		Schwabbauer</mail>cybersystem</dev>
		<dev role="Lead" description="User Relations Project"><mail
		link="brandy@gentoo.org">Brandy Westcott</mail>brandy</dev>


<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>I Want to Participate</title>
<body>
<p>
To participate in the Gentoo Developer Relations project, please contact
seemant or avenj via email or irc.  Additionally the recruiters email
address, as listed in the above table can be contacted with the subject:
DevRel Personnel.
</p>
</body>
</extrachapter>
</project>
