<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/base/sparc/at/procedures.xml,v 1.6 2015/01/19 08:45:25 armin76 Exp $ -->

<!-- The context of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommonds.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<guide lang="en" disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:SPARC/AT/Procedures">
<title>Gentoo/SPARC Arch Testers' Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="hparker@gentoo.org">hparker@gentoo.org</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This Guide shows you how to test packages for stablization/inclusion into the testing tree.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.4</version>
<date>2008-12-08</date>

<chapter>
<title/>
<section>
<title>Marking Stable:  When and How?</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~tcunha/reports/imlate-sparc.txt">imlate</uri> 
file is there to show which packages on sparc are lagging
behind on x86 and need to be tested and eventually marked stable. It's
very useful to have people systematically testing these packages - it
helps to keep sparc as up-to-date as possible. The following guidelines
are specifically aimed at Gentoo/SPARC Arch Testers (ATs) doing testing.
</p>

<ul>
<li>
  Check the newest version of the package is marked ~sparc (TESTING),
  if not please read the next section of the document for the steps
  to follow to quickly/efficiently have a package keyworded ~sparc.
  <br/><br/>
</li>

<li>
  If the package is already ~sparc, then:
  <ul>
    <li>
      Check to see when it was marked ~sparc. There should be a date
      in the package changelog, but if there isn't please use the
      ViewCVS functionality on http://sources.gentoo.org to look for
      the date it was keyworded ~sparc. If it was less than 30 days
      ago, the package is not eligible to be marked stable, but
      testing and feedback are still greatly appreciated.
    </li>
    <li>
      Check for bugs on this particular version of the package. If a
      bug has been open in the last 30 days, it is not eligible.
    </li>
    <li>
      If it has been in testing for more than 30 days, and has not
      had an open bug in the last 30 days, you need to test it in a
      thorough and systematic manner. Every conceivable permutation
      should be checked and rechecked - if it breaks you need to go
      onto Bugzilla and open a relevent bug. If it doesn't break and
      you are totally satisfied it's stable, continue to the final
      step -- but beware, its your head if this package breaks!
    </li>
    <li>
      Assuming it meets all the criteria (tested for 30+ days, no
      bugs in the last 30 days, AT tested) you may open a bug with
      the title '&lt;category&gt;/&lt;package&gt;-&lt;version&gt; is stable on SPARC'.
      Assign the bug directly to sparc@gentoo.org to avoid making
      more work for the poor Bug Wranglers. You should include the
      output of your 'emerge --info' and keyword the bug <c>STABLE</c>. Just
      wait a while, a developer will review the bug, and mark stable.
    </li>
  </ul>
</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Marking Testing:  What's the drill?</title>
<body>

<p>
In some cases the imlate file may show packages where the latest version is
not yet ~sparc, or a new and popular package needs to be keyworded ~sparc. In
these cases, we need to have them 'marked testing' - so when they're bug free
for thirty days they can be made sparc stable.
</p>

<ul>
<li>
  Check the package hasn't already got any open bugs regarding it being
  marked testing. Quite often users will prod us about popular packages
  needing a keyword before any devs/ATs even notice ;)<br/><br/>
</li>

<li>
  If the package doesn't have a bug yet, go ahead and start:<br/><br/>
  <ul>
    <li>
      Check to see whether previous versions of the package were in
      testing or stable on SPARC. If the version increment is only a
      minor one (1.4.0 to 1.4.1) and previous version was stable, it's
      slightly different to where a package has had a major version
      increment or has never been ~sparc/sparc.<br/><br/>
      <ul>
	<li>
	  <b>
	    Previous version keyworded, minor version increment</b><br/>
	    Check the changelog for the version increment, install the package
            and test any new, improved or otherwise modified features. Check
            the install is smooth, everyday functionality is there and there
            are no glaringly obvious bugs. If you see any bugs, file them on
            Bugzilla and when they're resolved test again. If everything seems
            okay, proceed to the final stage (putting in the ~sparc request).
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <b>Previous version keyworded, major version increment</b><br/>
	    Check the changelog, install the package and test all the new and
            improved features. Check for bugs in previous versions, see if they
            have been fixed and be especially careful to see whether new ones
            crept in with all the new code. Test all the other functionality,
            even stuff which you 'think' will work - a major version increment
            means a lot of changes, and it's treated almost like a new addition
            to the tree - everything has to be tested and verified. If you're
            happy it seems to be running okay, proceed to the final stage.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    <b>New package, not keyworded before</b><br/>
	    Anything which has never been sparc keyworded before is a little
            more tricky to process. You don't have a nice changelog to refer
            to for a list of things to test, a previous version which worked
            to use as reference or much other help. You need to install the
            package and then test thoroughly:<br/><br/>
            <ol>
              <li>
                 Package should install without errors and be ready to run
                 'out of the box' with minimal effort on the part of user.
              </li>
              <li>
                 Major functionality (which isn't hard to test) should all
                 work with no significant errors. Minor errors like a typo
                 are probably acceptable, and we understand you can't go
                 through every operation possible, but it should work in
                 an acceptable manner for day-to-day usage by a user.
              </li>
              <li>
                 Package shouldn't break anything related...
              </li>
            </ol><br/>
            Assuming it installs, loads and works pretty well with no major
            errors - please proceed to the final step and congratulate your
            computer on adding yet another package to the expanding arsenal!
	  </li>
	<li>
	    <b>Package requires patches that are in bugs.gentoo.org</b><br/>
	    Make a comment in your bug stating that these patches fix issues
	    with the package, and CC the maintainer of the package. Developers
	    will then wait 7-30 days to commit if maintainer does not handle
	    the bug. The types of patches in this category include: arch 
	    specific patches, multi-lib strict, etc.
	</li>
	</ul>
      <br/>
      </li>
      
      <li>
	Assuming your testing efforts above went well, and all procedures were
        followed, you are now ready to open a bug and metaphysically prod a dev
	into committing the change.
	<br/><br/>
	<ul>
	  <li>
	    Open a bug with '&lt;category&gt;/&lt;package&gt;-&lt;version&gt; is TESTED on SPARC'
	    as the title. Assign the bug a keyword:  TESTED
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Assign the bug directly to sparc@gentoo.org - saves giving those
	    Bug Wranglers yet another grey hair on their already snowy heads.
	  </li>
	  <li>
	    Include a short description of the package, what you tested and
            your 'emerge info'. Explicitly specify you wish the ~sparc to be
            added to the keywords, it helps us grumpy old developers focus
	    at 3am in the morning when sleep is probably a good idea ;)
	  </li>
	  <li>Sit back and wait, someone will resolve the bug ASAP.</li>
	</ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
