<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide type="newsletter" lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Monthly Newsletter</title>
<subtitle>20 May 2008</subtitle>

<!-- Be sure to add yourself if you write an article -->
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="anant"/>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="andrey@afalko.net">Andrey Falko</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dol-sen@telus.net">Brian Dolbec</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="phajdan.jr@gmail.com">Paweł Hajdan, Jr</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="auke.booij@gmail.com">Auke Booij</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="opfer"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dberkholz"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This is the fifth issue of the Gentoo Monthly Newsletter, for April 2008
&ndash; May 2008.
</abstract>

<summary/>

<version>Volume 1, Issue 5</version>
<date>2008-05-20</date>

<!-- GMN Intro -->
<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>

<section>
<title>This month in the GMN</title>
<body>

<p>
Welcome to the May issue of the Gentoo monthly newsletter!
</p>

<p>
As usual, you can discuss any aspect of this issue of the GMN in the
corresponding <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-p-5071942.html">
forum thread</uri>. We look forward to hearing from you!
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo News -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo News</title>

<section>
<title>Gentoo Foundation reinstated</title>
<body>

<p>
Thanks to the efforts of the <uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/foundation/en/">Gentoo Trustees</uri>, the Gentoo
Foundation is once again a <uri
link="http://archives.gentoo.org/gentoo-nfp/msg_d2632d76e6582187bb1816897bb81ffd.xml">nonprofit
organization</uri>.
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <uri
    link="http://www.nmprc.state.nm.us/cgi-bin/prcdtl.cgi?2463313+GENTOO+FOUNDATION+INC">The
    completed legal paperwork</uri>
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<!-- Council Summary -->
<section>
<title>Council Meeting Summary</title>
<body>

<p>
The <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/council/">Gentoo Council</uri> held
its monthly meeting on May 8, 2008. The items put up for discussion were:
</p>

<ul>
 <li>
   <b>Active-developer document</b>: We reviewed it and made some suggestions
   for improving both the document and the online developer list (adding
   dates).
 </li>
 <li>
   <b>ChangeLog entries</b>: Always required. If you aren't making them now, fix
   your script to call <c>echangelog</c>.
 </li>
 <li>
   <b>Ignored arch-team bugs</b>: What's the workflow for undermanned arch
   teams?  Can we improve it?
 </li>
 <li>
   <b>8-digit versions</b>: Ask package maintainers with extremely long PVs
   whether they were needed and test the impact of extending
   <path>versionator.eclass</path>.  Make decision once this data is available.
 </li>
 <li>
   <b>Enforced retirement</b>: After 2.5 hours on the previous topics, people
   had to go to sleep and <mail link="jokey@gentoo.org">jokey</mail>'s computer
   broke. Instead of waiting till the next regular meeting, because of its
   urgency, we scheduled a special session next week at the same time. The
   appeals will *not* be decided then -- it's about figuring out the validity
   and the process.
 </li>
 <li>
   <b>New meeting process</b>: 105 minutes were closed and 57 were open. It
   might save some time if we always moderated, but it won't cut it in half.
   Should we keep doing this, or modify it a little to have a moderated
   #gentoo-council and open backchannel?

 </li>
</ul>

<p>
Some items were rolled over from the previous meeting:
</p>

<ul>
 <li>
   <b>Document of being an active developer</b>: <mail
   link="araujo@gentoo.org">araujo</mail> made
   <uri>http://dev.gentoo.org/~araujo/gcert1.pdf</uri> in Scribus. He'd like to
   ask for approval of this design and discuss the script, in particular its
   infrastructure requirements.
 </li>
 <li><b>Slacker arches</b>: No updates</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>

<!--- Coming up -->
<section>
<title>Coming Up</title>
<body>

<ul>
 <li>
   <b><uri link="http://www.linuxtag.org/2008/">LinuxTag Berlin</uri></b>: The
   biggest European Linux event is on again. On the Berlin Fairgrounds, Gentoo
   will be featured again. Join developers and users on the booth between
   <b>May 28 and 31</b>, we hope it'll be as much fun as Chemnitz was!
 </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Heard in the Community -->
<chapter>
<title>Heard in the Community</title>

<section>
<title>Interview: Google Summer of Code Student Eric Thibodeau</title>
<body>

<p>
GSOC has started, and GMN editor <mail link="anant"/> has interviewed one of
Gentoo's students, <mail link="kyron@neuralbs.com">Eric Thibodeau</mail>.
</p>

<p>
<b>GMN:</b> Give us a brief introduction of yourself. Where are you from? Where
and what do you study? What's your homepage or other means for fans to stalk
you?
</p>

<p>
<b>Eric:</b> I am from Montréal, Québec (Canada) and have been studying at the
École de technologies supérieures (aka ETS) since 2000. I've completed a
bachelor's degree in Electrical Engineering (Information Technology profile) and
was offered to continue on with a masters in parallel processing and
Multi-objective Genetic Algorithm profiling which I am hoping/have to finish
this summer ;). I've given BASH labs and classes at that same University on and
off depending on my time availability (now why am I giving a lab this summer is
beyond me ;) ).
</p>

<p>
I use my personal wiki (<uri>http://wiki.neuralbs.com</uri>) mostly as a sandbox
for jotting down stuff I do with Gentoo. I am not a big fan of personal web
pages since they are outdated by definition and would require too much of my
time. The best way to reach me is usually by poking at me on Freenode where I
lurk around and pester the really smart people from
#gentoo-(cluster|science|server).
</p>

<p>
<b>GMN:</b> Were you already involved with Gentoo and/or open source in general
before acceptance into SoC? If yes, briefly tell us how you got involved and why
you like writing open source code.
</p>

<p>
<b>Eric:</b> I've been mostly involved with Gentoo as a sysadmin, user and a
preacher (of some sorts). Due to my studies, my involvement usually revolved
around creating ebuilds for packages that were missing from the tree (ie:
OpenMPI which I was really glad a real dev took over ;) ),  reporting bugs and
sharing my experience/expertise surrounding parallel processing, NFS booted
Gentoo SSI (Single System Image) and High Performance Computing.
</p>

<p>
<b>GMN:</b> How has your experience with the Gentoo community been so far?
</p>

<p>
<b>Eric:</b> I can't really give an assessment of the Gentoo "community" since
I've been using Gentoo since 2002 and might be biased by my first impression
which was 1) excellent documentation, 2) The "raison d'être" of open-source and
Linux: software compiled and optimized specifically for your hardware and
finally 3) A very active community where anyone can easily contribute (ebuilds
are <e>just</e> text files).
</p>

<p>
<b>GMN:</b> Please tell our readers a little about the project you're working
on, and why you think it will be helpful to Gentoo users. What was your
inspiration for starting the project? What do you expect to achieve with it?
</p>

<p>
<b>Eric:</b> I'll be working on building a Gentoo LiveCD/DVD with a twist: it
will be used to create a Beowulf computation cluster "on the fly". I picked this
project up after seeing a request for such a CD on the gentoo-science mailing
list (it was actually "if there is someone crazy enough out there").
</p>

<p>
What prompted me to take on the project is the fact that I have rebuilt a
cluster a few years back by creating my own Gentoo SSI and cluster head node.
The process was long, frustrating, half-documented and mostly not completed to
my satisfaction due to lack of tool integration and poor reproducibility of my
setup. My primary goal is to make clustering under Gentoo more accessible and
faster to deploy rather than learning every bits and pieces required to build
such an infrastructure. 
</p>

<p>
<b>GMN:</b> What do you do when you're not coding? (hobbies, interests, favorite
T.V. shows etc.)
</p>

<p>
<b>Eric:</b> Apart from coming up with excuses to stay in front of the computer
to "chat with this otherwise never accessible godlike dev" on IRC, I enjoy
taking care of my nine month old daughter, watching off-beat movies with my
girlfriend. Although it's been a while since I've had a chance to do so, I
usually help out in designing some eccentric clothing
(<uri>http://www.mekkreations.com</uri>) which tend to reuse computer parts
(hard disks are so cool!)
</p>

<p>
<b>GMN:</b> Thanks for your time, and wish you all the best for the Summer!
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Porthole 0.6.0 nearing release</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://porthole.sourceforge.net/">Porthole</uri> is a gtk+ Portage
tree browser and front-end. It strives to put the most important and
useful information there for you to learn about a package before deciding to
upgrade or install it. It also provides the most commonly used emerge operations
with just a click or two. One of Porthole's greatest features is that information
is much quicker to find, especially if you do not know what you are looking for.
Porthole can search for (partial or complete) package names, as well as
searching package descriptions.
</p>

<p>
Porthole allows you to easily select and set USE flags, keywords, select
specific versions to emerge or unmerge, and toggle any of the emerge options off
or on. There is also a "Run Custom Command" option to send nearly any command to
Porthole's terminal. The terminal has configurable message filtering (since
before Portage implemented elog capabilities) and has a command queue that can
be paused and restarted.
</p>

<p>
New in porthole-0.6.0 is a saved description database that Porthole creates and
automatically updates when it sees that the Portage tree has been updated. This
provides for very fast description searches even on older slower hardware. The
results are browseable with just a mouse click.
</p>

<p>
Another new feature in porthole-0.6.0 is the ability to add "Sets" support to
existing Portage versions without waiting for <c>portage-2.2</c> or switching to
<c>pkgcore</c> or <c>paludis</c>. Sets let you easily create your own package
groups such as a custom Gnome set, a server set, etc.
</p>

<p>
Porthole is available in several languages, and its developers are looking for
volunteers to update the translations and add new languages. They would also
like additional arch testing. Follow its development on <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/show_bug.cgi?id=219968">Bugzilla</uri> and <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-550420.html">this forum
thread</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Project Sunrise: the Gentoo user overlay</title>
<body>

<p>
We all know that the Portage tree is huge, but even with the size of Portage,
sometimes some package is missing: a plug-in for some specific mail client, or a
brand-new fork of a web server. In such cases, you'd usually file a bug at <uri
link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>, but there's some chance
your ebuilds won't make it to the tree from there, at least not for awhile.
</p>

<p>
The trouble is "maintainer-wanted@gentoo.org" in the AssignedTo field, which
indicates that a Gentoo developer has yet to step up and maintain your package.
How about being your own maintainer of a package? Guess what: it's possible!
</p>

<p>
Thanks to <uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/sunrise">Project
Sunrise</uri>, you can make your own ebuild and add it to a package overlay
maintained by users. After a review of your ebuild by Gentoo developers (which
usually takes at most two days), everyone will be able to easily install your
ebuild, as transparently as if it was in the Portage tree.
</p>

<p>
Interested? Check out <uri>http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/sunrise</uri> or stop
by on IRC at <uri
link="irc://irc.freenode.net/gentoo-sunrise">#gentoo-sunrise</uri> on
irc.freenode.net. Happy ebuild crafting!
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Interview with Donnie Berkholz</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo developer <mail link="dberkholz"/> talked to David Abbott of <uri
link="http://linuxcrazy.com/">LinuxCrazy</uri>. Download the <uri
link="http://linuxcrazy.com/?q=node/33">podcast</uri>. A transcript is available
on the <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?p=5099210#5099210">Gentoo
Forums</uri>.
</p>

<p>
He described how he became a developer and his work on X, the council, and the
public relations team and the Summer of Code project he's mentoring for. Donnie
also recommended the best video cards to buy if you want to support open source.
He saw the Linux desktop's future as increasing integration and security. Here's
how Donnie described how Gentoo makes progress and where to go from here:
</p>

<p>
"The more time I spend in Gentoo, the more I realize that it's the 
individual developers who really drive most of our innovations. They 
don't happen because the council makes a decision. They happen because 
the developer, or a few of them, think that it sounds like a cool idea, 
and make it happen."
</p>

<p>
"Making Gentoo great is my biggest goal right now, and greatness is a 
process. It's not a place. So you can't get somewhere and say you're 
great. You always have to keep striving for it. For a while we've been 
content to stick with the status quo instead of striving for greatness, 
but we have to change that and to always improve Gentoo."
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- Planet Gentoo -->
<section>
<title>Planet Gentoo</title>
<body>

<p>
<b>Decibel Audio Player</b>: <mail link="nightmorph"/> has been <uri
link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/nightmorph/2008/04/26/new_ebuild_decibel_audio_player">working</uri>
to bring <uri link="http://decibel.silent-blade.org">Decibel</uri>, a clean,
userfriendly gtk+ audio player, to Gentoo. It's finally been <uri
link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/nightmorph/2008/05/16/decibel_hits_the_tree">added
to the tree</uri>, so <uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~nightmorph/decibel/">try
it out</uri>.
</p>

<p>
<b>Microcode</b>: <mail link="dirtyepic"/> informs how one can load <uri
link="http://psykil.livejournal.com/324031.html">microcode updates</uri> for
Intel-based processors.
</p>

<p>
<b>Python</b>: As Python is the base for our main package manager, <mail
link="hawking"/> tells us about the <uri
link="http://hawking.nonlogic.org/archives/2008/04/19/latest_news_from_gentoopython/">current
state</uri> of Python.
</p>

<p>
<b>Portage</b>: Portage developer <mail link="zmedico"/> describes some new
features of Portage and documents the behavior of Portage in detail: <uri
link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/zmedico/2008/04/22/portage_dependency_resolution_decision_m">dependency
resolution</uri> and <uri
link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/zmedico/2008/05/06/blocker_conflict_automatic_uninstall">automatic
unmerge</uri> on <uri
link="http://planet.gentoo.org/developers/zmedico/2008/05/09/blocking_package_file_collisions">blocker</uri>
</p>

<p>
<b>No Gentoo on virtual server? No problem!</b>: <mail link="wrobel"/> has a
guide on how to install Gentoo on rented <uri
link="http://log.onthebrink.de/2008/04/gentoo-on-1-vserver.html">virtual
servers</uri>.
</p>

<p>
<b>System tool</b>: <mail link="araujo"/> announces the 0.20 version of his tool
<uri
link="http://araujoluis.blogspot.com/2008/05/himerge-020-release.html">Himerge</uri>,
a graphical frontend to Portage.
</p>

<p>
<b>Replacing grep</b>: Although it sounds weird, <mail link="klausman"/>
describes why there is nice <uri
link="http://blog.i-no.de//archives/2008/05/06/index.html#e2008-05-06T16_44_51.txt">alternative</uri>
to <uri
link="http://blog.i-no.de//archives/2008/05/07/index.html#e2008-05-07T21_31_43.txt">grep</uri>.
</p>

<p>
<b>LZMA vs. bzip2</b>: As more and more GNU tarballs are available as LZMA
compressed files, <mail link="klausman"/> does a quick <uri
link="http://blog.i-no.de//archives/2008/05/08/index.html#e2008-05-08T16_35_13.txt">comparison</uri>
of the standard compression tools.
</p>

<p>
<b>Organising meetings on IRC</b>: <mail link="dberkholz"/> has some experience
in organising IRC meetings as member of the Gentoo council. His <uri
link="http://dberkholz.wordpress.com/2008/05/13/how-to-run-an-effective-meeting-on-irc/">experience</uri>
is worth sharing.
</p>

<p>
<b>RDEPEND vs. DEPEND</b>: <mail link="flameeyes"/> has written down a <uri
link="http://blog.flameeyes.eu/articles/2008/05/15/when-you-should-use-rdepend-and-when-you-should-use-depend">summary</uri>
of the differences between RDEPEND and DEPEND and why you should respect them.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<!-- Gentoo in the News -->
<section>
<title>Gentoo in the News</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo received a <uri
link="http://jonesproductionsltd.com/opinion/gentoo.aspx">favorable review</uri>
from Jones Productions, even beating Ubuntu 8.04. The author also praised the
extensive documentation.
</p>

<p by="From the review">
The thing I love most about Gentoo is it gives the user the power to do anything
they want, and its just awesome to be able to use a Distro that you built
yourself.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Tips and Tricks -->
<chapter>
<title>Tips and Tricks</title>

<section>
<title>Command-line network monitoring</title>
<body>

<p>
Have you ever wanted facilities like top, but for your computer's network? This
tip shows you what options you have in command-line network monitors.
</p>

<p>
The first is <uri link="http://iptraf.seul.org/">IPTraf</uri>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing IPTraf">
# <i>emerge iptraf</i>
</pre>

<p>
Using it is easy:
</p>

<pre caption="Using IPTraf">
$ <i>iptraf</i>
</pre>

<p>
It is a highly advanced <c>ncurses</c> interface. You can choose view your
network status from many angles: IP traffic by port and IP address, general
interface statistics such as number of packets passing through, speed and volume
of packets passing through, and much more.
</p>

<p>
Another network monitor is <c>vnstat</c>. This program is useful for historical
statistics. It keeps a database for your interfaces.
</p>

<pre caption="Installing vnstat">
# <i>emerge vnstat</i>
</pre>

<p>
It will need an hour to gather enough statistics. <c>vnstat</c> is installed
with a cron script (<path>/etc/cron.hourly/vnstat</path>) that updates
<c>vnstat</c>'s database every hour.  Once you have enough data in the database
you can get hourly, daily, and monthly data from <c>vnstat</c>. For example, to
see hourly statistics:
</p>

<pre caption="Viewing hourly statistics">
$ <i>vnstat -h</i>
</pre>

<p>
A third program is <c>iftop</c>. <c>iftop</c> does for networking what
<c>top</c> does for CPU usage. It shows you which connections have the most
traffic going in and out. Install <c>iftop</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing iftop">
# <i>emerge iftop</i>
</pre>

<p>
Then run and use it just like top:
</p>

<pre caption="Running iftop">
$ <i>iftop</i>
</pre>

<p>
You can press <c>?</c> to view options that you can use.
</p>


</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Gentoo developer moves -->
<chapter>
<title>Gentoo developer moves</title>

<section>   
<title>Summary</title>
<body>

<p>
Gentoo is made up of 261 active developers, of which 43 are currently away.
Gentoo has recruited a total of 642 developers since its inception.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Moves</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently left the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Stephen Bennet (spb)</li>
  <li>Richard Brown (rbrown)</li>
  <li>Wulf C. Krueger (philantrop)</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Adds</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently joined the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>Jeremy Olexa (darkside) joined the Gentoo/Alt Prefix team</li>
  <li>Michael Hammer (mueli) joined the Kerberos team</li>
  <li>Markus Duft (mduft) joined the Gentoo/Alt Prefix team</li>
  <li>Chris Henhawk (bunder) joined the Forums staff</li>
  <li>Andrey Grozin (grozin) joined the Science team</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Changes</title>
<body>

<p>
The following developers recently changed roles within the Gentoo project:
</p>

<ul>
 <li>Joshua Saddler (nightmorph) joined the GMN team</li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Portage summaries -->
<chapter>
<title>Portage</title>

<section>
<title>Summary</title>
<body>

<p>
This section summarizes the current state of the Portage tree.
</p>

<figure link="/images/gmn/20080520/keywords.png" short="Packages by keyword" caption="Package distribution by keyword"/>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The following section lists packages that have either been moved or added to the
tree. The package removals come from many locations, including the <uri
link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/">Treecleaners</uri> and various developers.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Removals:</title>
<body>

<p>

</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Additions:</title>
<body>

<p>

</p>

</body>
</section>
<!-- paste from the last rites script -->
<!-- On hiatus :( -->
</chapter>

<!-- Bugzilla -->
<chapter>
<title>Bugzilla</title>

<section>
<title>Statistics</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo community uses Bugzilla
(<uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>) to record
and track bugs, notifications, suggestions and other interactions
with the development team. The following chart summarizes activity on
Bugzilla between 20 April 2008 and 20 May 2008.
</p>

<figure link="/images/gmn/20080520/activity.png" short="Bug activity" caption="Bug activity split-up"/>

<p>
Of the <b>11141</b> currently open bugs: <b>16</b> are labeled <e>blocker</e>,
<b>103</b> are labeled <e>critical</e>, and <b>374</b> are labeled <e>major</e>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Closed bug ranking</title>
<body>

<p>
The developers and teams who have closed the most bugs during this period are as follows.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Rank</th>
  <th>Developer/Team</th>
  <th>Bug Count</th>
</tr>

<tr>
  <ti>0</ti>
  <ti>Others</ti>
  <ti>1181</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>1</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</ti>
  <ti>61</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>2</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo Security</ti>
  <ti>47</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>3</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo Games</ti>
  <ti>46</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>4</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</ti>
  <ti>45</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>5</ti>
  <ti>Perl Devs @ Gentoo</ti>
  <ti>43</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>6</ti>
  <ti>Java team</ti>
  <ti>42</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>7</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo KDE team</ti>
  <ti>41</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>8</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo Sound Team</ti>
  <ti>38</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>9</ti>
  <ti>Python Gentoo Team</ti>
  <ti>38</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<figure link="/images/gmn/20080520/closed.png" short="Bugs closed" caption="Bug closed rankings"/>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Assigned bug ranking</title>
<body>

<p>
The developers and teams who have been assigned the most bugs during this period are as follows.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th>Rank</th>
  <th>Developer/Team</th>
  <th>Bug Count</th>
</tr>

<tr>
  <ti>0</ti>
  <ti>Others</ti>
  <ti>817</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>1</ti>
  <ti>Default Assignee for New Packages</ti>
  <ti>88</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>2</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo's Team for Core System packages</ti>
  <ti>77</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>3</ti>
  <ti>Java team</ti>
  <ti>45</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>4</ti>
  <ti>Default Assignee for Orphaned Packages</ti>
  <ti>42</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>5</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo Security</ti>
  <ti>37</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>6</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo Linux Gnome Desktop Team</ti>
  <ti>32</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>7</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo KDE team</ti>
  <ti>27</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>8</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo Release Team</ti>
  <ti>26</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>9</ti>
  <ti>Gentoo Games</ti>
  <ti>26</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<figure link="/images/gmn/20080520/opened.png" short="Bugs assigned" caption="Bugs assigned rankings"/>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- GMN feedback information -->
<chapter>
<title>Getting Involved</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The GMN relies on volunteers and members of the community for content every
month.  If you are interested in writing for the GMN, do write in to
<mail>gmn-writers@gentoo.org</mail> with your articles in plaintext or GuideXML
format.
</p>

<!-- Don't forget to change the deadline date -->
<note>
The deadline for articles to be published in the next issue is
<b><e>June 13, 2008</e></b>.
</note>

<p>
We solicit feedback from all our readers on the newsletter. If you have any
ideas for articles, sections, or have anything to say about the GMN, don't
hesitate to email us at <mail>gmn-feedback@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>

<p>
You can also give us your feedback and comment on this particular issue of the
GMN on the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-p-5071942.html">forum 
thread</uri>.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- GMN subscription information -->
<chapter>
<title>GMN subscription information</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
To subscribe to the Gentoo Monthly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail>gentoo-gmn+subscribe@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p> 

<p>
To unsubscribe to the Gentoo Monthly Newsletter, send a blank e-mail to
<mail>gentoo-gmn+unsubscribe@gentoo.org</mail> from the e-mail address you are
subscribed under.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<!-- Other Languages -->
<chapter>
<title>Other languages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Monthly Newsletter is available in the following languages:
</p>

<ul>
 <li><uri link="/news/en/gmn/index.xml">English</uri></li>
 <li><uri link="/news/de/gmn/index.xml">German</uri></li>
 <li><uri link="/news/it/gmn/index.xml">Italian</uri></li>
 <li><uri link="/news/pl/gmn/index.xml">Polish</uri></li>
 <li><uri link="/news/es/gmn/index.xml">Spanish</uri></li>
 <li><uri link="/news/zh_cn/gmn/index.xml">Simplified Chinese</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
