<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/gnome/howtos/gnome-2.32-upgrade.xml,v 1.3 2014/09/05 18:18:25 creffett Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete">
<title>Gnome 2.32 Upgrade Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="pacho"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This is a guide for upgrading from GNOME 2.30.x to GNOME 2.32.x.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2011-01-31</date>

<chapter>
<title>Changes</title>

<section>
<title>General changes</title>
<body>

<p>
Please see the <uri
link="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.32/">GNOME 2.32 Release
Notes</uri> for what is new in this major release of GNOME.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<section>
<title>Gnome Panel hangs at startup</title>
<body>

<p>
Some people reported hanging problems with <c>gnome-base/gnome-panel</c> notably with dual monitor setups. Please visit <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/351439">bug #351439</uri> for details on the issue.
If you are suffering this problem, you should try to remove your old <b>interface</b> configuration as follows:
</p>

<pre caption="Remove old configuration causing panel to hang">
$ <i>gconftool-2 --recursive-unset /desktop/gnome/interface</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gnome Panel problems and crashers on multiscreen setups</title>
<body>
   
<p>
As reported in <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/348253">bug #348253</uri>,
you could suffer panel crashers when using multiscreen setups. This is an upstream problem
(<uri link="https://bugzilla.gnome.org/632369">gnome bug #632369</uri>) that is
partially fixed applying some patches from the upstream report (<uri
link="https://bugzilla.gnome.org/632369#c12">gnome bug #632369 comment #12</uri>).
</p>
<p>
However, even with these patches, some people have reported problems showing
applet menus. Any help on fixing this is highly appreciated.
</p>
</body>
</section>
   
<section>
<title>Problems with Evolution address books</title>
<body>

<p>
Some people have reported problems like duplicated entries or errors while
trying to open Evolution Address Books after updating (see <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/348063">gentoo bug #348063</uri> and <uri
link="https://bugzilla.gnome.org/634897">gnome bug #634897</uri> for reference).
These problems will likely affect people that updated from 2.30.x versions of
<c>mail-client/evolution</c> and <c>gnome-extra/evolution-data-server</c> to 
versions any version prior to 2.32.1-r1.
</p>

<p>
A script is available to help you on fixing these problems. It
removes <c>uri</c> attribute from local Address Books and also removes the
additional address books that could have been wrongly created by pruning
those not part of the group with the most local Address Books.
</p>

<p>At first, it is important to backup your address book configuration to prevent any data
loss by running the following command:
</p>
<pre caption="Backup old address books configuration">
$ <i>gconftool-2 --get /apps/evolution/addressbook/sources > evoaddrbook.bak</i>
</pre>

<p>
After that, you will need to run the script as follows:
</p>

<pre caption="Fix Evolution Address Books with fix-addressbook.py script">
$ <i>wget "http://bugs.gentoo.org/attachment.cgi?id=262523" -O fix-addressbook.py</i>
$ <i>chmod +x fix-addressbook.py</i>
$ <i>evolution -q</i>
$ <i>./fix-addressbook.py</i>
</pre>

<p>
If this does not fix your problems, you will probably need to use 
<c>gnome-extra/gconf-editor</c> to try to fix
<c>/apps/evolution/addressbook/sources</c> key yourself. If you need more
help on this, please check for any opened bug related with this problem and,
if none of them fits with your issue, open a new one after reading <uri
link="https://bugs.gentoo.org/348063">bug #348063</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section> 
<title>Compilation errors due to python3 being set as main interpreter</title>
<body>

<p>
During our work on getting Gnome 2.32 ready to be stabilized, we have
focused on making every new package compile and work even when python3 is
set as main interpreter, either using it if possible or going back to
python2 when needed at compilation and run times.
</p>

<p>
On the other hand, because a lot of other packages in the tree used by GNOME
still do not work well on a system with python3 set as the default interpreter,
you will still need to use eselect to set python2 as the default one to
avoid problems.
</p>

<pre caption="Use Python 2.6 as main interpreter">
# <i>eselect python set python2.6</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
