<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/gnome/howtos/gnome-2.20-upgrade.xml,v 1.4 2014/09/05 18:18:25 creffett Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete">

<title>Gnome 2.20 Upgrade Guide</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dang@gentoo.org">Daniel Gryniewicz</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="leio@gentoo.org">Mart Raudsepp</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This is a guide for upgrading from GNOME 2.18.x to GNOME 2.20.x.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2007-11-22</date>

<chapter>
<title>Changes</title>
<section>
<title>Font, Theme, and Background Preferences</title>
<body>

<p>
The Font, Theme, and Background control panels have been merged into the
"Appearance" control panel.  This means that changing almost anything
related to the appearance of your desktop is now done in a single window in
tabs.  Go to System -> Preferences -> Appearance to change these settings.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Spam Filter Choice in Evolution</title>
<body>

<p>
Evolution now has a real choice of spam filters.  It comes built in with
plugins for Spamassassin and Bogofilter, and can choose which one to use at
runtime.  The USE flags for choosing are now gone.  To choose a spam plugin,
go to Preferences -> Mail Preferences -> Junk and set the Default junk plugin
from the drop box.  It will tell you if you have the correct programs
installed.  If you only have one of Spamassassin and Bogofilter installed, it
will choose that one by default.  If you have both, it defaults to
Spamassassin.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Migration to Rarian document metadata library</title>
<body>

<p>
For as long as we know, the GNOME user help documents have been maintained and
indexed with the scrollkeeper package.  However it has been long without an
upstream maintainer and has a good amount of issues, including conceptual.
</p>

<p>
GNOME 2.20 brings you a replacement in the form of the new Rarian package.
Some of its benefits include allowing yelp to generate the table of contents
much quicker, eventually allowing to get rid of the install-time penalty
on all packages installing user documentation in the form of scrollkeeper
database updating, and much more.  Fortunately it comes with a full
compatibility layer to scrollkeeper, so the migration from scrollkeeper to
rarian should be painless.
</p>

<p>
We, the Gentoo GNOME team, believe that we have
made this migration painless during the upgrade to Gnome 2.20 also on Gentoo
Linux. This is achieved through a migration version of scrollkeeper that
only brings in the rarian package together with its scrollkeeper compatibility
layer and not the old scrollkeeper package.  So have no fear, the version 9999
of scrollkeeper is that migration version stub and not a live CVS ebuild.
A recent stable Portage should be able to figure out the way to do a
successful migration on its own without manual intervention.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Other changes</title>
<body>

<p>
Please see the <uri link="http://www.gnome.org/start/2.20/notes/en/">GNOME 2.20 Release Notes</uri>
for what else new is in this major release of GNOME.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Known Issues</title>
<section>
<title>Gnome Power Manager Tray icon missing (fixed)</title>
<body>

<p>
The problem with gnome-power-manager's tray icon being missing on startup has
been fixed.  If you had any automatic workarounds in place, you should remove
them after upgrading.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
