<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/gnome/howtos/gnome-2.28-upgrade.xml,v 1.5 2014/09/05 18:18:25 creffett Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete">
<title>Gnome 2.28 Upgrade Guide</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="pacho"/>
</author>

<abstract>
This is a guide for upgrading from GNOME 2.26.x to GNOME 2.28.x.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2010-05-02</date>

<chapter>
<title>Changes</title>

<section>
<body>
<note>You can select the <b>gnome</b> subprofile to automatically enable most
USE flags needed by <c>gnome-base/gnome</c>. Please follow <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml#doc_chap3">these instructions</uri> 
to select this profile if desired.</note>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<body>
<note>When running <c>gconftool-2</c> to change settings, you
can run it as root appending <c>--config-source
xml:readwrite:/etc/gconf/gconf.xml.defaults</c> to the end of the command to
set default preferences for <b>all</b> users.
</note>
</body>   
</section>

<section>
<title>Drives auto-mounting</title>
<body>

<p>
<c>sys-apps/gnome-disk-utility</c> support in <c>gnome-base/gvfs</c> is now required
by nautilus to auto-mount drives. Because of this, you need to be sure gvfs is built
with <c>gdu</c> USE flag enabled. 
</p>

<p> We have decided to not enable by default that USE flag in gvfs
because it would add too many extra dependencies to people using gvfs but not full
Gnome desktop. Because of this, we have decided to make <c>gnome-base/gnome</c> require
gvfs to be built with <c>gdu</c> USE flag enabled since most of users installing this meta
will expect to get a fully working desktop. Regarding <c>gnome-base/gnome-light</c> meta,
we finally decided to let its users handle this dependency as they prefer configuring
<c>automount</c> USE flag (enabled by default).
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Policykit</title>
<body>

<p>
A dependency on <c>gnome-extra/polkit-gnome</c> has been added to <c>gnome-base/gnome</c>
meta ebuild to be sure users who enable <c>policykit</c> USE flag get information when they 
do not have the correct privileges.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Suspend/hibernate from power manager tray icon</title>
<body>

<p>
Upstream decided to hide suspend/hibernate options from systray icon as they think
it was not a great shortcut for them. You can still enable them again through gconf
running: 
</p>
<pre caption="Show actions in systray icon menu">
# <i>gconftool-2 --type boolean --set /apps/gnome-power-manager/ui/show_actions_in_menu true</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Suspend/hibernate requires consolekit</title>
<body>

<p>
ConsoleKit became a runtime dependency of <c>gnome-extra/gnome-power-manager</c> in 2.27/2.28
cycle as explained in <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/287025">bug #287025</uri>.
If you know how to solve this, we will welcome patches in above bug report to make consolekit depend
optional again.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Icons in menus and buttons</title>
<body>

<p>
Icons in menus and buttons were disabled by default by upstream as reported in <uri link="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.28/index.html.en#rnusers.cleanup">Gnome 2.28 Release Notes</uri> since they think it will standardize the look and feel of menus and present a cleaner interface to users.
Since we know some people will disagree with that decision, you can revert the change through
gconf running:
</p> 

<pre caption="Show icons in menus and buttons">
# <i>gconftool-2 --type boolean --set /desktop/gnome/interface/buttons_have_icons true</i>
# <i>gconftool-2 --type boolean --set /desktop/gnome/interface/menus_have_icons true</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Synaptics hal settings are ignored</title>
<body>

<p>
Due to <c>sys-apps/hal</c> deprecation, upstream decided to drop its support causing
synaptics hal settings to be ignored. As a workaround until migration away
from hal ends, you can try to configure your touchpad using the settings tool in
<c>System->Preferences->Mouse->Touchpad</c>,
but it will not allow you to define some settings like touchpad size, tap zones, tap sensitivity, etc. 
</p>
	
<p>
If it is not good enough for your setup, you can try to disable mouse plugin through
gconf running:
</p>
<pre caption="Disable mouse plugin">
# <i>gconftool-2 --type boolean --set /apps/gnome_settings_daemon/plugins/mouse/active false</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Other changes</title>
<body>

<p>
Please see the <uri
link="http://library.gnome.org/misc/release-notes/2.28/">GNOME 2.28 Release
Notes</uri> for what else new is in this major release of GNOME.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Troubleshooting</title>
<section>
<title>Missing information in menus while upgrading</title>
<body>

<p>
Menus might loose their long version/translation while upgrading because of
<c>gnome-base/gnome-menus</c> changes during the progress. It should get back 
to normal once log off/on cycle has been done.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Epiphany 2.28 not marked stable</title>
<body>

<p>
Since it was released, some of Gnome team members have been using new epiphany every day to test
if it is ready to go stable. Due their important regressions like missing password saving support,
missing extensions, crashes related with <c>net-libs/webkit-gtk</c> and upstream focusing more in
2.29/2.30 to solve most of the problems, we have decided to keep using 2.26 series until 2.30 (or
newer) are ready to go stable with a newer <c>net-libs/webkit-gtk</c> version also.
</p>
	
<p>
You can install newer epiphany and epiphany-extensions simply following 
<uri
link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-amd64.xml?part=3&amp;chap=3#doc_chap2">handbook 
instructions</uri> to install testing packages on a stable system.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Gvfs problems while upgrading</title>
<body>

<impo>
Be sure to restart gvfs at the end of the update is needed to avoid weird
errors.
</impo>

<p>
The safest way to restart it is to log off/on again because doing it on a
logged in session could cause crashing problems.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Can not click on Flash elements and other problems related with mouse interaction</title>
<body>

<p>
GDK has been rewritten to use client-side windows. This means that GDK maintains its own window 
hierarchy and only uses X windows where it is necessary or explicitly requested. Some of the 
benefits of this change are reduced flicker, the ability to do transformed and animated rendering 
of widgets, easier embedding of GTK+ widgets, etc. Click <uri link="http://blogs.gnome.org/alexl/2009/06/12/the-return-of-client-side-windows/">
here</uri> to see client-side windows in action.
</p>

<p>
On the other hand, this change can cause problems with applications still not prepared to use it like
flashplayer or vmware-workstation. To workaround these issues, you simply need to launch the app
running <c>GDK_NATIVE_WINDOWS=1 application</c> like, for example, <c>GDK_NATIVE_WINDOWS=1 firefox</c>,
getting flashplayer working ok again since that variable turns off this new feature.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
