<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/gnome/howtos/gnome-2.18-upgrade.xml,v 1.15 2014/09/05 18:18:25 creffett Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete">

<title>Gnome 2.18 Upgrade Guide</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dang@gentoo.org">Daniel Gryniewicz</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
<mail link="leio@gentoo.org">Mart Raudsepp</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="nightmorph@gentoo.org">Joshua Saddler</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="cla@gentoo.org">Dawid Węgliński</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This is a guide for upgrading from GNOME 2.16.x to GNOME 2.18.x.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.5</version>
<date>2007-08-18</date>

<chapter>
<title>Major Changes</title>
<section>
<title>System Sounds and ESD</title>
<body>

<p>
Upstream has decided to remove the autospawn capabilities of esd, because they
were broken and led to lots of problems. This means that if you use system
sounds, you will need to have the esound boot service running. It is started
like this:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting esound at boot">
# <i>rc-update add esound default</i>
</pre>

<p>
Note that this will not start it until after a reboot, so to start it this time,
use this:
</p>

<pre caption="Starting esound in running system">
# <i>/etc/init.d/esound start</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Totem doesn't have a xine USE flag!</title>
<body>

<p>
We have decided to remove the xine backend due to various issues that we can
not fix easily. We know this makes playing DVDs harder. However, you can
still play DVDs. Make sure you have <c>media-video/totem</c> built with
<c>dvd</c> USE flag, and then run:
</p>

<pre caption="Playing DVDs with Totem">
# <i>totem dvd://</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will play the main feature. There's no menu support, sorry.
</p>

<p>
We are looking into making it possible to have the xine backend live in totem
alongside gstreamer and have xine backend selectable as non-default from the
command line. However this would still be unsupported and provided merely as a
convenience. We would appreciate coding help to make this happen sooner.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Totem's browser plugin flags have changed! Now I get seamonkey!</title>
<body>

<p>
Totem's gecko USE flags have been rearranged. Instead of defaulting to
seamonkey and selecting firefox or xulrunner based on flags, it now defaults to
firefox, and selects xulrunner or seamonkey based on flags. This is for 2
reasons. First, because seamonkey doesn't run on all arches, so it needed to
have a USE flag that could be masked. And second, to bring totem in line with
the usage of other Gnome apps, such as epiphany. Here are the possible
combinations of flags, and what they mean to totem now:
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th colspan="2">Totem browser plugin USE flag combinations</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>USE flags</th>
  <th>Result</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>USE="<c>-nsplugin</c>"</ti>
  <ti>Disable the browser plugin; no gecko will be pulled in</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>USE="<c>nsplugin -xulrunner -seamonkey</c>"</ti>
  <ti>
    Build the plugin against firefox. This is the default in all profiles.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>USE="<c>nsplugin xulrunner -seamonkey</c>"</ti>
  <ti>Build the plugin against xulrunner</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>USE="<c>nsplugin xulrunner seamonkey</c>"</ti>
  <ti>Build the plugin against xulrunner. (xulrunner beats seamonkey.)</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>USE="<c>nsplugin -xulrunner seamonkey</c>"</ti>
  <ti>Build the plugin against seamonkey</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Known Issues</title>
<section>
<title>Tray icons missing (specifically gnome-power-manager)</title>
<body>

<p>
There is a known bug in Gnome 2.18 where tray icons for things starting up in
your session sometimes do not show up in the tray. The program is running, but
its tray icon is missing. This happens to gnome-power-manager in many cases. We
are hoping to fix this in the future, but meanwhile the workaround is to restart
the program after the session is up, and the icon will be there for the rest of
the session. For gnome-power-manager, open a terminal and follow these steps:
</p>

<pre caption="Getting the gnome-power-manager tray icon back">
# <i>killall gnome-power-manager</i>
# <i>gnome-power-manager</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will get your g-p-m tray icon back.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Deskbar-applet errors out on login when using tracker</title>
<body>

<p>
There is a known bug in trackerd that causes a race at login, where trackerd is
starting, and deskbar-applet tries to start it via its dbus interface.  This
causes deskbar-applet to error out. To get deskbar-applet working again (with
tracker), open a terminal and do the following:
</p>

<pre caption="Getting deskbar-applet working">
# <i>killall deskbar-applet</i>
</pre>

<p>
Then, when the dialog comes up asking to restart it, select "Reload".
</p>

<p>
This must be done once on login. Deskbar-applet will then work for the rest of
the session.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The compile fails with XML:: errors, and other compilation notes</title>
<body>

<p>
This happens because <c>expat</c> was moved to stable at the same time as Gnome
2.18. You need to rebuild everything that links to it once expat has been
upgraded, which is usually at the start of the upgrade process. To do so, run:
</p>

<pre caption="Fixing expat breakages">
# <i>revdep-rebuild -X</i>
</pre>

<p>
This will rebuild everything broken by expat, as well as performing other
upgrades as it continues. Once it's finished, you should be able to finish
upgrading the rest of Gnome.
</p>

<p>
Once the entire 2.18 upgrade process is finished, you need to run
<c>revdep-rebuild</c> a few more times until there's no more output, indicating
that Gnome and its dependencies have been properly built. After that, don't
forget about running <c>dispatch-conf</c>!
</p>

<p>
Finally, dbus and hal need to be restarted if they were running during the
upgrade:
</p>

<pre caption="Restarting services">
# <i>/etc/init.d/dbus restart</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/hald restart</i>
</pre>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
