<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/base/amd64/howtos/bugs.xml,v 1.4 2006/03/31 13:06:42 blubb Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The context of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommonds.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<sections>

<version>2004.3</version>
<date>2005-02-20</date>

<section>

<title>How To File Keyword-Bugs On Gentoo/AMD64</title>

<body>
<p>
First we want to thank you for helping out with the Gentoo/AMD64 project. Your diligent efforts
in testing applications is greatly appreciated. In the following we want to explain the steps to
submitting a bug report if you want to let us know that a masked application works on your Gentoo/AMD64 installation.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section><title>Register First!</title>
<body>
<p>
If you haven't registered for an ID on <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/createaccount.cgi">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>,
please do that first.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section><title>Steps For Submission</title>
<body>
<p>
Perform the following steps to submit a bug:
</p>
<ul>
	<li>Browse to <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org/createaccount.cgi">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>.</li>
	<li>Click on <c>Report A Bug</c> near the top of the page.</li>
	<li>Choose <c>Gentoo Linux</c> from the product list.</li>
	<li>Log in using your bugs.gentoo.org account.</li>
	<li>Search for your bug
		<ul>
			<li>Enter <c>ALL</c> and the name of the ebuild into the search textbox. Be carefull,
			<c>ALL</c> is casesensitive.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>
<pre caption="Example">ALL k3b</pre>
<ul>
	<li>Continue searching for your bug
		<ul>
			<li>Click the <c>Search</c> button.</li>
			<li>Check if anyone has already submitted a bug report on the masked application that works for you.</li>
			<li>You should see two thing.
				<ul>
					<li>The Plt column should say <c>amd64</c>.</li>
					<li>The Summary column should say something like <e>working on amd64</e>.</li>
				</ul>
			</li>
			<li>If you don't say anything applicable in the search subframe, move on to the next step.
			Otherwise, we already know about the application and you don't need to (and shouldn't) submit a new bug report.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>Give us your information
		<ul>
			<li>Select <c>Ebuilds</c> for the <e>Component</e>.</li>
			<li>Select <c>amd64</c> for the <e>Hardware Platform</e>.</li>
			<li>In the <e>Summary</e> textbox, enter your summary in the form: ${category}/${application}-${version} works on amd64.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>
<pre caption="Example">app-cdr/k3b-0.11.6 works on amd64</pre>
<ul>
	<li>Continue giving us info
		<ul>
			<li>In the <e>Description</e> textarea, enter a brief description in the from: Please add "~amd64" to the KEYWORDS for
			${category}/${application}-${version}.</li>
		</ul>
	</li>
</ul>
<pre caption="Example">Please add "~amd64" to the KEYWORDS for app-cdr/k3b-0.11.6</pre>
<ul>
	<li>Continue giving us info
		<ul>
			<li>Paste the output from <c>emerge info</c> into the <e>Details</e> textarea. This step is very
			helpful and gives us the environmental conditions (e.g USE flags) you used.</li>
			<li>Select <c>Enhancement</c> from the <e>Severity</e> drop-down listbox. <e>Please don't select anything other here. The
			devs can (and will) change the severity of your bug report in case of nessesity.</e></li>
		</ul>
	</li>
	<li>Doublecheck your work to make sure you've entered the correct data.</li>
	<li>Click <c>Submit Bug Report</c> when you're ready to file the report.</li>
</ul>
<p>
Thank you very much !
</p>
</body>
</section>

</sections>
