<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>Gentoo for PS3</name>
<longname>Gentoo Linux for PS3 Development</longname>
<date>Decemeber 18, 2006</date>

<description>
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
  With Sony's recent introduction of the PS3, you can now run Linux on it as well as use it as a gaming console.  
    The PS3 is based on a Cell processor and therefore can run most of the ppc64 64ul or 32ul binaries without change.  As of now, the kernel does differ.
</p>
 <p>
  This project page is commited to Linux running on the PS3.  Here you will find all kinds of information
  related to Gentoo for the PS3, Cell processors, toolchains, and the Gentoo LiveCD for PS3 and PowerMacs.
  </p>
  <p>
  If you are curious about the project, please join us on #gentoo-ppc64 on irc.freenode.net.
  </p>

  </longdescription>

<extrachapter position="top">
<title>LiveCD for the Sony PS3 and Apple PowerMacs</title>
<section>
<title>12-26-2006</title>
<body>
<p>We have now released a beta LiveCD for PPC64, which supports PS3s and Apple PowerMac G5s.  It is available on the Gentoo mirrors under experimental/ppc64/livecd.</p>
<p>If you are wondering what a livecd is, check out the hi-res <uri link="beta.jpg">screen shot</uri> from Ranger. In addition to a full Gnome desktop, it contains:
<ul>
<li>Firefox-2x (Bon Echo)</li>
<li>Audacious</li>
<li>Xchat</li>
<li>Gaim</li>
<li>Evolution</li>
<li>Gimp-2</li>
</ul>
<note>We are currently having compilation problems with the mozilla products.  Once these compilation problems are sorted out, we will include Thunderbird.  As of now, we are including Firefox-2 with an uncommitted patch.</note>
</p>
<p>For a full list of packages included on the LiveCD, see this <uri link="livecd_pkgs.txt">list</uri>. </p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Stages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>There are now 32-bit and 64-bit userland stages in the experimental section of the Gentoo mirrors.  These are stage 4 tarballs, which means they contain a precompiled working system that requires minimal configuration before it is usable.  The stage contains a precompile kernel and modules, Fluxbox window manager, vim, and X.  Both stages run a 64-bit kernel.
</p>
<p>For instructions on how to install these stages, check out the <uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/cell/wiki/InstallGentooOnPS3">Installing Gentoo on a PS3 </uri> instructions.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>GRP Packages</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>GRP packages are precompiled binary tarballs of Gentoo packages.  An example would be kde and its dependancy packages.  For example, suppose you want to eliminate the compilation time for installing KDE, you would simply need to make your system aware of the GRP repository and then can emerge the binary packages quickly.
</p>
<p>For instructions on how to install GRP packages, check out the <uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/cell/wiki/InstallGentooOnPS3">Installing Gentoo on a PS3 </uri> instructions.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>


<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Relevant links</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The following is a list of relevant links:
<ul>
<li><uri link="http://www.playstation.com/ps3-openplatform/index.html">Open Platform for PLAYSTATION 3</uri></li>
<!--<li><uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org/dev/lu_zero">lu_zero's cell and ps3 overlay</uri></li>-->
<li><uri link="http://overlays.gentoo.org/proj/cell">Gentoo Cell and PS3 Overlay and Project page</uri></li>
</ul>

</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>

