<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>ops</name>
<longname>The #gentoo Operators Project</longname>
<date>2007-10-11</date>
<author title="Author">
<mail link="jer" />
</author>

<description>
The #gentoo Operators project describes the tasks and policies carried out by the operators of the #gentoo channel on the Freenode network.
</description>

<longdescription>
<p>
The #gentoo Operators project describes the tasks and policies carried out by the operators (ops) of the #gentoo channel on the Freenode network. Among other things, it aims to clarify the way #gentoo is run and by whom, who to address to resolve conflicts between channel ops and other channel users.
</p>
</longdescription>

<goals>
<p>
The goal of the #gentoo operators project is to clarify how #gentoo is maintained. Most of the communication about actual channel management takes place on IRC, and this project aims to describe who do it and how we do it.
</p>
</goals>

<extrachapter>
<title>List of #gentoo Operators</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>The following table lists the current official #gentoo operators.</p>

<table>
<tr><th>Nickname(s)</th><th>Real Name</th></tr>
<tr><ti>astinus</ti><ti>Alex Howells</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>avenj</ti><ti>Jon Portnoy</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>bit, kutsuya</ti><ti>Jason Shoemaker</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>blackace</ti><ti>Nicholas D. Wolfwood</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>bonsaikitten, DrEeevil</ti><ti>Patrick Lauer</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>BrianW</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>christel</ti><ti>Christel Dahlskjaer</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>doc</ti><ti>Dave O'Connor</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>DrChandra</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>Fieldy</ti><ti></ti></tr>
<tr><ti>fox2mike</ti><ti>Shyam Mani</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>hlieberman</ti><ti>Harlan Lieberman-Berg</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>kojiro</ti><ti>Michael A. Smith</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>marienz</ti><ti>Marien Zwart</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>moreon</ti><ti>Daniel Lynch</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>NeddySeagoon</ti><ti>Roy Bamford</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>rej</ti><ti>Jeroen Roovers (jer)</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>roger55</ti><ti>Roger Miliker</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>seemant</ti><ti>Seemant Kulleen</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>SwifT</ti><ti>Sven Vermeulen</ti></tr>
<tr><ti>RiverRat</ti><ti>Tres Melton</ti></tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Tasks of the Ops Team</title>
<section>
<body>

<table>
	<tr><th>Task</th><th>Description</th></tr>
	<tr><ti>Chanserv access levels</ti><ti>Chanserv access levels determine who gets which privileges in #gentoo (and #gentoo-ops).</ti></tr>
	<tr><ti>Channel etiquette management</ti><ti>#gentoo has a language policy that the ops uphold. Furthermore, the channel's topic is <e>Gentoo Linux support</e> and it is not a "chat" channel &mdash; ops may direct users to other channels that are more appropriate when a discussion has little or nothing to do with Gentoo Linux support.</ti></tr>
	<tr><ti>Abuse management</ti><ti>When a user abuses #gentoo, he gets warned, muted (+q), banned or banforwarded. Conflicts are resolved in #gentoo-ops. Bans may normally only be unset by the banner &mdash; she has a responsibility to set reasonable bans.</ti></tr>
	<tr><ti>Topic updates</ti><ti>When many users come to the channel having the same technical issue with Gentoo, the channel's topic is updated with references to bot FAQs or web page URLs.</ti></tr>
	<tr><ti>Bot FAQs</ti><ti>#gentoo has three official ircbots: jeeves, mzbot and Naamah. While the latter only serves to kick users who paste more than a few lines in rapid succession (flood protection), the former two respond to simple commands and may offer information that is regularly updated by the ops.</ti></tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Channel management</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Compared to most IRC channels on Freenode and indeed on other IRC networks, #gentoo has a very strict policy and this policy is enforced as strictly as possible. #gentoo is the focal point of many support enquiries and can be very busy at times. Because of the ~1000 users that chat (and lurk) in #gentoo, making it one of the largest channels on the Freenode network, and perhaps also because of the mild animosity that any Linux distribution causes among users of other Linux distributions, it is also the focal point of spammers, pranksters, and trolls.</p>
<p>The policy set up to manage #gentoo is therefore very straightforward and simple:</p>
<ul>
<li>The topic of the channel is Gentoo Linux support. Off topic chat, even mild flamewars about program X versus program Y, will usually be met with a request to take the discussion elsewhere, and consequent muting (+q) or banishment if users persist.</li>
<li>Discussion of #gentoo management is off topic. The appropriate place to discuss matters of #gentoo policy and its enforcement is #gentoo-ops, the userrel project or the ops mailing list (and not #gentoo &mdash; it's just too busy for that).</li>
<li>Because of the varied nature of Gentoo users and the varied environments in which they might use #gentoo, the channel has a strict language policy, meaning that anything you wouldn't dare say to your proverbial grandmother, you shouldn't say in #gentoo.</li>
</ul>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>


<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>How to contact us</title>
<section>
<title>Via e-mail</title>
<body>

<p>
To send e-mail to the #gentoo operators team, point your favourite e-mail client to ops@gentoo.org.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>On Freenode</title>
<body>
<p>
/join #gentoo-ops if you want to chat directly with #gentoo operators. Also, any urgent issues with regard to #gentoo channel management (abuse, pointers to important bugs that affect many users) should be brought to our attention there.
</p>
</body>
</section>

</extrachapter>

</project>
