<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<guide>
<title>Gentoo Linux Security Affiliations</title>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="rbu@gentoo.org">Robert Buchholz</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="a3li@gentoo.org">Alex Legler</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This document details the groups that the Gentoo Linux Security Team is a part of or working
with in order to coordinate vulnerabilities.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.1</version>
<date>2012-02-02</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>What and why</title>
<body>
<p>
The Gentoo Linux Security Team is dedicated to an open development process
and supports responsible disclosure. This means we closely collaborate with software upstreams,
other distributions, security researchers and CERTs to ensure the security of our distribution.
</p>
<p>
Our group affiliations allow us to access vulnerability information and receive notifications
as early as possible. As participants in a coordinated release process, we are able to assess
vulnerabilities before they publicly known. We work with Gentoo developers, upstream and
other distributions to prepare updates that reach Gentoo users as soon as the vulnerability
is public. We commit ourselves to publish all our own findings, but we respect if third parties
decide to keep certain information private.
</p>
<p>
Members and contributors of the Security team should review this list before attempting to become
part of a mailing list. <b>Any such requests are to be discussed internally and acknowledged by
a team lead first.</b>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Affiliations</title>
<section>
<title>linux-distros</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is part of the <uri link="http://oss-security.openwall.org/wiki/mailing-lists/distros">distros and linux-distros</uri> mailing list.
The mailing list discusses vulnerabilities in several free software products and is often
used for coordinated disclosure.
</p>
<p>
Current members: a3li, craig
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>oCERT</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is a member of <uri link="http://www.ocert.org/">oCERT</uri> ever since its incarnation
in 2008. The Open Source Computer Emergency Response Team is an effort to assist free software
projects in vulnerability management and usually performs responsible disclosure.
We are proud to say that three of the five oCERT founding team members are former Gentoo 
developers.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CERT/CC</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is a listed vendor with the  <uri link="http://www.cert.org/certcc.html">CERT Coordination Center (CERT/CC)</uri>.
We receive general vulnerability notifications through the most widely known CERT.
</p>
<p>
Current members: a3li, keytoaster
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>WebKit Security</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is part of the <uri link="http://webkit.org/security/">WebKit Security</uri> mailing list and bugzilla group
since 2009. This group discusses vulnerabilities in products based on the WebKit web browsing engine, such as
WebKit-GTK, Qt 4 and Google Chrome.
</p>
<p>
<uri link="http://webkit.org/security/security-group-members.html">Current members</uri>: a3li, keytoaster
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Mozilla Security</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is seeking membership of the <uri link="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/security/membership-policy.html">Mozilla Security Group</uri>.
</p>
<p>
<uri link="http://www.mozilla.org/projects/security/secgrouplist.html">Current members</uri>: none.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>OpenOffice.org</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is part of the <uri link="http://www.openoffice.org/security/">OpenOffice.org Security Group</uri>.
</p>
<p>
Current members: a3li, suka.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Samba</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is subscribed to the samba-pkg-sec mailing list where advance Samba announcements are distributed.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>oss-security</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is a member of the <uri link="http://oss-security.openwall.org/wiki/mailing-lists/oss-security">oss-security</uri>
mailing list since it was founded in 2008. It is a public discussion channel targeted towards security flaws in free software.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>CVE</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is committed to the <uri link="http://cve.mitre.org/compatible/index.html">Common Vulnerabilities and Exposures
project</uri> that seeks to enumerate
information vulnerabilities. We automatically monitor the CVE feed for vulnerabilities and
are seeking for our GLSAs and Bugzilla channels to output CVE identifiers. We are seeking
<uri link="http://cve.mitre.org/compatible/index.html">CVE-Compatible</uri> status in the near future.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Secunia</title>
<body>
<p>
Gentoo is using vulnerability feeds provided by <uri link="http://secunia.com/">Secunia</uri>
in order to improve vulnerability assessment and workflow automation.
</p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>
