<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/release/2006.0/alpha-release-notes.xml,v 1.1 2006/02/27 00:14:57 plasmaroo Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="alpha-release-notes.xml">
<title>Alpha Release Notes for Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>

<author title="Author">
 <mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>

<author title="Alpha Release Coordinator">
	<mail link="kloeri@gentoo.org">Bryan Østergaard</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo 2006.0 Release Notes.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>23 February 2006</date>

<chapter>
	<title>The Gentoo Linux Project</title>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<body>
			<p>Gentoo Linux is a community driven project committed to producing
			high quality opensource software. These release notes for Gentoo Linux 2006.0
			summarize important package updates, security updates, and many other changes
			that have happened since Gentoo Linux 2005.1</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Table of Contents</title>
		<body>
		<ul>
			<li>1. Overview</li>
			<li>2. Important Changes</li>
			<li>	2.1 Profile Changes</li>
			<li>	2.2 Stage Tarballs</li>
			<li>	2.3 Security Updates</li>
			<li>	2.4 Errata</li>
			<li>	2.5 Critical Package Updates</li>
			<li>	2.6 Portage Updates</li>
			<li>	2.7 Documentation Updates</li>
			<li>3. Upgrading from previous versions of Gentoo Linux</li>
		</ul>

		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Important Changes for 2006.0</title>
	<section>
		<title>Profile Changes</title>
		<body>
			<p>Due to glibc problems we're now providing two different profiles. The default profile 
			is default-linux/alpha/2006.0 requires a 2.6 kernel as it forces use of NPTL. Users that
			need a 2.4 kernel or don't want to use NPTL can use the default-linux/alpha/no-nptl profile
			instead.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Stage Tarballs</title>
		<body>
			<p>Because of the profile changes we now provide stage tarballs built for both the default
			alpha profile and the no-nptl profile. It's important to choose the no-nptl stage tarball
			if using a 2.4 kernel or if you don't want a NPTL enabled system.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Security Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>Gentoo Linux 2006.0 contains security updates to address GLSAs 
			(Gentoo Linux Security Advisories) numbered 200507-29 to 200601-17.
			</p>
			
			<p>Individual GLSAs can be referenced by going to
			<c>http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-$x.xml</c>, and substituting <c>$x</c>
			with the desired GLSA number. </p>
			
			<p>For more information, please consult the the 
			<uri link="http://security.gentoo.org/">Gentoo Linux Security Project home page</uri>.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Errata</title>
		<body>
			<table>
			<tr>
				<th>Errata</th>
				<th>Workaround</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti>Some alpha models may hang when booting</ti>
				<ti>Boot using the gentoo-2.4 kernel</ti>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<ti>The default gentoo-2.6 doesn't support SMP due to kernel bugs</ti>
				<ti>Boot using the gentoo-2.4 kernel</ti>
			</tr>
				
			</table>
			
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Critical Package Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>Important package-versions in this release:</p>

			<ul>
				<li>gcc 3.4.4-r1</li>
				<li>glibc-2.3.5-r3</li>
				<li>vanilla-sources-2.4.30</li>
				<li>vanilla-sources-2.6.15.1</li>
				<li>Portage-2.0.54</li>
				<li>xorg-x11-6.8.2-r6</li>
			</ul>

			<p>There is both 2.6 and 2.4 kernels available on the InstallCD that will run on both, uniprocessor and smp machines.</p>

			<p>For information about how to change your profile please read <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml">
			http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml</uri></p>
			
			<warn>Cascading profiles will only work with Portage >=2.0.51. Make sure to first upgrade to an appropriate version of Portage
			and <b>then</b> upgrade your profile!</warn>
			
			
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Portage Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>The Portage version included in this release is 2.0.54 and
			the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/portage/ChangeLog?root=gentoo-src">ChangeLog</uri>
			can be found via our online CVS repository.</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Documentation Updates</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			Much consideration and time has been spent on the Gentoo Installation Handbook in 
			order to get it more in sync with Gentoo 2006.0. Please note that it is a constant 
			work in progress, and if any bugs are encountered, please refer them to the Gentoo Linux 
			bugtracking system at http://bugs.gentoo.org.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
	
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Upgrading and Installation of Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
	<section>
		<title>Installing Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
		<body>
			<p>The entire Gentoo Linux installation process is documented 
			in the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo Handbook</uri>. </p>
			
			<p>Alpha architecture offers two InstallCDs. The first one being a universal
			bootable InstallCD which can be used to install with or without an Internet connection.
			The second InstallCD is a bootable minimal InstallCD that is smaller in size and includes only the basics needed to simply boot a machine.</p>
			
			<p>At minimum, the universal or minimal InstallCD is required to boot the machine and install Gentoo.
			The universal InstallCD does not require an Internet connection to install
			from a stage3 installation tarball. The minimal InstallCD requires an Internet connection
			to install Gentoo Linux.</p>

			<p>There is one kernel available on both bootable cds. It will run on both, uniprocessor and smp systems.
			The default kernel are based on linux-2.6.14.2 (vanilla-sources-2.6.14.2). The alternative kernel, <c>gentoo2.4</c>, 
			is based on linux-2.4.30 (vanilla-sources-2.4.30).</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

</guide>
