<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/release/2006.0/ia64-release-notes.xml,v 1.1 2006/02/27 00:14:57 plasmaroo Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="ia64-release-notes.xml">
<title>IA/64 Release Notes for Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>

<author title="ia64 Release Coordinator">
	<mail link="plasmaroo@gentoo.org">Tim Yamin</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo Linux/IA64 2006.0 Release Notes.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>13 February 2006</date>

<chapter>
	<title>The Gentoo Linux Project</title>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			Gentoo Linux is a community driven project committed to producing
			high quality open-source software. These release notes for Gentoo Linux 2006.0
			summarize important release changes and the installation process for Gentoo Linux
			2006.0 for Itanium systems.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Table of Contents</title>
		<body>
		<ul>
			<li>1. Overview</li>
			<li>2. Important Changes</li>
			<li>3. Installing and upgrading Gentoo Linux</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Important Changes for 2006.0</title>
	<section>
		<title>Important Changes for 2006.0</title>
		<body>
		<p>
			Following on from the availability of the Gentoo/IA64 InstallCD for 2005.1; the 2006.0 InstallCD features
			a media refresh with updated software versions as well as support for SGI Prism systems (thanks to Bob
			Sanders from SGI QA for his support).
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
	<title>Installing and Upgrading to Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
	<section>
		<title>Installing Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			Once you have booted Linux, whether from a InstallCD or an existing installation, you should fetch the stages
			and chroot as normal. It is <b>important</b> that you keep in mind the following considerations to
			achieve a bootable installation:
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
				Use only GNU parted to create your partitions. Other
				applications such as fdisk or cfdisk do not support EFI GPT
				partition tables, so your partitions will be lost on reboot.
				</li>
				<li>
				You must use ELILO as your bootloader. Other bootloaders do not
				support IA-64.
				</li>
				<li>
				You should use a 2.6 kernel; 2.4 kernels have known issues and
				are thus not supported by us.
				</li>
			</ul>			
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Upgrading to Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			If you already have a working installation of Gentoo Linux there is no need to reinstall. You will automatically get
			Gentoo 2006.0 if you sync your Portage tree and run <c>emerge --update world</c>.
			</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
