<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/releng/release/2006.0/ppc-release-notes.xml,v 1.1 2006/02/13 12:51:34 pylon Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="ppc-release-notes.xml">
<title>ppc Release Notes for Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>

<author title="Author">
 <mail link="wolf31o2@gentoo.org">Chris Gianelloni</mail>
</author>

<author title="PPC Release Coordinator">
  <mail link="pylon@gentoo.org">Lars Weiler</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Gentoo 2006.0 Release Notes.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-02-13</date>

<chapter>
  <title>The Gentoo Linux Project</title>
  <section>
    <title>Overview</title>
    <body>
      <p>Gentoo Linux is a community driven project committed to producing high
        quality opensource software. These release notes for Gentoo Linux 2006.0
        summarize important package updates, security updates, and many other
        changes that have happened since Gentoo Linux 2005.1</p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Table of Contents</title>
    <body>
    <ul>
      <li>1. Overview</li>
      <li>2. Important Changes</li>
      <li>  2.1 Security Updates</li>
      <li>  2.2 Profile Update</li>
      <li>  2.3 Errata</li>
      <li>  2.4 Critical Package Updates</li>
      <li>  2.5 Portage Updates</li>
      <li>  2.6 Userland Updates</li>
      <li>  2.7 Documentation Updates</li>
      <li>3. Upgrading from previous versions of Gentoo Linux</li>
    </ul>

    </body>
  </section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Important Changes for 2006.0</title>
  <section>
    <title>Security Updates</title>
    <body>
      <p>Gentoo Linux 2006.0 contains security updates to address GLSAs (Gentoo
        Linux Security Advisories) numbered 200507-28 to 200601-14.  </p>

      <p>Individual GLSAs can be referenced by going to
        <c>http://www.gentoo.org/security/en/glsa/glsa-$x.xml</c>, and
        substituting <c>$x</c> with the desired GLSA number. </p>

      <p>For more information, please consult the the <uri
          link="http://security.gentoo.org/">Gentoo Linux Security Project home
          page</uri>.</p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Profile Update</title>
    <body>
      <p>With Gentoo Linux 2006.0 the PowerPC team made rather big changes to
        the profile.  The merge of the ppc32 and ppc64 profiles went forward.
        Furthermore the ppc32 profile has been changed in a way, that it offers
        a minimalistic generic profile for all purposes, located in
        <path>/usr/portage/profiles/default-linux/ppc/ppc32</path>.  The
        release-dependent profile is optimized for desktop-usage and located in
        <path>/usr/portage/profiles/default-linux/ppc/ppc32/2006.0</path>.
        There are some subprofiles available for <path>G3</path> and
        <path>G4</path> processors, and <path>G3/Pegasos</path> and
        <path>G4/Pegasos</path> for the Pegasos Open Desktop Workstation.
        Please update you profile as described in <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml" />.</p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Errata</title>
    <body>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Errata</th>
          <th>Workaround</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti><c>pbbuttonsd</c> fails to start.</ti>
          <ti>This tool gives some power and keyboard advantages to Apple Laptop
            and Desktop users.  On some systems it fails to start, but that
            would not harm anything for the installation.</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>There is no bootsplash</ti>
          <ti>As the bootsplash, known from previous releases, consumes 25 MB of
            disk-space on the CD, we decided to leave it out in order to hand
            you a smaller ISO.</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>The fan on some G4 Apple laptops don't work during installation.</ti>
          <ti>After the CD has booted you have to call <c>modprobe
              therm_adt746x</c>.  This will load the appropriate kernel module for
            the fan-controler.  The initial <c>coldplug</c> does not take care of
            it.</ti>
        </tr>
      </table>

    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Critical Package Updates</title>
    <body>
      <p>Important package-versions in this release:</p>

      <ul>
        <li>sys-devel/gcc-3.4.4-r1</li>
        <li>sys-libs/glibc-2.3.5-r3</li>
        <li>sys-kernel/gentoo-sources-2.6.15-r4</li>
        <li>sys-kernel/vanilla-sources-2.6.15.3</li>
        <li>sys-apps/portage-2.0.54</li>
        <li>x11-base/xorg-x11-6.8.2-r6</li>
        <li>kde-base/kde-3.4.3</li>
        <li>gnome-base/gnome-2.12.2</li>
        <li>xfce-base/xfce4-4.2.2</li>
      </ul>

      <p>There are two kernels on the InstallCD:</p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>Kernel filename</th>
          <th>Capabilites</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>ppc32</ti>
          <ti>Supports uniprocessor and multiprocessor 32-bit PowerPC
            machines.</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>pegasos</ti>
          <ti>Supports Genesi's Pegasos I and II Open Desktop Workstation,
            with multiprocessor support.</ti>
        </tr>
      </table>

      <p>For information about how to change your profile please read <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/gentoo-upgrading.xml" />.</p>

      <warn>Cascading profiles will only work with Portage &gt;=2.0.51. Make sure
        to first upgrade to an appropriate version of Portage and <b>then</b>
        upgrade your profile!</warn>


    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Portage Updates</title>
    <body>
      <p>The Portage version included in this release is 2.0.54 and the <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/portage/ChangeLog?root=gentoo-src">ChangeLog</uri>
        can be found via our online CVS repository.</p>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Userland Updates</title>
    <body>
      <ul>
        <li>Catalyst, the Gentoo Release Metatool, is stable in Portage as
          version 2.0. To use Catalyst, simply <c>emerge catalyst</c>.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </body>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Documentation Updates</title>
    <body>
      <p>Much consideration and time has been spent on the <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook-ppc.xml">Gentoo
          Installation Handbook</uri> in order to get it in sync with Gentoo
        2006.0. Please note that it is a constant work in progress, and if any
        bugs are encountered, please refer them to the Gentoo Linux bugtracking
        system at <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org" />.</p>
    </body>
  </section>

</chapter>

<chapter>
  <title>Upgrading and Installation of Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
  <section>
    <title>Installing Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
    <body>
      <p>The entire Gentoo Linux installation process is documented in the <uri
          link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/handbook/handbook.xml">Gentoo
          Handbook</uri>.</p>

      <p>The PowerPC release team offers three InstallCDs. The first one being a universal
        bootable InstallCD which can be used to install with or without an Internet
        connection.  The second InstallCD is a non-bootable subarch-optimized
        Gentoo Reference Platform (GRP) CD which contains precompiled
        binaries of popular programs such as X.org-X11, KDE, and GNOME. The
        third InstallCD is a bootable minimal CD that is smaller in size and
        includes only the basics needed to simply boot a machine.</p>

      <p>At minimum, the universal or minimal InstallCD is required to boot the
        machine and install Gentoo.  The universal InstallCD requires an Internet
        connection to install from a stage1 installation tarball, but does not
        require an Internet connection to install from a stage3 installation
        tarball. The minimal InstallCD requires an Internet connection to install
        Gentoo Linux.</p>

      <p>There are two kernel available on both bootable CDs. It will run on
        both, uniprocessor and multiprocessor systems.  The kernel is based on
        linux-2.6.15.4 (gentoo-sources-2.6.15-r4).  Please refer to the handbook
        for booting the CD</p>

      <p>The InstallCDs are located on the mirrors as follows: </p>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>InstallCD Description</th>
          <th>Location on Mirrors</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>Universal bootable InstallCD</ti>
          <ti>/releases/ppc/2006.0/installcd/install-ppc-universal-2006.0.iso</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>Minimal bootable InstallCD</ti>
          <ti>/releases/ppc/2006.0/installcd/install-ppc-minimal-2006.0.iso</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>Non-bootable GRP-/Packages CD for generic PowerPC</ti>
          <ti>/releases/ppc/2006.0/packagecd/$subarch/packages-ppc-2006.0.iso</ti>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <ti>Non-bootable GRP-/Packages CD optimized for G4</ti>
          <ti>/releases/ppc/2006.0/packagecd/$subarch/packages-g4-2006.0.iso</ti>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </body>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Upgrading to Gentoo Linux 2006.0</title>
    <body>
      <p>If you already have a working installation of Gentoo Linux (Version
        1.4, 2004.0 through 2005.1) there is no need to reinstall. You will
        automatically get Gentoo 2006.0 if you sync your Portage tree and run
        <c>emerge --update world</c>. If you still have an installation with a
        Gentoo 1.2 profile it might make sense -- in some cases -- that you do a
        new installation.</p>

      <p>There is also the possibility to update your system to a 1.4 profile
        from which you -- as already stated -- can easily get to Gentoo 2006.0.
        This update includes recompiling of glibc and some essential system
        packages; it will take a very long time (possibly longer as a complete
        re-installation) and it might also fail. So if you still have an
        installation with a Gentoo 1.2 profile, it's your decision whether you
        update or reinstall.</p>
    </body>
  </section>
</chapter>

</guide>
