<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/faq.xml,v 1.4 2012/10/28 15:21:12 swift Exp $: -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide>
<title>Frequence Asked questions about the TreeCleaner Project</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="masterdriverz@gentoo.org">Charlie Shepherd</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide covers questions frequently asked by users of Gentoo Linux
about the TreeCleaner project.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>2</version>
<date>2010-11-04</date>

<!-- Note: TreeCleaner > treecleaner > Treecleaner -->

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo TreeCleaner Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<section>
<title>I'm a Gentoo Developer. Will TreeCleaners remove my package for me?</title>
<body>
<p>Short answer: no. The TreeCleaner project encourages maintainers to remove
their own packages. If you no longer wish to maintain a package, you should
consider reassigning it to maintainer-needed, to indicate its unmaintained
status.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>TreeCleaners are removing a package I use! What should I do?</title>
<body>
<p>Please comment on the removal bug (it should be apparent in the masking).
If there isn't one, please tell us in #gentoo-qa on irc.freenode.org.
If you are interested in maintaining the package, you should contact the
proxy-maintainer project by emailing <mail>proxy-maint@gentoo.org</mail>.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>What resources do TreeCleaners provide?</title>
<body>
<p>TreeCleaners provide some documentation on their policy. We also provide
some tools to aid package maintainer who wish to mask/remove a package. We
have an overlay where removed packages are moved to and we hope to have a
database containing treecleaner information (package removal history etc)
available soon.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cool. Where can I get these scripts?</title>
<body>
<p><uri link="http://dev.gentoo.org/~masterdriverz/mask.py">Here.</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>How to get files out of the cvs attic</title>
<body>
<p>Take a look at
<uri>http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo-x86/?hideattic=0</uri>
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>I'm a Gentoo dev. I want to fix a maintainer-needed package.
Do I have to support it forever now?</title>
<body>
<p>Not at all. While the 'you clean up your own mess' rule applies, it
only applies to that commit - you are not expected to look after that
package any more.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>I'm a Gentoo dev, and want to join the TreeCleaner project</title>
<body>
<p>Great! Please read up on TreeCleaner policy and then drop into
#gentoo-qa on irc.freenode.org and talk to antarus (project lead).
</p>
</body>
</section>


<section>
<title>I don't understand something in this FAQ!</title>
<body>
<p>Please join #gentoo-qa on irc.freenode.org, or mail
<mail>treecleaner@gentoo.org</mail> if you want clarification on any of
TreeCleaner's policies, or any decisions that have been made by TreeCleaners.
</p>
</body>
</section>

</chapter>
</guide>
