<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<!-- <project link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/index.xml"> -->

<project>
<name>TreeCleaners</name>
<longname>Gentoo Tree Cleaning Team</longname>
<description>
The Tree Cleaning Team is primarily concerned with removing unmaintained
and broken packages from the tree.  We aim to make less work for everyone
by reducing the number of broken and unmaintained packages in the tree.  
We also aim to increase the user experience by removing broken packages 
from the tree; therefore users have less hair-raising experiences with
packages in-tree that just don't work.
</description>

<longdescription>
Gentoo currently has a number of packages that lack maintainers and are
broken in one or more ways.  Due to the large number of packages that
exhibit this behavior in the gentoo package database the tree cleaner
subproject was created.   The overall goal of this subproject is to reduce
the number of unmaintained and broken packages in the tree.  This is
accomplished by either finding a maintainer for the package, fixing the
package, or removing the package from the package database.
</longdescription>

<goals>
<ul>
    <li>Remove broken and unmaintained packages from the tree.</li>
    <li>Aid developers in finding packages that need a maintainer.</li>
</ul>
</goals>

<dev role="Lead">Antarus</dev>
<dev role="Member">beandog</dev>
<dev role="Member">phreak</dev>
<dev role="Member">cardoe</dev>
<dev role="Member">falco</dev>
<dev role="Member">jakub</dev>
<dev role="Member">neddyseagoon</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Current contributors</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>A list of the current contributors (non-devs).</p>

<p>
<table>
    <tr>
	<th>Contributor</th>
	<th>Nickname</th>
	<th>e-mail</th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
	<ti>Ahmed Ammar</ti>
	<ti>b33fc0d3</ti>
	<ti>b33fc0d3@gmail.com</ti>
    </tr>
    <tr>
	<ti>Ryan Hill</ti>
	<ti>dirtyepic.sk</ti>
	<ti>dirtyepic.sk@gmail.com</ti>
    </tr>
    <tr>
	<ti>Jean-Francois Gagnon Laporte</ti>
	<ti>kioshen</ti>
	<ti>kioshen@gmail.com</ti>
    </tr>
</table>
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Criteria for Removal</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>Treecleaners are reachable at treecleaner@gentoo.org</p>

<p>
The goal of the tree cleaning project is not to remove packages that
developers are willing to work on.  To this end there exists certain
criteria that must be met for a package to be eligible for removal by
the tree cleaning project.  They are:
</p>
<ol>
    <li>The Package has open bugs on the Gentoo bugzilla.  These open bugs
are assigned to maintainer-needed and have typically been neglected for
some time.  It is the policy of the tree cleaning project to attempt to fix
simple bugs (such as a bad DEPEND atom, minor QA violations, and simple
revbumps), however fixing of simple bugs is not required.  Especially in
the case where a package has only simple bug filed against it, it is often
easier to just fix the bug as opposed to removing it from the tree (a
process that takes a bit of work).</li>
    <li>Package has no active maintainer.  This can mean any of the following:
        <ul>
            <li>The package has no metadata.xml.</li>
            <li>The package is assigned to maintainer-needed.</li>
            <li>The team who oversees the package's herd has been contacted
and no one has shown interest.</li>
            <li>The listed maintainer has shown no interest and does not 
respond to e-mails or on bugs.gentoo.org.</li>
            <li>The listed maintainer is no longer a Gentoo developer.</li>
       </ul>
    </li>    
    <li>Package should have dead or unresponsive upstream.  If upstream isn't
taking or fixing bugreports this causes problems as Gentoo relies heavily on
upstream in many cases.  Note the wording here is <b>should</b>, packages
are not required to have a dead upstream, this is merely a heuristic that the
tree cleaning project relies on.</li>
</ol>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Maintainer-Needed</title>
<body>
<p>Removing a package isn't the only solution offered by the tree cleaner project.
The project strives to maintain a list of packages that have no maintainer.  This
package list is created by two methods.  One is to look in the tree for packages
lacking a metadata.xml file.  The second is to look at packages assigned to
maintainer-needed in metadata.xml.  The final method involves looking on bugs for
bugs assigned to maintainer-needed.  All of these methods are combined to create
the Gentoo Packages that Need Lovin' (GPNL) List.
</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Bugs Usage for the Treecleaner Project</title>
<body>
<p>Tracking bugs is an important part of the TreeCleaner project.  Improper tracking
leads to lost packages (not assigned to anyone useful) or packages assigned that are
not canidates for removal.  To avoid this some general policy must be set up.</p>
<ol>
    <li>Only take bugs from maintainer-needed unless you have spoken with the current
        herd or maintainer.  We are here to clean out packages no one is maintaining
        or that the maintainer/herd deems horribly broken and unfixable.</li>
    <li>When taking a bug, keep maintainer-needed in the CC field.  Some people
        actually watch that alias and the goal is not to hide progress (or lack
        thereof) from maintainer-needed.  Don't disturb their mailflow.</li>
    <li>When assigning a bug from maintainer-needed be sure you are going to either
        work on the bug; the goal is not to dump maintainer-needed on treecleaners.
        The goal is to have a focussed set of bugs that the treecleaner project is
        currently working on.  Don't assign a bug to treecleaners unless you have
        spoken to a project member on irc, or e-mail the alias and be like "hey this
        package sucks take a look at it for me."  Generally inappropriately assigning
        bugs angers project members and they will assign it back to the original
        assignee.</li>
    <li>PMASKED is a keyword we use to indicate that we have package.masked the
        package in question.  Use it when you know that the package is in pmask.</li>
    <li>PENDING REMOVAL [date] is a status whiteboard phrase we use to indicate when
        the package is scheduled for removal.  PENDING REMOVAL implies you have sent
        last rites for the package.  Please do not forget to send last rites for a
        package that you masked.</li>
</ol>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Package Removals</title>
<body>
<p>As time passes and developers move on, some packages in the Gentoo tree
will inevitably become unmaintained. For the most part, these packages
will continue to work, albeit without new releases being added, but
sometimes bugs will be found, and if there is no maintainer, or the
package is dead upstream, they must be removed from the tree,
especially in the case of security bugs. Usually the package will be
masked at the repository level with package.mask for a few weeks to
give warning to anyone using it that it is about to be removed, but you
still may find that a package you need has been removed from CVS. If
this happens, do not panic -- there are still ways to use the package.
</p>

<p>
All ebuilds, including deleted ones, are available from the web
interface to Gentoo's CVS repository, which you can find at 
<uri link="http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo-x86/">http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo-x86/.</uri>
Ebuilds and directories that have been removed will appear in the Attic, and can be
accessed by clicking the (Show &lt;n&gt; dead files) link at the top of the
folder view. You can then download any ebuilds you may need from
ViewCVS and place them in a local overlay, where they can be installed
as normal. Any distribution files will remain on Gentoo's mirrors for
at least two weeks after the ebuild is removed from the tree, and even
after removal from our mirrors they will in most cases continue to be
available from the original source.
</p>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>But I love that package!</title>
<body>
<p>I'm glad you like that package, however without a maintainer it sits stale in
the tree.  Maintaining a package involves a time commitment, even if your ebuild
you submitted to bugzilla works, or your patch works, it takes time fixing other
bugs, testing the package, checking for updates, and so on.  Sometimes there is
no one to take this resposibility on.  If you are confident there are enough users
for the package, feel free to take it to Gentoo Sunrise once the ebuild has been
removed from the tree (not before mind, their policy states you can't have
something in sunrise and the tree, so be patient).  For more information on Sunrise
please see <uri link="http://gentoo-sunrise.org">gentoo-sunrise.org</uri> and 
#gentoo-sunrise on chat.freenode.net.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extraproject name="Gentoo Packages that Need Lovin'">
<p>The GPNL is a set of pages that is currently under development to list packages
that need maintainers.  At present it is only an idea with no scripts driving it,
however integration with packages.gentoo.org is being considered as it already has
most of what a GPNL site would need.  Package search, package metadata, bugs links,
really only herdstat integration is the major component left.
</p>
</extraproject>
</project>

<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; indent-mode normal; -->
