<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/index.xml,v 1.56 2015/06/16 16:32:54 creffett Exp $: -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<!-- <project link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/index.xml"> -->

<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Treecleaner">
<name>TreeCleaners</name>
<longname>Gentoo Tree Cleaning Team</longname>

<date>2012-12-09</date>

<author title="Author">
	<mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
	<mail link="masterdriverz@gentoo.org">Charlie Shepherd</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="hwoarang@gentoo.org">Markos Chandras</mail>
</author>
<author title="Editor">
	<mail link="scarabeus" />
</author>

<description>
The Tree Cleaning Team is primarily concerned with removing unmaintained and
broken packages from the tree.  We aim to make less work for everyone by
reducing the number of broken and unmaintained packages in the tree.  We also
aim to increase the user experience by removing broken packages from the tree;
therefore users have less hair-raising experiences with packages in-tree that
just don't work.
</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
Gentoo currently has a number of packages that lack maintainers and are broken
in one or more ways. Due to the large number of packages that exhibit this
behavior in the gentoo package database the tree cleaner subproject was created.
The overall goal of this subproject is to reduce the number of unmaintained and
broken packages in the tree.  This is accomplished by either finding a
maintainer for the package, fixing the package, or removing the package from the
package database.
</p>

</longdescription>

<goals>

<p>
To find and remove broken and unmaintained packages from the tree.
</p>

</goals>

<recruitment>
	<job>
		<summary>"Ghostbusters"</summary>
		<details>
		Our project is understaffed. We are constantly looking for users and developers to assist us in identifying broken and unmaintained packages on portage tree
		</details>
		<requirements>
		Candidates must be familiar with Bugzilla and portage tree structure. Experience with portage tools ( equery, etc ) is also a plus
		</requirements>
		<contact>treecleaner@gentoo.org</contact>
	</job>
</recruitment>

<dev role="Lead">hwoarang</dev>
<dev role="Member">pacho</dev>
<dev role="Member">ssuominen</dev>
<dev role="Member">vostorga</dev>
<dev role="Member">moult</dev>

<extrachapter>
<title>Contact</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The TreeCleaner project is available at <mail>treecleaner@gentoo.org</mail>
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Orphaned packages</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Removing a package isn't the only solution offered by the tree cleaner project.
The Treecleaner Project maintains
<uri link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/maintainer-needed.xml">a list of orphaned (aka maintainer-needed) packages</uri>.
Feel free to grab and maintain one if you want to.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Package Removals</title>
<section>
<title>CVS Attic</title>
<body>

<p>
All ebuilds, including deleted ones, are available from the web interface to
Gentoo's CVS repository, which you can find at <uri
link="http://sources.gentoo.org/cgi-bin/viewvc.cgi/gentoo-x86/">http://sources.gentoo.org/viewcvs.py/gentoo-x86/.</uri>
Ebuilds and directories that have been removed will appear in the Attic, and can
be accessed by clicking the (Show &lt;n&gt; dead files) link at the top of the
folder view. You can then download any ebuilds you may need from ViewCVS and
place them in a local overlay, where they can be installed as normal. Any
distribution files will remain on Gentoo's mirrors for at least two weeks after
the ebuild is removed from the tree, and even after removal from our mirrors
they will in most cases continue to be available from the original source.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>But I love that package!</title>
<body>

<p>
I'm glad you like that package, however without a maintainer it sits stale in
the tree.  Maintaining a package involves a time commitment, even if your ebuild
you submitted to bugzilla works, or your patch works, it takes time fixing other
bugs, testing the package, checking for updates, and so on.  Sometimes there is
no one to take this resposibility on.  If you are confident there are enough
users for the package, feel free to contact the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/qa/proxy-maintainers/index.xml">proxy-maintainers</uri> team and hopefully they will be able to help you.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>TreeCleaner Docs</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The TreeCleaner Project currently have two docs:
</p>

<ul>
	<li>
		<uri link="faq.xml">Frequently Asked Questions about the Gentoo TreeCleaner project</uri>
	</li>
	<li><uri link="policy.xml">Gentoo TreeCleaner Policy</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

</project>
