<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<!-- <project link="/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/index.xml"> -->

<project>
<name>TreeCleaners</name>
<longname>Gentoo Tree Cleaning Tream</longname>
<description>
The Tree Cleaning Team is primarily concerned with removing unmaintained
and broken packages from the tree.  We aim to make less work for everyone as
there are less packages in the tree.  We also aim to increase the user
experience by removing broken packages from the tree.
</description>

<longdescription>
Gentoo currently has a number of packages that lack maintainers and are
broken in one or more ways.  Due to the large number of packages that
exhibit this behavior in the gentoo package database the tree cleaner
subproject was created.   The overall goal of this subproject is to reduce
the number of unmaintained and broken packages in the tree.  This is
accomplished by either finding a maintainer for the package, fixing the
package, or removing the package from the package database.
</longdescription>

<goals>
<ul>
    <li>Remove broken and unmaintained packages from the tree.</li>
    <li>Aid developers in finding packages that need a maintainer.</li>
</ul>
</goals>

<dev role="Lead">Antarus</dev>

<!--<subproject ref="/proj/en/qa/something/index.xml"/>-->

<extrachapter position="bottom">
<title>Criteria for Removal</title>
<section>
<body>
<p>
The goal of the tree cleaning project is not to remove packages that
developers are willing to work on.  To this end there exists certain
criteria that must be met for a package to be eligible for removal by
the tree cleaning project.  They are:
</p>
<ol>
    <li>The Package has open bugs on the Gentoo bugzilla.  These open bugs
are assigned to maintainer-needed and have typically been neglected for
some time.  It is the policy of the tree cleaning project to attempt to fix
simple bugs (such as a bad DEPEND atom, minor QA violations, and simple
revbumps), however fixing of simple bugs is not required.  Especially in
the case where a package has only simple bug filed against it, it is often
easier to just fix the bug as opposed to removing it from the tree (a
process that takes a bit of work).</li>
    <li>Package has no active maintainer.  This can mean any of the following:
        <ul>
            <li>The package has no metadata.xml.</li>
            <li>The package is assigned to maintainer-needed.</li>
            <li>The team who oversees the package's herd has been contacted
and no one has shown interest.</li>
            <li>The listed maintainer has shown no interest and does not 
respond to e-mails or on bugs.gentoo.org.</li>
            <li>The listed maintainer is no longer a Gentoo developer.</li>
       </ul>
    </li>    
    <li>Package should have dead or unresponsive upstream.  If upstream isn't
taking or fixing bugreports this causes problems as Gentoo relies heavily on
upstream in many cases.  Note the wording here is <b>should</b>, packages
are not required to have a dead upstream, this is merely a heuristic that the
tree cleaning project relies on.</li>
</ol>
</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Maintainer-Needed</title>
<body>
<p>Removing a package isn't the only solution offered by the tree cleaner project.
The project strives to maintain a list of packages that have no maintainer.  This
package list is created by two methods.  One is to look in the tree for packages
lacking a metadata.xml file.  The second is to look at packages assigned to
maintainer-needed in metadata.xml.  The final method involves looking on bugs for
bugs assigned to maintainer-needed.  All of these methods are combined to create
the Gentoo Packages that Need Lovin' (GPNL) List.
</p>
</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>
</project>

<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; indent-mode normal; -->
