<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/qa/treecleaners/policy.xml,v 1.3 2012/10/28 15:21:12 swift Exp $ -->

<guide lang="en">
<title>TreeCleaner Policy</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="antarus@gentoo.org">Alec Warner</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This guide covers policy that should be followed by TreeCleaner project
members.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>0.2</version>
<date>2008-12-14</date>

<chapter>
<title>Policy</title>

<section>
<title>Removal Criteria</title>
<body>
<p>
The goal of the tree cleaning project is not to remove packages that
developers are willing to work on.  To this end there exists certain
criteria that must be met for a package to be eligible for removal by
the tree cleaning project.  They are:</p>
<ol>
    <li>The Package has open bugs on the Gentoo bugzilla.  These open bugs
are assigned to maintainer-needed and have typically been neglected for
some time.  It is the policy of the treecleaner project to attempt to fix
simple bugs (such as a bad DEPEND atom, minor QA violations, and simple
revbumps).</li>
    <li>Package has no active maintainer.  This can mean any of the following:
        <ul>
            <li>The package has no metadata.xml.</li>
            <li>The package is assigned to maintainer-needed.</li>
            <li>The team who oversees the package's herd has been contacted
                and no one has shown interest.</li>
            <li>The listed maintainer has shown no interest and does not
                respond to e-mails or on bugs.gentoo.org.</li>
            <li>The listed maintainer is no longer a Gentoo developer.</li>
       </ul>
    </li>
    <li>The package should have dead or unresponsive upstream.  If upstream isn't
        taking or fixing bugreports this causes problems as Gentoo relies heavily on
        upstream in many cases.  Note the wording here is <b>should</b>, packages
        are not required to have a dead upstream, this is merely a heuristic that the
        tree cleaning project relies on.
    </li>
</ol>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Using Bugzilla</title>
<body>
<p>Tracking bugs is an important part of the TreeCleaner project.  Improper tracking
leads to lost packages (not assigned to anyone useful) or packages assigned that are
not canidates for removal.  To avoid this some general policy must be set up.</p>
<ol>
    <li>Only take bugs from maintainer-needed unless you have spoken with the current
        herd or maintainer.  We are here to clean out packages no one is maintaining
        or that the maintainer/herd deems horribly broken and unfixable.</li>
    <li>When taking a bug, keep maintainer-needed in the CC field.  Some people
        actually watch that alias and the goal is not to hide progress (or lack
        thereof) from maintainer-needed.  Don't disturb their mailflow.</li>
    <li>When assigning a bug from maintainer-needed be sure you are going to either
        work on the bug; the goal is not to dump maintainer-needed on treecleaners.
        The goal is to have a focussed set of bugs that the treecleaner project is
        currently working on.  Don't assign a bug to treecleaners unless you have
        spoken to a project member on irc, or e-mail the alias and be like "hey this
        package sucks take a look at it for me."  Generally inappropriately assigning
        bugs angers project members and they will assign it back to the original
        assignee.</li>
    <li>PMASKED is a keyword we use to indicate that we have package.masked the
        package in question.  Use it when you know that the package is in pmask.</li>
    <li>PENDING REMOVAL [yyyy-mm-dd] is a status whiteboard phrase we use to indicate when
        the package is scheduled for removal.  PENDING REMOVAL implies you have sent
        last rites for the package.  Please do not forget to send last rites for a
        package that you masked.</li>
    <li>VOTE is a status whiteboard phrase we used to indicate when a package is up
        for a removal vote.  A vote typically requires 1/3rd of the TreeCleaner project
        to vote in an affirmative manner.  See the above section on the removal process
        for more information</li>
</ol>
<p>When you are working on a particular bug for TreeCleaners and
it has dependencies or blockers do NOT close them until the package
is removed.  There have been cases when a package was masked and the
dependencies were closed only to have the package taken over by a developer.
Please close the dependencies when the package is removed</p>
</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Removal Process</title>
<body>
<p><b>Heuristics</b><br/>
Treecleaners search the tree using basic heuristics; things like:</p>
<ul>
   <li>When the package was last touched via cvs</li>
   <li>Packages that have no maintainer and/or no herd</li>
   <li>Packages that missed major Gentoo upgrades, for example things
       unported to modular X or things that don't compile with gcc-4</li>
   <li>Packages that have multiple open bugs that have been open many months
       with what appears to be no interested from the community</li>
</ul>
<p>Once located, a package is inspected by a Treecleaner project member.  The developer
attempts to ascertain the package's problem and tries to find a solution.  This may
involve asking a related herd for advice, revbumping the package in question, making
QA ebuild fixes, patching the software, or a number of other tasks.</p>
<p>If the Treecleaner decides that the package is beyond fixing they must notify the rest
of the Treecleaner project and the project will vote on the package.  In order for a Vote
to be had, the developer in question must present a case for removing the package.  If
1/3rd of the team agrees with the presented case the packages will be 'voted off' survivor
style.</p>
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
<!-- kate: space-indent on; indent-width 2; replace-tabs on; indent-mode normal; -->
