<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>planet</name>
<longname>Planet Gentoo</longname>
<date>2009-03-31</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="christel@gentoo.org">Christel Dahlskjær</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="beandog"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tampakrap"/>
</author>

<description>
Planet Gentoo provides a central aggregation of developers' blogs, to keep users
and other developers informed of what they are working on
</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
We run a service, <uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org">Planet Gentoo</uri>, which
aggregates articles written by contributing developers. This is optional, but it
is encouraged that you participate. It helps communication between developers and
users find it to be an interesting read too.
</p>

<p>
In order to post content to the planet, you need to have your own weblog
("blog"). Many sites provide this as a free service, or you can host it
yourself (if you have the resources). Alternatively, we can host a blog for
you.
</p>

<p>
We aim to keep Planet Gentoo's content relevant to Gentoo and/or Gentoo-related
developments and events.
</p>

<p>
If we host your blog for you, you are expected to keep the content on-topic
(Gentoo and Gentoo-related articles). You also need to understand that if you
ever lose or drop your developer status, you will no longer be able to write
articles on your blog.
</p>

<p>
If you have a blog elsewhere, then it needs to be able to provide an XML
content feed. If you blog into categories, we need to be able to get an XML
feed which covers your "Gentoo" category but no others. This is probably a
non-issue, as almost all blogs provide standardised feeds like this.
</p>

<p>
This aggregation is currently available in two forms. Planet Gentoo shows only
posts marked
as 'on-topic', and related to Gentoo development.
 <uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/universe">Gentoo Universe</uri> shows
all posts to that developer's blog, for those who are interested in more
than strictly Gentoo-related news.
</p>

<p>
Although this is somewhat common sense, please be careful with what you write
about. Your views may be inappropriately interpreted as the views of Gentoo.
Please be careful not to damage our image.
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in contributing to Planet Gentoo, please <uri
link="https:///bugs.gentoo.org">file a bug</uri>, selecting Product
<c>Website www.gentoo.org</c> and Component <c>Planet</c>. You'll need
to provide us your blog link, RSS feed links for Planet and Universe
and your <uri link="#doc_chap4">gravatar</uri> email, if applicable.
</p>

</longdescription>

<extrachapter>
<title>Blog Hosting</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Using <uri link="http://www.b2evolution.net/">b2evolution</uri>, Planet
Gentoo hosts blogs for any Gentoo developers who are in need of a home.
</p>

<p>
If you want a Gentoo hosted blog, please <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org">file a bug</uri>,
selecting Product <c>Website www.gentoo.org</c> and Component <c>Planet</c>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Avatars</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Planet Gentoo and Gentoo Universe can display an icon or headshot of the
developer on the website.
</p>

<p>For ease of maintenance, we use gravatars (globally recognized avatars)
which the developer can manage personally.  Users can create their own gravatar
at <uri>http://www.gravatar.com/</uri>.  By default, the MD5 string we use to
access the personalized avatars is username@gentoo.org.  If you already have
an account under a different e-mail address and would like to use that instead,
please contact a developer to have your configuration updated.</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<dev role="Lead">beandog</dev>
<dev>tampakrap</dev>

<resource link="http://planet.gentoo.org">Planet Gentoo</resource>
<resource link="http://planet.gentoo.org/universe">Gentoo Universe</resource>
<resource link="http://blogs.gentoo.org/">Gentoo Developer Blogs</resource>

</project>
