<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">

<project disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Planet">
<name>Planet</name>
<longname>Planet Gentoo</longname>
<date>2010-10-17</date>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="christel@gentoo.org">Christel Dahlskjær</mail>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="beandog"/>
</author>
<author title="Author">
  <mail link="tampakrap"/>
</author>

<description>
Planet Gentoo provides a central aggregation of developers' blogs, to keep users
and other developers informed of what they are working on
</description>

<longdescription>

<p>
We run a service, <uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org">Planet Gentoo</uri>, which
aggregates articles written by contributing developers. This is optional, but any
developer is encouraged to participate. It helps communication between developers,
and users find it to be an interesting read too.
</p>

<p>
While Planet is strictly Gentoo-themed, an additional service runs to cover any
non Gentoo related posts, called <uri link="http://planet.gentoo.org/universe">
Universe</uri>.
</p>

<p>
In order to post content to Planet/Universe, you need to have your own weblog
("blog"). Many sites provide this as a free service, or you can host it
yourself (if you have the resources). Alternatively, we can host a blog for
you at <uri link="http://blogs.gentoo.org/">Gentoo Developer Blogs</uri>.
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in contributing to Planet Gentoo, please read the
<uri link="#doc_chap4">Terms</uri>, and then file a bug providing the relevant
information needed (more info <uri link="#doc_chap5">here</uri>).
</p>

</longdescription>

<extrachapter>
<title>Terms</title>
<section>
<body>

<ul>
  <li>
    Blogs at blogs.gentoo.org are provided to Gentoo Developers only, thus if
    you lose your developer status we'll revoke your access to your blog.
  </li>
  <li>
    The content in blogs.gentoo.org will stay there for archive reasons.
  </li>
  <li>
    Planet posts should be strictly Gentoo related and in English. Universe posts
  don't have to follow that rule.
  </li>
  <li>
    Please be careful with what you write about. Your views may be inappropriately
    interpreted as the views of Gentoo. Please be careful not to damage our image.
  </li>
  <li>
    The Gentoo community is consisted of all kinds of people, so please avoid any
    racist comments.
  </li>
  <li>
    While constructive criticism is welcome, flamewars and attacks towards other
    projects or people are forbidden.
  </li>
  <li>
    The Planet Gentoo team has the right to ban people from Planet/Universe or
    suspend authors from Gentoo Developer Blogs that don't follow the above terms.
  </li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Contact</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
To ask for a new blog hosted in blogs.gentoo.org, or to be included in Planet /
Universe, please make sure you have read the <uri link="#doc_chap4">Terms</uri>,
and then <uri link="https://bugs.gentoo.org">file a bug</uri>, selecting Product
<c>Website www.gentoo.org</c> and Component <c>Planet</c>. You'll need to provide
us the following information:
</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    An RSS feed reflecting your Gentoo category or tag, for Planet posts.
  </li>
  <li>
    Optional: An RSS feed that will reflect wider range of posts, for Universe.
    An RSS feed that aggregates the whole blog is also acceptable
  </li>
  <li>
    A gravatar mail (see <uri link="#doc_chap6">below</uri> for more info).
  </li>
  <li>
    For a new blog in blogs.gentoo.org, state it clearly in the bug. After that
    you'll be asked to set up a Gentoo category/tag and a gravatar mail, for
    Planet / Universe aggregation.
  </li>
</ul>

<p>
Also, you can file a bug in case something is wrong with Planet/Universe/Blogs, or
in case you want a new plugin/theme added for WordPress.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Avatars</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
Planet Gentoo and Gentoo Universe can display an icon or headshot of the
developer on the website.
</p>

<p>
For ease of maintenance, we use gravatars (globally recognized avatars)
which the developer can manage personally.  Users can create their own gravatar
at <uri>http://www.gravatar.com/</uri>.  By default, the MD5 string we use to
access the personalized avatars is username@gentoo.org.  If you already have
an account under a different e-mail address and would like to use that instead,
please contact a developer to have your configuration updated.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter>
<title>Wordpress Plugins</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
A list of plugins available at blogs.gentoo.org wordpress installation:
</p>

<ul>
  <li><uri link="http://akismet.com/">akismet</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.viper007bond.com/wordpress-plugins/clean-archives-reloaded/">Clean archives reloaded</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.poradnik-webmastera.com/projekty/google_integration_toolkit/">Google intergration toolkit</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/openid">openid</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://www.prelovac.com/vladimir/wordpress-plugins/smart-youtube">Smart Youtube</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/stats/">wordpress.com stats</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/wp-syntax/">wp-syntax</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/wp-security-scan/">wp-security-scan</uri></li>
  <li><uri link="http://wordpress.org/extend/plugins/limit-login-attempts/">limit-login-attempts</uri></li>
</ul>

</body>
</section>
</extrachapter>

<dev description="Planet, Blogs">nightmorph</dev>
<dev description="Planet, Blogs">tampakrap</dev>


<resource link="http://planet.gentoo.org">Website: Planet Gentoo (An aggregation of Gentoo-related weblog articles)</resource>
<resource link="http://planet.gentoo.org/universe">Website: Gentoo Universe (An aggregation of weblog articles on all topics)</resource>
<resource link="http://blogs.gentoo.org/">Website: Gentoo Developer Blogs</resource>
<resource link="admin.xml">Admininstration: Instructions for Planet and Blogs administrators</resource>
<resource link="http://git.overlays.gentoo.org/gitweb/?=proj/planet-gentoo.git">Administration: Planet Gentoo config files</resource>
<resource link="http://git.overlays.gentoo.org/gitweb/?=proj/blogs-gentoo.git">Administration: Gentoo Blogs plugins/themes</resource>

</project>
