<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/forums/draft/user-policy.xml,v 1.3 2012/10/28 15:21:04 swift Exp $ -->

<guide lang="en">
<title>Gentoo Forums User Policy (Draft)</title>
<author title="Author/Editor">
  <mail link="deathwing00@gentoo.org">Ioannis Aslanidis</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="klieber@gentoo.org">Kurt Lieber</mail>
</author>
<author title="Contributor">
  <mail link="nitro@gentoo.org">Kyle Manna</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The intention of this guide is to merge in a single document all the user
guidelines to form a global policy. Additionally, this guide will try to
cover all basic questions a user could have towards the forums.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2005-08-12</date>

<chapter>
<title>Introduction</title>
<section>
<title>Targeted Audience</title>
<body>

<p>
This document is meant for <b>every Gentoo Forums user</b>, including
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/groupcp.php?g=916">Forums Staff</uri> and
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/groupcp.php?g=24">Developers</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Forums as a way of technical assistance</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Forums represent possibly the most practical way of technical
assistance for Gentoo related issues. There are two main benefits:
</p>

<ol>
<li>You can search for existing solutions on your issue, where other means like
IRC do not let you</li>
<li>You can get an answer from other users or developers pretty quickly, maybe
not as quickly as in IRC, however your question will always be there, you won't
need to be asking all the time for help.</li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The structuring of Gentoo Forums</title>
<body>

<p>
The Gentoo Forums are structured in four great blocks, each one intended for a
different objective:
</p>

<ol>
<li>
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/index.php?c=1">Assistance</uri>: Here you
can find Gentoo-related <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-16.html">
News &amp; Announcements</uri>,
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-40.html">FAQs</uri> and
differentiated forums where to post determined type of questions.
</li>
<li>
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/index.php?c=4">Discussion &amp;
Documentation</uri>: This block is not intended for assistance with getting
Gentoo to work, but to post documents on how to do things, talk about
non-gentoo related things, provide feedback on the forums mainly. Here you can
find the <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-38.html">Duplicate
Threads</uri> and our <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-48.html">
Dustbin</uri>, where all spam goes.
</li>
<li>
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/index.php?c=11">International Gentoo
Users</uri>: The perfect place to have users post whatever they like in their
prefered language.
</li>
<li>
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/index.php?c=12">Architectures &amp;
Platforms</uri>: Alternative supported architectures block, for issues specific
to them, not related to x86.
</li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Contents of this guide</title>
<body>

<p>
There are two main sections in this guide, each one related to different
aspects:
</p>

<ol>
<li>
<uri link="#doc_chap2">User policies</uri>: The expected behaviour of people
when using the forums.
</li>
<li>
<uri link="#doc_chap3">User account issues</uri>: Description of common user
account issues and possible ways to solve them.
</li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>User policies</title>
<section>
<title>Essential rules</title>
<body>

<impo>
We know that this document might be a little extensive and that probably most
users know almost everything about this, however consider reading at least
these essential rules.
</impo>

<ol>
  <li>
    <b>Use common sense</b>: Just because it isn't explicitly stated as
    one of the rules below it doesn't mean it's OK. Use common sense and good
    <uri link="http://www.albion.com/netiquette/corerules.html">Netiquette</uri>
    when posting, replying and browsing these forums. This includes the
    following:
    <ul>
      <li>
        No posts for the sole purpose of increasing your postcount.
      </li>
      <li>
        No <e>senseless</e> posts. This might be subjective, however bear in
	mind that if a coherent conversation cannot be read in the thread, it
	might be senseless.
      </li>
      <li>
        No posting of <e>SPAM</e> to the forum. Also, please do not reply to
	SPAM, just <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-28820.html">
	report</uri> it.
      </li>
      <li>
        No Personal Messaging SPAM to people. SPAM includes unsolicited
	messaging. If it takes you hours to send hundreds of Personal Messages,
	it is still SPAM.
      </li>
      <li>
        Do not participate in
	<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=211695">quote
	pyramids</uri>.
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Check that your question isn't answered anywhere else</b>: Gentoo
    Linux is very well <uri link="http://docs.gentoo.org">documented</uri>, but
    most users seem to overlook the obvious. Check out a collection of helpful
    links <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic.php?t=556">here</uri>.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Search before posting</b>: Please try to use the
    <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/search.php">search feature</uri>
    on the website prior to starting a new topic regarding a problem you are
    experiencing. Chances are, due to the rapid growth of the forum, your
    problem may have been solved already or a problem similar to it. However,
    bear in mind that due to performance issues, some search words have been
    filtered out. Please, have a look at the
    <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-223530.html">stopword
    list</uri>. By searching prior to posting, you will help yourself by find a
    solution sooner, and keep the newer problems in focus. Please also search
    the <uri link="http://bugzilla.gentoo.org">Bugzilla</uri> and file a bug if
    appropriate.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Include logs and explicit the commands you executed</b>: Nobody
    can help you if they don't know what's wrong or what you did to get the
    error you recieved. Providing this information will greatly aid others in
    assisting you, and will allow an easier and faster diagnosis of your
    problem.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Choose a good subject</b>: Do not make your subject say just
    "<e>Help gentoo newbie</e>" because nobody wants to hear this. Describe
    your problem briefly in your subject, then you can describe your problem in
    greater depth in the body of your article. Repeat the subject in the body
    if it will make things clearer. Avoid "<e>Subject says it all</e>" in the
    body of your article.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Use BBCodes if you feel you can</b>:
    <uri link="https://forums.gentoo.org/faq.php?mode=bbcode">BBCodes</uri>
    help to make articles more readable.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Thank those who help you</b>: If you post a problem and someone
    helps you, simply replying with a thank you message or an acknowledgement
    that their suggestions worked are very much appreciated. This will also
    help other users know that the proposed solution worked.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>No bashing</b>: If someone is posting about a problem they are
    experiencing, don't simply tell them they are using the wrong program and
    recommend they try your recommendation. Instead, provide facts or opinions
    supporting your recommendation, provide positive feedback, and please keep
    the criticism low.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Keep on topic</b>: If you are replying about something to do with
    iptables, for instance, and someone mentions a configuration tool that runs
    in KDE, don't start talking about KDE, stick to the topic. Go start a new
    topic and post a link to the old one if there is relevant information
    there.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>One thread per topic</b>: Please, do not post issues of different
    kind in the same thread. Split them into several ones and have them placed
    in the appropiate assistance forum.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>No personal attacks</b>: These forums are not a place for you to
    take cheap shots at somebody because he/she did something. Do that somewhere
    place else (or even better, get over it). You have been warned.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>No illegal activites</b>: Please do not discuss illegal
    activities, such as cracking software, breaking into web sites and so on.
    While such activities might not be illegal in all countries, this server is
    hosted in the US and, as such, must abide by US laws. By allowing
    discussions about illegal activities to take place on these forums, we may
    expose the Gentoo project to unnecessary legal liability. Therefore, any
    posts that advocate activities that are illegal under US laws may be
    deleted or edited without notice.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>No cross posting</b>: Please do not post the same question into
    multiple forums. Cross posting clutters up the forums and makes things like
    searching harder for other users. If you feel your question could fit in
    multiple forums, please pick the best one and post there. If you would like
    your topic moved, request it
    <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-28820.html">here</uri>.
    Also, please do not post about the same subject multiple times. One thread
    is sufficient.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Be careful with thread bumping</b>: We understand that sometimes
    a user might need a quick reply to his question, however, let 24 hours pass
    before bumping a thread. Excessive thread bumps will not produce the
    expected results.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>Ask questions the smart way</b>: If you are new to the internet,
    forums or the world of Linux, or if you just aren't sure what kinds of
    questions are okay to ask and how they should be phrased, then please read
    <uri link="http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html">How To Ask
    Questions The Smart Way</uri> and
    <uri link="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/bugs.html">How To
    Report Bugs Effectively</uri>. It covers many of the same points as
    covered in this guide, but goes into far more detail and offers detailed
    explanations and suggestions.
  </li>
  <li>
    <b>No multiple accounts</b>: Each person should have only one
    account. If you get banned for some reason and simply create another
    account, it will get banned the minute the moderators become aware of it.
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Special rules: Documentation, Tips &amp; Tricks</title>
<body>

<warn>
This is not a support forum, so please, do not ask for support.
</warn>

<ol>
  <li>
    Feel free to use the other assistance forums to ask questions regarding a
    tip or trick. You are encouraged to include a link to the tip/trick you are
    referring to make it easier for other to help you.
  </li>
  <li>
    Do not ask for tip or trick to be posted. If you ask here, your post will
    be moved to the appropiate place.
  </li>
  <li>
    Users are encouraged to simply thank the author if their tip or trick
    worked for them.
  </li>
  <li>
    Provide detailed information about what your tip or trick does, and how it
    works. <e>Please, do not merely link to another website.</e>
  </li>
  <li>
    If you are willing to submit a Document, tip or trick, first of all, make
    sure it works. Also make sure it is easy to read. We suggest you to use
    <uri link="https://forums.gentoo.org/faq.php?mode=bbcode">BBCodes</uri>
    to improve your text's readability.
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Special rules: Off The Wall</title>
<body>

<note>
The Off The Wall forum is intended for pretty much anything not related to
Gentoo. This includes political, religious, racial, ethnic, and other
<e>sensitive</e> topics. You are free to say what you want in this forum,
however keep the guidelines in mind.
</note>

<ol>
  <li>
    <brite>All posts must be professional and courteous.</brite> You are free
    to disagree with your fellow community members. You are not allowed however
    to attack, degrade, troll or malign them. It doesn't matter what forum
    title you have, <b>you are expected to follow this rule</b>.
  </li>
  <li>
    If you are easily offended, have thin skin or are otherwise
    overly-sensitive, <e>this is not the forum for you</e>. There are a lot of
    people who have opinions here and they are not afraid to share them.
    Subject to the first provision, they are free to do so.
  </li>
  <li>
    If you feel that a thread is getting out of hand, or you see a post where
    you feel one member is being disrespectful to another, feel free to bring it
    to the attention of a global moderator. At the bottom of the front page, you
    can see a list of who's online. Moderators are listed in green, site admins
    in orange. Drop a PM to whomever happens to be online at the moment. If
    nobody is online, report it
    <uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-28820.html">here</uri>.
  </li>
  <li>
    The phrases "<e>you are an idiot</e>", "<e>shut up bitch</e>" and "<e>when
    you're done having sex with your computer</e>" are generally indicative of
    a problematic post. Suggested alternatives include, "<e>I disagree with your
    points and here's why</e>", "<e>please</e>" and "<e>thank you</e>".
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>About Duplicate Threads</title>
<body>

<p>
If a thread is moved to the
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-38.html">Duplicate Threads
forum</uri>, it means that the topic it covers is discussed somewhere else in
another thread. The reason such threads are kept is due to the fact that
there are different ways to explain an issue as well as there may be different
problems that might have the same solution. If your thread is moved to this
forum in favor of another thread, consider following up that other thread and
optionally provide additional information you might have if there is no
solution to the problem yet or you feel that the proposed solution does not
fit you well.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Issues with threads and posts</title>
<body>

<p>
If you feel a post or a thread is missplaced or is a duplicate of another one,
please let use know
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-28820.html">here</uri>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>User account issues</title>
<section>
<title>I am unable to create a user account for myself</title>
<body>

<p>
If you have trouble registering to our forums using the
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=register">registration
page</uri>, feel free to send an email to
<mail link="forum-mods@gentoo.org">forum-mods@gentoo.org</mail> with a subject
that denotes that you need an account created for you ("<e>Forums account
creation</e>", for instance). Explicit your desired <e>username</e> and the
<e>email address</e> you want your account to be registered to, so we can
setup an account for you. Please, <e>avoid sending us your password</e> as we
will not set it for you. You will have to use the
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=sendpassword">lost
password feature</uri> in order to set it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I created an account but I did not receive a confirmation email</title>
<body>

<p>
If you created an account but after some hours you did not receive a
confirmation mail to activate your account, please send an email to
<mail link="forum-mods@gentoo.org">forum-mods@gentoo.org</mail> with subject
"<e>No forums confirmation mail received</e>" and provide your <e>username</e>
and <e>e-mail address</e> in the body of the message.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I changed my email address and my account got locked</title>
<body>

<p>
If you changed your email address in your profile, you should have received a
confirmation email into the new email address. If that did not happen, your
account might have got locked. Please, send an email to
<mail link="forum-mods@gentoo.org">forum-mods@gentoo.org</mail> with an
appropiate subject, providing <e>your old and your new email addresses</e> and your
forums <e>username</e> as well.
</p>
<p>
Please, also contact us if you inserted and erroneous/unexistant email address
with your forums <e>username, the old email address and the erroneous one</e>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I forgot my password</title>
<body>

<p>
Please, do not contact us if you lost your password. Use the
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/profile.php?mode=sendpassword">lost
password feature</uri> to reset it.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I want to change my username</title>
<body>

<p>
If you want to change your forums username, please, do not contact us. Post
your new desired username in the
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewtopic-t-102323.html">Username change
request thread</uri> and we will gladly do it for you.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I received a warning from a moderator</title>
<body>

<p>
If you received a warning from a moderator, it might have been because you
performed an action that either is borderline to the <uri link="#doc_chap2">
policies</uri> or implies an undesired behaviour from you. Please, read
the warning message carefully and follow the instructions if any. If you ignore
a warning and keep on conducting in an unwanted way, you will get banned.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>My account was banned</title>
<body>

<warn>
Your account will be immediately banned with no prior notice if your actions
clearly warrant it. Do not intend to create another forums account, as it will be
banned as well in a matter of minutes.
</warn>

<p>
Your account will be banned for one or more of the following reasons:
</p>
<ul>
<li>You ignored several warning messages</li>
<li>You spammed the forums</li>
<li>You conducted a personal aggression against another forums user</li>
<li>You created another account after being banned with your previous one
(Such action might get your IP address banned from the forums)</li>
<li>Other reasons that might imply unacceptable behaviour</li>
</ul>

<note>
If you behaved in an inappropriate way in the
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-10.html">Off the Wall
forum</uri>, you will temporally be set aside of that forum. You may also
receive a warning from a moderator.
</note>

<p>
If you feel sorry for what you did and mean to retract yourself, please send a
<e>200 word essay</e> describing the reasons that pushed you to perform your
actions and the reasons for which we should consider unbanning you.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>The IP address I am using is banned</title>
<body>

<p>
An IP address or IP address range is banned from the forums if there was some
kind of abuse from these. That implies spam account creation and multiple
account creation among other reasons.
</p>

<p>
If you think that your IP address should not have been banned, please
<mail link="forum-mods@gentoo.org">contact us</mail>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Tor servers are banned</title>
<body>

<p>
Due to abusive use of tor servers, the
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/forums/">Gentoo Forums Staff</uri>
decided to ban all tor servers that have an exit policy allowing connections
to forums.gentoo.org on ports 80 (HTTP) and/or 443 (HTTPS).
</p>

<p>
In an effort to purge the abuse of the Tor Network generating the least
problem to our users, only Tor servers with an exit to forums.gentoo.org on the
ports above stated will be banned. If they have those exits removed, they will
automatically be unbanned. Please, notice that this process of retrieving the
list of Tor servers is performed automatically and that it might take a while
to have the ban-list synced.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>I have other issues that are not stated in this document</title>
<body>

<p>
Unless it is something with high priority, please use the
<uri link="http://forums.gentoo.org/viewforum-f-5.html">Gentoo Forums
Feedback forum</uri>, as we review it several times per day. Otherwise,
feel free to <mail link="forum-mods@gentoo.org">contact us</mail>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
