<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/base/pam/service-file.xml,v 1.2 2012/10/28 15:20:58 swift Exp $ -->

<guide lang="en">
<title>Analysis of a PAM service configuration file</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="flameeyes@gentoo.org">Diego Pettenò</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Simple documentation about the format of PAM service configuration files.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2007-07-14</date>

<chapter>
<title />

<section>

<body>

<p>
A PAM service configuration file is a simple ASCII text file installed in
<path>/etc/pam.d/</path>, describing the chain of modules to load and call to be
able to fullfill one of four possible management facilities (account validation,
authentication, password changing, and session handling). The comments, as often
happens with Unix configuration files, are prefixed with a hash mark (#).
</p>

<p>
Every non-comment line of a PAM service file is composed of at least three
elements: the management facility, the control directive and the parameter of
this last one (always a module with the exclusion of the <c>include</c>
directive, that instead takes another service name) following these three
elements there are optional parameters to pass to the module (they are not
supported for <c>include</c>). When a single element needs to contain spaces, it
can be quoted in between square parenthesis (<b>[ ]</b>), we'll see later where
this is used.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>The four facilities</title>

<body>
<p>
The four management facilities are specified with a shortened version of their
name:
</p>

<dl>
  <dt><c>account</c></dt>
  <dd>
  Verifies the validity of the account, whether it's expired, enabled, if login
  for that service is possible for that particular account. This is when you
  should check for <path>/etc/nologin</path>, presence in
  <path>/etc/ftpusers</path>, valid shell, and so on.
  </dd>

  <dt><c>auth</c></dt>
  <dd>
  Handle the authentication of users: asks and checks password values, One-Time
  Passwords, smartcards, biometric scans, USB keys, and so on. This is probably
  the most critical facility as a mistake done by this chain might allow an
  attacker to spoof the identity of an user.
  </dd>

  <dt><c>password</c></dt>
  <dd>
  Takes care of changing the authentication data for the user (password,
  biometric data, smartcard public key, and so on).
  </dd>

  <dt><c>session</c></dt>
  <dd>
  Manages the session opened for the user, by setting up and destroying the
  environment as needed, this is the only chain that is called twice: at login
  and logout. Here you should call modules that handle mounting, chrooting, or
  changing various permissions.
  </dd>
</dl>

<p>
The order of each chain is related to the order in which the modules are listed
in the configuration file; when you use the <c>include</c> directive, the
lines declaring and configuring the modules for that facility are read from the
specified service file and expanded in the place of the <c>include</c> line. The
order of the four facilities is ignored, you can mix them.
</p>

<pre caption="ordering of PAM service file directives">
<comment># If this is the service file to read...</comment>
auth     required   pam_foo1.so
account  required   pam_foo2.so
auth     required   pam_foo3.so
account  include    other-service
session  required   pam_foo4.so
password required   pam_foo5.so

<comment># And this is the other-service file...</comment>
password required   pam_bar1.so
session  required   pam_bar2.so
account  required   pam_bar3.so

<comment># The actual chains are equivalent to a file like this:</comment>
auth     required   pam_foo1.so
auth     required   pam_foo3.so
account  required   pam_foo2.so
account  required   pam_bar3.so
password required   pam_foo5.so
session  required   pam_foo4.so
</pre>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>The control directives</title>

<body>

<p>
The control directives - beside <c>include</c>, that as we have seen just loads
the content of the homologous chain in another file - tell PAM what to do when
the module fails or succeeds. This is important because you usually want to
treat failures and successes of the modules in different ways depending on the
chain and on the semantic of the module. The directives for this are:
</p>

<dl>
  <dt><c>required</c></dt>
  <dd>
  The module success is necessary to allow the facility to complete, if this
  module fail, the facility will ultimately fail, but the rest of the chain is
  still executed.
  </dd>

  <dt><c>requisite</c></dt>
  <dd>
  Again, the module success is necessary to allow the facility to complete, but
  this time if the module fails, the chain is aborted immediately.
  </dd>

  <dt><c>sufficient</c></dt>
  <dd>
  A success of the module will make the chain complete immediately; a failure,
  instead, will leave the response to the following modules. If the last module
  of a chain is sufficient and fails, the facility fails.
  </dd>

  <dt><c>optional</c></dt>
  <dd>
  The result of this module is disregarded unless it's the last one to be
  executed, in which case the chain result will be the same as the result of the
  module (minus <c>required</c> modules failing).
  </dd>

  <dt><c>binding</c> (OpenPAM only)</dt>
  <dd>
  The result of the module will dictate the result of the whole chain: if it
  succeeds, it is treated like sufficient, and the chain will complete
  immediately, if it fails, it is treated like required, the chain will continue
  even if the final result will certainly be a failure.
  </dd>

</dl>

<p>
In addition to those, Linux-PAM also provides a more flexible way to define the
behaviour of the modules, albeit quite more complex: you can decide what PAM
will do in the various case (missing module, failure in loading the module,
error in the call to the module's functions, failure of the implementation).
To set this up, you need to pass a compless directive, quoted in square
parenthesis (<b>[ ]</b>) as the second token of the line, and in it pass
<c>condition=result</c> couples, separated by commas, as needed. As this syntax
is limited to Linux-PAM, and is usually more useful to advanced users than for
default configurations, please refrain to use this syntax for the PAM service
files installed by ebuilds.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>Module name and parameters</title>

<body>

<p>
The following token in the line is the module name; As modules are shared
objects, they have the name <path>pam_$something.so</path>. A common mistake is
to use the full path of the module for this token; although this works on basic
setups, it is suboptimal for multilib architectures (like AMD64), where it
breaks for the non-default ABI. So please always use just the base name of the
library.
</p>

<impo>
On AMD64, the 32-bit PAM modules come out of the <c>sys-libs/pam</c> package,
and are just the default set. If your 32-bit software using PAM has a
configuration that includes <path>system-auth</path>, the users will not be able
to add extra modules to that service file. This is a drawback that needs to be
tackled down soon.
</impo>

<p>
After these three tokens, there are the parameters to pass to the modules. Each
parameter is separated by whitespace, and as we said, if it contains spaces it
should be quoted through square parenthesis (<b>[ ]</b>); this is the case for
the SQL queries used together with the frontend modules for MySQL or PostgreSQL.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</chapter>

</guide>

<!--
 Local Variables: **
 mode:nXML **
 fill-column: 80 **
 End: **
-->
