<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/gnome/faq.xml,v 1.6 2014/09/05 18:18:25 creffett Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete">
<title>Gentoo GNOME Project FAQ</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="allanonjl@gentoo.org">John N. Laliberte</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dang@gentoo.org">Daniel Gryniewicz</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
Frequently Asked Questions about GNOME on Gentoo.
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>2.1</version>
<date>2010-11-06</date>

<chapter>
<title>Gentoo GNOME FAQ</title>
<section>
<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
<body>

<ol>
  <li>
    <uri link="#doc_chap1_sect2">How do I turn off desktop icons?</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#doc_chap1_sect3">How do I use Keychain with GNOME?</uri>
  </li>
  <li>
    <uri link="#doc_chap1_sect4">What is FAM, and should I use gamin
    instead?</uri>
  </li>
</ol>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>How do I turn off desktop icons?</title>
<body>		

<p>
Desktop icons are drawn by Nautilus. In order to remove them, you have to stop
nautilus from drawing the desktop. The quickest way is to modify the Nautilus
GConf key to controlling drawing. You can either use <c>gconf-editor</c> or
<c>gconftool-2</c> to set the
<path>/apps/nautilus/preferences/show_desktop</path>.
</p>

<pre caption="using gconftool-2">
% gconftool-2 -s /apps/nautilus/preferences/show_desktop -t bool false
</pre>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>How do I use Keychain with GNOME?</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/doc/en/keychain-guide.xml">Keychain</uri>
manages your SSH keys and SSH agent for you. To use it with your GNOME session,
you will need to install <c>gtk2-ssh-askpass</c> or <c>x11-ssh-askpass</c>.
These give an X interface to prompting you for a passphrase. Setup Keychain as
the guide suggests and you should be prompted for your passphrase on your next
login.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>What is FAM, and should I use gamin instead?</title>
<body>

<p>
<uri link="http://http://oss.sgi.com/projects/fam/">FAM</uri> (or the File
Alteration Monitor) is a daemon responsible for notifying GUI applications of
changes to files. Typically, on a GNOME desktop, this is used by nautilus (the
file manager), to keep file listings current with the underlying system - even
when modifications to the files are made from outside of nautilus.
</p>

<p>
In short, FAM watches your filesystem to make sure what nautilus displays is up
to date.
</p>

<p>
<uri link="http://www.gnome.org/~veillard/gamin/">Gamin</uri> (an alternative to
FAM), is library implementation of a subset of FAM's functionality, although
its purpose in monitoring the file system for changes, is the same.  Gamin is
not a complete FAM replacement - some of FAM's more exotic features are missing,
but Gamin's main aims are to be an API/ABI compatible replacement for FAM, and
to address resource consumption issues.
</p>

<p>
So which of these two should you choose?
</p>

<p>
We'd recommend you use Gamin over FAM for your GNOME desktop. The project is now
more mature, it doesn't need to run as a daemon (saving some resources), and is
easier to use than FAM.
</p>

<p>
If you don't have FAM installed, installing gamin is easy:
</p>

<pre caption="Installing gamin">
# <i>emerge gamin</i>
</pre>

<p>
If you already have FAM installed, it's still easy to switch to gamin.  You'll
need to stop FAM, remove it, and then install gamin:
</p>

<pre caption="Replacing FAM with gamin">
# <i>rc-update del famd default</i>
# <i>/etc/init.d/famd stop</i>
# <i>emerge -C fam</i>
# <i>emerge gamin</i>
</pre>

<p>
Now you'll just need to restart GNOME, or nautilus (<c>killall -9 nautilus</c>)
to use Gamin for file-monitoring.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Desktop profile and subprofiles</title>
<body>

<p>
Desktop profile has been split to KDE and GNOME subprofiles.
This means that KDE and GNOME specific USE flags have been stripped
from the basic desktop profile and have been migrated to the subprofiles.
Choosing a subprofile doesn't restrict you to use only the equivalent
DE.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
