<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/desktop/gnome/gnome-policy.xml,v 1.12 2014/09/05 18:18:25 creffett Exp $ -->

<guide disclaimer="obsolete" redirect="http://wiki.gentoo.org/wiki/Project:Gnome/Policy">
<title>Gnome Project Policy</title>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="allanonjl@gentoo.org">John N. Laliberte</mail>
</author>

<author title="Author">
  <mail link="dang@gentoo.org">Daniel Gryniewicz</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
This the policy document for the Gnome Project
</abstract>

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->
<license/>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2006-08-03</date>

<chapter>
<title>Meta Ebuild Policy</title>
<section>
<body>

<p>
The Gnome Herd maintains a meta ebuild named gnome.  This meta ebuild is intended to
install all of the packages considered by the upstream GNOME project as being part of the
Gnome Desktop.  It is not intended to be customizable, with two exceptions: hardware
customization (cdr, dvdr, hal), and accessibility.  This is the recommended method of
installing the Gnome desktop on a Gentoo system.
</p>
<p>
The primary alternative, if you require specific Gnome programs, is to emerge them
individually.  If, for example, you want to use Evolution for email, you should emerge
evolution.  This should pull in any necessary dependencies to run evolution.
</p>
<p>
There are many subsets of Gnome that can be installed and usable.  There is no way that
the Gnome Herd can support them all, or any significant fraction of them.  We do make one
such subset available: gnome-light.  This subset is intended to include the programs
necessary for basic desktop functionality without any additional applications.  It
basically includes gnome-session, gnome-panel, gnome-terminal, nautilus, metacity, and
yelp.  This is a session manager, a start menu/panel, a terminal program, a desktop, a
file browser, a window manager, and a help browser.  This subset is largely unsupported
(as none of the Gnome Herd members actually use it), but we will fix problems with it as
we can.  Gnome-light can be used as a jumping-off point for installing intermediate
subsets of Gnome between it and the full gnome meta ebuild, by emerging extra
applications as necessary.  No other subsets, including making the gnome ebuild more
customizable with USE flags, will be supported.
</p>
  
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>CFLAGS Support</title>
<section>
<body>
  
<p>
Upstream GNOME does not support any advanced CFLAGS beyond -O2, and neither does the
Gnome Herd.   Unreproducable bugs with any CFLAGS beyond -O2 and appropriate -march
are liable to be closed as INVALID unless they can be reproduced with valid CFLAGS.
</p>
  
</body>
</section>
</chapter>

<chapter>
<title>Bug Priority</title>
<section>
<body>
  
<p>
Bug priority table
</p>
 
<table>
<tr>
  <th>Priority</th>
  <th>Description</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Pri-1</ti>
  <ti>
	Major bugs in the desktop.  This will also include Trackers (so the trackers are easy
	to find).
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Pri-2</ti>
  <ti>
    Most bugs in the packages we maintain that have been verified as "real"
    bugs and require fixing. Also includes version bumps.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Pri-3</ti>
  <ti>
    Bugs identified as "user-specific", those that aren't verified and are most
    likely to do with a specific users settings/issues.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Pri-4</ti>
  <ti>
    Requests for new ebuilds that we'd like to maintain, time permitting.
    Requests for new ebuilds that we don't want to maintain should be
    re-assigned to maintainer-wanted.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Pri-5</ti>
  <ti>The Gentoo Gnome wishlist</ti>
</tr>
</table>
  
</body>
</section>
</chapter>
  
</guide>
