<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "/dtd/project.dtd">
<project>
<name>gnome</name>

<longname>Gentoo GNOME Desktop</longname>
<date>12 March 2004</date>

<author title="Developer">
   <mail link="liquidx@gentoo.org">Alastair Tse</mail>
</author>

<author title="Developer">
   <mail link="foser@gentoo.org">Marinus Schraal</mail>
</author>

<author title="Developer">
   <mail link="obz@gentoo.org">Mike Gardiner</mail>
</author>

<description>
	Gentoo GNOME Project aims to bring the current and complete
	GNOME Desktop Environment to Gentoo.
</description>

<longdescription>
	Gentoo GNOME Project aims to bring the current and complete
	GNOME Desktop Environment to Gentoo. We maintain the GNOME core libraries,
	media framework (gstreamer), GNOME Office Applications (gnumeric, abiword,
	evolution) and various applications that are part of the GNOME Desktop.
</longdescription>

<dev role="lead" description="GNOME core, GStreamer and everything">foser</dev>
<dev role="member">spider</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Evolution and other GNOME apps">liquidx</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Gdesklets and other GNOME apps">obz</dev>
<dev role="member" description="A11Y and other GNOME apps">leonardop</dev>
<herd name="gnome"/>
<herd name="gnome-accessibility"/>

<task id="projectpage" lead="liquidx" finished="no">
	<name>Complete Project Page</name>
	<description>Kick off the all-new exciting GNOME Project Page</description>
	<longdescription>
		We need to get this thing start off so we can start
		putting in some documentation that we've always talked
		about. For instance we should document gst-plugins, FAQs for GNOME
		upgrades and common misfiled bugs. Maybe even a Top 10 GNOME bugs!
	</longdescription>
	<startdate>10 October 2003</startdate>
	<milestone finished="no">
		<enddate>1st Dec 2003</enddate>
		<description>add common bug links</description>
	</milestone>		
	<milestone finished="no">
		<enddate>20th April 2004</enddate>
		<description>add gstreamer notes</description>
	</milestone>			
</task>

<extrachapter position="goals">
	<title>Gentoo GNOME News</title>
	<section>
		<title>Accessibility herd created</title>
		<body>
		<p><i>Sat, 13 March 2004</i></p>
		<p>A gnome accessibility herd has been created to take care of the gnome accessibility framework. 
		With this move we hope to make it easier for accessibility developers and users to come in direct contact with eachother and thereby 
		noticably improve support for these technologies in Gentoo GNOME. The herd will be the joint responsibility of the accessibility project
		 and gnome project. </p>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>			  			  
		<title>First Post!</title>
		<body>
		<p><i>Fri, 10 October 2003</i></p>
		<p>We have our first outing as a Project page.</p>
		</body>
	</section>		
</extrachapter>

<extrachapter position="goals">
	<title>GStreamer Setup</title>
	<section>
		<body>
		<p>Some words about how and why GStreamer is setup in Gentoo and
		to get the most out of it.
		</p>
		</body>
	</section>
</extrachapter>

<!--
<extrachapter position="goals">
	<title>Top Gentoo GNOME Bugs</title>
	<section>
		<body>
		<ul>
		<li>All bugs assigned to Gentoo GNOME Team</li>
		<li>All enhancement bugs Assigned to Gentoo GNOME Team</li>
		<li>All normal bugs assigned to the Gentoo GNOME Team</li>
		<li>All bugs marked as "Later"</li>
		<li>All bugs resolved in the last 30 days</li>
		</ul>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Most Frequently Reported Bugs</title>
		<body>These are bugs that are most frequently reported.</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>In Progress Bugs</title>
		<body>Bugs that we are working on.</body>
	</section>
</extrachapter>
-->

<extrachapter position="bottom">
	<title>Gentoo GNOME FAQ</title>
	<section>
		<title>Frequently Asked Questions</title>
		<body>
		<ol>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect2">How do I turn off desktop icons?</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect3">How do I use Keychain with GNOME?</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect4">Why doesn't USE="-gtk gtk2" work?</uri></li>
		<li><uri link="#doc_chap7_sect5">What is FAM, and should I use gamin instead?</uri></li>
		</ol>
		</body>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>How do I turn off desktop icons?</title>
		<body>		
			<p>Desktop icons are drawn by Nautilus. In order to 
			remove them, you have to stop nautilus from drawing the desktop. 
			The quickest way is to modify the Nautilus GConf key to 
			controlling drawing. You can either use
			<c>gconf-editor</c> or <c>gconftool-2</c> to set the
			<path>/apps/nautilus/preferences/show_desktop</path>.</p>

			<pre caption="using gconftool-2">
% gconftool-2 -s /apps/nautilus/preferences/show_desktop -t bool false
			</pre>
		</body>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>How do I use Keychain with GNOME?</title>
		<body>
			<p><uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/keychain.xml">Keychain</uri>
			manages your SSH keys and SSH agent for you. To use it with your GNOME
			session, you will need to install <c>gtk2-ssh-askpass</c> or
			<c>x11-ssh-askpass</c>. These give an X interface to prompting you for a
			passphrase. Setup Keychain as the guide suggests and you should be prompted
			for your passphrase on your next login.</p>
		</body>
	 </section>
	 
	 <section>
	 	<title>Why doesn't USE="-gtk gtk2" work?</title>
		<body>
			<p>This is a very common misconception about the usage of the <c>gtk</c>
			USE flag. <c>gtk</c> USE flag represents the choice of enabling any
			GTK+ interface if a choice exists. It does not represent the option
			for GTK+-1.2.x support. On the other hand <c>gtk2</c> USE flag is used
			only in the presences of a choice between GTK+-1.2.x and GTK+-2.x.
			When such a choice is available, <c>gtk2</c> will choose GTK+-2.x
			support over GTK+-1.2.x.</p>
			
			<p>So if you would prefer to have GTK+-1.2 support in a package
			that gives you a choice, use:
			<pre caption="Prefer GTK+-1.2">
USE="gtk -gtk2"
			</pre>
			</p>
			
			<p>If you prefer to have GTK+-2.x support in a package that
			gives you a choice, use:
			<pre caption="Prefer GTK+-2">
USE="gtk gtk2"
			</pre>
			</p>
			
			<p>If you prefer not to have any GTK+ support in a package that
			gives you a choice, use:
			<pre caption="No GTK+">
USE="-gtk"
			</pre>
			Note that in this case, <c>gtk2</c> is not required and has no
			effect on a package that observes both.
			</p>
			
			<p>Therefore <c>USE="-gtk gtk2"</c> is equivalent to <c>USE="-gtk"</c>
			in most packages and if a package only has a GTK+ interface and no
			choice remains except for what version of GTK+ to use, then use
			GTK+-2. But for all intents and purposes, this combination should
			not be used. More importantly, this does not mean you will have a
			GTK+-1 free system because many packages exist that only have GTK+-1
			interfaces.
			</p>
		</body>
	 </section>

	<section>
		<title>What is FAM, and should I use gamin instead?</title>
		<body>
			<p>
			<uri link="http://http://oss.sgi.com/projects/fam/">FAM</uri>
			(or the File Alteration Monitor) is a daemon responsible for 
			notifying GUI applications of changes to files. Typically, on a
			GNOME desktop, this is used by nautilus (the file manager), to keep
			file listings current with the underlying system - even when modifications
			to the files are made from outside of nautilus.
			</p>
			<p>
			In short, FAM watches your filesystem to make sure what nautilus
			displays is up to date.
			</p>
			<p>
			<uri link="http://www.gnome.org/~veillard/gamin/">Gamin</uri>
			(an alternative to FAM), 
			is library implementation of a subset of FAM's functionality, although
			it's purpose in monitoring the file system for changes, is the same.
			Gamin is not a complete FAM replacement - some of FAM's more exotic
			features are missing, but Gamin's main aims are to be an API/ABI compatible
			replacement for FAM, and to address resource consumption issues.
			</p>
			<p>
			So which of these two should you choose?
			</p>
			<p>
			We'd recommend you use Gamin over FAM for your GNOME desktop. The project
			is now more mature, it doesn't need to run as a daemon (saving some
			resources), and is easier to use than FAM.
			</p>
			<p>
			If you don't have FAM installed, installing gamin is easy:
			<pre caption="Installing gamin">
emerge gamin
			</pre>
			</p>
			<p>
			If you allready have FAM installed, it's still easy to switch to gamin.
			You'll need to stop FAM, remove it, and then install gamin:
			<pre caption="Replacing FAM with gamin">
rc-update del famd default
/etc/init.d/famd stop
emerge -C fam
emerge gamin
			</pre>
			</p>
			<p>
			Now you'll just need to restart GNOME, or nautilus (<c>killall -9 nautilus</c>)
			to use Gamin for file-monitoring.
			</p>
		
		</body>
	 </section>
	
</extrachapter>

</project>
