<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/base/ppc/AT/arch-testers.xml,v 1.2 2006/04/18 02:46:24 josejx Exp $ -->
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The context of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommonds.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<sections>

<version>1.0</version>
<date>2005-06-23</date>

<section>
<title>PPC Arch Testers Information</title>

<body>
<p>
Gentoo/PPC will maintain a pool of "Arch Testers" (ATs) and one or more PPC 
Developers will take the responsibility of managing the AT group.  ATs will be 
included on the ppc@gentoo.org alias, so they can be informed of all bug 
activity. The current AT head for PPC is Joseph Jezak. Any problems, suggestions
 and/or flames should be directed at him.
</p>

<p>
ATs will be responsible for responding to all test requests in a timely
manner (including keywording, security, marking stable, requests from devs on 
irc, etc...) and ensuring that the application works, as well as check that the
ebuild doesn't contain any glaring errors. ATs must keep their system up to
date, use reasonable CFLAGS, and keep with the current profile.  When marking
a bug as tested all ATs will use the keyword "TESTED" in bugzilla (in the
"keywords" field)
</p>

<p>
Gentoo/PPC developers will be able to take ATs word at their own discretion 
since ultimately, committing the requested changes will be the dev's 
responsibility .  Feel free to ask for more than one tester if you feel the bug
warrants it.
</p>

<p>
Prospective AT's will have to pass the <uri link="http://www.gentoo.org/proj/en/devrel/quiz/ebuild-quiz.txt">ebuild quiz.</uri>
Additionally, all quizes should be submitted to the PPC AT leader and hparker
(who has graciously volunteered to mentor potential PPC ATs).
</p>

<p>
A note about arch testers "status": Gentoo/PPC Arch Testers are not official
Gentoo developers.  They are, however, a recognized part of the Gentoo/PPC arch
team.  All AT's should keep this in mind when selecting email signatures or 
other forms of communication.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
<th>Current PPC Arch Testers</th>
<th>Nickname</th>
<th>GPG key</th>
<th>Status</th>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>Johannes Traub</ti>
<ti>_bambam</ti>
<ti>C02196D6</ti>
<ti>Active</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>Nathan Sullivan</ti>
<ti>CpuID</ti>
<ti>DE9B4353</ti>
<ti>Active</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>Matti Bickel</ti>
<ti>mabi</ti>
<ti></ti>
<ti>Active</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
<ti>Michael Prorock</ti>
<ti>mfproroc</ti>
<ti></ti>
<ti>Active</ti>
</tr>
</table>

</body>
</section>
</sections>
