<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/project.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/base/alpha/index.xml,v 1.3 2006/05/02 13:45:33 yoswink Exp $ -->

<!DOCTYPE project SYSTEM "http://www.gentoo.org/dtd/project.dtd">

<project>
<name>Gentoo Alpha</name>

<longname>Gentoo Linux Alpha Development</longname>

<date>05-09-2005</date>

<author title="Gentoo/Alpha">
  <mail link="yoswink@gentoo.org">José Luis Rivero</mail>
</author>

<description>
  The Gentoo/Alpha Arch Team is devoted to keeping Gentoo in good shape
  on the Alpha architecture.
</description>

<longdescription>
  The Gentoo/Alpha Port works to keep Gentoo the most up to date and
  fastest Alpha distribution available. We are responsible for the
  maintenance of all Alpha specific meta-data and the testing of all other
  non Alpha specific meta-data on the Alpha architecture to ensure
  portability. Portability implies reusable meta-data.
</longdescription>

<goals>
  <p>
  The goal of the Gentoo/Alpha Port is to guarantee that the Alpha packages
  build using Gentoo meta-data are up to date.  By continuously enhancing the
  meta-data, we provide the Alpha user with the Gentoo community feeling,
  performance, freedom and up to dateness.  The meta-distribution notion
  allows for a user to to be as bleeding edge as he/she wants:
  </p>

  <p>
  Gentoo is unique because of its interpretation of the Meta-Distribution
  notion: all architectures share the same 'generic' meta-data (information
  about how to build packages - how to build a distribution). The Alpha
  developers are responsible for building and testing packages using this
  meta-data.  The meta-data gets marked 'tested' or 'stable' afterwards,
  depending on the building and testing experience. Our users can use (but
  don't have to use) this information to build a system that suits their
  needs.
  </p>
</goals>

<dev role="Strategic Manager" description="Gentoo/alpha">kloeri</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Porting">agriffis</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Porting, security">ferdy</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Porting, security">yoswink</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Hardened">spb</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Modular X">stefaan</dev>
<dev role="member" description="Porting, security">tcort</dev>

<extraproject name="Alpha Releng" lead="kloeri">
  <p>
  Development and maintenance of the Gentoo/Alpha LiveCDs, the installation
  stages and the related development tools (Catalyst and Genkernel).
  The Release Engineering team is crosses architecture boundaries while trying
  to develop generic multi-architecture and multi-platform release media.
  </p>
</extraproject>

<extraproject name="Documentation" lead="">
  <p>
  The aim of the <uri link="/proj/en/base/alpha/doc/index.xml">Alpha
  Documentation</uri> is to ensure that installation instructions are
  up to date and offer a high quality Gentoo/Alpha docs to our devs and
  community.
  </p>
</extraproject>

<extraproject name="Status Reports" lead="">
  <p>
  The <uri link="/proj/en/base/alpha/status/index.xml">Status Reports
  Project</uri> appears to improve comunication between Gentoo/Alpha
  Port and the users community. It tries to be a semestral report where
  Gentoo/Alpha devs talk about the port progress during last months, on what we
  are working on and what are the next steps programmed for the future.
  </p>
</extraproject>

<extraproject name="Hardened" lead="spb">
  <p>
  The Hardened/Alpha project aims to bring some features of the Hardened
  project to the Alpha platform. Current efforts are limited to SELinux
  support and the hardened-sources.
  </p>
</extraproject>

<extraproject name="Arch Testers" lead="ferdy">
  <p>
  The <uri link="/proj/en/base/alpha/AT/index.xml">Gentoo/Alpha Arch Tester
  project</uri> is heavily based on the Gentoo/AMD64 Arch Tester
  Project and the Gentoo/PPC Arch Tester Project. The Project is meant to help
  the Gentoo/Alpha Arch Team providing an stable, secure and up to date Gentoo
  Linux port.
  </p>
</extraproject>

<extrachapter position="bottom">
  <title>How to Participate</title>
  <section>
  <body>

  <p>
  Can you make computers do amazing things? Are you excited about
  exploring areas of computing never explored before? We are
  continuously looking for volunteers willing to spend some of their
  free time on this project. In return for your work, you get the
  respect of the alpha community.
  </p>

  <p>
  If you are interested in helping, but don't have a niche that you are
  interested in filling, you can always look through <uri
  link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>. There are many
  many bugs waiting to be found and fixed and many enhancements looking
  to find someone to code them. Figure out a fix, implement it, test it,
  and then keep trying to make the patch smaller. Post it for review on
  <uri link="http://bugs.gentoo.org">bugs.gentoo.org</uri>, and keep
  working on it. If it seems ignored, make a new comment in the bug
  and/or mention it in #gentoo-alpha.
  </p>

  </body>
  </section>
</extrachapter>

<herd name="alpha"/>

</project>
