<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/releng/installer/meetings/2004/20040912.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Installer Meeting Summary</title>
<subtitle>12 Sep 2004</subtitle>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="blackace@gentoo.org">Blackace</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The meeting began at 1800 UTC, and the meeting chair was esammer (Eric Sammer).
The primary speaker was esammer.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version/>
<date>17 Sep 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>General Summary</title>
<section>
<title>Meeting Purpose</title>
<body>

<p>
esammer stated the purpose for the meeting: "the reason for this meeting is to
discuss current status, releng integration efforts, live cd requirements, and a
release date".
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Releng Coordination</title>
<body>

<p>
zhen took the floor and stated that if the Gentoo Linux Installer can be
released as an ebuild there will be no problem integrating it into a LiveCD.
He also stated that the Releng project is flexible to do whatever the Installer
project requires, including creation of X and CLI LiveCDs.
</p>

<p>
zhen opened the floor to questions regarding Releng coordination.
</p>

<p>
samyron asked about execution points on the LiveCDs, where the installer should
start in the LiveCD boot process, and what should occur after the installer
exits.  zhen answered that the execution points will vary based on the specific
LiveCDs and that it is up to the Installer project to determine the execution
specifics.
</p>

<p>
esammer noted that the LiveCD requirements would be a future issue, and that the
only problem he could forsee is being able to run the installer before unpacking
the stage since as zhen stated earlier "python is not on the livecd and [releng]
would like to keep it that way for size constraints".
</p>

<p>
klieber pointed out "we also need to support both guided and automatic
installations from the liveCD.  We can't just assume everyone wants a guided
install".
</p>

<p>
esammer noted that there is now a point of contact with the Releng project and
that this line of communication could be helpful in determining when and how the
installer should be run from the LiveCDs and what libraries and utilities will
be required.
</p>

<p>
In further discussion of the LiveCD integration, variant suggested that running
the command <c>installer</c> at any point should start the installer.  In
response spyderous noted "that doesn't really work for an automated one, though.
maybe it should check for existence of some kickstart-like file".  samyron noted
"we have to *standardize* on a filename/location".  esammer suggested that a
special LiveCD may be needed for automated deployments that might probe devices
and network interfaces for a configuration.
</p>

<p>
codeman asked about parted being on the LiveCDs and esammer pointed out that
parted has not been decided on as the partitioning tool since there are still
some architecture issues to be overcome and that it can be discussed outide of
the meeting.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Release Date</title>
<body>

<p>
esammer asked zhen what release the Installer project was aiming for, and zhen
answered "esammer: anything 2005".  zhen stated that 2005 was not yet planned
and would not be planned until after the 2004.3 release.  klieber suggested
setting an internal date of Dec 31st and codeman answered that a 
non-partitioning release could be possible by that date.
</p>

<p>
It was then suggested by klieber that if an x86 specific installer could be
released sooner than a multi-arch installer, that would be preferable.  It was
then discussed to drop to a shell on architectures it cannot partition in order
to allow manual partitioning.
</p>

<p>
The release date discussion was then postponed in order to discuss current
code status.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Code Status</title>
<body>

<p>
codeman reported his success at installing a laptop using some hacked together
scripts to drive the installer with only 3 interventions.  samyron reported on
the status of the GLIClientController class, with agaffney suggesting the
capability to bypass parts of or the whole of the GLIClientController class
to allow installation from within a chroot.
</p>

<p>
samyron expressed a desire to review the arch templates as the current design
seems unnatural, but it was reiterated that they currently work.
</p>

<p>
samyron then summarized the remaining code work, estimating the installer to be
70% complete:
</p>
<ul>
  <li>Notifications</li>
  <li>Frontend-Backend Interfacing</li>
  <li>Testing</li>
</ul>
<p>
esammer noted that he could implement the notification system very quickly.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Release Date (continued)</title>
<body>

<p>
klieber suggested a public beta before releasing on a LiveCD, and the idea was
generally accepted.  esammer asked "can we be tested and working for 2005.0?",
with samyron answering "i'm pretty confident", and codeman answering "we can do
it".
</p>

<p>
klieber also brought up the topic of documentation, with samyron stating he
would write the API documentation, and esammer stating the end-user
documentation should wait until things solidify more, with codeman adding there
were many people who volunteered to help with documentation who did not show up
to the meeting.
</p>

<p>
The release date discussion ended with the target release date as end of year,
and a possibility of a public beta by the end of November.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Open Floor</title>
<body>

<p>
No additional questions were brought forth, and the meeting was adjourned at
1930 UTC.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
