<?xml version='1.0' encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="/xsl/guide.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE guide SYSTEM "/dtd/guide.dtd">

<guide link="/proj/en/releng/installer/meetings/2004/20040715.xml">
<title>Gentoo Linux Installer Meeting Summary</title>
<subtitle>15 Jul 2004</subtitle>

<author title="Editor">
  <mail link="blackace@gentoo.org">Blackace</mail>
</author>

<abstract>
The meeting began at 1900 UTC, and the meeting chair was samyron (Scott Myron).
The primary speaker was samyron.
</abstract>

<license/>

<version/>
<date>05 Sep 2004</date>

<chapter>
<title>General Summary</title>
<section>
<title>Meeting Purpose</title>
<body>

<p>
samyron stated the purpose for the meeting: "basically, i want to talk about:
What we've done thus far, what needs to get done in the short term, and what
long term projects are".
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Status Quo</title>
<body>

<p>
esammer answered the first of samyron's questions: "we've completed a basic
design, implemented profile objects, controller skeleton, utility functions and
classes, and done research into some of the more difficult topics such as
partitioning".
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Partitioning</title>
<body>

<p>
It was decided that partitioning is a stumbling block and as such should be put
on the "back burner" so other goals can be met.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Short Term Goals</title>
<body>

<p>
esammer stated some short term goals: "we need to finish the controller with
networking setup, routing setup, misc file generation (/etc/hosts,
/etc/conf.d/*, etc...)".
</p>

<p>
samyron added: "Other things that I consider important: a way to download the
profile from a given URI".
</p>

<p>
esammer noted that cshields is working on a PHP profile generator, and homer
volunteered to implement same.
</p>

<p>
Along the lines of a profile generator, codeman asked for a complete sample
profile to be committed to CVS, samyron volunteered one and esammer asked for
it to be committed as <path>sample_profile.xml</path>.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Long Term Goals</title>
<body>

<p>
samyron noted that the GLIInstallProfile class is basically done except for the
partitioning code, and it was agreed to keep that as a long term goal.
</p>

<p>
samyron noted that a test frontend is needed to test the installer, and codeman
volunteered to send samyron some test scripts to build on for that purpose.
</p>

</body>
</section>
<section>
<title>Meeting Conclusion</title>
<body>

<p>
samyron opened the meeting up to questions, comments, and suggestions.
</p>

<p>
codeman volunteered further help, samyron accepted the offer.
</p>

<p>
homer offered to help build a PHP profile generator, esammer asked homer to
speak with cshields regarding collaboration on that project.
</p>

<p>
There was a small amount of discussion on kernel configuration.
</p>

<p>
klieber noted that the Infrastructure project could supply hosting for a
PHP-based profile generator, and has VMWare GSX Server running in order to
provide testing environments to the Installer project team members.
</p>

<p>
The meeting was adjourned at 2006 UTC.
</p>

</body>
</section>
</chapter>
</guide>
