<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/base/embedded/handbook/cross-compiler.xml,v 1.12 2013/06/21 16:07:22 vapier Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
Build a cross-compiler on your machine!
</abstract>

<version>0.3</version>
<date>2010-04-13</date>

<section>
<title>Overview</title>
<body>

<p>
The first thing you should know about building a toolchain is that some
versions of toolchain components refuse to work together.  Exactly which
combinations are problematic is a matter that's constantly in flux as the
Portage tree evolves.  The only reliable way to determine what works is to run
crossdev, adjusting individual component versions as necessary, until crossdev
completes the toolchain build successfully.  Even then, the cross toolchain
may build binaries which break on the target system.  Only through trial and
error and patience will you arrive at a favorable combination of all factors.
</p>

<p>
You do not have to worry about the cross-compiler interfering with your
native build system.  All of the toolchain packages are designed such
that they are isolated from each other based on the target.  This way
you can install cross-compilers for whatever architecture you wish
without breaking the rest of your system.
</p>

<p>
However, there are some scenarios, albeit fewer as time goes on, which
causes portage to require or to inflict changes to real root. To keep
your Gentoo installation clean, we highly recommend that crossdev
installation and all cross-compiling activities occur inside a Gentoo 
stage3 chroot. (This is the same chroot you used to install Gentoo.)
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>crossdev</title>
<subsection>
<title>Intro</title>
<body>

<p>
Generating a cross-compiler by hand was a long and painful process.  This is why
it has been fully integrated into Gentoo! A frontend called <c>crossdev</c> will
run <c>emerge</c> with all of the proper environment variables and install all
the right packages to generate arbitrary cross-compilers based on your needs.
First you'll need to install <c>crossdev</c>:
</p>

<pre caption="Install crossdev">
# <i>emerge crossdev</i>
</pre>

<p>
You'll probably want to install the ~arch keyworded version of crossdev to get
all the latest fixes.
</p>

<note>
If you are upgrading from an older version of crossdev, and have
<c>crossdev-wrappers</c> installed, be sure to uninstall crossdev-wrappers
first. Your existing cross-toolchains will remain intact.
</note>

<p>
We only cover the basic usage of crossdev here, but crossdev can customize the
process fairly well for most needs. Run <c>crossdev --help</c> to get some ideas
on how to use crossdev. Here are a few common uses:
</p>

<pre caption="Useful crossdev options">
<comment>(Use specific package versions)</comment>
# <i>crossdev --g [gcc version] --l [(g)libc version] --b [binutils version] --k [kernel headers version] -P -v -t [tuple]</i>
<comment>(Use the stable version only)</comment>
# <i>crossdev -S -P -v -t [tuple]</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Installing</title>
<body>

<p>
The first step is to select the proper tuple for your target.  Here we will
assume you want to build a cross-compiler for the SH4 (SuperH) processor with
glibc running on Linux.  We will do this on a PowerPC machine.
</p>

<pre caption="Generating SH4 cross-compiler">
# <i>crossdev --target sh4-unknown-linux-gnu</i>
-----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
 * Host Portage ARCH:     ppc
 * Target Portage ARCH:   sh
 * Target System:         sh4-unknown-linux-gnu
 * Stage:                 4 (C/C++ compiler)

 * binutils:              binutils-[latest]
 * gcc:                   gcc-[latest]
 * headers:               linux-headers-[latest]
 * libc:                  glibc-[latest]

 * PORTDIR_OVERLAY:       /usr/local/portage
 * PORT_LOGDIR:           /var/log/portage
 * PKGDIR:                /usr/portage/packages/powerpc-unknown-linux-gnu/cross/sh4-unknown-linux-gnu
 * PORTAGE_TMPDIR:        /var/tmp/cross/sh4-unknown-linux-gnu
  _  -  ~  -  _  -  ~  -  _  -  ~  -  _  -  ~  -  _  -  ~  -  _  -  ~  -  _  -  ~  -  _  -  ~  -  _  
 * Forcing the latest versions of {binutils,gcc}-config/gnuconfig ...                          [ ok ]
 * Log: /var/log/portage/cross-sh4-unknown-linux-gnu-binutils.log
 * Emerging cross-binutils ...                                                                 [ ok ]
 * Log: /var/log/portage/cross-sh4-unknown-linux-gnu-gcc-stage1.log
 * Emerging cross-gcc-stage1 ...                                                               [ ok ]
 * Log: /var/log/portage/cross-sh4-unknown-linux-gnu-linux-headers.log
 * Emerging cross-linux-headers ...                                                            [ ok ]
 * Log: /var/log/portage/cross-sh4-unknown-linux-gnu-glibc.log
 * Emerging cross-glibc ...                                                                    [ ok ]
 * Log: /var/log/portage/cross-sh4-unknown-linux-gnu-gcc-stage2.log
 * Emerging cross-gcc-stage2 ...                                                               [ ok ]
</pre>

<note>
At the moment it's not possible to set <c>PORTAGE_CONFIGROOT</c> before calling
<c>crossdev</c> to a folder set to the arch you're targetting. You have to use
your own config.  If you want to use arch specific use flags, like
<c>altivec</c> in a non powerpc architecture, you need to unmask the use flag in
<c>/usr/portage/base/use.mask</c>, or temporarily change your profile.
</note>
	
</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Quick Test</title>
<body>

<p>
If everything goes as planned, you should have a shiny new compiler on your
machine.  Give it a spin!
</p>

<pre caption="Using SH4 cross-compiler">
$ <i>sh4-unknown-linux-gnu-gcc --version</i>
sh4-unknown-linux-gnu-gcc (GCC) 4.2.0 (Gentoo 4.2.0 p1.4)
Copyright (C) 2007 Free Software Foundation, Inc.
This is free software; see the source for copying conditions.  There is NO
warranty; not even for MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.
$ <i>echo 'int main(){return 0;}' > sh4-test.c</i>
$ <i>sh4-unknown-linux-gnu-gcc -Wall sh4-test.c -o sh4-test</i>
$ <i>file sh4-test</i>
sh4-test: ELF 32-bit LSB executable, Renesas SH, version 1 (SYSV), for GNU/Linux 2.6.9, dynamically linked (uses shared libs), not stripped
</pre>

<p>
If the crossdev command failed, you have the log file which you can review to
see if the problem is local.  If you're unable to fix the issue, you're welcome
to file a bug in our bugzilla.  See the <uri
link="communication.xml">Communication page</uri> for more information.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Uninstalling</title>
<body>

<p>
To uninstall a toolchain, simply use the <c>--clean</c> option.  If you modified
the sysroot by hand, you'll be prompted to delete things inside of it, so you
may want to pipe <c>yes |</c> into the command.
</p>

<pre caption="Uninstalling cross-compiler">
# <i>crossdev --clean sh4-unknown-linux-gnu</i>
</pre>

<p>
In case you didn't already notice, deleting any and all files in the
<path>/usr/CTARGET/</path> directory is completely safe.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Options</title>
<body>

<p>
Obviously crossdev can do a lot more, so to find out more, simply run
<c>crossdev --help</c>.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

<section>
<title>Cross-compiler Internals</title>

<subsection>
<body>
<warn>
This section is included for posterity and in the hopes that others will find
it useful.  The target audience is people who (for some stupid reason or
another) really really want to create their own cross compiler with
binutils/(glibc|uclibc)/gcc all by themselves.  This section is <b>not</b>
meant to cover/document/whatever the myriad of build failures you are likely
to see along the way.  If you need such help, see the
<uri link="the-more-you-know.xml">Beyond section</uri> in the handbook for
some pointers.  You certainly should not bug me or anyone else in Gentoo.
</warn>

<warn>
If you're still reading, you should really check out the crosstool project
(refer to the <uri link="the-more-you-know.xml">Beyond section</uri>) as
that provides a distribution independent method for generating cross-compilers.
While it does kind of suck (imo), it is certainly the best (and really only)
option out there for creating cross-compilers.
</warn>
</body>
</subsection>

<subsection>
<title>Overview</title>
<body>

<p>
There are generally two ways to build up your cross-compiler. The "accepted"
way, and the cheater's shortcut.
</p>

<p>
The current "accepted" way is:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>binutils</li>
  <li>kernel headers</li>
  <li>libc headers</li>
  <li>gcc stage1 (c-only)</li>
  <li>libc</li>
  <li>gcc stage2 (c/c++/etc...)</li>
</ol>

<p>
The cheater's shortcut is:
</p>

<ol>
  <li>binutils</li>
  <li>kernel headers</li>
  <li>gcc stage1 (c-only)</li>
  <li>libc</li>
  <li>gcc stage2 (c/c++/etc...)</li>
</ol>

<p>
The reason people are keen on the shortcut is that the libc headers step tends
to take quite a while, especially on slower machines. It can also be kind of a
pain to setup kernel/libc headers without a usuable cross compiler. Note though
that if you seek help with cross-compilers, upstream projects will not want to
help you if you took the shortcut.
</p>

<p>
Also note that the shortcut requires the gcc stage1 to be "crippled". Since
you're building without headers, you cannot enable the sysroot option nor can
you build up proper gcc libs. This is OK if the only thing you use the stage1 is
building the C library and a kernel, but beyond that you need a nice sysroot
based compiler.
</p>

<p>
Below I will describe the "accepted" way as the steps are pretty much the
same.  You just need some extra patches for gcc in order to take the
shortcut.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Sysroot</title>
<body>

<p>
We will be cross-compiling using the sysroot method. But does the sysroot do?
</p>

<p>
The sysroot tells GCC to consider dir as the root of a tree that contains a
(subset of) the root filesystem of the target operating system. Target system
headers, libraries and run-time object files will be searched in there.
</p>

<p>
The top level dir is commonly rooted in /usr/$CTARGET
</p>

<pre caption="typical sysroot layout">
/usr/$CTARGET/
|-- bin/
|-- lib/            critical runtime libs (libc/ldso/etc...)
`-- usr/
    |-- include/    development headers
    |   |-- linux/      like the linux kernel
    |   `-- asm/        like the arch-specific
    `-- lib/        non critical runtime libs / development libs
</pre>

<p>
As you can see, it's just like the directory setup in <path>/</path> but in
<path>/usr/$CTARGET</path>.  This setup is of course not an accident but
designed on purpose so you can easily migrate applications/libraries out of
<path>/usr/$CTARGET</path> and into <path>/</path> on your target board. If you
wanted, you could even be lazy and use the <path>/usr/$CTARGET</path> as a quick
NFS root!
</p>

<note>
The old style of cross-compilers was to use <c>--prefix=/usr/$CTARGET</c>. If
you are using versions of binutils/gcc that predate sysroot support, you may
have to do just this. I will not document this because (1) you should not be
using such old/crusty/busted versions and (2) it's quite a huge pain compared to
sysroot.
</note>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Binutils</title>
<body>

<p>
Grab the latest binutils tarball and unpack it.
</p>

<p>
The <c>--disable-werror</c> configure option is to prevent binutils from
aborting the compile due to warnings. Great feature for developers, but a pain
for users.
</p>

<pre caption="configure and build binutils">
$ <i>./configure \
	--target=$CTARGET \
	--prefix=/usr \
	--with-sysroot=/usr/$CTARGET \
	--disable-werror</i>
$ <i>make</i>
$ <i>make install DESTDIR=$PWD/install-root</i>
</pre>

<p>
The reason we install into the localdir is so we can remove crap that doesn't
belong.  For example, a normal install will give us
<path>/usr/lib/libiberty.a</path> which doesn't belong in our host
<path>/usr/lib</path>. So clean out stuff first:
</p>

<pre caption="cleaning binutils">
$ <i>rm -rf install-root/usr/{info,lib,man,share}</i>
</pre>

<p>
And install what's left:
</p>

<pre caption="install binutils">
# <i>cp -a install-root/* /</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Kernel headers</title>
<body>

<p>
Grab the latest Linux tarball and unpack it. There are two ways of
installing the kernel headers: sanitized and unsanitized. The former
is clearly better (but requires a recent version of the Linux kernel),
but we'll quickly cover both.
</p>

<note>
Clearly you'll have to replace $ARCH with a value that makes sense for your
platform.
</note>

<pre caption="building/installing unsanitized headers">
$ <i>yes "" | make ARCH=$ARCH oldconfig prepare</i>
# <i>mkdir -p /usr/$CTARGET/usr/include</i>
# <i>cp -a include/linux include/asm-generic /usr/$CTARGET/usr/include/</i>
# <i>cp -a include/asm-$ARCH /usr/$CTARGET/usr/include/asm</i>
</pre>

<pre caption="building/installing sanitized headers">
# <i>make ARCH=$ARCH headers_install INSTALL_HDR_PATH=/usr/$CTARGET/usr</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>System libc headers</title>
<body>

<p>
Grab the latest glibc tarball and unpack it. Glibc is picky, so you'll
have to compile in a directory separate from the source code.
</p>

<pre caption="building/installing glibc headers">
$ <i>mkdir build</i>
$ <i>cd build</i>
$ <i>../configure \
	--host=$CTARGET \
	--prefix=/usr \
	--with-headers=/usr/$CTARGET/usr/include \
	--without-cvs \
	--disable-sanity-checks</i>
# <i>make -k install-headers install_root=/usr/$CTARGET</i>
</pre>

<p>
Glibc sucks at life so you have to do a few things by hand:
</p>

<pre caption="help glibc">
# <i>mkdir -p /usr/$CTARGET/usr/include/gnu</i>
# <i>touch /usr/$CTARGET/usr/include/gnu/stubs.h</i>
# <i>cp bits/stdio_lim.h /usr/$CTARGET/usr/include/bits/</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>GCC Stage 1 (C only)</title>
<body>

<p>
We first have to help gcc find the current libc headers.
</p>

<pre caption="help gcc">
# <i>ln -s usr/include /usr/$CTARGET/sys-include</i>
</pre>

<p>
Then grab the latest gcc tarball and unpack it.
</p>

<pre caption="building gcc stage 1">
$ <i>mkdir build</i>
$ <i>cd build</i>
$ <i>../configure \
	--target=$CTARGET \
	--prefix=/usr \
	--with-sysroot=/usr/$CTARGET \
	--enable-languages=c \
	--disable-shared \
	--disable-checking \
	--disable-werror \
	--disable-libmudflap \
	--disable-libssp \
	--disable-libgomp</i>
$ <i>make</i>
$ <i>make install DESTDIR=$PWD/install-root</i>
</pre>

<p>
Same as binutils, gcc leaves some stuff behind we don't want.
</p>

<pre caption="cleaning gcc stage 1">
$ <i>rm -rf install-root/usr/{info,include,lib/libiberty.a,man,share}</i>
</pre>

<p>
Then install what's left (everything should be in CTARGET specific directories
which prevents overwriting your host files):
</p>

<pre caption="installing gcc stage 1">
# <i>cp -a install-root/* /</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>System libc</title>
<body>

<p>
Remove the old glibc build dir and recreate it.
</p>

<pre caption="building/installing glibc">
$ <i>rm -rf build</i>
$ <i>mkdir build</i>
$ <i>cd build</i>
$ <i>../configure \
	--host=$CTARGET \
	--prefix=/usr \
	--without-cvs</i>
$ <i>make</i>
# <i>make install install_root=/usr/$CTARGET</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>GCC Stage 2 (All frontends)</title>
<body>

<p>
Build up a full GCC now. Select whichever compiler frontends you like; we'll
just do C/C++ for simplicity.
</p>

<pre caption="building/installing gcc stage 2">
$ <i>./configure \
	--target=$CTARGET \
	--prefix=/usr \
	--with-sysroot=/usr/$CTARGET \
	--enable-languages=c,c++ \
	--enable-shared \
	--disable-checking \
	--disable-werror</i>
$ <i>make</i>
# <i>make install</i>
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
<subsection>
<title>Core Runtime Files</title>
<body>

<p>
There are many random core runtime files that people wonder what they may be
for. Let's explain.
</p>

<table>
<tr>
  <th colspan="2">Files provided by glibc</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>File</th>
  <th>Purpose</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crt0.o</ti>
  <ti>
    Older style of the initial runtime code. No one generates this anymore.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crt1.o</ti>
  <ti>
    Newer style of the initial runtime code. Contains the _start symbol which
    sets up the env with argc/argv/libc _init/libc _fini before jumping to the
    libc main.  glibc calls this file 'start.S'.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crti.o</ti>
  <ti>
    Defines the function prolog; _init in the .init section and _fini in the
    .fini section. glibc calls this 'initfini.c'.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crtn.o</ti>
  <ti>Defines the function epilog. glibc calls this 'initfini.c'.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Scrt1.o</ti>
  <ti>Used in place of crt1.o when generating PIEs.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>gcrt1.o</ti>
  <ti>
    Used in place of crt1.o when generating code with profiling information.
    Compile with -pg. Produces output suitable for the gprof util.
  </ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>Mcrt1.o</ti>
  <ti>
    Like gcrt1.o, but is used with the prof utility. glibc installs this as a
    dummy file as it's useless on linux systems.
  </ti>
</tr>
</table>

<table>
<tr>
  <th colspan="2">Files provided by GCC</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <th>File</th>
  <th>Purpose</th>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crtbegin.o</ti>
  <ti>GCC uses this to find the start of the constructors.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crtbeginS.o</ti>
  <ti>Used in place of crtbegin.o when generating shared objects/PIEs.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crtbeginT.o</ti>
  <ti>Used in place of crtbegin.o when generating static executables.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crtend.o</ti>
  <ti>GCC uses this to find the start of the destructors.</ti>
</tr>
<tr>
  <ti>crtendS.o</ti>
  <ti>Used in place of crtend.o when generating shared objects/PIEs.</ti>
</tr>
</table>

<p>
The general linking order:
</p>

<pre caption="general linking order">
... crt1.o crti.o crtbegin.o [-L paths] [user objects] [gcc libs] [C libs] [gcc libs] crtend.o crtn.o	
</pre>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>

</sections>
