<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<!DOCTYPE sections SYSTEM "/dtd/book.dtd">

<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/2.5 -->

<!-- $Header: /var/cvsroot/gentoo/xml/htdocs/proj/en/base/embedded/handbook/faq.xml,v 1.4 2010/08/30 03:59:07 nightmorph Exp $ -->

<sections>

<abstract>
Frequently Asked Questions for Gentoo Embedded.
</abstract>

<version>0.2</version>
<date>2008-03-20</date>

<section>
<title>I get "configure: error: C compiler cannot create executables"</title>
<body>

<p>
This is a generic error and can be caused by just about anything.  The test is
pretty simple: can the requested compiler create an executable?  However, this
relies on many things being correct: the toolchain itself being completely
sane, the compiler and compiler flags being appropriate, your environment set
up properly, etc...  The only way to find out the real source of the problem is
to open up the generated <path>config.log</path> file and scroll down to where
this test is run and see what exactly the error message is that the toolchain
is spitting out.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>"epatch" always fails in newly compiled system</title>
<body>

<p>
The bash package does not properly cross-compile and mixes the host signal
definitions with those of the target.  This manifests itself differently
depending on the combination of host architecture and target architecture.  To
resolve the issue, simply re-compile bash natively.  "But bash uses epatch!"
you exclaim.  In that case, you will need to modify the ebuild and comment out
all the calls to epatch.  Once you've installed the fixed bash this way,
uncomment all of the bash lines and rebuild it again.
</p>

</body>
</section>

<section>
<title>uClibc build segfaults/crashes while building locale</title>
<body>

<p>
The uClibc locale support is pretty experimental at this point.  Unless you
really need support for it (and you're willing to help bang on the problem),
simply disable support by adding <c>-nls -iconv -pregen -userlocales</c> to
your <c>USE</c> when building uClibc.
</p>

</body>
</section>

</sections>
